<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Houthis release crew of Greek-operated cargo ship struck in Red Sea</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/houthis-release-crew-greek-operated-cargo-ship-struck-red-sea</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/houthis-release-crew-greek-operated-cargo-ship-struck-red-sea</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Dec 3 (Reuters) - The crew of the Greek-operated cargo ship Eternity C, which sank in the Red Sea in July after being attacked by Yemen's Houthis, have been released, an official with the ship's operator and a maritime security source told Reuters on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crew of the Liberia-flagged Eternity C abandoned the ship before it sank following repeated strikes by the Iran-aligned militants with sea drones and rocket-propelled grenades.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:01:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu pardon plea seen as bid to ensure survival ahead of 2026 vote</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-pardon-plea-seen-bid-ensure-survival-ahead-2026-vote</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-pardon-plea-seen-bid-ensure-survival-ahead-2026-vote</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Netanyahu's request for a pardon in three ongoing corruption cases is widely seen as his latest bid to ensure his political survival, as the canny premier stares down the prospect of close elections in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first sitting Israeli prime minister to stand trial, Netanyahu has been dogged by the allegations for years, and has had to appear in front of a judge weekly for hearings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He has repeatedly denied any wrongdoing and denounced the cases as a politically motivated plot against him.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says received presumed remains of Gaza hostage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-says-received-presumed-remains-gaza-hostage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-says-received-presumed-remains-gaza-hostage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel announced Wednesday it had received hostage remains found in Gaza from the Red Cross, which were being transported to the morgue for identification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It comes as the US-brokered ceasefire between Israel and Hamas remains fragile, with both sides accusing each other of violating the terms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the first phase of the deal -- which came into effect in October -- Palestinian militants were due to return all 48 hostages they held captive, 20 of whom were still alive.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 17:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says to attend World Cup draw in apparent U-turn</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-says-attend-world-cup-draw-apparent-u-turn</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-says-attend-world-cup-draw-apparent-u-turn</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran said Wednesday it would now send representatives to the World Cup finals draw in Washington in a complete reversal of an earlier decision to boycott the event over visa issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Amir Ghalenoei, head coach of Iran's national team, will participate in the World Cup draw ceremony as the technical representative of the national football team with one or two other people," the Iranian Football Federation spokesperson told state television.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Celebrities back 'Free Marwan' campaign for Palestinian leader</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/celebrities-back-free-marwan-campaign-palestinian-leader</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/celebrities-back-free-marwan-campaign-palestinian-leader</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;More than 200 celebrities, including actors Benedict Cumberbatch and Josh O’Connor, called on Israel on Wednesday to release imprisoned Palestinian politician Marwan Barghouti, who is seen by supporters as a key unifying figure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barghouti, 66, has been in jail since 2002 but is regarded as a likely major player in the creation of any Palestinian state because of his ability to unite various political factions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The open letter calling for his release featured film A-listers Josh O’Connor, Benedict Cumberbatch and Javier Bardem, as well as musicians Fontaines D.C. and Sting.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 16:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel publishes draft law seeking to boost state revenues from Dead Sea minerals</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-publishes-draft-law-seeking-boost-state-revenues-dead-sea-minerals</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-publishes-draft-law-seeking-boost-state-revenues-dead-sea-minerals</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Israel on Wednesday published a draft law that aims to boost state revenues from a concession for extracting minerals from the Dead Sea as well as tackling its environmental consequences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Finance Ministry said the proposed law intends to redefine the concession to ensure the public and the state get their rightful share, while ensuring the preservation of nature and environmental values.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency dips to new low of 1.2M per dollar as sanctions bite: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</guid><description>Since US President Donald Trump took office in January, the rial has plummeted.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:21:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency dips to new low of 1.2M per dollar as sanctions bite: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</guid><description>Since US President Donald Trump took office in January, the rial has plummeted.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:21:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency dips to new low of 1.2M per dollar as sanctions bite: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</guid><description>Since US President Donald Trump took office in January, the rial has plummeted.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:21:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency dips to new low of 1.2M per dollar as sanctions bite: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-dips-new-low-12m-dollar-sanctions-bite-what-know</guid><description>Since US President Donald Trump took office in January, the rial has plummeted.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:21:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN chief Guterres: end to war in Ukraine should abide by international law</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-chief-guterres-end-war-ukraine-should-abide-international-law</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-chief-guterres-end-war-ukraine-should-abide-international-law</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;NEW YORK, Dec 3 (Reuters) - An end to Russia's war in Ukraine should abide by international law, United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I believe we are still far from a solution," Guterres said at the Reuters NEXT conference in New York.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia invaded Ukraine in February 2022, triggering the biggest confrontation between Moscow and the West since the depths of the Cold War.The United States is trying to broker an end to the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu's coalition skips parliamentary vote backing Trump's Gaza plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahus-coalition-skips-parliamentary-vote-backing-trumps-gaza-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahus-coalition-skips-parliamentary-vote-backing-trumps-gaza-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's governing coalition skipped a parliamentary vote on Wednesday endorsing U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the two-year war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vote, proposed by opposition leader Yair Lapid, was largely symbolic as Netanyahu had already publicly backed the plan after Israel agreed to a ceasefire with Hamas in October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Less than a third of the parliament's 120 lawmakers participated in it with 39 in favour and none against. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany deploys Arrow air defence to counter Russian missile threat</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/germany-deploys-arrow-air-defence-counter-russian-missile-threat</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/germany-deploys-arrow-air-defence-counter-russian-missile-threat</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;HOLZDORF, Germany, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Germany on Wednesday became the first European nation to deploy the Arrow air defence system, built to intercept intermediate-range ballistic missiles such as Russia's Oreshnik, as it seeks to counter what it sees as a growing threat from Moscow. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Operating at altitudes above 100 kilometres (62 miles), outside the earth's atmosphere, and with a range of 2,400 kilometres, the stationary Arrow system complements shorter-range air defences such as Patriot and IRIS-T which are mounted on trucks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gazans race to preserve cultural heritage damaged in war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gazans-race-preserve-cultural-heritage-damaged-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gazans-race-preserve-cultural-heritage-damaged-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GAZA, Dec 3 (Reuters) - With 70,000 dead, countless injured, hundreds of thousands of people homeless and whole districts laid to waste, the task of rebuilding Gaza is almost beyond comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But at a handful of sites where the enclave's most valuable historical monuments have been severely damaged, workers are already busy with shovels, trying to dig out the few surviving remnants of the past.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghan Taliban minister says US shooting has nothing to do with his people or government</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/afghan-taliban-minister-says-us-shooting-has-nothing-do-his-people-or-government</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/afghan-taliban-minister-says-us-shooting-has-nothing-do-his-people-or-government</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KABUL, Dec 3 (Reuters) - The shooting of National Guard members in Washington, D.C., over which an Afghan immigrant has been charged, has nothing to do with Afghanistan's people or its government, Afghan Taliban Foreign Minister Amir Khan Muttaqi said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Muttaqi's comments are the first on the incident by the Afghan Taliban government, and come a week after events in Washington when suspect Rahmanullah Lakanwal is accused of opening fire on guard members, killing one and critically wounding another.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Libya war crimes suspect makes first appearance at ICC</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libya-war-crimes-suspect-makes-first-appearance-icc</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libya-war-crimes-suspect-makes-first-appearance-icc</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Libyan prison boss accused of overseeing murder, rape, and torture at a notorious detention centre appeared at the International Criminal Court Wednesday to face charges of war crimes and crimes against humanity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khaled Mohamed Ali El Hishri, 47, sat impassively dressed in a dark blue jacket and light blue shirt, confirming his name and date of birth before the three-woman judging panel.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel, Lebanon officials meet in expanded truce talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-lebanon-officials-meet-expanded-truce-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-lebanon-officials-meet-expanded-truce-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/BEIRUT, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Israel and Lebanon sent new representatives to a military committee monitoring a truce between the countries, top officials from both said on Wednesday, in a move set to expand the scope of talks between the long-time foes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting was a step towards a months-long U.S. demand that the two countries broaden talks beyond monitoring the 2024 ceasefire, in line with U.S. President Donald Trump's broader agenda of peace agreements across the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Migrants in Lebanon hope Pope's peace message lingers amid fears of new war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/migrants-lebanon-hope-popes-peace-message-lingers-amid-fears-new-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/migrants-lebanon-hope-popes-peace-message-lingers-amid-fears-new-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Catherine  Cartier&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Filipina worker Loren Capobres said the world stood still when she kissed Pope Leo's hand this week in Lebanon, but hopes his message for peace will linger after his departure, leading to better working conditions and a lasting peace in the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Capobres, who is Catholic and has worked in Lebanon for 17 years, met Leo on Monday, alongside priests and other church volunteers on his first overseas trip as pope, in which he called on the Middle East's leaders to reject the horror of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas says it will hand over a Gaza hostage body, Israel to open Rafah crossing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-says-it-will-hand-over-gaza-hostage-body-israel-open-rafah-crossing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-says-it-will-hand-over-gaza-hostage-body-israel-open-rafah-crossing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/JERUSALEM, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Hamas said it will hand over a body of a hostage on Wednesday, as Israel said it would allow Gaza's gateway to Egypt to open in the next few days so that Palestinians who need medical care could leave the war-ravaged territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;  The handover of the last two hostages' bodies in Gaza would complete a key condition of the initial part of U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the two-yearGaza war, which also entails the Rafah border crossing between Gaza and Egypt opening in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon and Israel hold first direct talks in decades: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanon-and-israel-hold-first-direct-talks-decades-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanon-and-israel-hold-first-direct-talks-decades-what-know</guid><description>Lebanon and Israel sent civilian representatives to the latest US-led meeting of the committee overseeing the ceasefire, aiming to break the stalemate between the two countries as Israel intensifies its attacks on Lebanon over its delay in disarming Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:32:13 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>