<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Exclusive-US shoots down Iranian drone approaching aircraft carrier, official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-us-shoots-down-iranian-drone-approaching-aircraft-carrier-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-us-shoots-down-iranian-drone-approaching-aircraft-carrier-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 3 (Reuters)  - The U.S. military shot down on Tuesday an Iranian drone that approached the Abraham Lincoln aircraft carrier in the Arabian Sea, a U.S. official told Reuters on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Iranian Shahed-139 drone was flying towards the carrier and was shot down by a F-35 U.S. fighter jet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Idrees Ali and Phil Stewart; Editing by Chizu Nomiyama )&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian women describe 'journey of horror’ crossing back into Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-women-describe-journey-horror-crossing-back-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-women-describe-journey-horror-crossing-back-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Mahmoud Issa&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/GAZA, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Palestinian women among the few people let back into Gaza after Israel's delayed reopening of the Rafah crossing under last year's ceasefire have described being blindfolded, handcuffed and interrogated by Israeli forces as they tried to get home. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their journey from Egypt on Monday through the frontier post and across the "yellow line" zone controlled by Israel and an allied Palestinian militia group, involved lengthy delays and the confiscation of gifts including toys, one of the women said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria govt forces enter Qamishli under agreement with Kurds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-govt-forces-enter-qamishli-under-agreement-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-govt-forces-enter-qamishli-under-agreement-kurds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syrian government forces entered the Kurdish-majority city of Qamishli on Tuesday as part of a deal agreed last week to gradually integrate the Kurds' forces and institutions into the state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The arrival came after government security personnel entered the mixed Kurdish-Arab city of Hasakeh and the countryside around the Kurdish town of Kobane the day before.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Putin and Saudi crown prince discuss work of OPEC+, Kremlin says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-putin-and-saudi-crown-prince-discuss-work-opec-kremlin-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-putin-and-saudi-crown-prince-discuss-work-opec-kremlin-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Russian President Vladimir Putin held a phone call with Saudi Arabia's Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman, the Kremlin said on Tuesday, saying they had agreed to deepen cooperation in the political, economic, trade and humanitarian spheres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Kremlin statement, the two leaders also discussed the progress of their joint work within the OPEC+ format and efforts to maintain stability on global energy markets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saudi state news agency SPA said the prince and Putin discussed bilateral relations and regional and international developments.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudanese army says it has broken siege of famine-stricken Kadugli</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-army-says-it-has-broken-siege-famine-stricken-kadugli</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-army-says-it-has-broken-siege-famine-stricken-kadugli</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nafisa Eltahir and Khalid Abdelaziz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feb 3 - The Sudanese army said it broke a years-long siege on the city of Kadugli on Tuesday, potentially providing tens of thousands of people a reprieve from famine and signaling a shift in the war's momentum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conflict between the Sudanese army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) has displaced millions, drawn in regional powers and caused a vast humanitarian crisis since it broke out in April 2023.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu to meet US envoy Witkoff amid revived Iran nuclear talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-meet-us-envoy-witkoff-amid-revived-iran-nuclear-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-meet-us-envoy-witkoff-amid-revived-iran-nuclear-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emily Rose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu was scheduled to meet U.S. Special Envoy Steve Witkoff on Tuesday amid efforts to revive diplomacy over a long-running dispute about Iran's nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting was scheduled for 1430 GMT and would include the director of Israel's Mossad spy agency David Barnea, Israeli Defense Minister Israel Katz, and Israeli Military Chief of Staff Eyal Zamir, two Israeli officials told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's drone deployment to border raises stakes in Sudan's civil war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/egypts-drone-deployment-border-raises-stakes-sudans-civil-war-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/egypts-drone-deployment-border-raises-stakes-sudans-civil-war-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt; (Refiles to correct spelling of Janes in 22nd paragraph)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Dziadosz, Marine Delrue  and Maria Paula Laguna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Feb 2 (Reuters) - The deployment of a powerful model of Turkish combat drone to a remote airstrip on Egypt’s southwestern border signals a sharp escalation in Sudan’s civil war, suggesting one of its largest neighbours is being drawn deeper into the fray, more than a dozen officials and regional experts say.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Somaliland expects Israel trade deal, has minerals to offer, leader says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-somaliland-expects-israel-trade-deal-has-minerals-offer-leader-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-somaliland-expects-israel-trade-deal-has-minerals-offer-leader-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Somaliland expects to reach a trade agreement soon with Israel, the first country to recognise its independence, and is willing to offer rights to valuable mineral deposits as part of a deal, its leader said in an interview with Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On eve of Turkey talks, UAE's Gargash throws weight behind Iran-US deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</guid><description>Anwar Gargash, diplomatic adviser to the UAE president, spoke at a panel discussion at the World Governments Summit in Dubai, where he discussed the latest developments in Gaza, Iran, Sudan and Yemen.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:05:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On eve of Turkey talks, UAE's Gargash throws weight behind Iran-US deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</guid><description>Anwar Gargash, diplomatic adviser to the UAE president, spoke at a panel discussion at the World Governments Summit in Dubai, where he discussed the latest developments in Gaza, Iran, Sudan and Yemen.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:05:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On eve of Turkey talks, UAE's Gargash throws weight behind Iran-US deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</guid><description>Anwar Gargash, diplomatic adviser to the UAE president, spoke at a panel discussion at the World Governments Summit in Dubai, where he discussed the latest developments in Gaza, Iran, Sudan and Yemen.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:05:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On eve of Turkey talks, UAE's Gargash throws weight behind Iran-US deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eve-turkey-talks-uaes-gargash-throws-weight-behind-iran-us-deal</guid><description>Anwar Gargash, diplomatic adviser to the UAE president, spoke at a panel discussion at the World Governments Summit in Dubai, where he discussed the latest developments in Gaza, Iran, Sudan and Yemen.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:05:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian security convoy heads to key Kurdish city under US-backed deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrian-security-convoy-heads-key-kurdish-city-under-us-backed-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrian-security-convoy-heads-key-kurdish-city-under-us-backed-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 3 (Reuters) - Syrian government security forces moved towards the Kurdish-controlled northeastern city of Qamishli on Tuesday, security sources and witnesses said, as they implement a U.S.-backed deal to bring Kurdish-run regions under the control of Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deal, declared on Friday, staved off the prospect of further confrontation between Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa's government and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, which lost swathes of eastern and northern Syria to government troops in January.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran president confirms talks with US after Trump's threats</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-president-confirms-talks-us-after-trumps-threats</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-president-confirms-talks-us-after-trumps-threats</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's president confirmed on Tuesday that he had ordered the start of talks with the United States, provided they were free of threats, after his counterpart Donald Trump suggested "bad things" would happen without a deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has been no official confirmation from Iran on where the talks would be held, but an Arab official, speaking on condition of anonymity, told AFP a meeting was likely to take place in Turkey on Friday, following diplomatic interventions by Ankara, as well as Egypt, Oman and Qatar.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tearful Gazans finally reunite after limited Rafah reopening</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tearful-gazans-finally-reunite-after-limited-rafah-reopening</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tearful-gazans-finally-reunite-after-limited-rafah-reopening</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gazans long-separated from their loved ones shed tears of joy after the limited reopening of the Rafah crossing with Egypt allowed a handful to finally return to the war-shattered territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jubilant crowds filmed on their phones as they flocked around a bus carrying returnees to Nasser Hospital in the southern city of Khan Yunis late in the night on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AFP footage showed a man holding a young child up to the window to greet those arriving, while women wept as they were at last able to embrace.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greece to soon announce social media ban for children under 15, government source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/greece-soon-announce-social-media-ban-children-under-15-government-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/greece-soon-announce-social-media-ban-children-under-15-government-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Greece is "very close" to announcing a social media ban for children aged under 15, a senior government source told Reuters on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spain said on Tuesday that it plans to ban social media for those aged under 16 and will create a law to hold social media executives personally responsible for hate speech on their platforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Renee Maltezou; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 13:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine to adjust peace negotiators' work after Russia's strike, Zelenskiy says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukraine-adjust-peace-negotiators-work-after-russias-strike-zelenskiy-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukraine-adjust-peace-negotiators-work-after-russias-strike-zelenskiy-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Feb 3 (Reuters) - The work of Ukraine's negotiating team will be adjusted after Russia's overnight attack on Ukrainian energy facilities, which involved a record number of ballistic missiles, President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was a deliberate attack against energy infrastructure, involving a record number of ballistic missiles," Zelenskiy said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 12:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>WHO says first five patients evacuated via Gaza's Rafah crossing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/who-says-first-five-patients-evacuated-gazas-rafah-crossing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/who-says-first-five-patients-evacuated-gazas-rafah-crossing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Feb 3 (Reuters) - A World Health Organization official said on Tuesday that the first five patients were transferred through Gaza's Rafah crossing with Egypt, which reopened on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"On the second of February, WHO and partners supported the medical evacuation of five patients and seven companions to Egypt via the Rafah crossing," said WHO spokesperson Christian Lindmeier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was the first medical evacuation through this route since sometime in 2025," he said referring to a limited number of evacuations during an early 2025 ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisia upholds and increases jail terms for opponents and security officials</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tunisia-upholds-and-increases-jail-terms-opponents-and-security-officials</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tunisia-upholds-and-increases-jail-terms-opponents-and-security-officials</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS, Feb 3 (Reuters) - A Tunisian appeal court on Tuesday upheld and increased lengthy prison sentences on high-profile politicians, including opposition leader Rached Ghannouchi and former security officials, as part of a crackdown on dissent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among those sentenced on charges of conspiring against the state in the mass trial were Nadia Akacha, the former chief of staff to President Kais Saied. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Akacha, who was sentenced in absentia after fleeing abroad, received a 35-year jail term, TAP state news agency said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Middle East does not need Iran-US war, diplomatic adviser to UAE president says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/middle-east-does-not-need-iran-us-war-diplomatic-adviser-uae-president-says-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/middle-east-does-not-need-iran-us-war-diplomatic-adviser-uae-president-says-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 3 (Reuters) - The Middle East does not need another confrontation between the U.S. and Iran, and Tehran needs to reach a nuclear deal with Washington, the diplomatic adviser to the president of regional power United Arab Emirates said at a World Governments Summit panel in Dubai.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States will resume nuclear talks on Friday in Turkey, Iranian and U.S. officials told Reuters on Monday. U.S. President Donald Trump warned that with big U.S. warships heading to Iran, "bad things" would probably happen if a deal could not be reached.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>