<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Car ramming, stabbing attack in West Bank kills one, injures three</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/car-ramming-stabbing-attack-west-bank-kills-one-injures-three</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/car-ramming-stabbing-attack-west-bank-kills-one-injures-three</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -One man was killed and three other people were injured in a car ramming and stabbing attack in the Israeli-occupied West Bank on Tuesday, the Israeli military and ambulance service said, in what Israeli authorities described as a terror attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military said in a statement two attackers were also killed by soldiers, but did not provide further details. It said explosive materials were found in the vehicle used by the attackers, which were being neutralised by bomb disposal specialists.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 15:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria opens first trial over coastal violence after Assad's fall</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-opens-first-trial-over-coastal-violence-after-assads-fall-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-opens-first-trial-over-coastal-violence-after-assads-fall-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Suleiman Al-Khalidi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ALEPPO, Syria/AMMAN (Reuters) -Syria on Tuesday began the first trial of suspects in a wave of bloodshed in March during which pro-government fighters killed hundreds of members of the Alawite minority - a case seen as a test of President Ahmed al-Sharaa's promise of accountability.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 14:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi prince to press Trump to intervene to end Sudan war, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-prince-press-trump-intervene-end-sudan-war-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-prince-press-trump-intervene-end-sudan-war-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell and Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV/RIYDAH (Reuters) -Saudi Arabia's defacto ruler Mohammed bin Salman is set to press U.S. President Donald Trump to personally intervene to help end the war in Sudan during talks in Washington on Tuesday, five people familiar with the matter said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sources -- two Arab diplomats and three western diplomats -- said the Saudi Crown Prince believed Trump's direct pressure was needed to break a logjam in talks to end more than two and a half years of war, pointing to his work to achieve a ceasefire in Gaza last month. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 14:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rostec says defence exports halved since 2022 as Russian orders dominated</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/rostec-says-defence-exports-halved-2022-russian-orders-dominated</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/rostec-says-defence-exports-halved-2022-russian-orders-dominated</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI (Reuters) -Russian state conglomerate Rostec said on Tuesday that its defence exports fell by half since 2022 as domestic orders became a priority amid the fighting in Ukraine, but expects recovery soon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until 2022 Russia held second place in the world after the United States in defence exports, but the volumes dropped "due to the fact that we have had to supply most of our production to our army", Rostec Chief Sergey Chemezov told reporters. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sanctions have complicated operations both in civil and defence sectors, but did not affect overall output, he said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Senators press Trump administration over envoy's possible financial conflicts, letter says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/senators-press-trump-administration-over-envoys-possible-financial-conflicts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/senators-press-trump-administration-over-envoys-possible-financial-conflicts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Patricia Zengerle&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -Two Democratic U.S. senators wrote to President Donald Trump's administration on Monday raising "serious concerns" about Middle East envoy Steve Witkoff's potential financial conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 12:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria opens first trial over coastal violence after Assad's fall</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-opens-first-trial-over-coastal-violence-after-assads-fall</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-opens-first-trial-over-coastal-violence-after-assads-fall</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Suleiman Al-Khalidi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ALEPPO, Syria/AMMAN (Reuters) -Syria on Tuesday began the first trial of suspects in a wave of bloodshed in March during which pro-government fighters killed hundreds of members of the Alawite minority - a case seen as a test of President Ahmed al-Sharaa's promise of accountability.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 12:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After UN vote, Netanyahu calls for Hamas' expulsion from the region</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-un-vote-netanyahu-calls-hamas-expulsion-region</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-un-vote-netanyahu-calls-hamas-expulsion-region</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV/CAIRO (Reuters) -Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on Tuesday called for Hamas to be expelled from the region, a day after the U.N. Security Council endorsed President Donald Trump's plan to end the war that offers the Palestinian militant group amnesty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netanyahu publicly endorsed the plan during a White House visit in late September. However, his latest remarks appear to show that there are differences with the United States on the path forward. Hamas has also objected to parts of the plan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 12:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN chief welcomes Security Council's adoption of Trump's Gaza plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-chief-welcomes-security-councils-adoption-trumps-gaza-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-chief-welcomes-security-councils-adoption-trumps-gaza-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA (Reuters) -United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres on Tuesday called the passing of a U.S.-backed resolution on Gaza an important step in the consolidation of the ceasefire, in a statement sent to reporters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UN Security Council on Monday voted to adopt a U.S.-drafted resolution endorsing President Donald Trump's plan to end the war in Gaza and authorizing an international stabilization force there.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US cancels Lebanon army chief visit amid frustration over Hezbollah: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</guid><description>Washington canceled a planned visit by Lebanon’s army commander Gen. Rodolphe Haykal, signaling growing US frustration over Lebanon’s delay in disarming Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:30:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US cancels Lebanon army chief visit amid frustration over Hezbollah: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</guid><description>Washington canceled a planned visit by Lebanon’s army commander Gen. Rodolphe Haykal, signaling growing US frustration over Lebanon’s delay in disarming Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:30:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US cancels Lebanon army chief visit amid frustration over Hezbollah: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</guid><description>Washington canceled a planned visit by Lebanon’s army commander Gen. Rodolphe Haykal, signaling growing US frustration over Lebanon’s delay in disarming Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:30:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US cancels Lebanon army chief visit amid frustration over Hezbollah: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-cancels-lebanon-army-chief-visit-amid-frustration-over-hezbollah-what-know</guid><description>Washington canceled a planned visit by Lebanon’s army commander Gen. Rodolphe Haykal, signaling growing US frustration over Lebanon’s delay in disarming Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:30:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN says lacks billions of dollars to feed world's hungry</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-says-lacks-billions-dollars-feed-worlds-hungry</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-says-lacks-billions-dollars-feed-worlds-hungry</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The UN's World Food Programme warned Tuesday that funding cuts mean it will struggle to feed even a third of the 318 million people facing severe hunger in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Declines in global humanitarian funding are forcing WFP to prioritise food assistance to roughly one third of those in need," targeting 110 million of the most vulnerable, it said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That would cost $13 billion, the agency estimated -- but warned that "current funding forecasts indicate WFP may only receive close to half that goal".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin says Russia will not participate in Ukraine talks in Turkey this week</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kremlin-says-russia-will-not-participate-ukraine-talks-turkey-week</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kremlin-says-russia-will-not-participate-ukraine-talks-turkey-week</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW (Reuters) -Russian representatives will not take part in talks on Ukraine in Turkey on November 19, the Kremlin said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said earlier he would go to Turkey on Wednesday in an attempt to revive negotiations with Russia on ending the war. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Turkish source said that U.S. special envoy Steve Witkoff would join the planned talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kremlin spokesman Dmitry Peskov told reporters: "No, there will be no Russian representatives in Turkey tomorrow. For now, these contacts are taking place without Russian participation." &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza water provider suspends services after Hamas detains staff member</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-water-provider-suspends-services-after-hamas-detains-staff-member</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-water-provider-suspends-services-after-hamas-detains-staff-member</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -A Gaza company that operates water desalination plants serving nearly half of the enclave's population has stopped operations to protest at the detention by Hamas of one of its staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Youssef Yassin, a board member of the Abdul Salam Yassin Company, said the move would affect more than 1 million people who normally receive water from the company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 70 trucks that carry water containers across the enclave have also stopped operations, he added, risking further supply disruption after the pipeline network was badly damaged during the war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel hails Trump Gaza plan after UN Security Council vote</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-hails-trump-gaza-plan-after-un-security-council-vote</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-hails-trump-gaza-plan-after-un-security-council-vote</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel on Tuesday hailed Donald Trump's Gaza peace plan after its endorsement by the UN Security Council, as Hamas rejected the resolution which calls for the deployment of an international force in the Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Security Council voted Monday in favour of a US-drafted resolution bolstering President Trump's plan for the Gaza Strip -- which has allowed a fragile ceasefire to hold between Israel and Hamas since October 10.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine's Zelenskiy plans Turkey visit to try to revive peace talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ukraines-zelenskiy-plans-turkey-visit-try-revive-peace-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ukraines-zelenskiy-plans-turkey-visit-try-revive-peace-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV (Reuters) -President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said he planned to go to Turkey on Wednesday in an attempt to revive talks with Russia on how to end the war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Turkish source said that U.S. special envoy Steve Witkoff would also visit Turkey on Wednesday and join the planned talks there with Zelenskiy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 09:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian foreign minister says UN vote is 'first step towards peace'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-foreign-minister-says-un-vote-first-step-towards-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-foreign-minister-says-un-vote-first-step-towards-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MANILA (Reuters) -Palestinian Foreign Minister Varsen Aghabekian Shahin said on Tuesday the U.N. Security Council's adoption of a resolution endorsing U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the war in Gaza was a necessary first step on a long road toward peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Security Council on Monday adopted the U.S.-drafted resolution, which also authorises a multinational security force to be deployed to Gaza and imposes an international guardian mechanism for the territory ravaged by two years of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 08:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesia welcomes UN Security Council's adoption of Trump's Gaza plan, ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/indonesia-welcomes-un-security-councils-adoption-trumps-gaza-plan-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/indonesia-welcomes-un-security-councils-adoption-trumps-gaza-plan-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JAKARTA (Reuters) -Indonesia welcomes the UN Security Council's adoption of a U.S.-drafted resolution endorsing President Donald Trump's plan to end the war in Gaza and establish an international stabilisation force, the foreign ministry said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Monday, foreign ministry spokesperson Yvonne Mewengkang said it welcomed the resolution and stressed the importance of every party's involvement in it, "especially the Palestinian Authority".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 07:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump to welcome Saudi crown prince with offer of fighter jets, business deals</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-welcome-saudi-crown-prince-offer-fighter-jets-business-deals</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-welcome-saudi-crown-prince-offer-fighter-jets-business-deals</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steve Holland, Matt Spetalnick and Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump will roll out the red carpet for Saudi Arabia's de facto ruler, Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman, on Tuesday for a visit expected to advance the sale of F-35 fighter jets and a host of business deals with the kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It will be the first trip by bin Salman, widely known as MBS, to the U.S. since the 2018 killing of Saudi critic Jamal Khashoggi by Saudi agents in Istanbul, which triggered global outrage.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 06:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>