<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Dublin council delays vote on removing former Israeli president's name from park</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/dublin-council-delays-vote-removing-former-israeli-presidents-name-park</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/dublin-council-delays-vote-removing-former-israeli-presidents-name-park</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBLIN, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Dublin City Council has delayed a decision on whether to remove the name of a former Israeli president from a park amid a heated debate on whether the change would be justified or would represent an attack on the area's Jewish community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supporters of the move say the name of Chaim Herzog, who was raised in Dublin and served as president of Israel from 1983 to 1993, should be removed as an act of solidarity with Palestinians, citing Herzog's time in Israeli military intelligence and as military governor of the West Bank.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 16:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi PIF eyes $27B Japan portfolio as kingdom courts Asian investment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</guid><description>Saudi Arabia is strengthening economic ties with Asian countries as it pursues its economic transformation goals.</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 14:01:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi PIF eyes $27B Japan portfolio as kingdom courts Asian investment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</guid><description>Saudi Arabia is strengthening economic ties with Asian countries as it pursues its economic transformation goals.</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 14:01:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi PIF eyes $27B Japan portfolio as kingdom courts Asian investment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</guid><description>Saudi Arabia is strengthening economic ties with Asian countries as it pursues its economic transformation goals.</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 14:01:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi PIF eyes $27B Japan portfolio as kingdom courts Asian investment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-pif-eyes-27b-japan-portfolio-kingdom-courts-asian-investment</guid><description>Saudi Arabia is strengthening economic ties with Asian countries as it pursues its economic transformation goals.</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 14:01:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu appears in court after pardon request backed by Trump</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israels-netanyahu-appears-court-after-pardon-request-backed-trump</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israels-netanyahu-appears-court-after-pardon-request-backed-trump</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu appeared in court on Monday for the first time since asking the country's president for a pardon in his long-running corruption trial, a move backed by close ally U.S. President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opposition politicians have come out against the request, with some arguing that any pardon should be conditional on Netanyahu retiring from politics and admitting guilt. Others have said the prime minister must first call national elections, which are due by October 2026, before requesting any pardon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 12:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-Netanyahu's corruption trial divides Israeli public</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/explainer-netanyahus-corruption-trial-divides-israeli-public</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/explainer-netanyahus-corruption-trial-divides-israeli-public</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 1 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu took the stand on Monday for the first time since asking the country's president for a pardon in his long-running corruption trial.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is what you need to know about the charges that have divided the Israeli public at a time of Middle East turmoil. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHAT ARE THE CHARGES?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netanyahu was indicted in 2019 on charges of bribery, fraud and breach of trust - all of which Netanyahu denies. The trial began in 2020 and involves three criminal cases.He denies the charges and has pleaded not guilty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CASE 4000&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 12:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ICC chief says US sanctions won't change court's handling of cases</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/icc-chief-says-us-sanctions-wont-change-courts-handling-cases</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/icc-chief-says-us-sanctions-wont-change-courts-handling-cases</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;THE HAGUE, Dec 1 (Reuters) - The president of the International Criminal Court said on Monday U.S. sanctions imposed on senior court officials disrupt their personal lives but vowed the institution would not yield to outside pressure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump's administration slapped targeted sanctions on nine ICC officials, including prosecutors and judges, earlier this year in retaliation for investigations into suspected Israeli war crimes. Sources have said Washington is also mulling sanctions against the entire court.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 12:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Norway government budget in peril over oil, wealth fund's Israel investments</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/norway-government-budget-peril-over-oil-wealth-funds-israel-investments</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/norway-government-budget-peril-over-oil-wealth-funds-israel-investments</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;OSLO, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Norway's minority Labour government failed to win backing for its 2026 draft budget by an end-November deadline but talks will resume in parliament to find a compromise over oil drilling and the wealth fund's Israeli investments, a negotiator said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Norwegian parliament is due to vote on the budget on Friday, and Prime Minister Jonas Gahr Stoere could be forced to call a vote of confidence if no agreement is reached by then, putting his cabinet on the line.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 10:01:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Landmine casualties hit 4-year high as states exit ban treaty</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/landmine-casualties-hit-4-year-high-states-exit-ban-treaty</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/landmine-casualties-hit-4-year-high-states-exit-ban-treaty</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Deaths and injuries from landmines and unexploded ordnance hit a four-year high in 2024, driven by conflicts in Syria and Myanmar as well as European countries moving to withdraw from the treaty banning their use, a new report showed on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 6,000 incidents were recorded last year, including 1,945 deaths and 4,325 injuries - the highest annual total since 2020, according to the Landmine Monitor 2025 report. Nearly 90% were civilians, with almost half women and children.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope pushes peace message on second day in crisis-hit Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pope-pushes-peace-message-second-day-crisis-hit-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pope-pushes-peace-message-second-day-crisis-hit-lebanon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Pope Leo will meet with leaders from Lebanon's diverse religious sects on Monday, where he is expected to urge them not to flee the country despite years of conflict, political paralysis and economic crisis that have prompted waves of migration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leo, the first U.S. pope, will visit Lebanon's Christian community before hosting an inter-religious dialogue with members of Lebanon's Sunni Muslim, Shi'ite Muslim and Druze communities, as well as migrant workers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ex-officer tells inquiry UK military committed war crimes in Afghanistan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ex-officer-tells-inquiry-uk-military-committed-war-crimes-afghanistan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ex-officer-tells-inquiry-uk-military-committed-war-crimes-afghanistan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michael Holden&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Dec 1 (Reuters) - A former senior British officer has told a public inquiry that British special forces in Afghanistan appeared to commit war crimes by executing suspects and despite widespread knowledge in the chain of command nothing was done.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Britain's defence ministry (MoD) ordered the inquiry after a BBC TV documentary reported that soldiers from the elite Special Air Service (SAS) had killed 54 people during the war in Afghanistan more than a decade ago in suspicious circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 07:36:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope prays for peace in Lebanon and the region</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-prays-peace-lebanon-and-region</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-prays-peace-lebanon-and-region</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo XIV prayed for peace in Lebanon and the region on Monday on day two of his trip to the multi-confessional country, with joyful Lebanese welcoming the pontiff at two famous pilgrimage sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of people cheered, ululated and threw rice in celebration as the pope travelled in the popemobile to a monastery in Annaya in the mountains north of Beirut which hosts the tomb of Saint Charbel, AFP photographers said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 01:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghan suspect in Washington shooting likely radicalized in US: security official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghan-suspect-washington-shooting-likely-radicalized-us-security-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghan-suspect-washington-shooting-likely-radicalized-us-security-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Afghan suspect in the shooting of two National Guard members in Washington may have been radicalized after entering the US, Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said when questioned about his motive on Sunday talk shows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rahmanullah Lakanwal, 29, faces a first-degree murder charge in the November 26 shooting that left a 20-year-old guardsman dead and another critically wounded.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I will say we believe he was radicalized since he's been here in this country," Noem said on NBC's "Meet the Press." &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 17:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo: Palestinian state 'only' solution to Israeli conflict</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-palestinian-state-only-solution-israeli-conflict</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-palestinian-state-only-solution-israeli-conflict</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ABOARD THE PAPAL FLIGHT TO BEIRUT, Nov 30 (Reuters) - Pope Leo said on Sunday that the only solution in the decades-long conflict between Israel and the Palestinian people must include a Palestinian state, reaffirming the Vatican's position.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We all know that at this time Israel still does not accept that solution, but we see it as the only solution," Leo, the first U.S. pope, told journalists on a flight from Turkey to Lebanon during his first in-flight press conference.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 15:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>National Guard shooting suspect radicalized in US, homeland secretary says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/national-guard-shooting-suspect-radicalized-us-homeland-secretary-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/national-guard-shooting-suspect-radicalized-us-homeland-secretary-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ted Hesson and Jasper Ward&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Nov 30 (Reuters) - U.S. authorities believe the Afghan immigrant accused of ambushing National Guard members in Washington, D.C., was not radicalized until after he came to the United States, Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking on NBC's "Meet the Press" and ABC’s "This Week," Noem said authorities think that alleged shooter Rahmanullah Lakanwal was already living in Washington state when he became radicalized. Investigators are seeking more information from family members and others, Noem said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 15:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PKK urges Turkey to free Ocalan to advance peace process</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pkk-urges-turkey-free-ocalan-advance-peace-process</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pkk-urges-turkey-free-ocalan-advance-peace-process</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A senior Kurdistan Workers' Party commander told AFP the group will take no further steps in the peace process with Turkey, urging it to advance negotiations and free PKK founder Abdullah Ocalan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"All the steps the leader Apo has initiated have been implemented... there will be no further actions taken," commander Amed Malazgirt told AFP on Saturday in a bunker in the Qandil mountains in northern Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"From now on, we will be waiting for the Turkish state and they have to be the one taking steps," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The group has two demands, he added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 14:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu seeks pardon in corruption cases</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israels-netanyahu-seeks-pardon-corruption-cases</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israels-netanyahu-seeks-pardon-corruption-cases</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, on trial facing corruption charges, announced Sunday he had submitted a pardon request, saying the long-running cases were tearing the country apart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump wrote to Israeli President Isaac Herzog earlier this month, asking him to pardon Netanyahu, who has repeatedly denied wrongdoing in the proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The trial in my case has been ongoing for nearly six years, and is expected to continue for many more years," Netanyahu said in a video statement, without admitting guilt.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 12:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu officially asks Israeli president for pardon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-officially-asks-israeli-president-pardon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-officially-asks-israeli-president-pardon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nov 30 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has submitted an official request for his pardon to Israeli President Isaac Herzog, the Israeli president's office said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The Office of the President is aware that this is an extraordinary request which carries with it significant implications. After receiving all of the relevant opinions, the President will responsibly and sincerely consider the request," Herzog's office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no immediate comment from the prime minister's office.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope urges Lebanese to embrace reconciliation, stay in crisis-hit country</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-urges-lebanese-embrace-reconciliation-stay-crisis-hit-country</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-urges-lebanese-embrace-reconciliation-stay-crisis-hit-country</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Visiting Pope Leo XIV urged the Lebanese people on Sunday to embrace reconciliation and remain in their crisis-hit country, while calling on its leaders to put themselves fully at the service of their citizens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pope, bearing what he described as a message of peace, had previously visited Turkey, where he kicked off his first overseas tour since being elected leader of the world's 1.4 billion Catholics in May.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long hailed as a model of coexistence, multi-confessional Lebanon is nonetheless plagued by sectarian and political rifts, and has seen waves of emigration.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>