<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Two CMA CGM vessels navigate the Suez Canal in sign of easing tension</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/two-cma-cgm-vessels-navigate-suez-canal-sign-easing-tension</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/two-cma-cgm-vessels-navigate-suez-canal-sign-easing-tension</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Dec 23 (Reuters) - Two vessels from CMA CGM, the world's third-largest container shipping line, have travelled through the Suez Canal, the authority that runs the waterway said on Tuesday, in a sign the disruptions linked to the Gaza war could be easing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the Suez Canal provides the fastest link between Asia and Europe, since November 2023, shipping companies have had to take much longer routes because Yemen's Iran-aligned Houthi militants attacked commercial vessels, saying they were acting in solidarity with Palestinians during warfare in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 14:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US 'not satisfied' with M23 withdrawal from Congo town, official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-not-satisfied-m23-withdrawal-congo-town-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-not-satisfied-m23-withdrawal-congo-town-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 23 (Reuters) - The Trump administration is not satisfied with the Rwanda-backed M23's withdrawal from a strategic town in eastern Congo, a senior U.S. official told Reuters, as residents reported persistent clashes nearby on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;M23 seized the town of Uvira, near the border with Burundi, on December 10, days after Congolese President Felix Tshisekedi and Rwandan leader Paul Kagame met President Donald Trump in Washington and reaffirmed a U.S.-brokered peace deal.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 14:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli defence minister vows military to remain in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israeli-defence-minister-vows-military-remain-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israeli-defence-minister-vows-military-remain-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 23 (Reuters) - Israeli Defence Minister Israel Katz said on Tuesday that the military would never fully withdraw from the Gaza Strip for security reasons and that a civilian-military army unit would be established in the Palestinian enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a U.S.-backed peace plan signed by both Israel and Hamas in October, the Israeli military will gradually withdraw completely from the coastal enclave and Israel will not re-establish civilian settlements in the coastal territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Lavrov to meet Syrian counterpart for talks in Moscow, TASS cites foreign ministry</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/russias-lavrov-meet-syrian-counterpart-talks-moscow-tass-cites-foreign-ministry</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/russias-lavrov-meet-syrian-counterpart-talks-moscow-tass-cites-foreign-ministry</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Dec 23 (Reuters) - Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov will hold talks with his Syrian counterpart Asaad Al-Shaibani in Moscow on Tuesday, the TASS state news agency reported, citing ministry spokeswoman Maria Zakharova.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Reuters; Writing by Gleb Stolyarov; Editing by Andrew Osborn)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greta Thunberg arrested at pro-Palestinian protest in London, campaign group says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/greta-thunberg-arrested-pro-palestinian-protest-london-campaign-group-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/greta-thunberg-arrested-pro-palestinian-protest-london-campaign-group-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Dec 23 (Reuters) - British police arrested Swedish activist Greta Thunberg in London on Tuesday at a pro-Palestinian protest, UK-based campaign group Defend Our Juries said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thunberg was arrested under the Terrorism Act for holding a sign that said she supported prisoners linked to Palestine Action, an organisation which the British government has proscribed as a terrorist group, Defend Our Juries said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A City of London spokesperson said two people had been arrested for throwing red paint on a building. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sinkholes in Turkey's agricultural heartland fuel farmers' concerns</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/sinkholes-turkeys-agricultural-heartland-fuel-farmers-concerns</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/sinkholes-turkeys-agricultural-heartland-fuel-farmers-concerns</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ali Kucukgocmen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KONYA, Turkey, Dec 23 (Reuters) - Hundreds of sinkholes have emerged in Turkey's central agricultural region due to dwindling rainfall and receding groundwaters, causing concern among farmers and environmental experts who see it as a worrying sign of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gaping sinkholes pockmark farmland producing maize, wheat and sugar beet in Karapinar in Konya province, with more than 10 packed into a field in places. In mountainous areas, vast, ancient sinkholes previously filled with water have now mostly dried up.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 11:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia invites Israeli President Herzog for official visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australia-invites-israeli-president-herzog-official-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australia-invites-israeli-president-herzog-official-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 23 (Reuters) - Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese said on Tuesday he called Israeli President Isaac Herzog and invited him to visit Australia, expressing his shock and dismay over the attack at the Jewish community Chanukah event on Bondi Beach last week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herzog said he would accept the invitation and mentioned that the President of the Zionist Federation of Australia also sent him an official invitation expressing their wish for him to visit, and he intends to do so, Albanese said in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 09:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gazans fear renewed displacement after Israeli strikes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gazans-fear-renewed-displacement-after-israeli-strikes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gazans-fear-renewed-displacement-after-israeli-strikes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When her children, trembling with fear, ask where the family can go to escape Israel's continued bombardment in southern Gaza's Khan Yunis area, Umm Ahmed has no answer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In her small, devastated village near Khan Yunis city, recent Israeli drone and artillery strikes shattered the tenuous sense of peace delivered by a ceasefire that has largely held since October 10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Residents say the strikes have targeted neighbourhoods east of the so-called Yellow Line -- a demarcation established under the truce between Israel and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 03:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US Heritage Foundation thinktank staff quit amid antisemitism controversy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-heritage-foundation-thinktank-staff-quit-amid-antisemitism-controversy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-heritage-foundation-thinktank-staff-quit-amid-antisemitism-controversy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Andrew Hay&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dec 22 (Reuters) - Over a dozen employees have left jobs at the Heritage Foundation or were fired in recent days, according to the influential right-wing U.S. thinktank, as it grapples with allegations from former supporters that it has aligned itself with those accused of antisemitism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a statement about the resignations and firings on Monday, Heritage Foundation Chief Advancement Officer Andy Olivastro said a handful of staff had chosen "disruption" and "disloyalty."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 23:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian state set to pass tougher gun laws after Bondi attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australian-state-set-pass-tougher-gun-laws-after-bondi-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australian-state-set-pass-tougher-gun-laws-after-bondi-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Renju Jose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Dec 23 (Reuters) - Australia's most populous state is set to pass tougher gun laws, ban the display of terrorist symbols and curb protests after the state parliament's lower house cleared a bill late on Monday in an emergency sitting following the Bondi mass shooting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The terrorism and other legislation amendment bill won support from the opposition Liberal Party in New South Wales state, and is expected to clear the upper house on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 23:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deadly clashes in Aleppo as Turkey urges Kurds not to be obstacle to Syria's stability</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/deadly-clashes-aleppo-turkey-urges-kurds-not-be-obstacle-syrias-stability</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/deadly-clashes-aleppo-turkey-urges-kurds-not-be-obstacle-syrias-stability</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Syrian government and Kurdish-led forces on Monday ordered their fighters to cease fire following deadly clashes that came as Turkey's top diplomat urged the Kurds to integrate into the Syrian army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At least three people were killed in the clashes, which came ahead of a deadline for implementing a March 10 agreement between Damascus and the Kurds to integrate the SDF -- which controls vast swathes of Syria's oil-rich northeast -- into the state.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 21:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At least two civilians killed in Aleppo violence as Syrian government, SDF trade blame</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/least-two-civilians-killed-aleppo-violence-syrian-government-sdf-trade-blame</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/least-two-civilians-killed-aleppo-violence-syrian-government-sdf-trade-blame</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 22 (Reuters) - At least two civilians were killed and several wounded in a wave of attacks in the northern Syrian city of Aleppo on Monday, with government forces and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces trading blame for the deaths.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Syrian health ministry said two people were killed and several were wounded in shelling by the SDF on residential neighbourhoods in the city. The injuries included two children and two civil defense workers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 20:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu to discuss Iran, next phase of Gaza plan with Trump</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-discuss-iran-next-phase-gaza-plan-trump</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-discuss-iran-next-phase-gaza-plan-trump</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emily Rose, Michele Kambas and Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 22 (Reuters) - Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said on Monday he will discuss Iran's nuclear activities during his visit next week with U.S. President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a joint press conference with Greek Prime Minister Kyriakos Mitsotakis and Cypriot President Nikos Christodoulides in Jerusalem, Netanyahu said Israel was aware Iran had been conducting "exercises" recently, without elaborating.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 20:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria seizes anti-aircraft missiles near Iraqi border: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</guid><description>The Syrian government is stepping up efforts to combat arms smuggling, including in relation to Hezbollah, Kurdish-led forces and ISIS.</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 19:03:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria seizes anti-aircraft missiles near Iraqi border: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</guid><description>The Syrian government is stepping up efforts to combat arms smuggling, including in relation to Hezbollah, Kurdish-led forces and ISIS.</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 19:03:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria seizes anti-aircraft missiles near Iraqi border: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</guid><description>The Syrian government is stepping up efforts to combat arms smuggling, including in relation to Hezbollah, Kurdish-led forces and ISIS.</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 19:03:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria seizes anti-aircraft missiles near Iraqi border: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-seizes-anti-aircraft-missiles-near-iraqi-border-what-know</guid><description>The Syrian government is stepping up efforts to combat arms smuggling, including in relation to Hezbollah, Kurdish-led forces and ISIS.</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 19:03:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanese PM urges swift approval of law aimed at paying back depositors</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanese-pm-urges-swift-approval-law-aimed-paying-back-depositors</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanese-pm-urges-swift-approval-law-aimed-paying-back-depositors</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Dec 22 - Lebanese Prime Minister Nawaf Salam urged cabinet to swiftly approve a draft law allowing depositors to gradually recover funds frozen in the banking system since a financial collapse in 2019, a move critical to reviving the economy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The collapse - the result of decades of unsustainable financial policies, waste and corruption - led the state to default on its sovereign debt and sank the Lebanese pound.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 18:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Second Lebanon-Israel meeting sidelined France, saw US pressure on Netanyahu</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/second-lebanon-israel-meeting-sidelined-france-saw-us-pressure-netanyahu</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/second-lebanon-israel-meeting-sidelined-france-saw-us-pressure-netanyahu</guid><description>Differences over the so-called economic zone and the high civilian toll from Israeli strikes capped the second meeting between Lebanese and Israeli officials on Friday.</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 17:28:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Second Lebanon-Israel meeting sidelined France, saw US pressure on Netanyahu</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/second-lebanon-israel-meeting-sidelined-france-saw-us-pressure-netanyahu</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/second-lebanon-israel-meeting-sidelined-france-saw-us-pressure-netanyahu</guid><description>Differences over the so-called economic zone and the high civilian toll from Israeli strikes capped the second meeting between Lebanese and Israeli officials on Friday.</description><pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 17:28:55 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>