<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Germany open to deepening ties with Syrian government, says Berlin</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germany-open-deepening-ties-syrian-government-says-berlin</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germany-open-deepening-ties-syrian-government-says-berlin</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Germany is open to deepening relations with the new Syrian government, a German government spokesperson said, adding that Berlin is closely monitoring the situation in the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The German government is, of course, open to deepening relations and a fresh start with the new Syrian government," said the spokesperson at regular government press conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spokesperson added that Berlin is closely monitoring the situation in the Syrian city of Aleppo, where deadly clashes broke out recently, also in close consultation with Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Lavrov says the U.S. is smashing the world around with its raid on Venezuela and threats to Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russias-lavrov-says-us-smashing-world-around-its-raid-venezuela-and-threats-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russias-lavrov-says-us-smashing-world-around-its-raid-venezuela-and-threats-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov said on Wednesday that the United States was fragmenting the very international system which Washington helped to create by undertaking what he said was an illegal operation to topple Venezuelan leader Nicolas Maduro and by threatening Iran with attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are talking about a gross violation of international law," Lavrov said of the U.S. operation to capture Maduro. He added that Russia remained committed to its agreements with Venezuela, a Russian ally.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Where are the main US military bases in the Middle East?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/where-are-main-us-military-bases-middle-east</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/where-are-main-us-military-bases-middle-east</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 14 (Reuters) - Following are the significant military bases in the Middle East. Iran has threatened to strike U.S. bases in the region if attacked by Washington, after U.S. President Donald Trump told Iranians to keep protesting and declared "help is on the way".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAHRAIN:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Home to the headquarters of the U.S. Navy's Fifth Fleet, whose area of responsibility includes the Gulf, Red Sea, Arabian Sea and parts of the Indian Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QATAR:&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kazakhstan urges Europe and US to help secure oil transport after CPC attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kazakhstan-urges-europe-and-us-help-secure-oil-transport-after-cpc-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kazakhstan-urges-europe-and-us-help-secure-oil-transport-after-cpc-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Kazakhstan has urged Europe and the U.S. to help secure the transport of oil following drone attacks on tankers heading to a Black Sea terminal, the Central Asian country's foreign ministry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministry said in a statement that it made the request during meetings with ambassadors from several European countries, as well as U.S. representatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK prosecutors try to reinstate terrorism charge against Kneecap rapper</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uk-prosecutors-try-reinstate-terrorism-charge-against-kneecap-rapper</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uk-prosecutors-try-reinstate-terrorism-charge-against-kneecap-rapper</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 14 (Reuters) - British prosecutors sought to reinstate a terrorism charge against a member of Irish rap group Kneecap on Wednesday for displaying a flag of Iran-backed Lebanese militia Hezbollah at a London gig, after a court threw out the case last year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Liam Óg Ó hAnnaidh, whose stage name is Mo Chara, was accused of having waved the flag of the banned militant group Hezbollah during a November 2024 gig.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US expected to unveil post-war Gaza leadership, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-expected-unveil-post-war-gaza-leadership-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-expected-unveil-post-war-gaza-leadership-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 14 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump is expected on Wednesday to push ahead with his phased plan for Gaza's future by announcing the administration that will run the war-ravaged Palestinian territory, four Palestinian sources said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel and Hamas in October signed off on Trump's 20-point plan which says that a technocratic Palestinian body overseen by an international "Board of Peace" is meant to govern Gaza for a transitional period. It is not to include Hamas representation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's Revolutionary Guards point to battle readiness and increased missile stockpiles, state media says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-revolutionary-guards-point-battle-readiness-and-increased-missile</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-revolutionary-guards-point-battle-readiness-and-increased-missile</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Iran's stockpile of missiles has increased since a 12-day war with Israel last year, Revolutionary Guards' Aerospace Commander Majid Mousavi said on Wednesday according to state media, following U.S. President Donald Trump's threats of intervention amid anti-government protests in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are at the peak of our readiness," Mousavi was quoted as saying by state media, adding that wartime damages had been repaired and output in various areas by the guards' aerospace forces was higher than before June 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 11:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Some personnel were advised to leave U.S. military base in Qatar, diplomats tell Reuters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/some-personnel-were-advised-leave-us-military-base-qatar-diplomats-tell-reuters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/some-personnel-were-advised-leave-us-military-base-qatar-diplomats-tell-reuters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DOHA, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Some personnel were advised to leave the U.S. military's Al Udeid Air Base in Qatar by Wednesday evening, three diplomats told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. embassy in Doha had no immediate comment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al Udeid is the Middle East's largest U.S. base housing around 10,000 troops. Ahead of the U.S. air strikes on Iran in June some personnel were moved off U.S. bases in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Andrew Mills, Editing by Edmund Blair)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria asks Lebanon to hand over Assad-era officers after Reuters report</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-asks-lebanon-hand-over-assad-era-officers-after-reuters-report</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-asks-lebanon-hand-over-assad-era-officers-after-reuters-report</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Feras Dalatey  and Maya Gebeily&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Syrian authorities have asked Lebanese security forces to hand over more than 200 senior officers who fled to Lebanon after the fall of Bashar al-Assad, following a Reuters investigation that showed how the neighboring country was a hub for insurgent plotting.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Death toll from Iran approaches 2,600, rights group reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/death-toll-iran-approaches-2600-rights-group-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/death-toll-iran-approaches-2600-rights-group-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nayera Abdallah and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI/JERUSALEM, Jan 14 (Reuters) - The death toll from unrest in Iran climbed to almost 2,600, a rights group said on Wednesday, as Tehran stepped up diplomatic contacts with U.S.-allies in the region over a crisis that has drawn threats of intervention from President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to an Israeli assessment, Trump has decided to intervene but the scope and timing of this action remains unclear, an Israeli official said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran vows fast trials over protests after Trump threat</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-vows-fast-trials-over-protests-after-trump-threat</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-vows-fast-trials-over-protests-after-trump-threat</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran on Wednesday vowed fast-track trials for people arrested over a massive wave of protests, after US President Donald Trump threatened "very strong action" if the Islamic republic goes ahead with hangings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Tehran, authorities held a funeral ceremony for over 100 members of the security forces and other "martyrs" killed in the demonstrations, which authorities have branded as "riots" while accusing protesters of waging "acts of terror".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>George Vassiliou, 'eternal optimist' president who led Cyprus into the EU, dies at 94</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/george-vassiliou-eternal-optimist-president-who-led-cyprus-eu-dies-94</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/george-vassiliou-eternal-optimist-president-who-led-cyprus-eu-dies-94</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michele Kambas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NICOSIA, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Former Cyprus President George Vassiliou, who died on Wednesday aged 94, once risked arrest in Cold War Hungary smuggling a banned political manifesto past the Iron Curtain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1956, as Soviet tanks crushed a popular uprising in Budapest, he agreed to carry to the West the document, one of the anonymous "Hungaricus" pamphlets that gave the outside world its first uncensored accounts of the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 07:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French foreign minister: Iran crackdown could be most violent in its contemporary history</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-foreign-minister-iran-crackdown-could-be-most-violent-its-contemporary</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-foreign-minister-iran-crackdown-could-be-most-violent-its-contemporary</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Jan 14 (Reuters) - France suspects that Iran's crackdown on demonstrations across the country is the most violent in the country's contemporary history, French Foreign Minister Jean-Noel Barrot said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"What we suspect is that this is the most violent repression in Iran's contemporary history and that it must absolutely stop," Barrot said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Benoit Van Overstraeten and John Irish;Editing by Louise Rasmussen)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 07:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At least 2,571 killed in Iran's protests, US-based rights group HRANA says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/least-2571-killed-irans-protests-us-based-rights-group-hrana-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/least-2571-killed-irans-protests-us-based-rights-group-hrana-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 14 (Reuters) - The death toll from protests in Iran has reached 2,571 people, the U.S.-based HRANA rights group said on Wednesday, as the Islamic Republic's clerical rulers face the biggest wave of dissent in years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump urged Iranians on Tuesday to keep protesting, promising help is on the way. Iranian officials, however, have accused U.S. and Israel of fuelling violence in the country and blamed the deaths on "terrorist operatives" receiving foreign guidance to instigate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 06:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Far-right group targeting pro-Palestinian voices to close New York operation, NY AG says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/far-right-group-targeting-pro-palestinian-voices-close-new-york-operation-ny-ag</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/far-right-group-targeting-pro-palestinian-voices-close-new-york-operation-ny-ag</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 13 (Reuters) - New York Attorney General Letitia James' office said on Tuesday it reached a settlement with Betar US that would wind down the far-right Zionist group's New York operations after an investigation found the group intimidated pro-Palestinian activists.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 04:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>West Bank Bedouin community driven out by Israeli settler violence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-bedouin-community-driven-out-israeli-settler-violence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-bedouin-community-driven-out-israeli-settler-violence</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;With heavy hearts, Bedouins in a West Bank village dismantle their sheep pens and load belongings onto trucks, forced from their homes in the Israeli-occupied territory by rising settler violence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While attacks by Israeli settlers affect communities across the West Bank, the semi-nomadic Bedouins are among the territory's most vulnerable, saying they suffer from forced displacement due in large part to a lack of law enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 04:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>2025 was third hottest year on record: EU, US experts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/2025-was-third-hottest-year-record-eu-us-experts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/2025-was-third-hottest-year-record-eu-us-experts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The planet logged its third hottest year on record in 2025, extending a run of unprecedented heat, with no relief expected in 2026, US researchers and EU climate monitors said Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last 11 years have now been the warmest ever recorded, with 2024 topping the podium and 2023 in second place, according to the EU's Copernicus Climate Change Service and Berkeley Earth, a California-based non-profit research organisation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 03:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brunei sultan to undergo knee replacement surgery</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/brunei-sultan-undergo-knee-replacement-surgery</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/brunei-sultan-undergo-knee-replacement-surgery</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BANDAR SERI BEGAWAN, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Brunei's ruler Sultan Hassanal Bolkiah will undergo knee replacement surgery this weekend, with a recovery period expected to last between two to three months, his office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 79-year-old sultan, one of the world's longest-reigning monarchs, will be limiting his presence at national and official ceremonies during the recovery process for rest and physiotherapy sessions, the office said in a statement on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 02:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump vows 'very strong action' if Iran hangs protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-vows-very-strong-action-if-iran-hangs-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-vows-very-strong-action-if-iran-hangs-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump said Tuesday that the United States would react strongly if authorities in Iran started hanging people in their crackdown on a popular uprising against the government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We will take very strong action if they do such a thing," he told CBS News in an interview, when asked about hangings potentially beginning on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"When they start killing thousands of people -- and now you're telling me about hanging. We'll see how that's going to work out for them," Trump said in a video clip released online.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 22:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US will take 'very strong action' if Iran hangs protesters, Trump tells CBS News</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-will-take-very-strong-action-if-iran-hangs-protesters-trump-tells-cbs-news</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-will-take-very-strong-action-if-iran-hangs-protesters-trump-tells-cbs-news</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 13 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump said on Tuesday the United States would take "very strong action" if the Iranian government starts hanging protesters, but did not elaborate on what those actions would be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I haven't heard about the hanging. If they hang them, you're going to see some things... We will take very strong action if they do such a thing," Trump told CBS News in an interview. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Bhargav Acharya in Toronto;)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 21:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>