<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Palestinian coach gets hope, advice from mum in Gaza tent</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/palestinian-coach-gets-hope-advice-mum-gaza-tent</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/palestinian-coach-gets-hope-advice-mum-gaza-tent</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Coach Ehab Abu Jazar is guiding a national team that carries on its shoulders all the hopes and sorrows of Palestinian football, but it is his mother, forced by war to live in a Gaza tent, who is his main inspiration and motivation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The war that broke out following Hamas's unprecedented attack on Israel on October 7, 2023 put an end to Palestinian league matches, and left athletes in exile fearing for their loved ones in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 10:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Jerusalem, Merz reaffirms Germany's support for Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/jerusalem-merz-reaffirms-germanys-support-israel-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/jerusalem-merz-reaffirms-germanys-support-israel-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;German Chancellor Friedrich Merz reaffirmed Berlin's support for Israel during a visit to the Yad Vashem Holocaust memorial in Jerusalem on Sunday before talks with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Merz flew into Israel the day before for his first trip to the country since traditionally solid ties between the two nations were shaken by the Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 10:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran awaits second plane of nationals deported from US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-awaits-second-plane-nationals-deported-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-awaits-second-plane-nationals-deported-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 7 (Reuters) - Fifty-five Iranians deported from the United States will return to their home country in the coming days, Iran's foreign ministry said on Sunday, in the second such deportation under President Donald Trump's immigration crackdown. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In September, officials said the U.S. had identified about 400 Iranians to be deported, with a first flight carrying 120 people making its way to Tehran via Qatar's capital. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 10:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bethlehem Christmas tree lit up for first time since Gaza war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/bethlehem-christmas-tree-lit-first-time-gaza-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/bethlehem-christmas-tree-lit-first-time-gaza-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Christmas cheer returned to the traditional birthplace of Jesus Christ on Saturday as Bethlehem in the occupied West Bank lit up a tree for the first time since the war in Gaza began over two years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Covered in red and gold baubles, the Christmas tree standing metres away from the Church of the Nativity on Manger Square has become a symbol of hope.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of a two-hour ceremony, the tree was illuminated to cheers, its yellow lights twinkling and a bright red star on top shining against the clouded night sky irradiated by a luminescent, almost full moon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 21:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hundreds in Tunisia protest against government</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hundreds-tunisia-protest-against-government</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hundreds-tunisia-protest-against-government</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of people demonstrated on Saturday in the Tunisian capital against the government under the slogan "opposition is not a crime", calling for the release of jailed activists.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rally in Tunis was called after the recent arrests of three opposition figures convicted of "conspiracy" against the state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tunisia emerged from the Arab Spring era of revolts as a democracy but, after Saied staged a sweeping power grab in 2021, rights groups have criticised a major rollback on freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 21:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Christmas lights return to Bethlehem, Palestinians look for hope</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/christmas-lights-return-bethlehem-palestinians-look-hope</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/christmas-lights-return-bethlehem-palestinians-look-hope</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BETHLEHEM, West Bank, Dec 6 (Reuters) - A giant Christmas tree adorned with red and gold baubles stands in the West Bank city of Bethlehem for the first time since 2022.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian city, revered by Christians as the birthplace of Jesus, had refrained from public Christmas celebrations over the past two years as war raged in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But as a precarious ceasefire in Gaza enters its second month, the city held a ceremony on Saturday night, lighting up the 20-metre tree at the edge of Manger Square.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 19:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisians step up protests against Saied's crackdown on opposition</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/tunisians-step-protests-against-saieds-crackdown-opposition</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/tunisians-step-protests-against-saieds-crackdown-opposition</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS, Dec 6 (Reuters) - Tunisians took to the streets on Saturday for a third straight week to protest against President Kais Saied's expanding crackdown on the opposition, critics and NGOs, urging the release of political prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protests against Saied are growing as rights groups accuse him of using the judiciary and police to suppress opponents and to cement an autocratic one-man rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saied denies having become a dictator or using the judiciary against opponents.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 16:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council delegation urges all sides to stick to Lebanon truce</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-security-council-delegation-urges-all-sides-stick-lebanon-truce</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-security-council-delegation-urges-all-sides-stick-lebanon-truce</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A United Nations Security Council delegation on Saturday urged all parties to uphold a year-old ceasefire between Israel and Hezbollah, expressing support for a state weapons monopoly at the end of a Lebanon visit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A November 2024 ceasefire was supposed to end more than a year of hostilities between Israel and Hezbollah militants, but Israel has kept up strikes on Lebanon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel has mainly said it is targeting the Iran-backed group, and has maintained troops in five south Lebanon areas it deems strategic.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 16:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says Gaza administration, police force should come before Hamas disarmament in ceasefire deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-says-gaza-administration-police-force-should-come-hamas-disarmament</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-says-gaza-administration-police-force-should-come-hamas-disarmament</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DOHA, Dec 6 (Reuters) - Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan told Reuters on Saturday that a credible Palestinian civil administration and a vetted, trained police force should be in place to allow Hamas to disarm, saying the group is prepared to hand over governance of the enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview on the sidelines of the Doha Forum, Fidan said that without those initial steps, expecting Hamas to disarm in the first phase of the ceasefire deal is neither "realistic nor doable."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 14:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mediators Qatar, Egypt call for next steps in Gaza truce</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/mediators-qatar-egypt-call-next-steps-gaza-truce</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/mediators-qatar-egypt-call-next-steps-gaza-truce</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Qatar and Egypt, guarantors of the Gaza ceasefire, called on Saturday for the withdrawal of Israeli troops and the deployment of an international stabilisation force as the necessary next steps in fully implementing the fragile agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The measures were spelt out in the US- and UN-backed peace plan that has largely halted fighting, though the warring parties have yet to agree on how to move forward from the deal's first phase. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 13:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey, US will find way of removing CAATSA sanctions 'very soon', Turkish FM says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-us-will-find-way-removing-caatsa-sanctions-very-soon-turkish-fm-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-us-will-find-way-removing-caatsa-sanctions-very-soon-turkish-fm-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DOHA, Dec 6 (Reuters) - Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan told Reuters on Saturday that he believed Turkey and the United States would find a way to remove U.S. CAATSA sanctions "very soon", and added the NATO allies had started working on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washington removed Ankara from its advanced F-35 fighter jet programme and imposed the sanctions in 2020 over its acquisition of Russian S-400 air defence systems. Turkey has called the move unjust, and voiced hope that the sides could overcome the issue during President Donald Trump's second term.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egyptian actor faces challenge in iconic role of singer Umm Kulthum</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/egyptian-actor-faces-challenge-iconic-role-singer-umm-kulthum</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/egyptian-actor-faces-challenge-iconic-role-singer-umm-kulthum</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It took Egyptian actor Mona Zaki more than a year's preparation to take on the hardest role of her career -- the iconic singer Umm Kulthum, a legend in the Arab world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marwan Hamed's "El Sett" ("The Lady") premiered this week at the Marrakech International Film Festival, where Zaki told AFP about the daunting task she faced.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I was very scared at the beginning," she said. "I didn't know where to start."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zaki is one of Egypt's more recognisable actors but her fears were not unfounded.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 11:30:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Jerusalem, Merz reaffirms Germany's support for Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/jerusalem-merz-reaffirms-germanys-support-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/jerusalem-merz-reaffirms-germanys-support-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;German Chancellor Friedrich Merz flew into Israel Saturday for his first visit since taking office, and reaffirmed Berlin's support after traditionally solid ties between the countries were shaken by the Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Merz landed at Tel Aviv's Ben Gurion airport just before 8:00 pm (1800 GMT) and was met by Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar, who called him "a friend of Israel". Germany, he added, was "an important partner". &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Merz met Israeli President Isaac Herzog in Jerusalem later Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 11:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'We'll bring him home': Thai family's long wait for Gaza hostage to end</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/well-bring-him-home-thai-familys-long-wait-gaza-hostage-end</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/well-bring-him-home-thai-familys-long-wait-gaza-hostage-end</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Thomas Suen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NONG KHAI, Thailand, Dec 6 (Reuters) - Two years after Thai worker Sudthisak Rinthalak was killed by Hamas militants, his family in northeastern Thailand is preparing to welcome his remains home and hold a Buddhist ceremony they believe will bring his spirit peace. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sudthisak was among 47 hostages whose bodies Hamas has returned under the current ceasefire agreement. The handover of deceased hostages was a key condition of the initial phase of the deal aimed at ending the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 09:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza talks at 'critical' moment, Qatari prime minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gaza-talks-critical-moment-qatari-prime-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gaza-talks-critical-moment-qatari-prime-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DOHA, Dec 6 (Reuters) - Qatari Prime Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman al-Thani said Saturday that negotiations on the war in Gaza were at a "critical" moment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mediators are working together to force the next phase of ceasefire forward, he said during a panel at the Doha Forum conference in Qatar.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Andrew Mills; Editing by Aidan Lewis)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 08:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia hits Afghan Taliban officials with sanctions, travel bans</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australia-hits-afghan-taliban-officials-sanctions-travel-bans</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australia-hits-afghan-taliban-officials-sanctions-travel-bans</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Dec 6 (Reuters) - Australia on Saturday imposed financial sanctions and travel bans on four officials in Afghanistan's Taliban government over what it said was a deteriorating human rights situation in the country, especially for women and girls.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Australia's Foreign Minister Penny Wong said the officials were involved "in the oppression of women and girls and in undermining good governance or the rule of law" in the Taliban-run country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 01:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada removes Syria from its list of foreign state supporters of terrorism</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/canada-removes-syria-its-list-foreign-state-supporters-terrorism</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/canada-removes-syria-its-list-foreign-state-supporters-terrorism</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;OTTAWA, Dec 5 (Reuters) - The Canadian government said on Friday that it has removed Syria from its list of foreign state supporters of terrorism and removed Hayat Tahrir al-Sham, the group that spearheaded the rebel alliance that helped oust President Bashar al-Assad, from its list of terrorist entities.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 22:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran’s new military drills near disputed islands ratchet up tensions with UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-new-military-drills-near-disputed-islands-ratchet-tensions-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-new-military-drills-near-disputed-islands-ratchet-tensions-uae</guid><description>By combining high-tech capabilities, publicized warnings to foreign vessels and historical framing of territorial sovereignty, Tehran is seeking to assertively position itself in a dispute that has resisted resolution for decades.</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 19:07:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran’s new military drills near disputed islands ratchet up tensions with UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-new-military-drills-near-disputed-islands-ratchet-tensions-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-new-military-drills-near-disputed-islands-ratchet-tensions-uae</guid><description>By combining high-tech capabilities, publicized warnings to foreign vessels and historical framing of territorial sovereignty, Tehran is seeking to assertively position itself in a dispute that has resisted resolution for decades.</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 19:07:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran’s new military drills near disputed islands ratchet up tensions with UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-new-military-drills-near-disputed-islands-ratchet-tensions-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-new-military-drills-near-disputed-islands-ratchet-tensions-uae</guid><description>By combining high-tech capabilities, publicized warnings to foreign vessels and historical framing of territorial sovereignty, Tehran is seeking to assertively position itself in a dispute that has resisted resolution for decades.</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 19:07:30 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>