<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Russia withdrawing troops from airport in northeast Syria, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-withdrawing-troops-airport-northeast-syria-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-withdrawing-troops-airport-northeast-syria-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt; (Refiles to insert dropped words in paragraph 5)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QAMISHLI, Syria, Jan 26 (Reuters) - Russia is withdrawing forces from an airport in northeastern Syria, movingto end its military presence in a corner of the country wherethe Damascus government is trying to seize control from Kurdish forces, five Syrian sources said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia has stationed forces at Qamishli airport in the northeast since 2019, a relatively small deployment compared to its air base and a naval facility on Syria's Mediterranean coast, both of which it is expected to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel retrieves last hostage body from Gaza in boost for Trump plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-retrieves-last-hostage-body-gaza-boost-trump-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-retrieves-last-hostage-body-gaza-boost-trump-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 26 (Reuters) - Israel has retrieved the remains of the last remaining hostage held in Gaza, the military said on Monday, fulfilling a key condition of the initial phase of U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the Gaza war. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The remains of police officer Ran Gvili have been identified and will be returned for burial, the military said in a statement. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>USS Abraham Lincoln carrier strike group reaches Middle Eastern waters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uss-abraham-lincoln-carrier-strike-group-reaches-middle-eastern-waters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uss-abraham-lincoln-carrier-strike-group-reaches-middle-eastern-waters</guid><description>The carrier's presence gives the White House greater options to authorize strikes deep within Iranian territory while reducing the potential risk of regional blowback.</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 13:32:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kibbutz defender Ran Gvili is Israel's last hostage killed on Oct 7</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kibbutz-defender-ran-gvili-israels-last-hostage-killed-oct-7</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kibbutz-defender-ran-gvili-israels-last-hostage-killed-oct-7</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ran Gvili, a young Israeli police officer, was on medical leave when Hamas launched its deadly attack on Israel on October 7, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Instead of staying home, the 24-year-old grabbed his personal gun and raced toward the area of the attack in southern Israel, where he fought until his last bullet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nicknamed the "Defender of Alumim" by his family and the kibbutz of that name, Gvili was killed in combat near the community and his body taken to Gaza by Hamas militants.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 13:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rights group says Iran protest toll nears 6,000 dead</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-iran-protest-toll-nears-6000-dead</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-iran-protest-toll-nears-6000-dead</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A US-based rights group said on Monday it had confirmed the deaths of nearly 6,000 people during a wave of protests in Iran suppressed by security forces, as Tehran warned Washington against intervening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests started in late December, driven by economic grievances, but turned into a mass movement against the Islamic republic, with huge street demonstrations for several days from January 8.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Appeal trial over 2020 teacher's beheading opens in France</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/appeal-trial-over-2020-teachers-beheading-opens-france</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/appeal-trial-over-2020-teachers-beheading-opens-france</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;An appeal trial opened in Paris on Monday for four men convicted over the 2020 jihadist beheading of schoolteacher Samuel Paty, a killing that horrified France.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paty, 47, was murdered in October 2020 by an 18-year-old Islamist radical of Chechen origin after showing cartoons of the Prophet Mohammed in class.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His attacker, Abdoullakh Anzorov, was killed in a shootout with police.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>German defence minister urges Trump to apologise for Afghanistan remarks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/german-defence-minister-urges-trump-apologise-afghanistan-remarks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/german-defence-minister-urges-trump-apologise-afghanistan-remarks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 26 (Reuters) - German Defence Minister Boris Pistorius has called on U.S. President Donald Trump to apologise for remarks suggesting that America's NATO allies in Afghanistan avoided frontline service, joining a chorus of criticism from European politicians and army veterans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump caused deep offence among U.S. allies when he told Fox Business Network last week that the U.S. had "never needed" the transatlantic alliance and accused allies of staying "a little off the front lines" in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rights group says confirmed Iran protest toll nears 6,000</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-confirmed-iran-protest-toll-nears-6000</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-confirmed-iran-protest-toll-nears-6000</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A US-based rights group said Monday it had confirmed the deaths of 5,848 people in a wave of protests in Iran suppressed by security forces, warning that it was still investigating thousands more potential fatalities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests started in late December sparked by economic grievances but turned into a mass movement against the Islamic republic, with huge street rallies for several days from January 8.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rights groups have accused authorities of an unprecedented crackdown by shooting directly at the protesters, and the demonstrations have, for now, petered out.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin sticks to demand that Ukraine cede all of Donbas in talks, TASS reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kremlin-sticks-demand-ukraine-cede-all-donbas-talks-tass-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kremlin-sticks-demand-ukraine-cede-all-donbas-talks-tass-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 26 (Reuters) - The Kremlin said on Monday that the issue of territory remained  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;fundamental to Russia when it came to getting a deal to end the fighting in Ukraine, the state TASS news agency reported after trilateral weekend talks in Abu Dhabi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Vladimir Putin has repeatedly said that Russia will take all of Ukraine's Donbas region - of which Moscow's forces currently control 90% - by force unless Kyiv gives it up in a peace deal. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Top Chinese officials hold talks with OIC secretary general</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/top-chinese-officials-hold-talks-oic-secretary-general</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/top-chinese-officials-hold-talks-oic-secretary-general</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIJING, Jan 26 (Reuters) - China's vice president and foreign minister held talks with the secretary-general of the 57-nation Organization of Islamic Cooperation on Monday, according to a ministry statement and the official news agency, Xinhua.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talks in the Chinese capital of Beijing come amid heightened Middle East tension after an Iranian official said the country would treat any attack "as an all-out war against us".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines lodges 'firm representations' to Chinese embassy over 'escalating' war of words on South China Sea</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/philippines-lodges-firm-representations-chinese-embassy-over-escalating-war-words</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/philippines-lodges-firm-representations-chinese-embassy-over-escalating-war-words</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MANILA, Jan 26 (Reuters) - The Philippine foreign ministry said on Monday it had made "firm representations" to China's embassy and its ambassador in Manila over what it described as an "escalation of public exchanges" between them and Philippine officials over disputes in the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel agrees to reopen Rafah crossing only for Gaza pedestrians</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-agrees-reopen-rafah-crossing-only-gaza-pedestrians</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-agrees-reopen-rafah-crossing-only-gaza-pedestrians</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel said Monday it would only allow pedestrians to travel through the Rafah crossing between Gaza and Egypt as part of its "limited reopening" once it has recovered the remains of the last hostage in the Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reopening Rafah, a vital entry point for aid into Gaza, forms part of a truce framework announced by US President Donald Trump in October, but the crossing has remained closed since Israeli forces took control of it during the war in the Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel to reopen Rafah crossing after search for last hostage body ends</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-reopen-rafah-crossing-after-search-last-hostage-body-ends</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-reopen-rafah-crossing-after-search-last-hostage-body-ends</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 25 (Reuters) - Israel will reopen Gaza's Rafah crossing with Egypt for the passage of people only after an operation to locate the body of the last remaining Israeli hostage in the enclave is completed, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said late on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Hatem Maher, editing by Deepa Babington)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 22:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Life-saving aid reaches Kurdish-majority town: UN</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/life-saving-aid-reaches-kurdish-majority-town-un</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/life-saving-aid-reaches-kurdish-majority-town-un</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A UN humanitarian convoy arrived Sunday in the Kurdish-majority town of Kobane, which has been filled recently with people displaced by clashes in northern Syria, a spokesperson told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier Sunday, Syria's military said it had opened a humanitarian corridor to the town, also known as Ain al-Arab in Arabic and once a symbol of Kurdish fighters' victory against Islamic State group (IS) jihadists.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aid came as the Syrian authorities and Kurdish forces extended a ceasefire agreement after Kurdish forces relinquished swathes of territory to government troops.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 22:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelenskiy says security guarantees document from US is 100% ready</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/zelenskiy-says-security-guarantees-document-us-100-ready</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/zelenskiy-says-security-guarantees-document-us-100-ready</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;VILNIUS, Jan 25 (Reuters) - A U.S. document on security guarantees for Ukraine is completely ready and Kyiv is waiting for a time and place for it to be signed, President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said on Sunday, indicating that weekend talks with Russia in Abu Dhabi made some progress. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"For us, security guarantees are first and foremost guarantees of security from the United States. The document is 100% ready, and we are waiting for our partners to confirm the date and place when we will sign it," Zelenskiy told a news conference during a visit to Vilnius, the Lithuanian capital.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 17:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US climber scales Taiwan's tallest building Taipei 101 without ropes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-climber-scales-taiwans-tallest-building-taipei-101-without-ropes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-climber-scales-taiwans-tallest-building-taipei-101-without-ropes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TAIPEI, Jan 25 (Reuters) - U.S. climber Alex Honnold scaled the Taipei 101 skyscraper without ropes or safety netting on Sunday, watched by thousands of cheering and waving fans as he clambered up one of the world's tallest buildings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Sick," Honnold said as he got to the top spire of Taiwan's tallest building after his 91-minute "free solo" ascent, which was organised and broadcast live by Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"What a beautiful way to see Taipei," he told reporters after his mission, which was postponed by a day due to wet weather.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 06:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia's UAE 'mudslinging' threatens new Gulf crisis</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabias-uae-mudslinging-threatens-new-gulf-crisis</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabias-uae-mudslinging-threatens-new-gulf-crisis</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Saudi Arabian media campaign targeting the UAE has deepened the Gulf's worst row in years, stoking fears of a damaging fall-out in the financial heart of the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fiery accusations of rights abuses and betrayal have circulated for weeks in state-run and social media after a brief conflict in Yemen, where Saudi air strikes quelled an offensive by UAE-backed separatists.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Arab Emirates is "investing in chaos and supporting secessionists" from Libya to Yemen and the Horn of Africa, Saudi Arabia's Al-Ekhbariya TV charged in a report this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 02:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistani court jails rights activist and husband for 10 years</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistani-court-jails-rights-activist-and-husband-10-years</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistani-court-jails-rights-activist-and-husband-10-years</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Pakistani court on Saturday jailed a prominent rights activist and her husband for 10 years over "anti-state" social media posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imaan Mazari, a 32-year-old lawyer and vocal critic of Pakistan's military, "disseminated highly offensive" content on her X account, according to an Islamabad court. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A court statement said Mazari and her husband, fellow lawyer Hadi Ali Chattha, "will have to remain in jail for 10 years".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 20:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump praises UK troops as brave warriors after widespread condemnation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-uk-troops-brave-warriors-after-widespread-condemnation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-uk-troops-brave-warriors-after-widespread-condemnation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 24 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump on Saturday praised "brave" British soldiers, calling them warriors, a day after remarks he made about NATO troops in Afghanistan were described as "insulting and appalling" by Britain's Prime Minister Keir Starmer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump provoked widespread anger in Britain and across Europe after he said European troops had stayed off the front lines in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 19:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK's Starmer discusses need for enhanced security in Arctic in call with Trump</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uks-starmer-discusses-need-enhanced-security-arctic-call-trump</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uks-starmer-discusses-need-enhanced-security-arctic-call-trump</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 24 (Reuters) - British Prime Minister Keir Starmer spoke with U.S. President Donald Trump by telephone on Saturday, with the leaders discussing the need for bolstered security in the Arctic, 10 Downing Street said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Starmer referred to the subject as an absolute priority for his government, the statement said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 19:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>