<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Yemeni government accuses separatists of Aden restrictions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemeni-government-accuses-separatists-aden-restrictions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemeni-government-accuses-separatists-aden-restrictions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Elimam and Maha El Dahan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 4 (Reuters) - Yemen's Saudi-backed government on Sunday accused UAE-backed southern separatists of cutting off the port city of Aden and warned it would "take all necessary measures" after recapturing territory from them in the east on Saturday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The separatists denied having restricted movement into Aden, but the government accusations indicate that hostility between the sides persists despite proposals for a dialogue that had raised hopes of a negotiated solution to the crisis. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 15:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>114 killed in week of attacks in Sudan's Darfur: medical sources</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/114-killed-week-attacks-sudans-darfur-medical-sources</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/114-killed-week-attacks-sudans-darfur-medical-sources</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Attacks by Sudan's army and its paramilitary foes on two towns in the western Darfur region over the past week have killed 114 people, medical sources told AFP Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since April 2023, Sudan has been gripped by a war between the army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF), which in October seized the army's last holdout position in Darfur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RSF has since pushed west to the Chadian border and east through the vast Kordofan region, where a drone strike on the North Kordofan capital of El-Obeid on Sunday caused a blackout in the key army-controlled city.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 15:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Radio frequency loss grounds flights in Greece, stranding thousands</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/radio-frequency-loss-grounds-flights-greece-stranding-thousands</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/radio-frequency-loss-grounds-flights-greece-stranding-thousands</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 4 (Reuters) - Flights across Greece were grounded on Sunday after a collapse of radio frequencies crippled air traffic communication, stranding thousands of travellers and bringing airport operations to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was little clarity on what caused the disruption, which began early Sunday and quickly escalated. Some overflights across Greek and regional airspace were still being serviced, but restrictions were imposed on airport operations for safety reasons, Greece's civil aviation authority said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rights group says at least 16 dead in Iran during week of protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-least-16-dead-iran-during-week-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-least-16-dead-iran-during-week-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Elwely Elwelly&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 4 (Reuters) - At least 16 people have been killed during a week of unrest in Iran, rights groups said on Sunday, as protests over soaring inflation spread across the country prompting violent clashes between demonstrators and security forces. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deaths and arrests have been reported through the week both by state media and rights groups, though the numbers have differed. Reuters has not been able to verify the figures independently. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Numerous teenagers among the dead in Swiss bar blaze, police say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/numerous-teenagers-among-dead-swiss-bar-blaze-police-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/numerous-teenagers-among-dead-swiss-bar-blaze-police-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ZURICH, Jan 4 (Reuters) - Teenagers as young as 14 and 15 years old were among those who died in the bar fire on New Year's Eve that killed 40 people in Switzerland, police said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police in Valais said they had identified 16 more of those who died in the blaze in Crans-Montana, one of the worst disasters in recent Swiss history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those newly identified included 10 Swiss nationals, two Italians, one person with Italian-Emirati citizenship, one Romanian, one person from France and one from Turkey, Valais police said. No names were given. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli forces kill three Palestinians in Gaza, local authorities say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-forces-kill-three-palestinians-gaza-local-authorities-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-forces-kill-three-palestinians-gaza-local-authorities-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 4 (Reuters) - Israeli forces shot and killed at least three Palestinians in separate incidents in the southern Gaza Strip city of Khan Younis on Sunday, local health authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medics reported that the dead included a 15‑year‑old boy, a fisherman killed outside areas still occupied by Israel in the enclave, and a third man who was shot and killed east of the city in areas under Israeli control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military had no immediate comment on the reported incidents.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 09:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond Venezuela, what does Maduro’s fall mean for isolated Iran?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</guid><description>To counter US influence and demonstrate global reach, Iran had for years invested heavily in Venezuela as a politically aligned, economically intertwined and rhetorically defiant ally.</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 02:05:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond Venezuela, what does Maduro’s fall mean for isolated Iran?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</guid><description>To counter US influence and demonstrate global reach, Iran had for years invested heavily in Venezuela as a politically aligned, economically intertwined and rhetorically defiant ally.</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 02:05:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond Venezuela, what does Maduro’s fall mean for isolated Iran?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</guid><description>To counter US influence and demonstrate global reach, Iran had for years invested heavily in Venezuela as a politically aligned, economically intertwined and rhetorically defiant ally.</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 02:05:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyond Venezuela, what does Maduro’s fall mean for isolated Iran?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/beyond-venezuela-what-does-maduros-fall-mean-isolated-iran</guid><description>To counter US influence and demonstrate global reach, Iran had for years invested heavily in Venezuela as a politically aligned, economically intertwined and rhetorically defiant ally.</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 02:05:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Shop for marble, threaten Iran, capture Maduro: Trump's dizzying holiday routine</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/shop-marble-threaten-iran-capture-maduro-trumps-dizzying-holiday-routine</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/shop-marble-threaten-iran-capture-maduro-trumps-dizzying-holiday-routine</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Gram Slattery&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PALM BEACH, Florida, Jan 3 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump capped the holidays with an unprecedented strike on Venezuela, overseeing a surprise snatch-and-grab operation early on Saturday targeted at Venezuelan leader Nicolas Maduro.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dramatic mission punctuated a winter sojourn to his Mar-a-Lago estate in Palm Beach, Florida, filled with an unusual mix of activities that have become oddly typical for the unconventional president.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 00:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At least four killed in protest clashes in western Iran: rights groups</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/least-four-killed-protest-clashes-western-iran-rights-groups</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/least-four-killed-protest-clashes-western-iran-rights-groups</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At least four people were killed in western Iran on Saturday in clashes between protesters and security forces, two rights groups said, accusing Revolutionary Guards of opening fire on demonstrators.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protests carried on in several cities nationwide throughout Saturday, the seventh day of a movement sparked by anger over the rising cost of living in the Islamic republic. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests are the most significant in Iran since a 2022-2023 movement that authorities quelled with a crackdown that left hundreds dead and thousands arrested, according to activists.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 23:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudanese flee across border and back to escape overrun oil town</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudanese-flee-across-border-and-back-escape-overrun-oil-town</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudanese-flee-across-border-and-back-escape-overrun-oil-town</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When paramilitary fighters closed in on the Sudanese border town and oil field of Heglig, paraplegic Dowa Hamed could only cling to her husband's back as they fled, "like a child", she told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, the 25-year-old mother of five -- paralysed from the waist down -- lies shell-shocked on a cot in the Abu al-Naga displacement camp, a dusty transit centre just outside the eastern city of Gedaref, nearly 800 kilometres (500 miles) from home.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 14:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran supreme leader says will not yield as protests simmer and US threatens</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-supreme-leader-says-will-not-yield-protests-simmer-and-us-threatens</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-supreme-leader-says-will-not-yield-protests-simmer-and-us-threatens</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 3 (Reuters) - Iran's Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei vowed not to yield after U.S. President Donald Trump threatened to come to the aid of protesters, as rights groups reported a sharp rise in arrests following days of unrest sparked by soaring inflation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking in a recorded appearance on television on Saturday, Khamenei said the Islamic Republic "will not yield to the enemy" and said rioters should be "put in their place".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemen presidency says Saudi-backed forces retake key province</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemen-presidency-says-saudi-backed-forces-retake-key-province</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemen-presidency-says-saudi-backed-forces-retake-key-province</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Saudi-backed troops on Saturday retook the resource-rich Yemeni province of Hadramawt, Yemen's presidency said, after confrontations between forces backed by Riyadh and Abu Dhabi deepened a rift between the two Gulf allies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Saudis and Emiratis have long supported rival factions in Yemen's fractious government, and a December offensive by the UAE-backed secessionist Southern Transitional Council (STC) to capture Hadramawt had angered Riyadh and left the oil-rich regional powers on a collision course.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 11:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE calls for restraint amid rapidly moving Yemen crisis</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uae-calls-restraint-amid-rapidly-moving-yemen-crisis</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uae-calls-restraint-amid-rapidly-moving-yemen-crisis</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 3 (Reuters) - The United Arab Emirates said on Saturday it was deeply concerned by ongoing escalation in Yemen after Saudi-backed government forces swept into areas seized last month by UAE-backed southern separatists seeking independence. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rapidly moving crisis in Yemen has opened a major feud between the two Gulf powers and fractured the coalition of forces, headed by the internationally recognised government, who are fighting the Iran-backed Houthi movement. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 10:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's Khamenei says protesters' economic demands fair, warns 'rioters'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-khamenei-says-protesters-economic-demands-fair-warns-rioters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-khamenei-says-protesters-economic-demands-fair-warns-rioters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Supreme leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei on Saturday acknowledged the economic demands of protesters in Iran, where demonstrations have spread to more than two dozen cities, even as he warned there would be no quarter for "rioters".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests began on Sunday as an expression of discontent over high prices and economic stagnation, but have since expanded to include political demands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian media have reported localised violence and vandalism in the west of the country in recent days.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 10:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN chief calls on Israel to reverse NGOs ban in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-chief-calls-israel-reverse-ngos-ban-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-chief-calls-israel-reverse-ngos-ban-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;UN Secretary General Antonio Guterres called on Friday for Israel to end a ban on humanitarian agencies that provided aid in Gaza, saying he was "deeply concerned" at the development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guterres "calls for this measure to be reversed, stressing that international non-governmental organizations are indispensable to life-saving humanitarian work and that the suspension risks undermining the fragile progress made during the ceasefire," his spokesperson Stephane Dujarric said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 23:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN chief deeply concerned over Israel's suspension of NGOs</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-chief-deeply-concerned-over-israels-suspension-ngos</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-chief-deeply-concerned-over-israels-suspension-ngos</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 2 (Reuters) - UN Secretary-General Antonio Guterres is deeply concerned by Israel's announcement of a suspension of the operations of several international non-governmental organizations in occupied Palestinian territory and called for the measure to be reversed, according to a statement on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 23:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran unrest: 4 scenarios as protests spread, regime weighs options</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-unrest-4-scenarios-protests-spread-regime-weighs-options</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-unrest-4-scenarios-protests-spread-regime-weighs-options</guid><description>As casualties mount amid nearly a week of unrest in Iran, Donald Trump's threat to "rescue" demonstrators has sharpened tensions, forcing Tehran to confront escalating unrest at home alongside renewed fears of foreign intervention and regime change.</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 19:41:18 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>