<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Palestinians say Israeli army killed man in occupied West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/palestinians-say-israeli-army-killed-man-occupied-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/palestinians-say-israeli-army-killed-man-occupied-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Ramallah-based Palestinian health ministry said that Israeli forces killed a man in the northern occupied West Bank on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Bahaa Abdel-Rahman Rashid (38 years old) was killed by Israeli fire in the town of Odala, south of Nablus," the health ministry said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shortly before, the Palestinian Red Crescent said its teams handled the case of a man "who suffered a critical head injury during clashes in the town of Odala near Nablus, and CPR is currently being performed on him".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military told AFP it was looking into the incident.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Amazing' figurines find in Egyptian tomb solves mystery</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/amazing-figurines-find-egyptian-tomb-solves-mystery</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/amazing-figurines-find-egyptian-tomb-solves-mystery</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A treasure trove of 225 funerary figurines have been discovered inside a tomb in the ancient Egyptian capital of Tanis in the Nile Delta, a rare find that has also solved a long-running mystery. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Finding figurines in place inside a royal tomb has not happened in the Tanis necropolis since 1946," French egyptologist Frederic Payraudeau told reporters in Paris on Friday. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Eurovision faces budget squeeze after walkouts over Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-faces-budget-squeeze-after-walkouts-over-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-faces-budget-squeeze-after-walkouts-over-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin, Johnny Cotton and Cecile Mantovani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Dec 5 (Reuters) - The Eurovision Song Contest was facing a potential budget squeeze after Spain, the Netherlands, Ireland and Slovenia said they would withdraw from next year's competition in protest at Israel's participation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The planned boycott brought to a head a row that has overshadowed the past two contests, and followed threats by the four they would pull out if the organiser did not exclude Israel over the conduct of its war against Hamas in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah's Qassem says sending civilian delegate to ceasefire talks is concession to Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hezbollahs-qassem-says-sending-civilian-delegate-ceasefire-talks-concession</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hezbollahs-qassem-says-sending-civilian-delegate-ceasefire-talks-concession</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Dec 5 (Reuters) - Hezbollah chief Naim Qassem on Friday criticised the Lebanese government's decision to send a civilian delegate to the ceasefire committee, calling it a "free concession" to Israel and a clear violation of previous government positions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, both Israel and Lebanon sent civilian envoys to a military committee monitoring their ceasefire, marking an expansion in the scope of talks between the two nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Maya Gebeily and Laila Bassam; Writing by Tala Ramadan; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 14:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon says ceasefire talks aim primarily at halting Israel's hostilities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanon-says-ceasefire-talks-aim-primarily-halting-israels-hostilities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanon-says-ceasefire-talks-aim-primarily-halting-israels-hostilities</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 5 (Reuters) - Lebanese President Joseph Aoun said on Friday that ceasefire talks with Israel are primarily aimed at stopping Israeli hostilities on Lebanese territory, after the Israeli prime minister's office said it seeks economic cooperation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel and Lebanon entered a U.S.-brokered ceasefire agreement last year, but Israel has not halted strikes against Lebanon's militant Hezbollah group.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Congo fighting flares within hours of Trump's peace deal ceremony</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/congo-fighting-flares-within-hours-trumps-peace-deal-ceremony</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/congo-fighting-flares-within-hours-trumps-peace-deal-ceremony</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 5 (Reuters) - Fighting raged in eastern Democratic Republic of Congo on Friday, a day after U.S. President Donald Trump hosted Congolese and Rwandan leaders in Washington to sign new deals aimed at ending years of conflict in a region rich in minerals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Congo's President Felix Tshisekedi and Rwanda's Paul Kagame on Thursday reaffirmed commitments to a U.S.-brokered deal reached in June to stabilise the vast country and open the way for more Western mining investment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran holds drills in Gulf, firing ballistic, cruise missiles at simulated targets</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-holds-drills-gulf-firing-ballistic-cruise-missiles-simulated-targets</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-holds-drills-gulf-firing-ballistic-cruise-missiles-simulated-targets</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 5 (Reuters) - Iran's Revolutionary Guards Navy fired ballistic and cruise missiles at simulated targets in the Gulf on Friday during a two-day military exercise aimed at countering foreign threats, state media reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, Iran hosted an anti-terrorism drill in its northwestern province of East Azerbaijan with members of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization, which, according to state Press TV, was intended to signal both “peace and friendship” to neighbouring states and warn enemies that “any miscalculation would meet a decisive response”.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After wins abroad, Syria leader must gain trust at home</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/after-wins-abroad-syria-leader-must-gain-trust-home</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/after-wins-abroad-syria-leader-must-gain-trust-home</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One year after ousting Bashar al-Assad, Ahmed al-Sharaa has restored Syria's international standing and won sanctions relief.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But analysts warn the former jihadist still needs to secure trust on the home front.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sectarian bloodshed in the country's Alawite and Druze minority heartlands -- alongside ongoing Israeli military operations -- have shaken Syria as President Sharaa tries to lead the country out of 14 years of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 10:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greek parliament approves purchase of rocket systems from Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/greek-parliament-approves-purchase-rocket-systems-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/greek-parliament-approves-purchase-rocket-systems-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Dec 5 (Reuters) - Greek lawmakers approved late on Thursday the purchase of 36 PULS rocket artillery systems from Israel for about 650 million euros ($757.84 million), two officials with knowledge of the issue told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Greece has said it will spend about 28 billion euros ($32.66 billion) by 2036 to modernise its armed forces as it emerges from a 2009-2018 debt crisis and tries to keep pace with its historic rival Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 09:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US widens travel ban to more than 30 countries, Noem says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-widens-travel-ban-more-30-countries-noem-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-widens-travel-ban-more-30-countries-noem-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 4 (Reuters) - The U.S. plans to expand the number of countries covered by its travel ban to more than 30, U.S. Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Noem, in an interview on Fox News' "The Ingraham Angle," was asked to confirm whether the administration of President Donald Trump would be increasing the number of countries on the travel ban list to 32.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I won't be specific on the number, but it's over 30, and the president is continuing to evaluate countries," she said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 02:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Land without laws': Israeli settlers force Bedouins from West Bank community</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/land-without-laws-israeli-settlers-force-bedouins-west-bank-community</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/land-without-laws-israeli-settlers-force-bedouins-west-bank-community</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As relentless harassment from Israeli settlers drove his brothers from their Bedouin community in the central occupied West Bank, Ahmed Kaabneh remained determined to stay on the land his family had lived on for generations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But when a handful of young settlers constructed a shack around 100 metres above his home and started intimidating his children, 45-year-old Kaabneh said he had no choice but to flee too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with scores of Bedouin communities across the West Bank, the small cluster of wood and metal houses where Kaabneh's father and grandfather had lived now lies empty. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 02:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US judge questions Trump administration's continued targeting of pro-Palestinian Tufts student</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-judge-questions-trump-administrations-continued-targeting-pro-palestinian</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-judge-questions-trump-administrations-continued-targeting-pro-palestinian</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nate Raymond&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BOSTON, Dec 4 (Reuters) - A federal judge on Thursday said she was "struggling" to understand why President Donald Trump's administration is preventing a Tufts University PhD student who had engaged in pro-Palestinian activism from working on campus nearly seven months after the Turkish citizen was released from an immigration detention center.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 22:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Congo, Rwanda leaders affirm commitment to Trump-backed peace deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/congo-rwanda-leaders-affirm-commitment-trump-backed-peace-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/congo-rwanda-leaders-affirm-commitment-trump-backed-peace-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Trevor Hunnicutt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Dec 4 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump gathered the leaders of the Democratic Republic of Congo and Rwanda to sign a peace deal in Washington on Thursday even as fighting continued in their war-scarred region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rwandan President Paul Kagame and Democratic Republic of Congo President Felix Tshisekedi affirmed commitments to an economic integration compact agreed last month, and to a U.S.-brokered peace deal reached in June. They were also due to sign an agreement on critical minerals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 20:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>To counter climate denial, UN scientists must be 'clear' about human role: IPCC chief</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/counter-climate-denial-un-scientists-must-be-clear-about-human-role-ipcc-chief</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/counter-climate-denial-un-scientists-must-be-clear-about-human-role-ipcc-chief</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;With US President Donald Trump and other sceptics calling climate change a hoax, the UN's climate science body must tell the world in a "very clear way" that humans are heating the planet, its chairman told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jim Skea, a Scottish professor, chairs the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), which held a five-day meeting in a skyscraper outside Paris this week to begin drafting the next major UN climate assessment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 19:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran filmmaker Panahi says to return home despite prison sentence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-filmmaker-panahi-says-return-home-despite-prison-sentence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-filmmaker-panahi-says-return-home-despite-prison-sentence</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dissident Iranian filmmaker Jafar Panahi has said he plans to return to Iran despite being sentenced to a year in prison and a travel ban earlier this week, a report said Thursday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 65-year-old is currently touring to promote his latest Oscar-nominated film "It Was Just an Accident", which won top prize at the Cannes Film Festival this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Although I was given the opportunity, even in the hardest years, I never considered leaving my country and being a refugee elsewhere," Panahi told an audience at the Marrakech Film Festival, according to Variety magazine. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 18:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What should happen next under the Gaza peace plan?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/what-should-happen-next-under-gaza-peace-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/what-should-happen-next-under-gaza-peace-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Negotiations on the next stage of the Gaza ceasefire continue without significant progress at a moment when the truce appears particularly fragile.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United States, alongside Qatar and Egypt, secured a truce in Gaza that came into effect on October 10 and has mostly halted two years of war between Israel and Palestinian militant group Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has since endorsed President Donald Trump's peace plan, yet there has been little progress over issues of reconstruction and post-war governance. AFP explains what could happen next:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- What is the plan? -&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 18:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ankara: Jailed PKK chief favors unitary Syria, no separate Kurdish defense force</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</guid><description>The militant leader called for “police-like” security units in Syrian Democratic Forces areas during his landmark meeting with a Turkish parliamentary delegation, according to a transcript summary.</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 17:26:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ankara: Jailed PKK chief favors unitary Syria, no separate Kurdish defense force</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</guid><description>The militant leader called for “police-like” security units in Syrian Democratic Forces areas during his landmark meeting with a Turkish parliamentary delegation, according to a transcript summary.</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 17:26:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ankara: Jailed PKK chief favors unitary Syria, no separate Kurdish defense force</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</guid><description>The militant leader called for “police-like” security units in Syrian Democratic Forces areas during his landmark meeting with a Turkish parliamentary delegation, according to a transcript summary.</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 17:26:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ankara: Jailed PKK chief favors unitary Syria, no separate Kurdish defense force</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ankara-jailed-pkk-chief-favors-unitary-syria-no-separate-kurdish-defense-force</guid><description>The militant leader called for “police-like” security units in Syrian Democratic Forces areas during his landmark meeting with a Turkish parliamentary delegation, according to a transcript summary.</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 17:26:40 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>