<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israeli airstrikes kill 10 Palestinians in Gaza, rattling ceasefire, medics say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-airstrikes-kill-10-palestinians-gaza-rattling-ceasefire-medics-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-airstrikes-kill-10-palestinians-gaza-rattling-ceasefire-medics-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -Israeli airstrikes killed 10 Palestinians in the Gaza Strip on Wednesday in a part of the enclave under Hamas control since a shaky ceasefire took effect in October, health authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medics said two people were killed in Shejaia suburb east of Gaza City and four in the nearby suburb of Zeitoun. A third airstrike killed four Palestinians in Mawasi area, west of Khan Younis in the south of Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 17:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fear in Palestinian camp in Lebanon after deadly Israel strike</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fear-palestinian-camp-lebanon-after-deadly-israel-strike</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fear-palestinian-camp-lebanon-after-deadly-israel-strike</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Residents of Lebanon's Ain al-Helweh Palestinian refugee camp described their fear and astonishment a day after a deadly strike that Israel said targeted a Hamas compound, a claim the Palestinian militant group rejected.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tuesday night's raid, which Lebanese authorities said killed 13 people, was the worst since a ceasefire took effect last year between Israel and Hezbollah. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emergency workers were still collecting human remains on Wednesday at the devastated site, located near one of the entrances to the overcrowded, impoverished Palestinian camp, an AFP correspondent saw.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 17:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands of Tunisian doctors strike, say health system close to collapse</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/thousands-tunisian-doctors-strike-say-health-system-close-collapse</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/thousands-tunisian-doctors-strike-say-health-system-close-collapse</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS (Reuters) -Thousands of young doctors went on strike across Tunisia on Wednesday to demand higher pay and warn of an impending collapse of the health system, part of a broader wave of social unrest convulsing the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A spate of environmental and anti-government protests prompted by a worsening economic crisis and disruptions in public services has posed the biggest challenge to President Kais Saied since he seized all power in 2021.    &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 16:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli military steps up strikes in south Lebanon, says targeting Hezbollah</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-military-steps-strikes-south-lebanon-says-targeting-hezbollah</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-military-steps-strikes-south-lebanon-says-targeting-hezbollah</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT (Reuters) -The Israeli military stepped up airstrikes in south Lebanon on Wednesday, killing at least one person as it pressed a campaign of near-daily attacks which it says is designed to block a military revival by Iran-backed Hezbollah in the border area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel has accused Hezbollah of trying to rearm since a U.S.-backed ceasefire its war with Hezbollah last year. The group says it has abided by requirements for it to end its military presence in the border region near Israel, and for the Lebanese army to deploy there.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt, Russia advance construction at Dabaa nuclear plant: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</guid><description>The Dabaa nuclear plant could help Egypt address its energy woes while boosting cooperation with Russia.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt, Russia advance construction at Dabaa nuclear plant: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</guid><description>The Dabaa nuclear plant could help Egypt address its energy woes while boosting cooperation with Russia.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt, Russia advance construction at Dabaa nuclear plant: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</guid><description>The Dabaa nuclear plant could help Egypt address its energy woes while boosting cooperation with Russia.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt, Russia advance construction at Dabaa nuclear plant: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-russia-advance-construction-dabaa-nuclear-plant-what-know</guid><description>The Dabaa nuclear plant could help Egypt address its energy woes while boosting cooperation with Russia.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:32:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Restorers dismantle and reconstruct a historic Cairo neighbourhood</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/restorers-dismantle-and-reconstruct-historic-cairo-neighbourhood</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/restorers-dismantle-and-reconstruct-historic-cairo-neighbourhood</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Patrick Werr&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -Egyptian restorers are reconstructing a dilapidated neighbourhood in Cairo's historic centre, dismantling houses and    then rebuilding them with materials from the old structures in a model they hope can be applied to other districts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Darb al-Labbana neighbourhood is nestled on a slope directly under Cairo's more than eight-century-old citadel, a prominent landmark built by Muslim general Saladin, and abutting the back of a historic hospital complex. But in recent decades it had become largely uninhabitable.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The gruelling search for Gaza's dead under the rubble</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gruelling-search-gazas-dead-under-rubble</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gruelling-search-gazas-dead-under-rubble</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Standing beside the mound of rubble that was once his home, Ahmed Salim cannot hold back the tears as he struggles to retrieve the bodies of loved ones trapped underneath tonnes of debris.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 30 people were killed when his home was struck, he told AFP, among them "my wife, my children, my mother, my father".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I'm the only one who survived," he told AFP, pointing to the pile of broken concrete and twisted metal that was once a five-storey building in Gaza City's Zeitoun neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:00:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's embrace of crown prince ushers in new era in US-Saudi ties</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trumps-embrace-crown-prince-ushers-new-era-us-saudi-ties</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trumps-embrace-crown-prince-ushers-new-era-us-saudi-ties</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman's trip to Washington has been a triumph, with Donald Trump rolling out the red carpet for "the future king" and absolving him of the criticism he has faced for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The heir to the Saudi throne was given a lavish welcome during his visit to the White House Tuesday on par with what American leaders regularly receive when they visit the kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trip marked the first visit by the prince to the US since the 2018 murder of journalist Jamal Khashoggi by Saudi agents sparked global outrage and transformed the heir into a pariah.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 14:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN nuclear head renews call for Iran to allow inspections at key sites</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-nuclear-head-renews-call-iran-allow-inspections-key-sites</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-nuclear-head-renews-call-iran-allow-inspections-key-sites</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The head of the UN nuclear agency on Wednesday renewed his call for Iran to allow inspections at key nuclear sites attacked by Israel and the United States in June.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tensions between Iran and the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) have repeatedly flared in recent years and were further inflamed after a 12-day war in June that saw Israeli and US strikes on key Iranian nuclear facilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the war, agency inspectors have not been granted access to sites such as Fordo and Natanz, which were hit in the strikes, but they have been able to visit other sites.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 14:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza water provider resumes services after Hamas frees employee</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-water-provider-resumes-services-after-hamas-frees-employee</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-water-provider-resumes-services-after-hamas-frees-employee</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GAZA (Reuters) -A Gaza company that operates water desalination plants serving nearly half of the enclave's population said on Tuesday it had resumed operations after Hamas-led security freed a staff member whom they detained on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A statement issued by the Abdul Salam Yassin Company, whose services reach more than 1 million people, said the decision to resume operations came after the issue was resolved, adding that the staff member was "fine and in good health".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza storms bring flooding, sewage and misery in tent camps</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-storms-bring-flooding-sewage-and-misery-tent-camps</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-storms-bring-flooding-sewage-and-misery-tent-camps</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAZA/CAIRO (Reuters) -Crammed into flimsy tent camps hard up against the seashore, Gazans have been flooded by heavy rain and storm surges in recent days, destroying some shelters, soaking mattresses and blankets and bringing new misery even after a ceasefire. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Hamas-run Gaza government has estimated losses from the stormy weather at around $4.5 million, including 22,000 tents, spoiled food and medicines and damage to infrastructure, while local aid groups say 300,000 new tents are urgently needed. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghanistan seeks Indian investments, goods as Taliban minister arrives in Delhi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-seeks-indian-investments-goods-taliban-minister-arrives-delhi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-seeks-indian-investments-goods-taliban-minister-arrives-delhi</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KABUL/NEW DELHI (Reuters) -Afghanistan's Taliban trade minister arrived in India on Wednesday on a maiden visit to draw greater investments and goods as both countries consider ways to enhance their relations in the backdrop of souring relations with neighbouring Pakistan. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;India last month upgraded its ties with the Taliban by reopening its embassy in Kabul that was shut after the Islamist group seized power in 2021 following the withdrawal of U.S.-led NATO forces. New Delhi is also ramping up its aid to the country as it competes with China for influence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 13:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France obtains freeze of Dubai properties linked to drug trafficking, minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/france-obtains-freeze-dubai-properties-linked-drug-trafficking-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/france-obtains-freeze-dubai-properties-linked-drug-trafficking-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS (Reuters) -The United Arab Emirates has agreed to seize around 40 Dubai apartments and luxury villas suspected of being linked to drug trafficking in France, French Justice Minister Gerald Darmanin said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Darmanin said in a post on X that the seizure of the properties, which had been bought by suspects using cash or cryptocurrencies, was part of broader judicial cooperation on international drug traffic between France and the UAE.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 13:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan's confidant Nuh Yilmaz appointed ambassador to Syria, first in 13 years: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</guid><description>Yilmaz’s formal appointment follows the UN’s lifting of sanctions on Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa as Ankara pushes for coordination with Washington and Damascus on the Syrian dossier.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 12:34:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan's confidant Nuh Yilmaz appointed ambassador to Syria, first in 13 years: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</guid><description>Yilmaz’s formal appointment follows the UN’s lifting of sanctions on Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa as Ankara pushes for coordination with Washington and Damascus on the Syrian dossier.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 12:34:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan's confidant Nuh Yilmaz appointed ambassador to Syria, first in 13 years: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</guid><description>Yilmaz’s formal appointment follows the UN’s lifting of sanctions on Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa as Ankara pushes for coordination with Washington and Damascus on the Syrian dossier.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 12:34:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan's confidant Nuh Yilmaz appointed ambassador to Syria, first in 13 years: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fidans-confidant-nuh-yilmaz-appointed-ambassador-syria-first-13-years-what-know</guid><description>Yilmaz’s formal appointment follows the UN’s lifting of sanctions on Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa as Ankara pushes for coordination with Washington and Damascus on the Syrian dossier.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 12:34:52 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>