<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>UN says lacks billions of dollars to feed world's hungry</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-says-lacks-billions-dollars-feed-worlds-hungry</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-says-lacks-billions-dollars-feed-worlds-hungry</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The UN's World Food Programme warned Tuesday that funding cuts mean it will struggle to feed even a third of the 318 million people facing severe hunger in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Declines in global humanitarian funding are forcing WFP to prioritise food assistance to roughly one third of those in need," targeting 110 million of the most vulnerable, it said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That would cost $13 billion, the agency estimated -- but warned that "current funding forecasts indicate WFP may only receive close to half that goal".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin says Russia will not participate in Ukraine talks in Turkey this week</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kremlin-says-russia-will-not-participate-ukraine-talks-turkey-week</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kremlin-says-russia-will-not-participate-ukraine-talks-turkey-week</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW (Reuters) -Russian representatives will not take part in talks on Ukraine in Turkey on November 19, the Kremlin said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said earlier he would go to Turkey on Wednesday in an attempt to revive negotiations with Russia on ending the war. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Turkish source said that U.S. special envoy Steve Witkoff would join the planned talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kremlin spokesman Dmitry Peskov told reporters: "No, there will be no Russian representatives in Turkey tomorrow. For now, these contacts are taking place without Russian participation." &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza water provider suspends services after Hamas detains staff member</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-water-provider-suspends-services-after-hamas-detains-staff-member</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-water-provider-suspends-services-after-hamas-detains-staff-member</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -A Gaza company that operates water desalination plants serving nearly half of the enclave's population has stopped operations to protest at the detention by Hamas of one of its staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Youssef Yassin, a board member of the Abdul Salam Yassin Company, said the move would affect more than 1 million people who normally receive water from the company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 70 trucks that carry water containers across the enclave have also stopped operations, he added, risking further supply disruption after the pipeline network was badly damaged during the war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel hails Trump Gaza plan after UN Security Council vote</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-hails-trump-gaza-plan-after-un-security-council-vote</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-hails-trump-gaza-plan-after-un-security-council-vote</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel on Tuesday hailed Donald Trump's Gaza peace plan after its endorsement by the UN Security Council, as Hamas rejected the resolution which calls for the deployment of an international force in the Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Security Council voted on Monday in favour of a US-drafted resolution bolstering President Trump's plan for the Gaza Strip -- which has allowed for a fragile ceasefire to hold between Israel and Hamas since October 10.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine's Zelenskiy plans Turkey visit to try to revive peace talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ukraines-zelenskiy-plans-turkey-visit-try-revive-peace-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ukraines-zelenskiy-plans-turkey-visit-try-revive-peace-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV (Reuters) -President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said he planned to go to Turkey on Wednesday in an attempt to revive talks with Russia on how to end the war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Turkish source said that U.S. special envoy Steve Witkoff would also visit Turkey on Wednesday and join the planned talks there with Zelenskiy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 09:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian foreign minister says UN vote is 'first step towards peace'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-foreign-minister-says-un-vote-first-step-towards-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-foreign-minister-says-un-vote-first-step-towards-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MANILA (Reuters) -Palestinian Foreign Minister Varsen Aghabekian Shahin said on Tuesday the U.N. Security Council's adoption of a resolution endorsing U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the war in Gaza was a necessary first step on a long road toward peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Security Council on Monday adopted the U.S.-drafted resolution, which also authorises a multinational security force to be deployed to Gaza and imposes an international guardian mechanism for the territory ravaged by two years of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 08:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesia welcomes UN Security Council's adoption of Trump's Gaza plan, ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/indonesia-welcomes-un-security-councils-adoption-trumps-gaza-plan-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/indonesia-welcomes-un-security-councils-adoption-trumps-gaza-plan-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JAKARTA (Reuters) -Indonesia welcomes the UN Security Council's adoption of a U.S.-drafted resolution endorsing President Donald Trump's plan to end the war in Gaza and establish an international stabilisation force, the foreign ministry said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Monday, foreign ministry spokesperson Yvonne Mewengkang said it welcomed the resolution and stressed the importance of every party's involvement in it, "especially the Palestinian Authority".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 07:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump to welcome Saudi crown prince with offer of fighter jets, business deals</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-welcome-saudi-crown-prince-offer-fighter-jets-business-deals</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-welcome-saudi-crown-prince-offer-fighter-jets-business-deals</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steve Holland, Matt Spetalnick and Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump will roll out the red carpet for Saudi Arabia's de facto ruler, Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman, on Tuesday for a visit expected to advance the sale of F-35 fighter jets and a host of business deals with the kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It will be the first trip by bin Salman, widely known as MBS, to the U.S. since the 2018 killing of Saudi critic Jamal Khashoggi by Saudi agents in Istanbul, which triggered global outrage.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 06:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump hosts Saudi prince for first time since Khashoggi killing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-hosts-saudi-prince-first-time-khashoggi-killing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-hosts-saudi-prince-first-time-khashoggi-killing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman will receive a lavish welcome from US President Donald Trump on Tuesday, signing defense and nuclear deals during his first visit to the United States since the 2018 murder of journalist Jamal Khashoggi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump is expected to roll out the red carpet for the prince with a fly-by, gun salute and a gala dinner -- giving the Saudi the equivalent of a state dinner, even though he is not a head of state and is only the kingdom's de facto ruler.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 06:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>W.Sahara autonomy plan sparks hopes of progress</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/wsahara-autonomy-plan-sparks-hopes-progress</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/wsahara-autonomy-plan-sparks-hopes-progress</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Many people in Western Sahara hope Morocco's long-discussed autonomy plan for the area -- now backed by the UN Security Council -- will accelerate development and end the half-century-long territorial dispute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its main city of Laayoune, with modern apartment blocks built among sand dunes some 20 kilometres (12 miles) from the Atlantic Ocean, already projects an image of growth and stability.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 02:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump would back Russia sanctions bill if he retains final authority, White House official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-would-back-russia-sanctions-bill-if-he-retains-final-authority-white-house</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-would-back-russia-sanctions-bill-if-he-retains-final-authority-white-house</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Gram Slattery, Andrea Shalal and Steve Holland&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -President Donald Trump is willing to sign legislation to impose sanctions on Russia as long as he retains ultimate decision-making authority over any such measures, a senior White House official said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump told reporters late on Sunday that it was "OK with me" that Republicans were working on legislation to impose sanctions on countries doing business with Russia over Moscow's failure to negotiate a peace deal with Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 23:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas rejects UN Gaza resolution, says international force would become party to conflict</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-rejects-un-gaza-resolution-says-international-force-would-become-party</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-rejects-un-gaza-resolution-says-international-force-would-become-party</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Hamas rejected the United Nations Security Council passing a U.S.-drafted resolution endorsing U.S. President Donald Trump's Gaza plan, saying it fails to meet Palestinians' rights and demands and seeks to impose an international trusteeship on the enclave that Palestinians and resistance factions oppose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Assigning the international force with tasks and roles inside the Gaza Strip, including disarming the resistance, strips it of its neutrality, and turns it into a party to the conflict in favor of the occupation," the group added.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 22:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rights group cites 98 Palestinian deaths in Israeli detention during Gaza war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/rights-group-cites-98-palestinian-deaths-israeli-detention-during-gaza-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/rights-group-cites-98-palestinian-deaths-israeli-detention-during-gaza-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -At least 98 Palestinians have died in Israeli detention since the Gaza war erupted in October 2023, a rights group said on Monday, alleging torture and medical neglect and calling for an international investigation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A report by Physicians for Human Rights Israel, entitled "Death Sentence for Palestinians in Custody," said at least 46 died in Israel Prison Service facilities and 52, all from the Gaza Strip, died in military custody. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 21:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu slams 'extremist' Israeli West Bank settlers</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-slams-extremist-israeli-west-bank-settlers-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-slams-extremist-israeli-west-bank-settlers-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu vowed he would deal with the violent "handful of extremists" among Israeli settlers in the occupied West Bank, following clashes and another attack on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homes and vehicles in a Palestinian village were torched on Monday evening, hours after members of the so-called Hilltop Youth movement clashed with security forces who were dismantling an illegal settler outpost.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Violence in the West Bank has soared since the Hamas attack on Israel triggered the Gaza war in October 2023.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 21:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US will sell F-35s to Saudi Arabia, first Arab country to acquire jets</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</guid><description>The deal could rattle Washington's ties with Israel and is not likely to be approved by Congress unless conditioned on Saudi normalization of ties with Israel.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 20:53:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US will sell F-35s to Saudi Arabia, first Arab country to acquire jets</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</guid><description>The deal could rattle Washington's ties with Israel and is not likely to be approved by Congress unless conditioned on Saudi normalization of ties with Israel.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 20:53:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US will sell F-35s to Saudi Arabia, first Arab country to acquire jets</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</guid><description>The deal could rattle Washington's ties with Israel and is not likely to be approved by Congress unless conditioned on Saudi normalization of ties with Israel.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 20:53:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US will sell F-35s to Saudi Arabia, first Arab country to acquire jets</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-will-sell-f-35s-saudi-arabia-first-arab-country-acquire-jets</guid><description>The deal could rattle Washington's ties with Israel and is not likely to be approved by Congress unless conditioned on Saudi normalization of ties with Israel.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 20:53:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council endorses US plan for Gaza security force</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-endorses-us-plan-gaza-security-force</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-endorses-us-plan-gaza-security-force</guid><description>The US-drafted resolution also endorses the Trump-led Board of Peace and references possible statehood for the Palestinians.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 20:45:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council endorses US plan for Gaza security force</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-endorses-us-plan-gaza-security-force</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-endorses-us-plan-gaza-security-force</guid><description>The US-drafted resolution also endorses the Trump-led Board of Peace and references possible statehood for the Palestinians.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 20:45:48 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>