<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Irish attorney general raises concerns on sanctioning services in Israeli settlements</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irish-attorney-general-raises-concerns-sanctioning-services-israeli-settlements</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irish-attorney-general-raises-concerns-sanctioning-services-israeli-settlements</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBLIN, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Ireland's top government lawyer has raised several "significant" legal and practical issues in long-awaited advice on whether planned curbs on trade with Israeli settlements should be extended to services, a junior minister said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ireland has been preparing a law to curb trade with settlements in the Israeli-occupied West Bank, facing pressure at home to widen the scope of the ban from goods to services, while Israel and the United States want the bill scrapped.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What does Iran want from talks with the US?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/what-does-iran-want-talks-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/what-does-iran-want-talks-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States are holding talks on Friday in Oman, with Tehran pushing to focus squarely on its nuclear programme, while Washington's demands go beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two foes had held several rounds of Oman-mediated nuclear talks in 2025, but the Iran-Israel war, which saw the United States conduct strikes on Iranian nuclear sites, derailed diplomacy days before a meeting was due.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey is doing its best to prevent US-Iran conflict, Erdogan says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-doing-its-best-prevent-us-iran-conflict-erdogan-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-doing-its-best-prevent-us-iran-conflict-erdogan-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tuvan Gumrukcu and Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL/ DUBAI, Feb 5 (Reuters) - President Tayyip Erdogan said Turkey is working hard to prevent U.S.-Iran tensions from tipping the Middle East into a new conflict, as the two adversaries signal that disagreement over Tehran’s missile arsenal threatens to torpedo a deal.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 12:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany's Merz shares concerns over Iran escalation on Gulf trip</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/germanys-merz-shares-concerns-over-iran-escalation-gulf-trip</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/germanys-merz-shares-concerns-over-iran-escalation-gulf-trip</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DOHA, Feb 5 (Reuters) - German Chancellor Friedrich Merz said on Thursday that concerns about a further escalation in the conflict with Iran have characterised his talks during a trip to the Gulf region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"In all my conversations yesterday and today, great concern has been expressed about a further escalation in the conflict with Iran," he said during a press conference in Doha. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He called on Iran to end what he called an aggression and enter into talks, saying Germany would do everything it can to de-escalate the situation and work towards stability in the region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 11:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey to stress need to update customs union with EU during commissioner's visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-stress-need-update-customs-union-eu-during-commissioners-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-stress-need-update-customs-union-eu-during-commissioners-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan will push for a speedy resumption of talks with the European Union to update their customs union during a visit to Turkey by the bloc's commissioner for enlargement, a Turkish Foreign Ministry source said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey has been an official candidate to join the EU since 1999, but its accession has been frozen for years over issues ranging from human rights to democratic backsliding. The sides have in recent months shown signs of increased engagement and economic cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US, Ukraine, Russia delegations agree to exchange 314 prisoners, Witkoff says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-ukraine-russia-delegations-agree-exchange-314-prisoners-witkoff-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-ukraine-russia-delegations-agree-exchange-314-prisoners-witkoff-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 5 (Reuters) - Delegations from the United States, Ukraine and Russia have agreed to exchange 314 prisoners, U.S. President Donald Trump's special envoy Steve Witkoff said in a post on X on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Discussions will continue, with additional progress anticipated in the coming weeks," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Shubham Kalia in BengaluruEditing by Bernadette Baum)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin dismisses Western claims that Epstein was Russian intelligence asset</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-dismisses-western-claims-epstein-was-russian-intelligence-asset</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-dismisses-western-claims-epstein-was-russian-intelligence-asset</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 5 (Reuters) - The Kremlin said on Thursday it did not want to waste time answering questions about unproven suggestions in Western media and by Poland's premier that late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein may have been some sort of Russian intelligence asset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polish Prime Minister Donald Tusk said on Tuesday that Warsaw would launch an investigation into what it said were possible links between Epstein and Russia's intelligence services, and into any potential impact on Poland.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN rights chief appeals for $400 million as crises mount and funding shrinks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-rights-chief-appeals-400-million-crises-mount-and-funding-shrinks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-rights-chief-appeals-400-million-crises-mount-and-funding-shrinks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Feb 5 (Reuters) - U.N. human rights chief Volker Turk appealed for $400 million on Thursday to address mounting human rights needs in countries such as Sudan and Myanmar, after donor funding cuts drastically reduced the work of his office and left it in "survival mode".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.N. office is appealing for $100 million less than last year, after a significant scale back of its work in some areas due to a fall in contributions from countries including the U.S. and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Dmitriev says progress made on Ukraine peace deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-dmitriev-says-progress-made-ukraine-peace-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-dmitriev-says-progress-made-ukraine-peace-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Russian President Vladimir Putin's envoy Kirill Dmitriev said on Thursday that there was progress and a positive movement forward in negotiations on peace in Ukraine, as delegations from Russia, Ukraine and the United States prepared for talks in Abu Dhabi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia invaded Ukraine in February 2022 after eight years of fighting in the east, triggering the deadliest war in Europe since World War Two and biggest confrontation between Moscow and the West since the depths of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine, Russia start second day of peace talks in Abu Dhabi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukraine-russia-start-second-day-peace-talks-abu-dhabi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukraine-russia-start-second-day-peace-talks-abu-dhabi</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Ukraine and Russia on Thursday started a second day of U.S.-brokered talks in Abu Dhabi to discuss how to end their four-year-old war, top Ukrainian negotiator Rustem Umerov said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The second day of negotiations in Abu Dhabi has begun," Umerov said on the Telegram app. "We are working in the same formats as yesterday: trilateral consultations, group work and further synchronizationof positions."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Olena Harmash; Editing by Daniel Flynn )&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 08:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia dodges call for arrest of visiting Israel president</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australia-dodges-call-arrest-visiting-israel-president</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australia-dodges-call-arrest-visiting-israel-president</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Australia's government sidestepped a call Thursday for Israeli President Isaac Herzog to be arrested when he visits the country to pay respect to victims of an antisemitic mass shooting on Bondi Beach.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Herzog has been invited to a four-day visit from Monday to meet with the Jewish community after the December 14 attack on a Hanukkah festival in Sydney killed 15 people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A UN-established inquiry found in 2025 that Herzog "incited the commission of genocide" by saying all Palestinians -- "an entire nation" -- were responsible for the October 7, 2023 Hamas attack on Israel.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 04:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US charges suspect with terrorism in killing of two Israeli diplomats</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-charges-suspect-terrorism-killing-two-israeli-diplomats</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-charges-suspect-terrorism-killing-two-israeli-diplomats</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jasper Ward&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 4 (Reuters) - A man accused of killing two Israeli diplomats in Washington, D.C., last year was indicted on four additional counts of terrorism, in a new indictment that was unsealed on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new indictment includes nine charges, including hate crimes, filed earlier. Several of the charges carry a maximum penalty of death or life imprisonment, the U.S. Attorney's Office for the District of Columbia said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 23:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia charges teenager over alleged death threats to Israeli President Herzog</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australia-charges-teenager-over-alleged-death-threats-israeli-president-herzog</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australia-charges-teenager-over-alleged-death-threats-israeli-president-herzog</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Feb 5 (Reuters) - An Australian teenager has been charged for allegedly making online death threats against Israeli President Isaac Herzog, ahead of his upcoming visit to Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 19-year-old man allegedly made the threats on a social media platform last month "towards a foreign head of state and internationally protected person", the Australian Federal Police said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The offence carries a maximum penalty of 10 years in jail.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 23:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Melania Trump says talks with Putin team continue to free Ukrainian kids</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/melania-trump-says-talks-putin-team-continue-free-ukrainian-kids</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/melania-trump-says-talks-putin-team-continue-free-ukrainian-kids</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Bo Erickson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 4 (Reuters) - U.S. first lady Melania Trump said on Wednesday she remains in contact with Russian President Vladimir Putin's team in an effort to secure the return of more Ukrainian children from Russia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I'm working on it, and we are in the process," she told reporters at the White House. "I hope we have success very soon."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She did not share details about talks between her representatives and Putin's team.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 22:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump has attacked pillars of democracy, says Human Rights Watch</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-has-attacked-pillars-democracy-says-human-rights-watch</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-has-attacked-pillars-democracy-says-human-rights-watch</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Daphne Psaledakis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 4 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump has attacked key pillars of his country's democracy, Human Rights Watch warned on Wednesday in its annual global report, citing the Republican president's immigration crackdown, threats to voting rights and other policies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 22:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran-U.S. talks to take place in Oman on Friday, U.S. official confirms</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-talks-take-place-oman-friday-us-official-confirms</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-talks-take-place-oman-friday-us-official-confirms</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 4 (Reuters) - U.S. talks with Iran will take place on Friday in Oman, a U.S. official confirmed on Wednesday, after Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi said that nuclear talks with the U.S. are set to be held in the Omani capital Muscat at around 10 a.m. on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Humeyra Pamuk; Writing by Daphne Psaledakis; Editing by Doina Chiacu)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 21:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran-US talks back on, as Trump warns supreme leader</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-talks-back-trump-warns-supreme-leader</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-talks-back-trump-warns-supreme-leader</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States said Wednesday they were going ahead with nuclear talks in Oman later this week, even as President Donald Trump piled pressure on Tehran's supreme leader by saying he should be "very worried."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doubts had swirled about the fate of the negotiations after a report earlier Wednesday that the talks between the bitter foes were falling apart due to disagreements about the format and the venue.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 21:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Washington Post cuts 30% of staff, guts foreign desk, Mideast team: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/washington-post-cuts-30-staff-guts-foreign-desk-mideast-team-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/washington-post-cuts-30-staff-guts-foreign-desk-mideast-team-what-know</guid><description>Foreign correspondents from the Post have extensively covered wars in Gaza, Ukraine and other global conflict zones.</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 20:26:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Washington Post cuts 30% of staff, guts foreign desk, Mideast team: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/washington-post-cuts-30-staff-guts-foreign-desk-mideast-team-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/washington-post-cuts-30-staff-guts-foreign-desk-mideast-team-what-know</guid><description>Foreign correspondents from the Post have extensively covered wars in Gaza, Ukraine and other global conflict zones.</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 20:26:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Washington Post cuts 30% of staff, guts foreign desk, Mideast team: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/washington-post-cuts-30-staff-guts-foreign-desk-mideast-team-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/washington-post-cuts-30-staff-guts-foreign-desk-mideast-team-what-know</guid><description>Foreign correspondents from the Post have extensively covered wars in Gaza, Ukraine and other global conflict zones.</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 20:26:33 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>