<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Shah's son confident Iran rulers to fall as Trump holds off</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/shahs-son-confident-iran-rulers-fall-trump-holds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/shahs-son-confident-iran-rulers-fall-trump-holds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The son of Iran's late shah said Friday he was confident that mass protests would topple the Islamic republic and urged international action, as President Donald Trump holds off on intervening in the unrest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reza Pahlavi, who lives in exile in the Washington area, has presented himself as leader of the opposition as the cleric-run state ruthlessly represses mass protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The Islamic republic will fall -- not if, but when," Pahlavi told a news conference in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Local UK police chief retires amid Maccabi fan ban row</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/local-uk-police-chief-retires-amid-maccabi-fan-ban-row</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/local-uk-police-chief-retires-amid-maccabi-fan-ban-row</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A top UK police chief who oversaw a contentious decision to ban Maccabi Tel Aviv football fans from a Birmingham match retired on Friday after public pressure for him to step down.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;West Midlands Police and its chief constable Craig Guildford, 52, have been under mounting pressure about how they came to the decision to bar the fans from the November 6 UEFA Europa League match with Aston Villa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move sparked political outrage in Britain, including from Prime Minister Keir Starmer, and in Israel, with Israeli leaders denouncing it as "antisemitic".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Latest US sanctions target Houthi funding networks, Treasury says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/latest-us-sanctions-target-houthi-funding-networks-treasury-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/latest-us-sanctions-target-houthi-funding-networks-treasury-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 16 (Reuters) - The Trump administration issuedfresh sanctions on Friday further targeting the Iran-backed Houthis in Yemen and the transfer of oil products, weapons and other so-called dual-use equipment that it said helped fund the group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The action targets 21 individuals and entities as well as one vessel, including some alleged front companies in Yemen, Oman and the United Arab Emirates, the U.S. Department of Treasury's Office of Foreign Assets Control said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Son of Iran's last Shah appeals for more pressure to help protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/son-irans-last-shah-appeals-more-pressure-help-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/son-irans-last-shah-appeals-more-pressure-help-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 16 - Iranian opposition figure Reza Pahlavi on Friday urged the international community to ramp up pressure on the Iranian government to help protesters overthrow clerical rule, even as a deadly crackdown appears to have broadly quelled demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pahlavi, the exiled son of Iran's toppled shah, held a news conference in Washington D.C. on Friday morning to call for political, economic and military pressure on Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 15:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff lays out conditions for deal with Iran, warns alternative 'bad one'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</guid><description>The US Middle East envoy has said he favors a diplomatic resolution of tensions with Iran rather than military action, in line with the president's recent remarks, but the threat of military escalation remains.</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:36:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff lays out conditions for deal with Iran, warns alternative 'bad one'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</guid><description>The US Middle East envoy has said he favors a diplomatic resolution of tensions with Iran rather than military action, in line with the president's recent remarks, but the threat of military escalation remains.</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:36:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff lays out conditions for deal with Iran, warns alternative 'bad one'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</guid><description>The US Middle East envoy has said he favors a diplomatic resolution of tensions with Iran rather than military action, in line with the president's recent remarks, but the threat of military escalation remains.</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:36:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff lays out conditions for deal with Iran, warns alternative 'bad one'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/witkoff-lays-out-conditions-deal-iran-warns-alternative-bad-one</guid><description>The US Middle East envoy has said he favors a diplomatic resolution of tensions with Iran rather than military action, in line with the president's recent remarks, but the threat of military escalation remains.</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:36:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US congress members visit Denmark to support Greenland</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-congress-members-visit-denmark-support-greenland</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-congress-members-visit-denmark-support-greenland</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A bipartisan US Congress delegation began a visit to Copenhagen on Friday to voice support for Denmark and Greenland after US President Donald Trump threatened to take over the Arctic island, an autonomous Danish territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two-day visit comes alongside a European show of support in the form of a military reconnaissance mission to Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 11 congressmen and women were to hold talks with Danish Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen and her Greenlandic counterpart Jens-Frederik Nielsen.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greece plans extension of territorial waters despite Turkish warning</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-plans-extension-territorial-waters-despite-turkish-warning</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-plans-extension-territorial-waters-despite-turkish-warning</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 16 (Reuters) - Greece plans to extend its territorial waters further, including potentially in the Aegean Sea, Foreign Minister George Gerapetritis said on Friday, despite Turkey's long-standing threat of war should Athens take such a step.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NATO allies, but historic rivals, have eased tensions in recent years but remain at odds over where their continental shelves begin and end in the Aegean - an area believed to hold significant energy potential and with implications for overflights and airspace.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Five pro-Palestinian activists plead not guilty over UK military base break-in</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/five-pro-palestinian-activists-plead-not-guilty-over-uk-military-base-break</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/five-pro-palestinian-activists-plead-not-guilty-over-uk-military-base-break</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 16 (Reuters) - Five pro-Palestinian activists pleaded not guilty on Friday to breaking into a British military air base and damaging two planes in protest against Britain's support for Israel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The five are accused of breaking into the Brize Norton  Royal Air Force base in central England in June and spraying red paint over two Voyager aircraft used for re-fuelling and transport.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Campaign group Palestine Action, which has since been banned by the government, said it was behind the incident.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French prosecutor seeks year in jail for Iranian over comments online</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-prosecutor-seeks-year-jail-iranian-over-comments-online</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-prosecutor-seeks-year-jail-iranian-over-comments-online</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A French prosecutor Friday sought a one-year jail term for an Iranian woman accused of promoting "terrorism" online in a case linked to a possible prisoner swap with two French citizens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mahdieh Esfandiari, a 39-year-old Iranian, was arrested in France in February on charges of promoting and inciting "terrorism" on social media over comments she is said to have made, including on Palestinian militant group Hamas attacking Israel on October 7, 2023, according to French authorities. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US envoy Barrack to meet Kurdish SDF chief Kobane in bid to avoid Syria escalation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-envoy-barrack-meet-kurdish-sdf-chief-kobane-bid-avoid-syria-escalation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-envoy-barrack-meet-kurdish-sdf-chief-kobane-bid-avoid-syria-escalation</guid><description>The US special envoy to Syria is expected to meet SDF leader Mazlum Kobane in Erbil amid mounting tensions that threaten to unravel a fragile agreement between the Kurdish-led administration and Damascus.</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:50:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Munich Security Conference scraps invitation to Iranian minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/munich-security-conference-scraps-invitation-iranian-minister</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/munich-security-conference-scraps-invitation-iranian-minister</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 16 (Reuters) - The Munich Security Conference, one of the world's top security forums, said on Friday it was withdrawing an invitation to Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi after the Tehran government's crackdown on protests across Iran this week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Several weeks ago, invitations were extended to individual government representatives from Iran. In light of current events, the Munich Security Conference will not be maintaining these invitations," it said in an emailed statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-What is the status of Iran's main nuclear facilities?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-what-status-irans-main-nuclear-facilities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-what-status-irans-main-nuclear-facilities</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Francois Murphy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VIENNA, Jan 16 (Reuters) - Regional fears of a U.S. attack on Iran have eased after President Donald Trump said Tehran had assured him that protesters would not be executed, but he is keeping "all of his options on the table", the White House said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last major strikes on Iran were carried out by Israel and the United States in June, mainly targeting key nuclear facilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHICH NUCLEAR SITES WERE HIT?&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi King Salman having tests in hospital, state media says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-king-salman-having-tests-hospital-state-media-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-king-salman-having-tests-hospital-state-media-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 16 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia's 90-year-old King Salman was undergoing medical tests in a hospital in Riyadh, the state news agency said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;King of the world's biggest oil exporter and a major U.S. ally in the Middle East, he had received medical care for lung inflammation in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He last chaired a cabinet meeting on Tuesday, according to state news agency SPA.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ahmed Elimam;Editing by Alison Williams and Andrew Cawthorne)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany's Merz to raise migrant returns in talks with Syrian leader</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germanys-merz-raise-migrant-returns-talks-syrian-leader</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germanys-merz-raise-migrant-returns-talks-syrian-leader</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 16 (Reuters) - German Chancellor Friedrich Merz will raise topics including the political transition in Syria and the return of migrants to their homeland in talks with Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa in Berlin next Tuesday, a government spokesperson said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have an interest in deepening relations and, if you like, making a fresh start with the new Syrian government," the spokesperson said. "We have many important issues to address ... One example is the return of Syrians to their home country."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Africa to probe Iran's role in war games that angered US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/south-africa-probe-irans-role-war-games-angered-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/south-africa-probe-irans-role-war-games-angered-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;South Africa's defence minister has ordered an inquiry into reports of Iran's participation in navy exercises, apparently against the instructions of the president, the ministry said Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The probe comes after the United States sharply criticised the past week's drills, which brought vessels from China, Iran, Russia and the United Arab Emirates to waters off Cape Town.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria poised to attack Kurdish-held towns to pressure stalled talks, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-poised-attack-kurdish-held-towns-pressure-stalled-talks-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-poised-attack-kurdish-held-towns-pressure-stalled-talks-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Suleiman Al-Khalidi, Mahmoud Hasano , Jonathan Spicer and Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 15 (Reuters) - Syrian troops are poised to attack towns in the north and east held by Kurdish fighters, sources familiar with the matter said, to pressure autonomy-minded Kurds into making concessions in deadlocked talks with the Damascus government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran protests abate after deadly crackdown, residents and rights group say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protests-abate-after-deadly-crackdown-residents-and-rights-group-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protests-abate-after-deadly-crackdown-residents-and-rights-group-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi and Nayera Abdallah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dubai, Jan 16 (Reuters) - Iran's deadly crackdown appears to have broadly quelled protests for now, according to a rights group and residents, as state media reported more arrests on Friday in the shadow of U.S. threats to intervene if killing continues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After President Donald Trump's repeated threats of military action against Iran in support of protesters, fears of a U.S. attack have retreated since Wednesday, when Trump said he'd been told killings in the crackdown were easing.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 11:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>