<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>U.S., in control of oil dollars, heaps pressure on Iraq over Iranian influence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-control-oil-dollars-heaps-pressure-iraq-over-iranian-influence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-control-oil-dollars-heaps-pressure-iraq-over-iranian-influence</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maha El Dahan, Timour Azhari and Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI/WASHINGTON, Jan 23 - Washington has threatened senior Iraqi politicians with sanctions targeting the Iraqi state — including potentially its critical supply of oil revenue sourced via the Federal Reserve Bank of New York — should Iran-backed armed groups be included in the next government, four sources told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian cleric says Iran may target US investments in region if attacked</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-cleric-says-iran-may-target-us-investments-region-if-attacked</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-cleric-says-iran-may-target-us-investments-region-if-attacked</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 23 (Reuters) - An influential Iranian cleric warned on Friday that Iran may target U.S.-linked investments in the region in retaliation for any U.S. attack on the Islamic Republic, Iranian news agencies reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump said on Thursday that the United States had an "armada" heading toward Iran but hoped he would not have to use it, as he renewed warnings to Tehran against killing protesters or restarting its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Israel aims to ensure more Palestinians are let out of Gaza than back in</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-israel-aims-ensure-more-palestinians-are-let-out-gaza-back</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-israel-aims-ensure-more-palestinians-are-let-out-gaza-back</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV, Jan 23 (Reuters) - Israel wants to restrict the number of Palestinians entering Gaza through the border crossing with Egypt to ensure that more are allowed out than in, three sources briefed on the matter said ahead of the border's expected opening next week.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Europeans among 150 IS detainees transferred from Syria to Iraq</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/europeans-among-150-detainees-transferred-syria-iraq</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/europeans-among-150-detainees-transferred-syria-iraq</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Europeans were among 150 senior Islamic State group detainees transferred this week by the US military from Kurdish custody in Syria to Iraq, whose premier urged EU countries to repatriate their nationals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They were among an estimated 7,000 jihadists due to be moved across the border to Iraq as the Kurdish-led force that has held them for years relinquishes swathes of territory to the advancing Syrian army.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>West Bank education centre could close in days due to Israeli seizure threat, says UNRWA</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-education-centre-could-close-days-due-israeli-seizure-threat-says-unrwa</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-education-centre-could-close-days-due-israeli-seizure-threat-says-unrwa</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 23 (Reuters) - A training centre for hundreds of Palestinians in the occupied West Bank could be closed within days by Israeli authorities, jeopardising the education of students, the U.N. Palestinian refugee agency said on Friday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;  The Kalandia Training Centre, which teaches 350 young male students from across the West Bank skills such as plumbing and vehicle maintenance, could be shut, as the land it sits on is at risk of expropriation by Israeli authorities, UNRWA said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's NATO front line comments 'deeply disappointing', UK minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-nato-front-line-comments-deeply-disappointing-uk-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-nato-front-line-comments-deeply-disappointing-uk-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 23 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump's comments that NATO troops stayed off the front line in Afghanistan were "deeply disappointing", a British minister said on Friday, noting that many European soldiers had died supporting American-led operations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Criticising NATO in a Fox News interview on Thursday, Trump said the United States had "never needed" the alliance and that its allies stayed "a little off the front lines" in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli Bedouin say hope for better life crushed after deadly crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-bedouin-say-hope-better-life-crushed-after-deadly-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-bedouin-say-hope-better-life-crushed-after-deadly-crackdown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When the Israeli Bedouin village of Tarabin al-Sana backed Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's party in the last elections, they expected their lives would improve. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three years later, the small community in the Negev has been left stunned after a two-week crackdown during which police shot dead a 36-year-old father of six.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israeli police set up roadblocks, fired tear gas and searched homes in scenes reminiscent of military raids on Palestinian towns in the occupied West Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tarabin's residents, however, are Israeli citizens.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-Who is leading Russia's delegation at the Ukraine talks in Abu Dhabi?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-who-leading-russias-delegation-ukraine-talks-abu-dhabi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-who-leading-russias-delegation-ukraine-talks-abu-dhabi</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 23 (Reuters) - Russian Admiral Igor Kostyukov is set to head Moscow's team at trilateral security talks with the U.S. and Ukraine on Friday in Abu Dhabi, as part of efforts to reach a deal to end the war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What do we know about Kostyukov?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAREER IN MILITARY INTELLIGENCE&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kostyukov is the director of Russia's military intelligence organisation, known as the GRU. Born in 1961, he received a naval education and went on to serve as a military diplomat, which included a posting as a military attache to the Russian embassy in Greece in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian government says it controls prison in Raqqa with Islamic State-linked detainees</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-says-it-controls-prison-raqqa-islamic-state-linked-detainees</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-says-it-controls-prison-raqqa-islamic-state-linked-detainees</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 23 (Reuters) - Syria's Interior Ministry said on Friday it had taken over al-Aktan prison in the city of Raqqa in northeastern Syria, a facility that was formerly under the control of Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prison has been holding detainees linked to the militant group Islamic State, and witnessed clashes in its vicinity this week between advancing Syrian government forces and the SDF.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelenskiy says territorial issue to be discussed at trilateral talks in UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/zelenskiy-says-territorial-issue-be-discussed-trilateral-talks-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/zelenskiy-says-territorial-issue-be-discussed-trilateral-talks-uae</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Anna Pruchnicka&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Jan 23 (Reuters) - President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said on Friday that the vital question of territory in Ukraine's war with Russia would be discussed at U.S.-brokered trilateral talks in Abu Dhabi on Friday and Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kyiv is under mounting U.S. pressure to secure a peace deal in the nearly four-year-old war with Moscow, which has demanded Ukraine give up its entire eastern area of Donbas before it stops fighting.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran lambasts Zelensky after Davos 'bully' warning</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-lambasts-zelensky-after-davos-bully-warning</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-lambasts-zelensky-after-davos-bully-warning</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's foreign minister on Friday launched a furious tirade against Volodymyr Zelensky after the Ukrainian president commented in Davos that the deadly crackdown on protests in the Islamic republic showed that if authorities "kill enough people" they stay in power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zelensky, whose country has been fighting the full-scale Russian invasion for almost four years, said in a speech at the World Economic Forum on Thursday that if Iran's clerical leadership was able to remain in power, it was a "clear signal to every bully".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN rights body holds emergency session on Iran's protest crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-body-holds-emergency-session-irans-protest-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-body-holds-emergency-session-irans-protest-crackdown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emma Farge and Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 23 (Reuters) - The U.N. Human Rights Council will hold an emergency session on Friday to discuss the "alarming violence" used in Iran against protesters, while a group of states will call on United Nations' investigators to document alleged abuses for future trials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rights groups say thousands, including bystanders, were killed during the unrest, which represented the biggest challenge to Iran's clerical government since 2022.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran: IAEA must clarify stance on June attacks before inspecting bombed sites</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-iaea-must-clarify-stance-june-attacks-inspecting-bombed-sites</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-iaea-must-clarify-stance-june-attacks-inspecting-bombed-sites</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 23 (Reuters) - The U.N. nuclear watchdog must clarify its stance on U.S. and Israeli attacks on Iran's nuclear sites last June before inspectors are allowed to visit those facilities, Iranian media on Friday quoted the country's atomic chief as saying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mohammad Eslami said the inspections so far had been limited to undamaged sites and he criticised the watchdog for letting Israeli and U.S. pressure influence its actions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spain will not join Trump's Board of Peace, PM says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/spain-will-not-join-trumps-board-peace-pm-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/spain-will-not-join-trumps-board-peace-pm-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MADRID, Jan 23 (Reuters) - Spain will not take part in the Board of Peace initiative launched by U.S. President Donald Trump to tackle global conflicts, saying the decision was consistent with its belief in multilateralism and the United Nations system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We appreciate the invitation, but we decline," Spanish Prime Minister Pedro Sanchez told reporters late on Thursday after an EU summit in Brussels. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump revokes Canada's invitation to join Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-revokes-canadas-invitation-join-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-revokes-canadas-invitation-join-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jasper Ward and Ismail Shakil&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/OTTAWA, Jan 22 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump withdrew on Thursday an invitation for Canada to join his Board of Peace initiative aimed at resolving global conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump's aboutface follows Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney's speech at the World Economic Forum in Davos, where he openly decried powerful nations using economic integration as weapons and tariffs as leverage.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 03:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US urges nations to repatriate their citizens from Iraqi facilities with ISIS members</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-urges-nations-repatriate-their-citizens-iraqi-facilities-isis-members</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-urges-nations-repatriate-their-citizens-iraqi-facilities-isis-members</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 22 (Reuters) - U.S. Secretary of State Marco Rubio said on Thursday that Washington welcomed Iraq's initiative to detain Islamic State members in secure facilities in Iraq while also urging nations to repatriate their citizens in these facilities "to face justice."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The United States welcomes the Government of Iraq's initiative to detain ISIS terrorists in secure facilities in Iraq, following recent instability in northeast Syria," Rubio said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 21:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US military assets heading to Middle East even as Trump backs off toughest Iran rhetoric</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-military-assets-heading-middle-east-even-trump-backs-toughest-iran-rhetoric</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-military-assets-heading-middle-east-even-trump-backs-toughest-iran-rhetoric</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 22 (Reuters) - A U.S. military aircraft carrier strike group and other assets will arrive in the Middle East region in the coming days, two U.S. officials said on Thursday, even as U.S. President Donald Trump voices hopes of avoiding new military action against Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. warships including the aircraft carrier USS Abraham Lincoln, several destroyers and fighter aircraft started moving from the Asia-Pacific last week as tensions between Iran and the United States soared following a severe crackdown on protests across Iran in recent months.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's economy can weather more Red Sea attacks, says finance minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-economy-can-weather-more-red-sea-attacks-says-finance-minister</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-economy-can-weather-more-red-sea-attacks-says-finance-minister</guid><description>Egypt lost some $13 billion worth of Suez Canal fees over two years due to Houthi attacks in the Red Sea, according to estimates from Egyptian officials.</description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:23:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's economy can weather more Red Sea attacks, says finance minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-economy-can-weather-more-red-sea-attacks-says-finance-minister</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-economy-can-weather-more-red-sea-attacks-says-finance-minister</guid><description>Egypt lost some $13 billion worth of Suez Canal fees over two years due to Houthi attacks in the Red Sea, according to estimates from Egyptian officials.</description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:23:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's economy can weather more Red Sea attacks, says finance minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-economy-can-weather-more-red-sea-attacks-says-finance-minister</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-economy-can-weather-more-red-sea-attacks-says-finance-minister</guid><description>Egypt lost some $13 billion worth of Suez Canal fees over two years due to Houthi attacks in the Red Sea, according to estimates from Egyptian officials.</description><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:23:29 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>