<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Saudi Arabia weighs expansion of premium residency program to lure rich</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabia-weighs-expansion-premium-residency-program-lure-rich</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabia-weighs-expansion-premium-residency-program-lure-rich</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 28 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia is drafting plans to extend its premium residency program to a wider selection of desirable individuals, including superyacht owners, those looking to live in the kingdom's flagship development projects and top students, a person with direct knowledge of the matter said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deliberations, which have not yet been finalized, are part of efforts to attract foreign capital and visitors under Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman's Vision 2030 plan to diversify the country's economy away from oil and transform society.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey aims to lift trade volume with Nigeria to $5 billion</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-aims-lift-trade-volume-nigeria-5-billion</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-aims-lift-trade-volume-nigeria-5-billion</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Camillus Eboh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ABUJA, Jan 28 (Reuters) - Turkey aims to lift its trade volume with Nigeria to $5 billion from about $2 billion, President Tayyip Erdogan said on Tuesday following a meeting with visiting Nigerian President Bola Tinubu.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey exports aircraft, helicopters, machinery, iron and steel, and chemical products to Nigeria, while Nigeria supplies crude oil and agricultural commodities to Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq PM candidate Maliki denounces Trump's 'blatant' interference</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraq-pm-candidate-maliki-denounces-trumps-blatant-interference</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraq-pm-candidate-maliki-denounces-trumps-blatant-interference</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iraq's main candidate for the premiership, Nouri al-Maliki, on Wednesday denounced Washington's "blatant interference", after President Donald Trump threatened to end all support to the country if Maliki took the post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The US has held significant sway over Iraqi politics since leading the 2003 invasion that ousted long-time ruler Saddam Hussein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We categorically reject the blatant American interference in Iraq's internal affairs," said Maliki, the only former Iraqi prime minister to have served two terms since the invasion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump tells Iran to make nuclear deal or next attack will be 'far worse'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-tells-iran-make-nuclear-deal-or-next-attack-will-be-far-worse</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-tells-iran-make-nuclear-deal-or-next-attack-will-be-far-worse</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 28 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump urged Iran on Wednesday to come to the table and make a deal on nuclear weapons or the next U.S. attack would be far worse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Hopefully Iran will quickly 'Come to the Table' and negotiate a fair and equitable deal - NO NUCLEAR WEAPONS - one that is good for all parties. Time is running out, it is truly of the essence!" Trump wrote in a social media post.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel steps up evictions of Palestinians from East Jerusalem</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-steps-evictions-palestinians-east-jerusalem</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-steps-evictions-palestinians-east-jerusalem</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 28 (Reuters) - In Silwan in East Jerusalem, south of the Al-Aqsa Mosque, Kayed Rajabi and his neighbors have been handed eviction orders in favor of an Israeli settler organization which has already taken over parts of the Palestinian district.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rajabi's home is surrounded by buildings that have raised large Israeli flags - a sign they are owned by settlers, who he said began buying homes in 2004, and have obtained about 40 buildings in Silwan now, many via forced evictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Intimidation and coercion': Iran pressuring families of killed protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/intimidation-and-coercion-iran-pressuring-families-killed-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/intimidation-and-coercion-iran-pressuring-families-killed-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When Hossein Mahmoudi, 36, was killed during the anti-government protests in Iran, it only marked the start of the trauma for his family.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mahmoudi was shot dead by security forces on January 8 in Falavarjan outside the central city of Isfahan, but it was only on January 16, over a week later, that his family were able to recover his body, according to Norway-based NGO Iran Human Rights (IHR), which has investigated the case.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli lawmakers to hold initial vote on draft budget as elections loom</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-lawmakers-hold-initial-vote-draft-budget-elections-loom</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-lawmakers-hold-initial-vote-draft-budget-elections-loom</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 28 (Reuters) - Israel's parliament was expected to take its initial vote on the 2026 state budget draft on Wednesday, in a test of Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's government at a time when his coalition has been beset by political fractures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The budget, as well as an accompanying economic plan, faces an uphill battle for approval as the government has become increasingly polarized. By law it must be approved by the end of March or a snap election would be triggered.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Pride of the entire nation': Israel holds funeral for last Gaza hostage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pride-entire-nation-israel-holds-funeral-last-gaza-hostage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pride-entire-nation-israel-holds-funeral-last-gaza-hostage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of tearful mourners packed a stadium in southern Israel on Wednesday for the funeral of Ran Gvili, the last Gaza hostage whose burial marks the end of a painful national saga triggered by Hamas's 2023 attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israeli forces on Monday brought home the remains of Gvili, who was killed in action and whose body Palestinian militants took into Gaza during their October 7 attack, which triggered a devastating two-year war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Comeback puts Iraq's Maliki in Trump's crosshairs</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/comeback-puts-iraqs-maliki-trumps-crosshairs</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/comeback-puts-iraqs-maliki-trumps-crosshairs</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Rasheed and Michael Georgy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD/DUBAI, Jan 28 (Reuters) - Former Iraqi Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki, who appeared poised for a remarkable comeback despite accusations he stoked sectarian strife and allowed the rise of Islamic State,now finds himself in U.S. President Donald Trump's crosshairs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inhis latest direct intervention in another country’s politics,Trump on Tuesday warned Iraq that if it picked the Iranian-backed Maliki as its prime minister again Washington would no longer help the major oil producer and close U.S. ally. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says 'time running out' as Iran rejects talks amid 'threats'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-time-running-out-iran-rejects-talks-amid-threats</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-time-running-out-iran-rejects-talks-amid-threats</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump on Wednesday warned Iran that time was running out for the Islamic republic to prevent American military intervention as Tehran rejected holding negotiations against a backdrop of threats.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump has never ruled out a new attack on Iran in the wake of its deadly crackdown on protests this month, to follow the 12-day June war between the Islamic republic and Israel which the US backed and joined. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A US naval strike group that Trump described as an "armada" led by aircraft carrier the USS Abraham Lincoln is now lurking in Middle East waters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo appeals against rising anti-Semitism in weekly audience</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pope-leo-appeals-against-rising-anti-semitism-weekly-audience</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pope-leo-appeals-against-rising-anti-semitism-weekly-audience</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;VATICAN CITY, Jan 28 (Reuters) - Pope Leo appealed against the global rise of anti-Semitism on Wednesday, marking the annual commemoration of the Holocaust during his weekly audience at the Vatican with a prayer for a world without prejudice or racism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"On this annual occasion of painful remembrance, I ask the Almighty for the gift of a world with no more antisemitism and, with no more prejudice, oppression, or persecution of any human being," said the pope.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian leader to meet Putin, Russia seeks deal on military bases</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-leader-meet-putin-russia-seeks-deal-military-bases</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-leader-meet-putin-russia-seeks-deal-military-bases</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa will meet Russian counterpart Vladimir Putin in Moscow on Wednesday, as the Kremlin seeks to secure the future of its military bases in the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Putin and Sharaa struck a conciliatory tone at their previous meeting in October, their first since Sharaa's rebel forces toppled Moscow-ally Bashar al-Assad in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But Russia's continued sheltering of Assad and his wife since their ouster remains a thorny issue. Sharaa has repeatedly pushed Russia for their extradition. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says it didn't request negotiations with U.S., foreign minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-it-didnt-request-negotiations-us-foreign-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-it-didnt-request-negotiations-us-foreign-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 28 (Reuters) - Iran's Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi denied being in contact with U.S. special envoy Steve Witkoff in recent days or requesting negotiations, state media reported on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The foreign minister added Tehran remains in contact with mediating countries that are "holding consultations".  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey urges US to resolve Iran disputes one by one, says Iran ready for nuclear talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-urges-us-resolve-iran-disputes-one-one-says-iran-ready-nuclear-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-urges-us-resolve-iran-disputes-one-one-says-iran-ready-nuclear-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 28 (Reuters) - Turkey's foreign minister on Wednesday urged the U.S. to resolve its disputes with Iran "one by one" instead of through a sweeping deal, saying this would avoid humiliating Iranian officials, and added that Tehran was ready for talks on its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump said last week that Washington had an "armada" heading toward Iran but hoped he would not have to use it, as he renewed warnings to Tehran against killing protesters or restarting its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel to hold funeral for last hostage recovered from Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-hold-funeral-last-hostage-recovered-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-hold-funeral-last-hostage-recovered-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MEITAR, Israel, Jan 28 (Reuters) - The remains of the last Israeli captive recovered from the Gaza Strip were set to be buried on Wednesday in a funeral that will help Israel turn the page after one of the most tramautising periods in its history. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ran Gvili, an off-duty police officer, was killed fighting militants during the October 7, 2023 Hamas attack on southern Israel. He was then seized and taken back into Gaza by the Islamic Jihad militant group, Israeli officials say. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-US intelligence raises doubts about Venezuela leader's cooperation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-us-intelligence-raises-doubts-about-venezuela-leaders-cooperation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-us-intelligence-raises-doubts-about-venezuela-leaders-cooperation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Erin Banco, Jonathan Landay and Matt Spetalnick&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NEW YORK, Jan 27 (Reuters) - U.S. intelligence reports have raised doubts about whether interim Venezuelan President Delcy Rodriguez will cooperate with the Trump administration by formally cutting ties with U.S. adversaries, four people familiar with the reports said in recent days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. officials have said publicly they want the interim president to sever relations with close international allies  like Iran, China and Russia, including expelling their diplomats and advisers from Venezuela. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 00:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US won't help Iraq if it picks Maliki as prime minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-us-wont-help-iraq-if-it-picks-maliki-prime-minister</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-us-wont-help-iraq-if-it-picks-maliki-prime-minister</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 27 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump on Tuesday warned Iraq against picking Nouri al-Maliki as its prime minister, saying the United States would no longer help the Middle Eastern country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I'm hearing that the Great Country of Iraq might make a very bad choice by reinstalling Nouri al-Maliki as Prime Minister," Trump wrote on Truth Social.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump warns US to end support for Iraq if Maliki returns</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-warns-us-end-support-iraq-if-maliki-returns</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-warns-us-end-support-iraq-if-maliki-returns</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump on Tuesday threatened to end all US support for Iraq if Nouri al-Maliki, a former prime minister with ties to Iran, returns to the post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump, in his latest blatant intervention in another country's politics, said that Iraq would make a "very bad choice" with Maliki, who has been nominated as prime minister by the largest Shiite bloc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Last time Maliki was in power, the Country descended into poverty and total chaos. That should not be allowed to happen again," Trump wrote on his Truth Social platform.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>YPG spokesman: Syrian forces' strategy is to isolate Kurdish towns and cities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ypg-spokesman-syrian-forces-strategy-isolate-kurdish-towns-and-cities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ypg-spokesman-syrian-forces-strategy-isolate-kurdish-towns-and-cities</guid><description>In an interview with Al-Monitor, YPG spokesman Siyamend Ali said Kurdish forces were successfully repelling advances by the Syrian army, while Damascus accused the Kurds of launching unprovoked attacks.</description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:37:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>YPG spokesman: Syrian forces' strategy is to isolate Kurdish towns and cities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ypg-spokesman-syrian-forces-strategy-isolate-kurdish-towns-and-cities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ypg-spokesman-syrian-forces-strategy-isolate-kurdish-towns-and-cities</guid><description>In an interview with Al-Monitor, YPG spokesman Siyamend Ali said Kurdish forces were successfully repelling advances by the Syrian army, while Damascus accused the Kurds of launching unprovoked attacks.</description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:37:47 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>