<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Trump, Netanyahu agreed US should press Iran to cut oil sales to China, Axios reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-netanyahu-agreed-us-should-press-iran-cut-oil-sales-china-axios-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-netanyahu-agreed-us-should-press-iran-cut-oil-sales-china-axios-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 14 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu agreed at a White House meeting on Wednesday that the U.S. would work to reduce Iran's oil exports to China, Axios reported, citing two U.S. officials briefed on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We agreed that we will go full force with maximum pressure against Iran, for example, regarding Iranian oil sales to China," Axios reported on Saturday, quoting a senior U.S. official.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli airstrikes kill 11 in Gaza, Palestinians say; Israel says Hamas violated truce</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-airstrikes-kill-11-gaza-palestinians-say-israel-says-hamas-violated-truce</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-airstrikes-kill-11-gaza-palestinians-say-israel-says-hamas-violated-truce</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/JERUSALEM, Feb 15 (Reuters) - Israel fired airstrikes across the Gaza Strip on Sunday, killing at least 11 Palestinians, Palestinian officials said, in what the military called a response to ceasefire violations by Palestinian militant group Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gaza medics said an Israeli airstrike on a tent encampment housing displaced families killed at least four people, while health officials said another strike killed five in Khan Younis in the south and another person was shot dead in the north.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rubio says US does not dispute Navalny poisoning assessment by Europeans</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/rubio-says-us-does-not-dispute-navalny-poisoning-assessment-europeans</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/rubio-says-us-does-not-dispute-navalny-poisoning-assessment-europeans</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BUDAPEST, Feb 15 (Reuters) - U.S. Secretary of State Marco Rubio on Sunday called "troubling" a report by five European allies blaming Russia for killing late Kremlin critic Alexei Navalny using toxin from poison dart frogs, adding that Washington had no reason to question it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We obviously are aware of the report. It's a troubling report. We're aware of that case of Mr. Navalny and certainly... we don't have any reason to question it," Rubio told reporters at a news conference in Brastislava during a visit to Slovakia.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says potential energy, mining and aircraft deals on table in talks with US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-says-potential-energy-mining-and-aircraft-deals-table-talks-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-says-potential-energy-mining-and-aircraft-deals-table-talks-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 15 (Reuters) - Iran is pursuing a nuclear agreement with the U.S. that delivers economic benefits for both sides, an Iranian diplomat was reported as saying on Sunday, days before a second round of talks between Tehran and Washington. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Board of Peace members have pledged more than $5 billion for Gaza, Trump says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/board-peace-members-have-pledged-more-5-billion-gaza-trump-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/board-peace-members-have-pledged-more-5-billion-gaza-trump-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 15 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said he will announce on Thursday that Board of Peace member states have pledged more than $5 billion for reconstruction and humanitarian efforts in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Sunday post on Truth Social, Trump wrote that member states have also committed thousands of personnel toward a U.N.-authorized stabilization force and local police in the Palestinian enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ryan Patrick Jones in Toronto; Editing by Sergio Non and Matthew Lewis)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli cabinet approves West Bank land registration, Palestinians condemn 'de-facto annexation'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-cabinet-approves-west-bank-land-registration-palestinians-condemn-de</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-cabinet-approves-west-bank-land-registration-palestinians-condemn-de</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 15 (Reuters) - Israel's cabinet on Sunday approved further measures to tighten Israel's control over the occupied West Bank and make it easier for settlers to buy land, in a move Palestinians called "a de-facto annexation".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The West Bank is among the territories that the Palestinians seek for a future independent state. Much of it is under Israeli military control, with limited Palestinian self-rule in some areas run by the Western-backed Palestinian Authority (PA).&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza civil defence says Israeli strikes kill 12</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-civil-defence-says-israeli-strikes-kill-12</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-civil-defence-says-israeli-strikes-kill-12</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gaza's civil defence agency reported that Israeli strikes killed at least 12 people since dawn on Sunday, while a military official said the attacks were in response to ceasefire violations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a US-brokered truce that entered its second phase last month, violence has continued in the Palestinian territory, with Israel and Hamas blaming each other for violating the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The civil defence agency, which operates as a rescue force under Hamas authorities, said one strike hit a tent of displaced people in northern Gaza and another targeted an area in the south.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 14:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza civil defence says Israeli strikes kill 12 since dawn</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-civil-defence-says-israeli-strikes-kill-12-dawn</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-civil-defence-says-israeli-strikes-kill-12-dawn</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gaza's civil defence agency reported that Israeli strikes killed at least 12 people since dawn on Sunday, while a military official said the attacks were in response to ceasefire violations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a US-brokered truce that entered its second phase last month, violence has continued in the Palestinian territory, with Israel and Hamas blaming each other for violating the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The civil defence agency, which operates as a rescue force under Hamas authorities, said one strike hit a tent of displaced people in northern Gaza and another targeted an area in the south.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 11:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hiam Abbass says 'cinema is a political act' after Berlin row</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hiam-abbass-says-cinema-political-act-after-berlin-row</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hiam-abbass-says-cinema-political-act-after-berlin-row</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The start of this year's Berlin Film Festival was marked by a row over how far film should venture into politics but for prominent French-Palestinian actor Hiam Abbass, "everything we do is a political act".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abbass is starring in two films being presented at this year's Berlinale festival and in an AFP interview she emphasised the importance of a politically engaged approach to cinema.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 11:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>250,000 at rally in Germany demand 'game over' for Iran's leaders</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/250000-rally-germany-demand-game-over-irans-leaders</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/250000-rally-germany-demand-game-over-irans-leaders</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Cheered by a massive crowd under a sea of flags, the son of Iran's toppled monarch told a mass rally in Munich on Saturday he wants to lead the country into a democratic future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police said some 250,000 pro-monarchist opponents of the Islamic republic's leadership travelled from across Europe to take part in the demonstration held while world leaders met nearby at the Munich Security Conference.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 18:30:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Swiss say Oman to host US-Iran talks in Geneva next week</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/swiss-say-oman-host-us-iran-talks-geneva-next-week</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/swiss-say-oman-host-us-iran-talks-geneva-next-week</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Switzerland said Saturday that Oman would host talks between the United States and Iran in Geneva next week, with Washington pushing Tehran to make a deal to limit its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Switzerland stands ready at all times to offer its good offices to facilitate dialogue between the United States and Iran," a Swiss foreign ministry spokesman told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On February 6, Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araghchi held talks in Oman with US envoy Steve Witkoff and US President Donald Trump's influential son-in-law Jared Kushner.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 17:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Son of Iran's last shah urges US action as supporters rally in Munich</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/son-irans-last-shah-urges-us-action-supporters-rally-munich</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/son-irans-last-shah-urges-us-action-supporters-rally-munich</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The exiled son of Iran's last shah said he was ready to lead the country to a "secular democratic future" at a rally in Munich on Saturday, after US President Donald Trump said a change of power would be the "best thing".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It came as Washington continued to engage diplomatically with Tehran's government, with Switzerland on Saturday confirming that mediator Oman would host a fresh round of talks in Geneva next week. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 16:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>About 200,000 join Iran demonstration in Munich: police</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/about-200000-join-iran-demonstration-munich-police</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/about-200000-join-iran-demonstration-munich-police</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;About 200,000 people joined a demonstration against the Iranian government in Munich on Saturday, police said, as world leaders gathered nearby for a security conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pro-monarchist protesters rallied on the German city's Theresienwiese fairgrounds, denouncing the leadership of Iran's Islamic Republic following the deadly repression of nationwide protests in January.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human rights groups have reported that thousands of protesters were killed in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 14:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian leader urges removal of all Israeli 'obstacles' on Gaza ceasefire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-leader-urges-removal-all-israeli-obstacles-gaza-ceasefire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-leader-urges-removal-all-israeli-obstacles-gaza-ceasefire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Palestinian president Mahmud Abbas called on Saturday for the removal of "all obstacles" he said Israel has imposed on implementing phase two of the Gaza ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We emphasise the need to lift all obstacles imposed by the Israeli occupation on the implementation of the provisions related to the second phase of the agreement," Abbas said, in a speech read by his prime minister Mohammed Mustafa at an African Union summit in Ethiopia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This included the work of a technocratic committee established to oversee the daily governance of Gaza, he added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 13:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Iran harnesses digital repression, China tech ties to quash dissent</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</guid><description>Though Iran’s street protests have largely subsided, the struggle has shifted to the digital front, where a complex infrastructure of servers, satellites and centralized controls is being used to stifle dissent.</description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:50:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Iran harnesses digital repression, China tech ties to quash dissent</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</guid><description>Though Iran’s street protests have largely subsided, the struggle has shifted to the digital front, where a complex infrastructure of servers, satellites and centralized controls is being used to stifle dissent.</description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:50:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Iran harnesses digital repression, China tech ties to quash dissent</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</guid><description>Though Iran’s street protests have largely subsided, the struggle has shifted to the digital front, where a complex infrastructure of servers, satellites and centralized controls is being used to stifle dissent.</description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:50:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Iran harnesses digital repression, China tech ties to quash dissent</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/how-iran-harnesses-digital-repression-china-tech-ties-quash-dissent</guid><description>Though Iran’s street protests have largely subsided, the struggle has shifted to the digital front, where a complex infrastructure of servers, satellites and centralized controls is being used to stifle dissent.</description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:50:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian writer Roy pulls out of Berlin Film Festival over Gaza row</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/indian-writer-roy-pulls-out-berlin-film-festival-over-gaza-row</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/indian-writer-roy-pulls-out-berlin-film-festival-over-gaza-row</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Award-winning Indian writer Arundhati Roy said Friday she was withdrawing from the Berlin Film Festival over jury president Wim Wenders's comments that cinema should "stay out of politics" when asked about Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Roy said in a statement sent to AFP that she was "shocked and disgusted" by responses from Wenders and other jury members to a question about the Palestinian territory at a press conference on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump tells troops 'fear' is powerful motivator in difficult Iran talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-tells-troops-fear-powerful-motivator-difficult-iran-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-tells-troops-fear-powerful-motivator-difficult-iran-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steve Holland and Trevor Hunnicutt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FORT BRAGG, North Carolina, Feb 13 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump told U.S. troops on Friday that Iran has been “difficult” in nuclear negotiations and suggested that instilling fear in Tehran may be necessary to resolve the standoff peacefully.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"They've been difficult to make a deal," Trump said of the Iranians before an audience of active-duty soldiers at Fort Bragg Army base in North Carolina after U.S. officials said they were sending a second aircraft carrier to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 20:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>