<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Syrian security convoy heads to key Kurdish city under US-backed deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrian-security-convoy-heads-key-kurdish-city-under-us-backed-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrian-security-convoy-heads-key-kurdish-city-under-us-backed-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 3 (Reuters) - Syrian government security forces moved towards the Kurdish-controlled northeastern city of Qamishli on Tuesday, security sources and witnesses said, as they implement a U.S.-backed deal to bring Kurdish-run regions under the control of Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deal, declared on Friday, staved off the prospect of further confrontation between Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa's government and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, which lost swathes of eastern and northern Syria to government troops in January.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran president confirms talks with US after Trump's threats</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-president-confirms-talks-us-after-trumps-threats</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-president-confirms-talks-us-after-trumps-threats</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's president confirmed on Tuesday that he had ordered the start of talks with the United States, provided they were free of threats, after his counterpart Donald Trump suggested "bad things" would happen without a deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has been no official confirmation from Iran on where the talks would be held, but an Arab official, speaking on condition of anonymity, told AFP a meeting was likely to take place in Turkey on Friday, following diplomatic interventions by Ankara, as well as Egypt, Oman and Qatar.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tearful Gazans finally reunite after limited Rafah reopening</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tearful-gazans-finally-reunite-after-limited-rafah-reopening</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tearful-gazans-finally-reunite-after-limited-rafah-reopening</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gazans long-separated from their loved ones shed tears of joy after the limited reopening of the Rafah crossing with Egypt allowed a handful to finally return to the war-shattered territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jubilant crowds filmed on their phones as they flocked around a bus carrying returnees to Nasser Hospital in the southern city of Khan Yunis late in the night on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AFP footage showed a man holding a young child up to the window to greet those arriving, while women wept as they were at last able to embrace.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greece to soon announce social media ban for children under 15, government source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/greece-soon-announce-social-media-ban-children-under-15-government-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/greece-soon-announce-social-media-ban-children-under-15-government-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Greece is "very close" to announcing a social media ban for children aged under 15, a senior government source told Reuters on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spain said on Tuesday that it plans to ban social media for those aged under 16 and will create a law to hold social media executives personally responsible for hate speech on their platforms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Renee Maltezou; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 13:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine to adjust peace negotiators' work after Russia's strike, Zelenskiy says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukraine-adjust-peace-negotiators-work-after-russias-strike-zelenskiy-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukraine-adjust-peace-negotiators-work-after-russias-strike-zelenskiy-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Feb 3 (Reuters) - The work of Ukraine's negotiating team will be adjusted after Russia's overnight attack on Ukrainian energy facilities, which involved a record number of ballistic missiles, President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was a deliberate attack against energy infrastructure, involving a record number of ballistic missiles," Zelenskiy said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 12:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>WHO says first five patients evacuated via Gaza's Rafah crossing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/who-says-first-five-patients-evacuated-gazas-rafah-crossing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/who-says-first-five-patients-evacuated-gazas-rafah-crossing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Feb 3 (Reuters) - A World Health Organization official said on Tuesday that the first five patients were transferred through Gaza's Rafah crossing with Egypt, which reopened on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"On the second of February, WHO and partners supported the medical evacuation of five patients and seven companions to Egypt via the Rafah crossing," said WHO spokesperson Christian Lindmeier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was the first medical evacuation through this route since sometime in 2025," he said referring to a limited number of evacuations during an early 2025 ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisia upholds and increases jail terms for opponents and security officials</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tunisia-upholds-and-increases-jail-terms-opponents-and-security-officials</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tunisia-upholds-and-increases-jail-terms-opponents-and-security-officials</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS, Feb 3 (Reuters) - A Tunisian appeal court on Tuesday upheld and increased lengthy prison sentences on high-profile politicians, including opposition leader Rached Ghannouchi and former security officials, as part of a crackdown on dissent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among those sentenced on charges of conspiring against the state in the mass trial were Nadia Akacha, the former chief of staff to President Kais Saied. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Akacha, who was sentenced in absentia after fleeing abroad, received a 35-year jail term, TAP state news agency said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Middle East does not need Iran-US war, diplomatic adviser to UAE president says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/middle-east-does-not-need-iran-us-war-diplomatic-adviser-uae-president-says-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/middle-east-does-not-need-iran-us-war-diplomatic-adviser-uae-president-says-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 3 (Reuters) - The Middle East does not need another confrontation between the U.S. and Iran, and Tehran needs to reach a nuclear deal with Washington, the diplomatic adviser to the president of regional power United Arab Emirates said at a World Governments Summit panel in Dubai.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States will resume nuclear talks on Friday in Turkey, Iranian and U.S. officials told Reuters on Monday. U.S. President Donald Trump warned that with big U.S. warships heading to Iran, "bad things" would probably happen if a deal could not be reached.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE urges US and Iran to strike nuclear deal ahead of talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-urges-us-and-iran-strike-nuclear-deal-ahead-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-urges-us-and-iran-strike-nuclear-deal-ahead-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maha El Dahan and Nayera Abdallah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 3 - Regional power United Arab Emirates urged Iran and the United States on Tuesday to strikea nuclear deal and reach a long-term solutionto tensions ahead of the resumption of talks between the foes and regional states, emphasizing that the Middle East does not need another war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire breaks out in Tehran shopping centre, state media reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fire-breaks-out-tehran-shopping-centre-state-media-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fire-breaks-out-tehran-shopping-centre-state-media-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 3 (Reuters) - A large fire broke out in a shopping centre in the west of the Iranian capital, state media reported on Tuesday, adding that firefighting teams were at the scene to extinguish it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom; Editing by Alison Williams)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spain to ban social media access for children under 16</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/spain-ban-social-media-access-children-under-16</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/spain-ban-social-media-access-children-under-16</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MADRID, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Spain will ban access to social media for minors under 16 and platforms will be required to implement age verification systems, Prime Minister Pedro Sanchez said on Tuesday at the World Government Summit in Dubai. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Our children are exposed to a space they were never meant to navigate alone... We will no longer accept that," Sanchez said. "We will protect them from the digital Wild West."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added that his government would also introduce a new bill next week to hold social media executives accountable for illegal and hateful content.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Middle East does not need Iran-US war, diplomatic adviser to UAE president says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/middle-east-does-not-need-iran-us-war-diplomatic-adviser-uae-president-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/middle-east-does-not-need-iran-us-war-diplomatic-adviser-uae-president-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dubai, Feb 3 (Reuters) - The Middle East does not need another confrontation between the U.S. and Iran, and Tehran needs to reach a nuclear deal with Washington, Anwar Gargash, the diplomatic adviser to the UAE president, said at a World Governments Summit panel in Dubai.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I think that the region has gone through variouscalamitous confrontations. I don't think we need another one, but I would like to see direct Iranian-American negotiations leading to understandings that we don't have these issues every other day," he said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 07:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia is ready for a new world with no nuclear limits, Ryabkov says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-ready-new-world-no-nuclear-limits-ryabkov-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-ready-new-world-no-nuclear-limits-ryabkov-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Russia is ready for the new reality of a world with no nuclear arms control limits after the New START treaty expires later this week, Russia's point man for arms control said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unless Moscow and Washington reach a last-minute bilateral understanding of some kind, the New START treaty, signed in 2010 by U.S. President Barack Obama and Russian President Dmitry Medvedev, will expire on February 5.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 06:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran president gives go-ahead for talks with US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-president-gives-go-ahead-talks-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-president-gives-go-ahead-talks-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Talks with the U.S. should be pursued to secure national interests as long as "threats and unreasonable expectations" are avoided, President Masoud Pezeshkian posted on X on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Taking into account demands from friendly regional countries to respond to the U.S. President's suggestion for talks, I instructed the foreign minister to prepare the ground for equitable and fair negotiations ... should an atmosphere free of threats and unreasonable expectations arise," Pezeshkian said.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom; Editing by Tom Hogue)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 05:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN to deploy ceasefire monitoring mission in Congo, Qatar says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-deploy-ceasefire-monitoring-mission-congo-qatar-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-deploy-ceasefire-monitoring-mission-congo-qatar-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAKAR, Feb 2 (Reuters) - The United Nations peacekeeping mission in Congo will send its first team to monitor a ceasefire between Congo’s government and the AFC/M23 rebel group in the coming days, Qatar’s foreign ministry said on Monday after hosting talks in Doha.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Qatar said the team would be deployed to Uvira, a strategic city in eastern Congo that AFC/M23 fighters captured in December during a rapid offensive, and which Congolese forces and allied militias re‑entered last month, restoring government control after the rebels announced they would withdraw.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 23:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says talks with Iran ongoing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-talks-iran-ongoing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-talks-iran-ongoing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 2 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said Monday that talks with Iran were ongoing amid high tensions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have ships heading to Iran right now, big ones ... and we have talks going on with Iran," Trump told reporters at the White House. "We'll see how it works out."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Steve Holland, Writing by Christian Martinez, editing by Michelle Nichols)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 22:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon’s army chief in Washington as Hezbollah disarmament enters critical phase</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</guid><description>Gen. Rodolphe Haykal is seeking US support for what is likely to be a cautious approach to expanding the geographic scope of the Lebanese army's efforts to disarm Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 21:58:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon’s army chief in Washington as Hezbollah disarmament enters critical phase</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</guid><description>Gen. Rodolphe Haykal is seeking US support for what is likely to be a cautious approach to expanding the geographic scope of the Lebanese army's efforts to disarm Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 21:58:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon’s army chief in Washington as Hezbollah disarmament enters critical phase</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</guid><description>Gen. Rodolphe Haykal is seeking US support for what is likely to be a cautious approach to expanding the geographic scope of the Lebanese army's efforts to disarm Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 21:58:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon’s army chief in Washington as Hezbollah disarmament enters critical phase</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanons-army-chief-washington-hezbollah-disarmament-enters-critical-phase</guid><description>Gen. Rodolphe Haykal is seeking US support for what is likely to be a cautious approach to expanding the geographic scope of the Lebanese army's efforts to disarm Hezbollah.</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 21:58:32 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>