<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>What lies ahead in Iraq: the hard task of forming a government</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/what-lies-ahead-iraq-hard-task-forming-government</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/what-lies-ahead-iraq-hard-task-forming-government</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Following Iraq's parliamentary election this week, the complex and often lengthy task of choosing the country's next leader is set to begin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incumbent Prime Minister Mohammed Shia al-Sudani claimed victory for his coalition after preliminary results showed it was the largest bloc -- though it still falls short of the majority needed to form a government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sudani now faces the tough quest of securing support from other parties, mostly from the Shiite majority, in his bid for a second term.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gazans begin to restore historic fort damaged in war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gazans-begin-restore-historic-fort-damaged-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gazans-begin-restore-historic-fort-damaged-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One bucket at a time, Palestinian workers cleared sand and crumbling mortar from the remains of an former medieval fortress turned museum in Gaza City, damaged by two years of fighting between Israel and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A dozen workers in high visibility jackets worked by hand to excavate the bombarded buildings that remain of the Pasha Palace Museum -- which reputedly once housed Napoleon Bonaparte during a one-night stay in Gaza -- stacking stones to be reused in one pile, and rubble to be discarded in another.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 12:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French interior minister likely to visit Algeria as relations thaw</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/french-interior-minister-likely-visit-algeria-relations-thaw</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/french-interior-minister-likely-visit-algeria-relations-thaw</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alessandro Parodi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -French Interior Minister Laurent Nunez said on Thursday there was a high chance he would visit Algeria, hailing the north African country's release of writer Boualem Sansal as a glimmer of hope that relations between the two nations could be mended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Algerian President Abdelmadjid Tebboune on Wednesday pardoned the French-Algerian writer who was arrested a year ago and sentenced in March to five years in jail for undermining national unity. The case strained already difficult relations between Algeria and its colonial-era master France.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 10:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Suicide bombers who attacked Pakistan were Afghan nationals, Pakistan interior minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/suicide-bombers-who-attacked-pakistan-were-afghan-nationals-pakistan-interior</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/suicide-bombers-who-attacked-pakistan-were-afghan-nationals-pakistan-interior</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD (Reuters) -Pakistan's Interior Minister Mohsin Naqvi said on Thursday that both suicide bombers involved in the attacks in the country this week were Afghan nationals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Asif Shahzad; Writing by Surbhi Misra; Editing by YP Rajesh)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says Gaza stabilisation force must guarantee lasting ceasefire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-gaza-stabilisation-force-must-guarantee-lasting-ceasefire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-gaza-stabilisation-force-must-guarantee-lasting-ceasefire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -Turkey's main expectation from a planned International Stabilisation Force in Gaza is for it to provide guarantees that the fragile ceasefire will last, its Defence Ministry said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NATO member Turkey has been one of the most vocal critics of Israel's devastating two-year assault on Gaza, calling it a genocide. It has emerged as a critical player and mediator in ceasefire efforts, voicing a desire to join the stabilisation force despite Israel's repeated objections.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey: too early to say what caused deadly plane crash</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-too-early-say-what-caused-deadly-plane-crash</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-too-early-say-what-caused-deadly-plane-crash</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -     Turkey's defence ministry said on Thursday it was too early to say what caused the crash this week of a military cargo plane in Georgia in which 20 soldiers died, and inspections continue. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The C-130 cargo aircraft had left Azerbaijan for Turkey and crashed on Tuesday, an incident marking the NATO member's highest military death toll since 2020. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Iran's dual reality: As veil restrictions ease, political crackdown deepens</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-irans-dual-reality-veil-restrictions-ease-political-crackdown-deepens</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-irans-dual-reality-veil-restrictions-ease-political-crackdown-deepens</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI (Reuters) -On Tehran's bustling streets, signs of change are unmistakable. Women walk unveiled in jeans and sneakers, men and women linger together in cafés where Western music hums softly, and couples stroll hand-in-hand — subtle acts that chip away at the rigid social codes that have long defined the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But beneath the surface, a darker reality is unfolding. Iran's clerical rulers are intensifying a crackdown on political dissent to instil fear and prevent unrest, four activists inside Iran told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 09:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Australia's green energy push, Pacific ties face setback from COP31 impasse</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-australias-green-energy-push-pacific-ties-face-setback-cop31-impasse</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-australias-green-energy-push-pacific-ties-face-setback-cop31-impasse</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Peter Hobson and Valerie Volcovici&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CANBERRA/BELEM, Brazil (Reuters) -     Australia risks undermining efforts to establish itself as a leader in the green energy transition and letting down its vulnerable Pacific island neighbours if its bid to host next year's biggest climate summit fails, diplomats and analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Australia was long considered the front-runner to hold the COP31 conference, aiming to bolster its ambitions to become "a renewable energy superpower" and highlight issues faced by Pacific island nations which it plans to co-host the conference with.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 07:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Royal ransoms, a top money-maker for Mali's jihadist kidnappers</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/royal-ransoms-top-money-maker-malis-jihadist-kidnappers</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/royal-ransoms-top-money-maker-malis-jihadist-kidnappers</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At least $50 million for the freedom of an Emirati sheikh: that is the king's ransom paid two weeks ago to jihadists linked to Al-Qaeda who are pushing to topple the Malian government and impose Islamic law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alongside a crippling fuel blockade, the Group for the Support of Islam and Muslims, known by its Arabic acronym JNIM, has made kidnapping wealthy foreigners for a ransom a pillar of its strategy of "economic jihad".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 07:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Where school is a tent: Yemeni kids learn without classrooms, textbooks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/where-school-tent-yemeni-kids-learn-without-classrooms-textbooks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/where-school-tent-yemeni-kids-learn-without-classrooms-textbooks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Crammed under a tattered tent on rough wooden benches, Yemeni children are learning Arabic grammar -- lucky to receive an education at all in a country hammered by years of war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The children, some without shoes or textbooks, were born into a divided state where fighting has destroyed nearly 3,000 schools. Those that remain are plagued by power cuts and a lack of running water.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al-Ribat al-Gharbi school near Aden, in Yemen's government-controlled south, is a typical case, with lengthy power outages, no water supplies and a lack of trained teachers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 03:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jailed Tunisian opposition leader faced brutal violence in prison, his lawyer says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/jailed-tunisian-opposition-leader-faced-brutal-violence-prison-his-lawyer-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/jailed-tunisian-opposition-leader-faced-brutal-violence-prison-his-lawyer-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS (Reuters) -The family and lawyers of jailed Tunisian opposition leader Jawhar Ben Mbarek accused prison authorities on Wednesday of brutally assaulting him to try to force an end to his two-week-old hunger strike.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ben Mbarek, one of the most prominent opponents of President Kais Saied, was detained in 2023 and sentenced this year to 18 years in prison on charges of conspiring to overthrow the president; he has denied the charges, which he said were fabricated.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 20:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Could Trump be the one to deliver peace to Syria and Turkey's Kurds?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</guid><description>As Trump deepens his Syria push, Washington is probing whether its leverage can turn fragile truces into lasting peace.</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 19:14:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Could Trump be the one to deliver peace to Syria and Turkey's Kurds?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</guid><description>As Trump deepens his Syria push, Washington is probing whether its leverage can turn fragile truces into lasting peace.</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 19:14:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Could Trump be the one to deliver peace to Syria and Turkey's Kurds?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</guid><description>As Trump deepens his Syria push, Washington is probing whether its leverage can turn fragile truces into lasting peace.</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 19:14:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Could Trump be the one to deliver peace to Syria and Turkey's Kurds?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/could-trump-be-one-deliver-peace-syria-and-turkeys-kurds</guid><description>As Trump deepens his Syria push, Washington is probing whether its leverage can turn fragile truces into lasting peace.</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 19:14:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US intel revealed Israeli officials discussing use of human shields in Gaza, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-intel-revealed-israeli-officials-discussing-use-human-shields-gaza-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-intel-revealed-israeli-officials-discussing-use-human-shields-gaza-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Erin Banco&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NEW YORK (Reuters) -The U.S. gathered intelligence last year of Israeli officials discussing how their soldiers had sent Palestinians into Gaza tunnels the Israelis believed were potentially lined with explosives, according to two former U.S. officials familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The information was shared with the White House and analyzed by the intelligence community in the final weeks of former President Joe Biden's administration, the officials said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;International law prohibits the use of civilians as shields during military activity.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 18:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US Treasury issues Iran-related missile and drone sanctions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-treasury-issues-iran-related-missile-and-drone-sanctions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-treasury-issues-iran-related-missile-and-drone-sanctions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -The U.S. on Wednesday sanctioned individuals and entities in several countries related to their support of Iran's ballistic missile and drone production, in the latest attempt to pressure Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 32 individuals and entities based in Iran, the United Arab Emirates, Turkey, China, Hong Kong, India, Germany and Ukraine that operate multiple procurement networks are being targeted in Wednesday's designations, the Treasury Department said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 17:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan bans UAE's Sky News Arabia following el-Fasher coverage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudan-bans-uaes-sky-news-arabia-following-el-fasher-coverage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudan-bans-uaes-sky-news-arabia-following-el-fasher-coverage</guid><description>The ban follows a controversial Sky News Arabia report from el-Fasher, where the network’s journalist was seen engaging with an RSF member just weeks after the group captured the city amid allegations of massacres and war crimes.</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 15:56:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan bans UAE's Sky News Arabia following el-Fasher coverage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudan-bans-uaes-sky-news-arabia-following-el-fasher-coverage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudan-bans-uaes-sky-news-arabia-following-el-fasher-coverage</guid><description>The ban follows a controversial Sky News Arabia report from el-Fasher, where the network’s journalist was seen engaging with an RSF member just weeks after the group captured the city amid allegations of massacres and war crimes.</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 15:56:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan bans UAE's Sky News Arabia following el-Fasher coverage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudan-bans-uaes-sky-news-arabia-following-el-fasher-coverage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudan-bans-uaes-sky-news-arabia-following-el-fasher-coverage</guid><description>The ban follows a controversial Sky News Arabia report from el-Fasher, where the network’s journalist was seen engaging with an RSF member just weeks after the group captured the city amid allegations of massacres and war crimes.</description><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 15:56:52 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>