<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>IAEA board passes resolution demanding answers and access from Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iaea-board-passes-resolution-demanding-answers-and-access-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iaea-board-passes-resolution-demanding-answers-and-access-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;VIENNA (Reuters) -The U.N. nuclear watchdog's 35-nation Board of Governors passed a resolution on Thursday saying Iran must inform the watchdog "without delay" of the status of its enriched uranium stock and bombed atomic sites, diplomats at the closed-door meeting said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The resolution's purpose was primarily to renew and adjust the International Atomic Energy Agency's mandate to report on aspects of Iran's nuclear programme but it also stated Iran must quickly provide the IAEA with the answers and access it wants, five months after military strikes by Israel and the U.S.   &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 11:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel launches fresh strikes on Gaza, Qatar warns of escalation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-fresh-strikes-gaza-qatar-warns-escalation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-fresh-strikes-gaza-qatar-warns-escalation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gaza health authorities said fresh Israeli air strikes killed four people Thursday as Qatar, a mediator of the weeks-long ceasefire, warned that renewed attacks threatened to undermine the fragile truce between Israel and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new strikes came the morning after one of the deadliest days in the Gaza Strip since the truce came into effect on October 10, and after Israel launched a string of attacks targeting Hezbollah in Lebanon despite the nearly year-long ceasefire there.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 11:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli fire kills four in Gaza, casting further doubt on ceasefire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-fire-kills-four-gaza-casting-further-doubt-ceasefire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-fire-kills-four-gaza-casting-further-doubt-ceasefire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/GAZA (Reuters) -Israeli airstrikes killed four people and wounded 18 others in Khan Younis in the southern Gaza Strip on Thursday, local health authorities said, as Hamas and Israel accused each other of violating a near six-week-old, U.S.-brokered ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medics said that one strike on a house in Bani Suhaila town east of Khan Younis killed three people, including a baby girl, and wounded 15 others, while another killed a man and wounded three others in the nearby Abassan town.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria condemns Netanyahu's visit to its Israeli-occupied south</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-condemns-netanyahus-visit-its-israeli-occupied-south</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-condemns-netanyahus-visit-its-israeli-occupied-south</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Israel's Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu visited Israeli troops deployed in southern Syria, drawing strong condemnation from the government in Damascus, which denounced the trip as a violation of sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel expanded its military presence in southern Syria after the ousting of Bashar al-Assad last December, seizing positions east of a U.N.-patrolled buffer zone that separates the Israeli-occupied Golan Heights from Syrian territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leaders of ethnically split Cyprus agree to work towards reviving talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/leaders-ethnically-split-cyprus-agree-work-towards-reviving-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/leaders-ethnically-split-cyprus-agree-work-towards-reviving-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -The rival leaders of ethnically split Cyprus said they were ready to meet the United Nations Secretary-General to discuss the potential for relaunching long-stalled peace talks, the U.N. mission on the island said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Greek Cypriot leader Nikos Christodoulides and Turkish Cypriot leader Tufan Erhurman met on Thursday, in their first encounter since Erhurman, a centre-left moderate, won by a landslide in an October presidential election in the breakaway Turkish Cypriot state, pledging to work to revive stalled U.N. talks on reunifying Cyprus.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The case of Africa's 'vanishing' carbon deals</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/case-africas-vanishing-carbon-deals</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/case-africas-vanishing-carbon-deals</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When Liberia's government signed an agreement with a little-known Dubai company run by a royal sheikh in 2023, the "carbon credit" deal promised to protect vast tracts of forests and offset big polluters' emissions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was one of a flurry of deals UAE-based Blue Carbon signed that year covering millions of hectares of forests across Africa from Liberia to Zimbabwe -– in one case amounting to a fifth of a country's landmass. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 06:30:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Human Rights Watch accuses Israel of war crimes in West Bank expulsions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/human-rights-watch-accuses-israel-war-crimes-west-bank-expulsions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/human-rights-watch-accuses-israel-war-crimes-west-bank-expulsions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Israel’s expulsion of tens of thousands of Palestinians from three West Bank refugee camps in early 2025 amounts to war crimes and crimes against humanity, Human Rights Watch said on Thursday, calling for urgent international measures to hold Israeli officials accountable and stop further abuses.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 05:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Behind Trump defense of Saudi crown prince, a deeper US shift on human rights</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-behind-trump-defense-saudi-crown-prince-deeper-us-shift-human-rights</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-behind-trump-defense-saudi-crown-prince-deeper-us-shift-human-rights</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Matt Spetalnick, Patricia Zengerle and Simon Lewis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -When President Donald Trump defended Saudi Arabia's crown prince this week over the 2018 killing of U.S.-based journalist Jamal Khashoggi, he did more than just stir renewed accusations from critics of an affinity toward strongmen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump's remarks, which contradicted U.S. intelligence findings, threw into stark relief just how far his administration has shifted away from the traditional U.S. support for human rights globally.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 02:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia PM says Turkey to host COP31 climate summit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-pm-says-turkey-host-cop31-climate-summit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-pm-says-turkey-host-cop31-climate-summit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY (Reuters) -Australia has agreed to allow Turkey to host next year's COP31 climate summit, but Canberra will lead the conference's negotiations among governments, Prime Minister Anthony Albanese said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"So what we've come up with is a big win for both Australia and Turkey," Albanese told ABC Radio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both Australia and Turkey had submitted bids in 2022 to host the annual COP, or Conference of the Parties, the world's main forum for driving climate action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Renju Jose in Sydney; Editing by Leslie Adler)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey set to host COP31 climate summit as deal with Australia takes shape</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-set-host-cop31-climate-summit-deal-australia-takes-shape</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-set-host-cop31-climate-summit-deal-australia-takes-shape</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BELEM, Brazil/CANBERRA (Reuters) -Turkey would host next year’s UN climate summit while Australia would lead the conference’s negotiations among governments, under a compromise deal that three sources familiar with the matter said was taking shape in talks on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Australia and Turkey both submitted bids in 2022 to host the annual COP, or Conference of the Parties, the world's main forum for driving climate action. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two nations have been in a protracted struggle to host, with neither willing to back down. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 23:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>G20 countries' medium-term growth to be weakest since 2009 crisis, IMF says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/g20-countries-medium-term-growth-be-weakest-2009-crisis-imf-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/g20-countries-medium-term-growth-be-weakest-2009-crisis-imf-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Andrea Shalal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -The world's 20 largest economies will grow by just 2.9% in 2030 amid headwinds from protectionism and policy uncertainty, their weakest medium-term outlook since the global financial crisis of 2009, the International Monetary Fund said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a report to the Group of 20, the global lender mapped out a series of challenges facing the global economy, including widening excessive balances and stretched public coffers, as well as aging populations in advanced economies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 23:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudis lift travel ban on US citizen sentenced for tweets: family</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudis-lift-travel-ban-us-citizen-sentenced-tweets-family</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudis-lift-travel-ban-us-citizen-sentenced-tweets-family</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia has lifted a travel ban on a US citizen who criticized the kingdom on social media, his family said Wednesday, as President Donald Trump welcomed the crown prince.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saad Ibrahim Almadi, a US citizen of Saudi origin, had been arrested during a visit to his native country in 2021 after tweets that mentioned corruption and the killing of Jamal Khashoggi, a dissident writer strangled and dismembered in a Saudi consulate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 21:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US F-35 jets to be sold to Saudi Arabia to lack Israel's advanced features</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-f-35-jets-be-sold-saudi-arabia-lack-israels-advanced-features</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-f-35-jets-be-sold-saudi-arabia-lack-israels-advanced-features</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mike Stone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -The F-35 fighter jets the U.S. plans to sell Saudi Arabia will be less advanced than those operated by Israel, in line with a U.S. law that guarantees Israel’s military edge in the region, U.S. officials and defense experts said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump announced the sale this week, but officials said the Saudi aircraft will lack superior features of Israel’s fleet that include advanced weapons systems and electronic warfare equipment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 20:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-US secures $1 trillion Saudi spending commitments spanning nuclear energy to F-35s</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/factbox-us-secures-1-trillion-saudi-spending-commitments-spanning-nuclear-energy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/factbox-us-secures-1-trillion-saudi-spending-commitments-spanning-nuclear-energy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump's lavish welcome of Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman to Washington this week, touted by many as rehabilitation of human rights record of Saudi Arabia's de facto ruler, has been followed by the kingdom ramping up its planned U.S. investments to $1 trillion. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move marks a remarkable increase from the $600 billion that the world's largest exporter announced during Trump's visit to Riyadh six month ago. Bin Salman is scheduled to meet top U.S. corporate leaders on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 20:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump vows to end Sudan war, in sudden pivot</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-vows-end-sudan-war-sudden-pivot</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-vows-end-sudan-war-sudden-pivot</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump vowed Wednesday to end Sudan's grinding civil war at the request of Saudi Arabia's crown prince, condemning "tremendous atrocities" in a conflict he has previously overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump admitted that the devastating war between Sudan's army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) was "not on my charts" before Prince Mohammed bin Salman pushed him to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 20:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia lifts travel ban on US citizen Saad Almadi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</guid><description>Almadi's release comes during Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman's visit to Washington.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 19:59:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia lifts travel ban on US citizen Saad Almadi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</guid><description>Almadi's release comes during Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman's visit to Washington.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 19:59:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia lifts travel ban on US citizen Saad Almadi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</guid><description>Almadi's release comes during Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman's visit to Washington.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 19:59:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia lifts travel ban on US citizen Saad Almadi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabia-lifts-travel-ban-us-citizen-saad-almadi</guid><description>Almadi's release comes during Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman's visit to Washington.</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 19:59:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says he will work on Sudan at Saudi's request</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-he-will-work-sudan-saudis-request</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-he-will-work-sudan-saudis-request</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump said he will work to help end the war in Sudan after Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman asked him to get involved in the matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We've already started working on that," Trump said at a Saudi investment conference a day after he met with Saudi Arabia's de facto ruler at the White House. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 19:01:50 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>