<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Britain's Prince William to visit Saudi Arabia in February</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/britains-prince-william-visit-saudi-arabia-february</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/britains-prince-william-visit-saudi-arabia-february</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Britain's Prince William will visit Saudi Arabia in February, Kensington Palace said in a statement on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"His Royal Highness' visit comes as the UK and Saudi Arabia celebrate growing trade, energy and investment ties, and as the two nations approach a century of diplomatic relations," the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trip, from February 9 to 11, will be his first official visit to Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by William James; Editing by Catarina Demony)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:01:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-What is Trump's 'Board of Peace' and who has joined so far?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-what-trumps-board-peace-and-who-has-joined-so-far</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-what-trumps-board-peace-and-who-has-joined-so-far</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Menna AlaaElDin and Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump has invited dozens of world leaders to join his Board of Peace initiative aimed at resolving global conflicts but diplomats say it could harm the work of the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While some traditional allies of the U.S. have responded cautiously, and in a few cases have rejected Trump's offer, others including nations that have long had strained ties with Washington such as Belarus have accepted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHAT IS TRUMP'S BOARD OF PEACE?&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:01:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli strike kills three Gaza journalists including AFP freelancer</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-strike-kills-three-gaza-journalists-including-afp-freelancer</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-strike-kills-three-gaza-journalists-including-afp-freelancer</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;An Israeli air strike killed an AFP freelancer and two other journalists in Gaza on Wednesday, the territory's civil defence agency said, while the military said it struck "suspects" operating a drone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since October 10, a fragile US-sponsored ceasefire in Gaza has largely halted the fighting between Israeli forces and Hamas, but both sides have alleged frequent violations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria's Rifaat al-Assad, the 'butcher of Hama', dies at 88</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-rifaat-al-assad-butcher-hama-dies-88</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-rifaat-al-assad-butcher-hama-dies-88</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - Rifaat al-Assad, the brother of the late Syrian President Hafez al-Assad known by critics as the "butcher of Hama" for crushing an Islamist uprising in the city in 1982 before unsuccessfully challenging for power and going into exile, died on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He was 88. He died in the United Arab Emirates, two sources with knowledge of his passing said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-How Syria's government has redrawn map with advances against the Kurds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-how-syrias-government-has-redrawn-map-advances-against-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-how-syrias-government-has-redrawn-map-advances-against-kurds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - The Syrian government has seized swathes of northern and eastern Syria from Kurdish forces, consolidating President Ahmed al-Sharaa's rule nearly 14 months after Bashar al-Assad was toppled.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rapid turn of events has brought almost all of Syria back under the authority of the Damascus-based state, following years of conflict that fractured the country, and puts a spotlight on shifting U.S. policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHAT TRIGGERED THE SYRIAN ARMY ADVANCES?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tensions had been simmering between the government and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces for months.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria accuses Kurds of breaking truce in threat to chances of deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-accuses-kurds-breaking-truce-threat-chances-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-accuses-kurds-breaking-truce-threat-chances-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Syria's government said a drone strike by the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces killed seven of its soldiers on Wednesday, though the SDF denied this, in an incident that threatens to derail a ceasefire after days of fighting in the northeast. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Syrian army called the attack, which it said took place as soldiers were securing a captured military base containing explosives, a dangerous escalation. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Where are Islamic State detainees in Syria?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/where-are-islamic-state-detainees-syria</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/where-are-islamic-state-detainees-syria</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;AMMAN, Jan 21 (Reuters) - The rapid collapse of the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces in the northeast of the country this week triggered uncertainty over the security of around a dozen prisons and detention camps that they had been guarding, where more than 10,000 Islamic State members and thousands more women and children with ties to the group are being held.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is an overview of some of the most important prisons and camps holding IS-linked people in northeast Syria:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;HASAKAH PRISONS UNDER SDF CONTROL&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran protest crackdown latest developments</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-crackdown-latest-developments-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-crackdown-latest-developments-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump has warned that Iran would be wiped "off the face of this earth" if Tehran ever succeeded in assassinating the US leader.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arch foes Iran and the United States in recent days have threatened broadscale wars if the leaders of either country are killed. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It came as both nations traded barbs over a protest wave Tehran blames on Washington, after Trump threatened military action if more protesters were killed in a deadly crackdown by Iranian authorities. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are the latest developments: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- 'Set their world on fire' -&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump warns Hamas will be 'blown away' if it fails to disarm</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-warns-hamas-will-be-blown-away-if-it-fails-disarm</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-warns-hamas-will-be-blown-away-if-it-fails-disarm</guid><description>“They were born with a weapon in their hands, so it's not easy to do," Trump said.</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:23:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran deaths went beyond protesters, hitting bystanders too, witnesses say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-deaths-went-beyond-protesters-hitting-bystanders-too-witnesses-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-deaths-went-beyond-protesters-hitting-bystanders-too-witnesses-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Art student Arash was walking home through the streets of Tehran when a shotgun blast ended his life. He had not shouted slogans, joined protesters or raised a fist. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A friend, speaking by telephone from the Iranian capital, described the moment in a voice cracking with grief: Arash fell instantly, lifeless on the pavement. He was 22.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Olympics-No formal communication yet with Trump on LA 2028 Games, says IOC</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/olympics-no-formal-communication-yet-trump-la-2028-games-says-ioc</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/olympics-no-formal-communication-yet-trump-la-2028-games-says-ioc</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LAUSANNE, Switzerland, Jan 21 (Reuters) - The International Olympic Committee has not yet had any formal communication with the White House and U.S. President Donald Trump on preparations for the Los Angeles 2028 Summer Olympics, IOC President Kirsty Coventry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump marked the end of a turbulent first year in office on Tuesday, havingrocked international diplomatic waters with his case for acquiring Greenland as an Arctic guard post against Russia and China, and threatening a trade war with Europeans who oppose him.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of jailed journalists fell from record high in 2025, CPJ report says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/number-jailed-journalists-fell-record-high-2025-cpj-report-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/number-jailed-journalists-fell-record-high-2025-cpj-report-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - The number of journalists jailed worldwide declined in 2025 but remains near record highs, the Committee to Protect Journalists said in a report on Wednesday that warned about ongoing threats to press freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The group said 330 journalists were behind bars as of December 1, down from a record high of 384 reported at the end of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report said there were 50 journalists imprisoned in China, the most of any single country, followed by Myanmar with 30 and Israel with 29. It said that all of the journalists imprisoned in Israel were Palestinian.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria says seven soldiers killed in a drone attack by Kurdish forces</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-says-seven-soldiers-killed-drone-attack-kurdish-forces</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-says-seven-soldiers-killed-drone-attack-kurdish-forces</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - Seven Syrian soldiers were killed in a drone attack by the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces in northeastern Syria's Hasakah province, Syria's Defence Ministry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The drone attack took place in the countryside against an explosives workshop that was being secured by the army, the state news agency reported. The SDF has pulled back from a swathe of northern and eastern Syria this week, handing over territory to the army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ahmed ElimamEditing by Peter Graff)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Drone attacks shock city in central Sudan as war inches closer</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/drone-attacks-shock-city-central-sudan-war-inches-closer</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/drone-attacks-shock-city-central-sudan-war-inches-closer</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Eltayeb Siddig&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EL OBEID, Sudan, Jan 21 - Drone strikes have intensified in and around al-Obeid in central Sudan as the country's devastating civil war closes in on the army-controlled city, causing significant civiliandeaths in at least two cases, residents say.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The city is one of Sudan's most important and the capital of North Kordofan state, part of the wider Kordofan region that stands between the RSF's Darfur stronghold and the army-controlled eastern half of the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan to join Trump's 'Board of Peace' on Gaza, says foreign office</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-gaza-says-foreign-office</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-gaza-says-foreign-office</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Asif Shahzad and Ariba Shahid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Pakistan will join U.S. President Donald Trump's "Board of Peace" to help achieve lasting peace in Gaza, its foreign ministry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pakistan hoped "concrete steps will be taken towards the implementation of a permanent ceasefire" as well as to boost aid and Gaza's reconstruction, the ministry said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcement came after Pakistani army chief Field Marshal Asim Munir flew to Davos, three Pakistani officials told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fate of IS detainees uncertain as Damascus reins in Kurds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fate-detainees-uncertain-damascus-reins-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fate-detainees-uncertain-damascus-reins-kurds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Syrian government's attempt to wrest back control of Kurdish-held areas has thrown into doubt the fate of thousands of suspected Islamic State group jihadists detained there, with Western observers worried many could take advantage of the chaos to escape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces spearheaded the battle against IS in Syria, backed by a US-led coalition, after it declared a "caliphate" in swathes of Syria and neighbouring Iraq in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's foreign minister to represent Erdogan on 'Board of Peace', source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-foreign-minister-represent-erdogan-board-peace-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-foreign-minister-represent-erdogan-board-peace-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan will represent Turkey's president on U.S. President Donald Trump's international "Board of Peace" initiative, a Turkish source told Reuters on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump had sent an invitation to President Tayyip Erdogan to become a member of the board, an initiative that initially aimed to end the conflict in Gaza but that Trump has said will resolve conflicts globally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump is due to preside over a ceremony marking the "Board of Peace" on Thursday at the annual meeting of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli fire kills five Palestinians as Trump seeks to advance Gaza peace deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-five-palestinians-trump-seeks-advance-gaza-peace-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-five-palestinians-trump-seeks-advance-gaza-peace-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Israeli fire killed five Palestinians, including two boys, in central and southern Gaza, local health authorities said, and the Israeli military said it had "eliminated" a Palestinian militant who posed a threat to soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel and Hamas have traded blame for many breaches of the October ceasefire after two years of war that devastated Gaza and caused a humanitarian disaster, and remain at odds over the next steps in U.S. President Donald Trump's 20-point peace plan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey, Israel, Pakistan to join Trump's Board of Peace as Italy hedges: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-israel-pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-italy-hedges-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-israel-pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-italy-hedges-what-know</guid><description>The Turkish president accepted the US leader's invitation to join the Gaza Board of Peace along with Egypt and Israel.</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:27:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey, Israel, Pakistan to join Trump's Board of Peace as Italy hedges: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-israel-pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-italy-hedges-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-israel-pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-italy-hedges-what-know</guid><description>The Turkish president accepted the US leader's invitation to join the Gaza Board of Peace along with Egypt and Israel.</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:27:30 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>