<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israel publishes draft law seeking to boost state revenues from Dead Sea minerals</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-publishes-draft-law-seeking-boost-state-revenues-dead-sea-minerals</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-publishes-draft-law-seeking-boost-state-revenues-dead-sea-minerals</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Israel on Wednesday published a draft law that aims to boost state revenues from a concession for extracting minerals from the Dead Sea as well as tackling its environmental consequences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Finance Ministry said the proposed law intends to redefine the concession to ensure the public and the state get their rightful share, while ensuring the preservation of nature and environmental values.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN chief Guterres: end to war in Ukraine should abide by international law</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-chief-guterres-end-war-ukraine-should-abide-international-law</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-chief-guterres-end-war-ukraine-should-abide-international-law</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;NEW YORK, Dec 3 (Reuters) - An end to Russia's war in Ukraine should abide by international law, United Nations Secretary-General Antonio Guterres said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I believe we are still far from a solution," Guterres said at the Reuters NEXT conference in New York.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia invaded Ukraine in February 2022, triggering the biggest confrontation between Moscow and the West since the depths of the Cold War.The United States is trying to broker an end to the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu's coalition skips parliamentary vote backing Trump's Gaza plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahus-coalition-skips-parliamentary-vote-backing-trumps-gaza-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahus-coalition-skips-parliamentary-vote-backing-trumps-gaza-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's governing coalition skipped a parliamentary vote on Wednesday endorsing U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the two-year war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vote, proposed by opposition leader Yair Lapid, was largely symbolic as Netanyahu had already publicly backed the plan after Israel agreed to a ceasefire with Hamas in October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Less than a third of the parliament's 120 lawmakers participated in it with 39 in favour and none against. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany deploys Arrow air defence to counter Russian missile threat</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/germany-deploys-arrow-air-defence-counter-russian-missile-threat</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/germany-deploys-arrow-air-defence-counter-russian-missile-threat</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;HOLZDORF, Germany, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Germany on Wednesday became the first European nation to deploy the Arrow air defence system, built to intercept intermediate-range ballistic missiles such as Russia's Oreshnik, as it seeks to counter what it sees as a growing threat from Moscow. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Operating at altitudes above 100 kilometres (62 miles), outside the earth's atmosphere, and with a range of 2,400 kilometres, the stationary Arrow system complements shorter-range air defences such as Patriot and IRIS-T which are mounted on trucks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gazans race to preserve cultural heritage damaged in war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gazans-race-preserve-cultural-heritage-damaged-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/gazans-race-preserve-cultural-heritage-damaged-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GAZA, Dec 3 (Reuters) - With 70,000 dead, countless injured, hundreds of thousands of people homeless and whole districts laid to waste, the task of rebuilding Gaza is almost beyond comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But at a handful of sites where the enclave's most valuable historical monuments have been severely damaged, workers are already busy with shovels, trying to dig out the few surviving remnants of the past.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghan Taliban minister says US shooting has nothing to do with his people or government</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/afghan-taliban-minister-says-us-shooting-has-nothing-do-his-people-or-government</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/afghan-taliban-minister-says-us-shooting-has-nothing-do-his-people-or-government</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KABUL, Dec 3 (Reuters) - The shooting of National Guard members in Washington, D.C., over which an Afghan immigrant has been charged, has nothing to do with Afghanistan's people or its government, Afghan Taliban Foreign Minister Amir Khan Muttaqi said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Muttaqi's comments are the first on the incident by the Afghan Taliban government, and come a week after events in Washington when suspect Rahmanullah Lakanwal is accused of opening fire on guard members, killing one and critically wounding another.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Libya war crimes suspect makes first appearance at ICC</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libya-war-crimes-suspect-makes-first-appearance-icc</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libya-war-crimes-suspect-makes-first-appearance-icc</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Libyan prison boss accused of overseeing murder, rape, and torture at a notorious detention centre appeared at the International Criminal Court Wednesday to face charges of war crimes and crimes against humanity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khaled Mohamed Ali El Hishri, 47, sat impassively dressed in a dark blue jacket and light blue shirt, confirming his name and date of birth before the three-woman judging panel.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel, Lebanon officials meet in expanded truce talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-lebanon-officials-meet-expanded-truce-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-lebanon-officials-meet-expanded-truce-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/BEIRUT, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Israel and Lebanon sent new representatives to a military committee monitoring a truce between the countries, top officials from both said on Wednesday, in a move set to expand the scope of talks between the long-time foes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting was a step towards a months-long U.S. demand that the two countries broaden talks beyond monitoring the 2024 ceasefire, in line with U.S. President Donald Trump's broader agenda of peace agreements across the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Migrants in Lebanon hope Pope's peace message lingers amid fears of new war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/migrants-lebanon-hope-popes-peace-message-lingers-amid-fears-new-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/migrants-lebanon-hope-popes-peace-message-lingers-amid-fears-new-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Catherine  Cartier&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Filipina worker Loren Capobres said the world stood still when she kissed Pope Leo's hand this week in Lebanon, but hopes his message for peace will linger after his departure, leading to better working conditions and a lasting peace in the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Capobres, who is Catholic and has worked in Lebanon for 17 years, met Leo on Monday, alongside priests and other church volunteers on his first overseas trip as pope, in which he called on the Middle East's leaders to reject the horror of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas says it will hand over a Gaza hostage body, Israel to open Rafah crossing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-says-it-will-hand-over-gaza-hostage-body-israel-open-rafah-crossing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-says-it-will-hand-over-gaza-hostage-body-israel-open-rafah-crossing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/JERUSALEM, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Hamas said it will hand over a body of a hostage on Wednesday, as Israel said it would allow Gaza's gateway to Egypt to open in the next few days so that Palestinians who need medical care could leave the war-ravaged territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;  The handover of the last two hostages' bodies in Gaza would complete a key condition of the initial part of U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the two-yearGaza war, which also entails the Rafah border crossing between Gaza and Egypt opening in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey slams ex-Iraqi Kurdish leader Barzani over his visit with heavily armed guards</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-slams-ex-iraqi-kurdish-leader-barzani-over-his-visit-heavily-armed-guards</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-slams-ex-iraqi-kurdish-leader-barzani-over-his-visit-heavily-armed-guards</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Turkey demanded an explanation from Iraqi Kurdish officials after former leader Masoud Barzani arrived in a mainly Kurdish Turkish border region last weekend surrounded by heavily armed and uniformed guards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barzani, who was president of Iraq's Kurdistan Regional Government from 2005-17 and remains Iraqi Kurdistan's most powerful figure, visited the Cizre district in southeast Turkey's Sirnak province for a symposium on a Kurdish poet. It was also attended by Turkish officials, including a deputy interior minister.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mass wedding brings hope amid destruction in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/mass-wedding-brings-hope-amid-destruction-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/mass-wedding-brings-hope-amid-destruction-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The couples walked hand in hand, the brides in traditional embroidered Palestinian white and red dresses adorned with red ribbons, the grooms walked beside them in black suits and ties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the backdrop told a different story: dilapidated buildings, piles of concrete and rubble -- the scars of two years of conflict in the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, 54 couples tied the knot in a mass wedding ceremony in Khan Yunis in southern Gaza -- a defiant celebration of life amid the wreckage of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey defense firms break record with $10B in revenues: SIPRI</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</guid><description>Turkey set a new record with five companies in the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute's Top 100 for 2024, which included nine Middle Eastern countries for the first time amid conflict-driven arms demand.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:40:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey defense firms break record with $10B in revenues: SIPRI</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</guid><description>Turkey set a new record with five companies in the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute's Top 100 for 2024, which included nine Middle Eastern countries for the first time amid conflict-driven arms demand.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:40:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey defense firms break record with $10B in revenues: SIPRI</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</guid><description>Turkey set a new record with five companies in the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute's Top 100 for 2024, which included nine Middle Eastern countries for the first time amid conflict-driven arms demand.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:40:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey defense firms break record with $10B in revenues: SIPRI</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-defense-firms-break-record-10b-revenues-sipri</guid><description>Turkey set a new record with five companies in the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute's Top 100 for 2024, which included nine Middle Eastern countries for the first time amid conflict-driven arms demand.</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:40:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon, Israel hold first direct talks in decades</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanon-israel-hold-first-direct-talks-decades</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/lebanon-israel-hold-first-direct-talks-decades</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Lebanese and Israeli civilian representatives held their first direct talks in decades on Wednesday, Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said, under a year-old ceasefire monitoring mechanism in the war with Hezbollah.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two sides met at the UN peacekeeping force's headquarters in Lebanon's Naqura near the border with Israel, as part of a mechanism to oversee the ceasefire that took hold in November 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until now Israel and Lebanon, which have no formal diplomatic relations, had insisted on keeping military officers in the role.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey discusses Black Sea safety with NATO after attacks on Russian ships</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-discusses-black-sea-safety-nato-after-attacks-russian-ships</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-discusses-black-sea-safety-nato-after-attacks-russian-ships</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan and NATO Secretary General Mark Rutte discussed Black Sea safety on Wednesday, a Turkish Foreign Ministry source said, after Ankara expressed alarm at attacks on Russia-linked tankers, some claimed by Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ankara, a NATO member that has kept warm relations with both sides in the Russian war in Ukraine, has condemned attacks on vessels with links to Moscow that took place inside Turkey's exclusive economic zone off its coast in the Black Sea.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Norway government secures budget backing, preventing cabinet fall</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/norway-government-secures-budget-backing-preventing-cabinet-fall</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/norway-government-secures-budget-backing-preventing-cabinet-fall</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Terje Solsvik and Gwladys Fouche&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OSLO, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Norway's governing Labour Party said on Wednesday it had reached agreement with four left-wing parties in parliament on a 2026 fiscal budget, ending a standoff that had threatened to bring down Prime Minister Jonas Gahr Stoere's cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deal, which excludes demands for a gradual phaseout of oil and divestment in Israeli companies, came ahead of a vote on the budget due on Friday. If the government had lost that vote, it would have forced the prime minister to call a vote of confidence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 11:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan, Afghanistan hold fresh peace talks in Saudi Arabia, say sources</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pakistan-afghanistan-hold-fresh-peace-talks-saudi-arabia-say-sources</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pakistan-afghanistan-hold-fresh-peace-talks-saudi-arabia-say-sources</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PESHAWAR, Pakistan, Dec 3 (Reuters) - Afghanistan's Taliban administration and Pakistan have held fresh peace talks in Saudi Arabia and agreed to maintain a ceasefire, the latest attempt to dial down tensions between the South Asian neighbours.     &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ceasefire has held in recent weeks between the two South Asian militaries, after the outbreak of deadly border clashes in October, following talks hosted by Qatar and Turkey, although the two sides failed to come to a peace agreement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 10:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>