<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Norway moves some of its 60 soldiers in Middle East due to security situation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-moves-some-its-60-soldiers-middle-east-due-security-situation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-moves-some-its-60-soldiers-middle-east-due-security-situation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;COPENHAGEN, Feb 20 (Reuters) - Norway is relocating some of the around 60 soldiers it has in the Middle East to Norway as well as to other countries in the region on security grounds, a spokesperson for the Norwegian armed forces said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump warned Iran on Thursday it must make a deal over its nuclear program or "really bad things" will happen, setting a deadline of 10 to 15 days, drawing a threat from Tehran to retaliate against U.S. bases in the region if attacked.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Soccer-FIFA and Board of Peace to support Gaza reconstruction through football</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/soccer-fifa-and-board-peace-support-gaza-reconstruction-through-football</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/soccer-fifa-and-board-peace-support-gaza-reconstruction-through-football</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 20 (Reuters) - FIFA and the Board of Peace signed a partnership agreement on Thursday to attract investment from global leaders and institutions for sustainable development in conflict-affected regions through football.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace, established under the U.S. President Donald Trump, held its first meeting focused on Gaza's reconstruction fund, aimed at rebuilding the territory once Hamas disarms.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 09:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Somaliland, where Muslims love Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/somaliland-where-muslims-love-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/somaliland-where-muslims-love-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;"I love Israel!" Three little words rarely heard together in the Muslim world, and yet have become a common phrase in Somaliland, the breakaway region of Somalia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel became the only country in the world to recognise Somaliland's independence in December -- something the territory has been seeking since declaring its autonomy from Somalia in 1991. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Ramadan started this week in the deeply Muslim territory, almost all its citizens -- young and old, men and women -- were happy to sing Israel's praises. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 09:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Journalist with Germany's Deutsche Welle detained in Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/journalist-germanys-deutsche-welle-detained-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/journalist-germanys-deutsche-welle-detained-turkey</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;FRANKFURT, Feb 20 (Reuters) - Turkish authorities have detained a veteran correspondent of German state-backed international broadcaster Deutsche Welle in Ankara, accusing him of "disseminating misleading information" and "insulting the president".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Istanbul Chief Public Prosecutor's Office said in a statement late on Thursday it detained Alican Uludag and launched a criminal investigation based on some of his social media posts. He will be brought before prosecutors on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 07:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Ukraine's 2026 defence exports could hit 'several billion dollars', official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-ukraines-2026-defence-exports-could-hit-several-billion-dollars</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-ukraines-2026-defence-exports-could-hit-several-billion-dollars</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Feb 20 (Reuters) - Ukraine could export several billion dollars of military goods and services this year after authorising its first wartime foreign sales and is considering introducing a tax on those exports, a senior Ukrainian defence official said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, the state commission handling related licences in wartime approved the majority of 40 applications from defence sector producers for exports of materiel and services, Davyd Aloian, deputy secretary of Kyiv's National Security and Defence Council, told Reuters in an interview. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 06:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli Druze leader says Syrian community 'besieged' months after clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-druze-leader-says-syrian-community-besieged-months-after-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-druze-leader-says-syrian-community-besieged-months-after-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Seven months after deadly clashes between Syria's Druze minority and government‑backed forces, the spiritual leader of Druze in neighbouring Israel said members of the community across the border remained in peril.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"They're still besieged -- completely encircled. They aren't allowed to bring in any humanitarian aid, including the aid we're trying to deliver," Sheikh Mowafaq Tarif told AFP in an interview this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 03:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Syria's Kurds, dream of autonomy fades under Damascus deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrias-kurds-dream-autonomy-fades-under-damascus-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrias-kurds-dream-autonomy-fades-under-damascus-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At a military base in northeast Syria, Roksan Mohammed recalled joining the battle against Islamic State group jihadists. Now her all-woman fighting unit is at risk after a deal with Damascus ended the Kurds' de facto autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We made many sacrifices," said Mohammed, spokesperson for the Women's Protection Units (YPJ), who stood with a gun slung over her shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Thousands of martyrs shed their blood, including many of my close comrades," the 37-year-old added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:30:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump mixes diplomacy and flattery at peace board meeting</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-mixes-diplomacy-and-flattery-peace-board-meeting</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-mixes-diplomacy-and-flattery-peace-board-meeting</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Bo Erickson, Trevor Hunnicutt and Gram Slattery&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - World leaders who accepted the invitation of President Donald Trump to join his new peace board were greeted in Washington on Thursday with a mix of fanfare and personal flattery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the U.S. president has been chummy with world leaders in the past, he has typically leaned in to a good-cop-bad-cop routine, alternating between praise and threats as his interests dictate. On Thursday, those in attendance saw Trump at his most convivial.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US removing guardrails from proposed Saudi nuclear deal, document says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-removing-guardrails-proposed-saudi-nuclear-deal-document-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-removing-guardrails-proposed-saudi-nuclear-deal-document-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timothy Gardner and Jonathan Landay&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump has told Congress he is pursuing a civil nuclear pact with Saudi Arabia that does not include non-proliferation safeguards the U.S. has long said would ensure the kingdom does not develop nuclear weapons, according to a copy of the document sent to Congress and reviewed by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump, a Republican, and former President Joe Biden, a Democrat, have worked with Saudi Arabia on paths to building the first civil nuclear power plants for the kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza deaths in war's first 15 months higher than reported, study says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-deaths-wars-first-15-months-higher-reported-study-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-deaths-wars-first-15-months-higher-reported-study-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Rami Ayyub&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 19 (Reuters) - More than 75,000 Palestinians were killed in the first 15 months of Israel's military assault in Gaza, a figure far higher than the 49,000 deaths local health officials announced at the time, says a new study by The Lancet Global Health medical journal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The peer-reviewed study, published on Wednesday, found that women, children and the elderly comprised some 56.2% of violent deaths in Gaza during that period, a composition that it said roughly aligned with reporting by Gaza's health ministry.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran tells UN chief it will respond 'decisively' if subjected to military aggression</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-tells-un-chief-it-will-respond-decisively-if-subjected-military-aggression</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-tells-un-chief-it-will-respond-decisively-if-subjected-military-aggression</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Iran told U.N. Secretary-General Antonio Guterres on Thursday that Tehran will consider bases, facilities and assets of the "hostile force" in the region as legitimate targets if it faces military aggression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump's rhetoric towards Iran "signals a real risk of military aggression," Iran's permanent mission to the United Nations said in the letter, adding Iran did not want a war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran will respond "decisively" if subjected to military aggression, the letter said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FIFA to lead $75m Palestinian soccer rebuilding fund</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fifa-lead-75m-palestinian-soccer-rebuilding-fund</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fifa-lead-75m-palestinian-soccer-rebuilding-fund</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;FIFA will spearhead a $75 million fund to rebuild soccer facilities in Gaza that were destroyed by the war between Israel and Hamas, President Donald Trump and the sport's governing body said Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump made the announcement in Washington at the first meeting of his "Board of Peace," an amorphous institution that features two dozen of the US president's close allies and is initially focused on rebuilding the Gaza strip.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I'm also pleased to announce that FIFA will be helping to raise a total of $75 million for projects in Gaza," said Trump.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisia jails lawmaker for eight months for mocking president</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tunisia-jails-lawmaker-eight-months-mocking-president</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tunisia-jails-lawmaker-eight-months-mocking-president</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS, Feb 19 (Reuters) - A Tunisian court on Thursday sentenced lawmaker Ahmed Saidani to eight months in prison over social media posts mocking President Kais Saied, a ruling that opponents say signals an intensifying crackdown on critics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once a supporter of Saied’s policies against political opponents, Saidani has become a vocal critic, accusing the president of seeking to monopolise all decision-making while leaving others to bear the blame for problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In letter, US lays out 7 demands for next Iraqi PM, with emphasis on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</guid><description>The Trump administration is pressing Baghdad on Iranian influence and the nomination of former Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki, with Iraq's top diplomat claiming the US stipulations include a "hint" toward potential sanctions.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:05:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In letter, US lays out 7 demands for next Iraqi PM, with emphasis on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</guid><description>The Trump administration is pressing Baghdad on Iranian influence and the nomination of former Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki, with Iraq's top diplomat claiming the US stipulations include a "hint" toward potential sanctions.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:05:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In letter, US lays out 7 demands for next Iraqi PM, with emphasis on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</guid><description>The Trump administration is pressing Baghdad on Iranian influence and the nomination of former Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki, with Iraq's top diplomat claiming the US stipulations include a "hint" toward potential sanctions.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:05:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In letter, US lays out 7 demands for next Iraqi PM, with emphasis on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/letter-us-lays-out-7-demands-next-iraqi-pm-emphasis-iran</guid><description>The Trump administration is pressing Baghdad on Iranian influence and the nomination of former Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki, with Iraq's top diplomat claiming the US stipulations include a "hint" toward potential sanctions.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 20:05:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Billions pledged, but Hamas' grip clouds Trump’s Gaza plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/billions-pledged-hamas-grip-clouds-trumps-gaza-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/billions-pledged-hamas-grip-clouds-trumps-gaza-plan</guid><description>The Board of Peace is touting new aid and military commitments, but will they make a difference if Hamas still holds the guns in Gaza?</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:45:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Belarus, issued rare invitation to Board of Peace, says it received no visas</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/belarus-issued-rare-invitation-board-peace-says-it-received-no-visas</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/belarus-issued-rare-invitation-board-peace-says-it-received-no-visas</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 19 (Reuters) - Belarus, a close ally of Russia rarely invited to international gatherings, said on Thursday it had intended to attend the inaugural meeting of U.S. President Donald Trump's Board of Peace in Washington but failed to receive the necessary visas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Belarus has long been subject to Western sanctions over its human rights record and punitive measures were intensified after President Alexander Lukashenko allowed his country's territory to be used for Moscow's 2022 invasion of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 19:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-Contributions for Gaza from Board of Peace members</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/factbox-contributions-gaza-board-peace-members</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/factbox-contributions-gaza-board-peace-members</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 19 (Reuters) - Several foreign dignitaries attending the first meeting of U.S. President Donald Trump's Board of Peace for Gaza made offers of aid on Thursday. These include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED STATES: pledges to make a contribution of $10 billion to the border peace, said President Donald Trump&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED ARAB EMIRATES: pledges $1.2 billion to the Board of Peace, said Foreign Minister Sheikh Abdullah bin Zayed al-Nahyan    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QATAR: pledges $1 billion to the Board of Peace, said Emir Sheikh Tamim bin Hamad Al-Thani&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 18:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>