<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israel urges evacuation of two villages in southern Lebanon ahead of strike</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-urges-evacuation-two-villages-southern-lebanon-ahead-strike</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-urges-evacuation-two-villages-southern-lebanon-ahead-strike</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 5 (Reuters) - An Israeli military spokesperson issued on Monday an evacuation order for two villages in southern Lebanon ahead of a strike.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Menna Alaa El-Din and Muhammad Al GebalyEditing by Gareth Jones)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's leaders struggle to end protests, US action in Venezuela stokes fears</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-leaders-struggle-end-protests-us-action-venezuela-stokes-fears</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-leaders-struggle-end-protests-us-action-venezuela-stokes-fears</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 5 (Reuters) - Iran's efforts to quell a wave of anti-government protests have been complicated by Donald Trump's threat to intervene on their side, a warning firmly underlined by the subsequent U.S. capture of Venezuela's Nicolas Maduro, officials and insiders said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia loses ally in Venezuela but hopes to gain from Trump's 'Wild West' realpolitik</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-loses-ally-venezuela-hopes-gain-trumps-wild-west-realpolitik</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-loses-ally-venezuela-hopes-gain-trumps-wild-west-realpolitik</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Guy Faulconbridge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 5 (Reuters) - Venezuelan leader Nicolas Maduro's capture by the United States has deprived Vladimir Putin of an ally and could increase U.S. "oil clout", but Moscow is eying potential gains from President Donald Trump's division of the world into spheres of influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Special Forces seized Maduro only eight months after the Russian president agreed a strategic partnership with his "dear friend", and Trump said the U.S. was taking temporary control of Venezuela, which has the world's biggest oil reserves.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dakar bike champion Sanders wins second stage to take lead</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/dakar-bike-champion-sanders-wins-second-stage-take-lead</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/dakar-bike-champion-sanders-wins-second-stage-take-lead</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Australia's defending Dakar Rally motorbike champion Daniel Sanders moved into the overall lead after winning Monday's second stage in Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 31-year-old covered the 518km route from Yanbu to Al Ula in 4hrs 13mins 37 seconds to cross the line 1min 35s clear of KTM teammate Edgar Canet, who lost time with a couple of minor crashes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;American Ricky Brabec, the 2024 winner, completed the day's podium for Honda.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria, Israel resume U.S.-mediated security talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-israel-resume-us-mediated-security-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-israel-resume-us-mediated-security-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 5 (Reuters) - U.S.-mediated talks between Syria and Israel have resumed after an interruption of several months, Syria's state news agency SANA reported on Monday, with Damascus seeking withdrawal of Israeli troops from territory seized after the fall of Bashar al-Assad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SANA, citing a Syrian government source, said the Syrian delegation was led by Foreign Minister Asaad al-Shibani and intelligence chief Hussein al-Salama. The resumption of the talks reflects a push by Damascus to reclaim what it describes as its non-negotiable national rights, the source said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 13:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Virtual museum preserves Sudan's plundered heritage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/virtual-museum-preserves-sudans-plundered-heritage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/virtual-museum-preserves-sudans-plundered-heritage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Destroyed and looted in the early months of Sudan's war, the national museum in Khartoum is now welcoming virtual visitors after months of painstaking effort to digitally recreate its collection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the museum itself, almost nothing remains of the 100,000 artefacts it had stored since its construction in the 1950s. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only pieces too heavy for looters to haul off, like the massive granite statue of the Kush Pharaoh Taharqa and frescoes relocated from temples during the building of the Aswan Dam, are still present on site.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 13:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey to stress 'strategic priority' of Black Sea security at Ukraine meeting in Paris</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-stress-strategic-priority-black-sea-security-ukraine-meeting-paris</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-stress-strategic-priority-black-sea-security-ukraine-meeting-paris</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 5 (Reuters) - Turkey's foreign minister will stress the "strategic priority" of maintaining security in the Black Sea at a summit on Ukraine in Paris this week, a Turkish Foreign Ministry source said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;French President Emmanuel Macron convened a meeting of the  "Coalition of the Willing" on Tuesday. The group, led by Britain and France, includes more than 30 nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The source said Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan would attend the meeting and would repeat Turkey's position on the need for "results-oriented" steps to end the war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Israel, capture of Venezuela’s Maduro seen as setback for Iran, Hezbollah</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</guid><description>Considering Venezuela an ally of Iran and Hezbollah, Israel welcomed the capture of Venezuelan President Maduro by American forces.</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 09:07:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Israel, capture of Venezuela’s Maduro seen as setback for Iran, Hezbollah</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</guid><description>Considering Venezuela an ally of Iran and Hezbollah, Israel welcomed the capture of Venezuelan President Maduro by American forces.</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 09:07:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Israel, capture of Venezuela’s Maduro seen as setback for Iran, Hezbollah</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</guid><description>Considering Venezuela an ally of Iran and Hezbollah, Israel welcomed the capture of Venezuelan President Maduro by American forces.</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 09:07:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Israel, capture of Venezuela’s Maduro seen as setback for Iran, Hezbollah</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-capture-venezuelas-maduro-seen-setback-iran-hezbollah</guid><description>Considering Venezuela an ally of Iran and Hezbollah, Israel welcomed the capture of Venezuelan President Maduro by American forces.</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 09:07:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'I can't walk anymore': Afghans freeze to death on route to Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/i-cant-walk-anymore-afghans-freeze-death-route-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/i-cant-walk-anymore-afghans-freeze-death-route-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Habibullah set off from his home in western Afghanistan determined to find work in Iran, only for the 15-year-old to freeze to death while walking across the mountainous frontier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"He was forced to go, to bring food for the family," his mother, Mah Jan, told AFP at her mud home in Ghunjan village.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have no food to eat, we have no clothes to wear. The house in which I live has no electricity, no water. I have no proper window, nothing to burn for heating," she added, clutching a photo of her son.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 07:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Swiss police: last 16 victims of New Year's bar fire have been identified</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/swiss-police-last-16-victims-new-years-bar-fire-have-been-identified</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/swiss-police-last-16-victims-new-years-bar-fire-have-been-identified</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ZURICH, Jan 4 (Reuters) - The last 16 people who died in the New Year's Eve bar fire at the Swiss mountain resort of Crans-Montana have been identified, police said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This means all 40 victims of the blaze, which broke out at the Constellation bar early on January 1, have now been identified, Swiss police said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police said they would not give details of their identities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by John RevillEditing by Ros Russell)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 20:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France, UK conduct joint strikes against IS in Syria</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/france-uk-conduct-joint-strikes-against-syria</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/france-uk-conduct-joint-strikes-against-syria</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Britain and France on Sunday said they had carried out joint strikes on the Islamic State group in Syria to prevent the Islamist extremists resurging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;France said it was part of Operation Inherent Resolve, a US-led international offensive against IS in Iraq, Syria and also Libya.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The British Ministry of Defence said it cooperated with France on Saturday night to strike an underground facility in Syria that had likely been used by the Islamic State group to store weapons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 19:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New clashes in Iran as protests enter second week: rights groups</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/new-clashes-iran-protests-enter-second-week-rights-groups</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/new-clashes-iran-protests-enter-second-week-rights-groups</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;New deadly clashes between protesters and security forces erupted in Iran, rights groups and local media said Sunday, as demonstrations first sparked by anger over the rising cost of living entered a second week. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At least 12 people, including members of the security forces, have been killed since the protests kicked off with a shopkeepers' strike in Tehran on December 28, according to a toll based on official reports.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 15:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemeni government accuses separatists of Aden restrictions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemeni-government-accuses-separatists-aden-restrictions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemeni-government-accuses-separatists-aden-restrictions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Elimam and Maha El Dahan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 4 (Reuters) - Yemen's Saudi-backed government on Sunday accused UAE-backed southern separatists of cutting off the port city of Aden and warned it would "take all necessary measures" after recapturing territory from them in the east on Saturday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The separatists denied having restricted movement into Aden, but the government accusations indicate that hostility between the sides persists despite proposals for a dialogue that had raised hopes of a negotiated solution to the crisis. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 15:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>114 killed in week of attacks in Sudan's Darfur: medical sources</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/114-killed-week-attacks-sudans-darfur-medical-sources</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/114-killed-week-attacks-sudans-darfur-medical-sources</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Attacks by Sudan's army and its paramilitary foes on two towns in the western Darfur region over the past week have killed 114 people, medical sources told AFP Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since April 2023, Sudan has been gripped by a war between the army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF), which in October seized the army's last holdout position in Darfur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RSF has since pushed west to the Chadian border and east through the vast Kordofan region, where a drone strike on the North Kordofan capital of El-Obeid on Sunday caused a blackout in the key army-controlled city.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 15:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Radio frequency loss grounds flights in Greece, stranding thousands</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/radio-frequency-loss-grounds-flights-greece-stranding-thousands</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/radio-frequency-loss-grounds-flights-greece-stranding-thousands</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 4 (Reuters) - Flights across Greece were grounded on Sunday after a collapse of radio frequencies crippled air traffic communication, stranding thousands of travellers and bringing airport operations to a halt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was little clarity on what caused the disruption, which began early Sunday and quickly escalated. Some overflights across Greek and regional airspace were still being serviced, but restrictions were imposed on airport operations for safety reasons, Greece's civil aviation authority said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rights group says at least 16 dead in Iran during week of protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-least-16-dead-iran-during-week-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rights-group-says-least-16-dead-iran-during-week-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Elwely Elwelly&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 4 (Reuters) - At least 16 people have been killed during a week of unrest in Iran, rights groups said on Sunday, as protests over soaring inflation spread across the country prompting violent clashes between demonstrators and security forces. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deaths and arrests have been reported through the week both by state media and rights groups, though the numbers have differed. Reuters has not been able to verify the figures independently. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Numerous teenagers among the dead in Swiss bar blaze, police say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/numerous-teenagers-among-dead-swiss-bar-blaze-police-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/numerous-teenagers-among-dead-swiss-bar-blaze-police-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ZURICH, Jan 4 (Reuters) - Teenagers as young as 14 and 15 years old were among those who died in the bar fire on New Year's Eve that killed 40 people in Switzerland, police said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police in Valais said they had identified 16 more of those who died in the blaze in Crans-Montana, one of the worst disasters in recent Swiss history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those newly identified included 10 Swiss nationals, two Italians, one person with Italian-Emirati citizenship, one Romanian, one person from France and one from Turkey, Valais police said. No names were given. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>