<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Trump to preside over first meeting of Board of Peace with many Gaza questions unresolved</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-preside-over-first-meeting-board-peace-many-gaza-questions-unresolved</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-preside-over-first-meeting-board-peace-many-gaza-questions-unresolved</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steve Holland, Simon Lewis and Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump will preside over the first meeting of his Board of Peace on Thursday with unresolved questions on the future of Gaza hanging over an event expected to include representatives from more than 45 nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The disarmament of Hamas militants, the size of the reconstruction fund and the flow of humanitarian aid to the war-battered populace of Gaza are among the major questions likely to test the effectiveness of the board in the weeks and months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Lavrov warns against any new US strike on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-lavrov-warns-against-any-new-us-strike-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-lavrov-warns-against-any-new-us-strike-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 18 (Reuters) - Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov, in an interview made public on Wednesday, said that any new U.S. strike on Iran would have serious consequences and called for restraint to find a solution to enable Iran to pursue a peaceful nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lavrov's interview with Saudi Arabia's Al-Arabiya television was aired a day after U.S. and Iranian negotiators held indirect talks in Geneva to head off a new mounting crisis between Washington and Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 01:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump kicks off his 'Board of Peace,' with eye on Gaza and beyond</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-kicks-his-board-peace-eye-gaza-and-beyond</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-kicks-his-board-peace-eye-gaza-and-beyond</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump on Thursday gathers allies to inaugurate the "Board of Peace," his new institution focused on progress on Gaza but whose ambitions reach much further.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around two dozen world leaders or other senior officials have come to Washington for the meeting -- including several of Trump's authoritarian-leaning friends and virtually none of the European democrats that traditionally sign on to US initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 01:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran expected to submit written proposal for resolving standoff with US, senior US official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-expected-submit-written-proposal-resolving-standoff-us-senior-us-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-expected-submit-written-proposal-resolving-standoff-us-senior-us-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 18 (Reuters) - Iran is expected to submit a written proposal on how to avoid its standoff with the United States in the wake of U.S.-Iran talks in Geneva on Tuesday, a senior U.S. official told Reuters on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Top national security advisers met in the White House Situation Room to discuss Iran and were told all U.S. forces deployed to the region should be in place by mid-March, the official said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State Marco Rubio will meet Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu in Israel on the weekend of February 28, the official said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 22:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In new flip, Trump attacks UK on base deal as US mulls Iran attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-flip-trump-attacks-uk-base-deal-us-mulls-iran-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-flip-trump-attacks-uk-base-deal-us-mulls-iran-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump, shifting his tone yet again, warned Britain on Wednesday not to "give away" a key Indian Ocean base, saying it would be vital if the United States attacks Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump, who is considering strikes on the Islamic republic, lashed out hours after the State Department offered the latest US support to British Prime Minister Keir Starmer's deal to return the Chagos Islands to Mauritius.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the agreement, Britain would instead pay to lease the strategic joint US-UK base at Diego Garcia for a century.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 21:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel conducting 'gradual de facto annexation' of W.Bank: UN official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-conducting-gradual-de-facto-annexation-wbank-un-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-conducting-gradual-de-facto-annexation-wbank-un-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A top UN official warned Wednesday that steps by Israel to tighten control of areas of the West Bank administered by the Palestinian Authority amount to "gradual de facto annexation."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since last week, Israel has approved a series of initiatives backed by far-right ministers to consolidate control over the West Bank where the Palestinians exercise limited autonomy under past deals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 21:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US withdrawing all forces from Syria, WSJ reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-withdrawing-all-forces-syria-wsj-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-withdrawing-all-forces-syria-wsj-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 18 (Reuters) - The United States is in the process of withdrawing all of its roughly 1,000 troops from Syria, the Wall Street Journal reported on Wednesday, citing three U.S. officials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters could not immediately verify the report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, the U.S. military said it completed a withdrawal from a strategic base in Syria, handing it over to Syrian forces, in the latest sign of strengthening U.S.-Syrian ties that could enable an even larger American drawdown.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>White House tells Iran to do deal as Trump hints at US strikes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/white-house-tells-iran-do-deal-trump-hints-us-strikes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/white-house-tells-iran-do-deal-trump-hints-us-strikes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The White House warned on Wednesday that Iran would be "wise" to do a deal with the United States as President Donald Trump once again hinted at military action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two sides recently resumed indirect talks, mediated by Oman, after Trump repeatedly threatened military action against Iran over a deadly crackdown on protesters last month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A previous attempt at negotiations collapsed when Israel launched surprise strikes on Iran last June, beginning a 12-day war that Washington briefly joined to bomb Iranian nuclear sites.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hopes for nuclear deal fade as US, Iran cling to red lines</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</guid><description>President Trump is unlikely to approve a limited nuclear agreement that would invite comparisons to the 2015 deal he once scorned.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 19:33:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hopes for nuclear deal fade as US, Iran cling to red lines</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</guid><description>President Trump is unlikely to approve a limited nuclear agreement that would invite comparisons to the 2015 deal he once scorned.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 19:33:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hopes for nuclear deal fade as US, Iran cling to red lines</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</guid><description>President Trump is unlikely to approve a limited nuclear agreement that would invite comparisons to the 2015 deal he once scorned.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 19:33:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hopes for nuclear deal fade as US, Iran cling to red lines</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hopes-nuclear-deal-fade-us-iran-cling-red-lines</guid><description>President Trump is unlikely to approve a limited nuclear agreement that would invite comparisons to the 2015 deal he once scorned.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 19:33:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump to host Board of Peace meeting on Thursday, White House says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-host-board-peace-meeting-thursday-white-house-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-host-board-peace-meeting-thursday-white-house-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 18 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump will host a Board of Peace meeting on Thursday in Washington, where he will announce that member states have pledged more than $5 billion for reconstruction and humanitarian efforts in Gaza, the White House said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt told reporters that member states had committed to provide thousands of personnel for an international stabilization force for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Steve Holland, writing by Andrea Shalal; Editing by Doina Chiacu)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 19:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After SDF-Damascus truce, is Kurdish haven still safe for Syria's Alawites?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/after-sdf-damascus-truce-kurdish-haven-still-safe-syrias-alawites</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/after-sdf-damascus-truce-kurdish-haven-still-safe-syrias-alawites</guid><description>Thousands of Alawites who fled violence in western Syria now face uncertainty as the Syrian government and Kurdish forces reach a tentative truce.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:50:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US imposing visa restrictions on Iranian officials, telecom leaders</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-imposing-visa-restrictions-iranian-officials-telecom-leaders</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-imposing-visa-restrictions-iranian-officials-telecom-leaders</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 18 (Reuters) - The United States is imposing visa restrictions on 18 Iranian officials and telecommunications industry leaders, the State Department said on Wednesday, in the latest such move against Tehran. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ryan Patrick Jones and Costas Pitas)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Berlin Film Festival rejects accusation of censorship on Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/berlin-film-festival-rejects-accusation-censorship-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/berlin-film-festival-rejects-accusation-censorship-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The director of the Berlin Film Festival on Wednesday rejected accusations from more than 80 film industry figures that the festival had helped censor artists who oppose Israel's actions in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an open letter published on Tuesday, Oscar-winning actors Javier Bardem and Tilda Swinton were among dozens who criticised the Berlinale's "silence" on the issue and said they were "dismayed" at its "involvement in censoring artists who oppose Israel's ongoing genocide against Palestinians in Gaza".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Few people left at Syria camp that held Islamic State families, former director says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/few-people-left-syria-camp-held-islamic-state-families-former-director-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/few-people-left-syria-camp-held-islamic-state-families-former-director-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Feras Dalatey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS, Feb 18 (Reuters) - Fewer than 1,000 families remain at a camp where relatives of suspected Islamic State militants had been held in Syria's northeast, the camp's former director said on Wednesday, with thousands having fled last month as government forces seized control of the area from Kurdish-led fighters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al-Hol, near the Iraqi border, was one of the main detention camps for relatives of suspected Islamic State fighters who were detained during the U.S.-backed campaign against the jihadist group in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia doubles down on Iran nuclear cooperation as US talks inch forward</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-doubles-down-iran-nuclear-cooperation-us-talks-inch-forward</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-doubles-down-iran-nuclear-cooperation-us-talks-inch-forward</guid><description>Moscow’s energy minister said Russia is currently building equipment for new units at Iran’s Bushehr nuclear plant.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 17:24:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia doubles down on Iran nuclear cooperation as US talks inch forward</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-doubles-down-iran-nuclear-cooperation-us-talks-inch-forward</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-doubles-down-iran-nuclear-cooperation-us-talks-inch-forward</guid><description>Moscow’s energy minister said Russia is currently building equipment for new units at Iran’s Bushehr nuclear plant.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 17:24:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia doubles down on Iran nuclear cooperation as US talks inch forward</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-doubles-down-iran-nuclear-cooperation-us-talks-inch-forward</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-doubles-down-iran-nuclear-cooperation-us-talks-inch-forward</guid><description>Moscow’s energy minister said Russia is currently building equipment for new units at Iran’s Bushehr nuclear plant.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 17:24:02 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>