<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Norway government budget in peril over oil, wealth fund's Israel investments</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/norway-government-budget-peril-over-oil-wealth-funds-israel-investments</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/norway-government-budget-peril-over-oil-wealth-funds-israel-investments</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;OSLO, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Norway's minority Labour government failed to win backing for its 2026 draft budget by an end-November deadline but talks will resume in parliament to find a compromise over oil drilling and the wealth fund's Israeli investments, a negotiator said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Norwegian parliament is due to vote on the budget on Friday, and Prime Minister Jonas Gahr Stoere could be forced to call a vote of confidence if no agreement is reached by then, putting his cabinet on the line.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 10:01:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Landmine casualties hit 4-year high as states exit ban treaty</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/landmine-casualties-hit-4-year-high-states-exit-ban-treaty</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/landmine-casualties-hit-4-year-high-states-exit-ban-treaty</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Deaths and injuries from landmines and unexploded ordnance hit a four-year high in 2024, driven by conflicts in Syria and Myanmar as well as European countries moving to withdraw from the treaty banning their use, a new report showed on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over 6,000 incidents were recorded last year, including 1,945 deaths and 4,325 injuries - the highest annual total since 2020, according to the Landmine Monitor 2025 report. Nearly 90% were civilians, with almost half women and children.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope pushes peace message on second day in crisis-hit Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pope-pushes-peace-message-second-day-crisis-hit-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pope-pushes-peace-message-second-day-crisis-hit-lebanon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Dec 1 (Reuters) - Pope Leo will meet with leaders from Lebanon's diverse religious sects on Monday, where he is expected to urge them not to flee the country despite years of conflict, political paralysis and economic crisis that have prompted waves of migration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leo, the first U.S. pope, will visit Lebanon's Christian community before hosting an inter-religious dialogue with members of Lebanon's Sunni Muslim, Shi'ite Muslim and Druze communities, as well as migrant workers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ex-officer tells inquiry UK military committed war crimes in Afghanistan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ex-officer-tells-inquiry-uk-military-committed-war-crimes-afghanistan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/ex-officer-tells-inquiry-uk-military-committed-war-crimes-afghanistan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michael Holden&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Dec 1 (Reuters) - A former senior British officer has told a public inquiry that British special forces in Afghanistan appeared to commit war crimes by executing suspects and despite widespread knowledge in the chain of command nothing was done.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Britain's defence ministry (MoD) ordered the inquiry after a BBC TV documentary reported that soldiers from the elite Special Air Service (SAS) had killed 54 people during the war in Afghanistan more than a decade ago in suspicious circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 07:36:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope prays for peace in Lebanon, region</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-prays-peace-lebanon-region</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-prays-peace-lebanon-region</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo XIV prayed for peace in Lebanon and the region on Monday as he kicked off day two of his trip to the multi-confessional country with a visit to a famous pilgrimage site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thousands of people cheered, ululated and threw rice in celebration as Leo travelled in the popemobile up a winding road to a monastery in Annaya in the mountains north of Beirut which hosts the tomb of Saint Charbel, AFP photographers said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 01:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghan suspect in Washington shooting likely radicalized in US: security official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghan-suspect-washington-shooting-likely-radicalized-us-security-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghan-suspect-washington-shooting-likely-radicalized-us-security-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Afghan suspect in the shooting of two National Guard members in Washington may have been radicalized after entering the US, Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said when questioned about his motive on Sunday talk shows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rahmanullah Lakanwal, 29, faces a first-degree murder charge in the November 26 shooting that left a 20-year-old guardsman dead and another critically wounded.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I will say we believe he was radicalized since he's been here in this country," Noem said on NBC's "Meet the Press." &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 17:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo: Palestinian state 'only' solution to Israeli conflict</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-palestinian-state-only-solution-israeli-conflict</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-palestinian-state-only-solution-israeli-conflict</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ABOARD THE PAPAL FLIGHT TO BEIRUT, Nov 30 (Reuters) - Pope Leo said on Sunday that the only solution in the decades-long conflict between Israel and the Palestinian people must include a Palestinian state, reaffirming the Vatican's position.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We all know that at this time Israel still does not accept that solution, but we see it as the only solution," Leo, the first U.S. pope, told journalists on a flight from Turkey to Lebanon during his first in-flight press conference.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 15:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>National Guard shooting suspect radicalized in US, homeland secretary says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/national-guard-shooting-suspect-radicalized-us-homeland-secretary-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/national-guard-shooting-suspect-radicalized-us-homeland-secretary-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ted Hesson and Jasper Ward&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Nov 30 (Reuters) - U.S. authorities believe the Afghan immigrant accused of ambushing National Guard members in Washington, D.C., was not radicalized until after he came to the United States, Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking on NBC's "Meet the Press" and ABC’s "This Week," Noem said authorities think that alleged shooter Rahmanullah Lakanwal was already living in Washington state when he became radicalized. Investigators are seeking more information from family members and others, Noem said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 15:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PKK urges Turkey to free Ocalan to advance peace process</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pkk-urges-turkey-free-ocalan-advance-peace-process</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pkk-urges-turkey-free-ocalan-advance-peace-process</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A senior Kurdistan Workers' Party commander told AFP the group will take no further steps in the peace process with Turkey, urging it to advance negotiations and free PKK founder Abdullah Ocalan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"All the steps the leader Apo has initiated have been implemented... there will be no further actions taken," commander Amed Malazgirt told AFP on Saturday in a bunker in the Qandil mountains in northern Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"From now on, we will be waiting for the Turkish state and they have to be the one taking steps," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The group has two demands, he added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 14:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu seeks pardon in corruption cases</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israels-netanyahu-seeks-pardon-corruption-cases</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israels-netanyahu-seeks-pardon-corruption-cases</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, on trial facing corruption charges, announced Sunday he had submitted a pardon request, saying the long-running cases were tearing the country apart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump wrote to Israeli President Isaac Herzog earlier this month, asking him to pardon Netanyahu, who has repeatedly denied wrongdoing in the proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The trial in my case has been ongoing for nearly six years, and is expected to continue for many more years," Netanyahu said in a video statement, without admitting guilt.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 12:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu officially asks Israeli president for pardon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-officially-asks-israeli-president-pardon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-officially-asks-israeli-president-pardon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nov 30 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has submitted an official request for his pardon to Israeli President Isaac Herzog, the Israeli president's office said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The Office of the President is aware that this is an extraordinary request which carries with it significant implications. After receiving all of the relevant opinions, the President will responsibly and sincerely consider the request," Herzog's office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no immediate comment from the prime minister's office.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope urges Lebanese to embrace reconciliation, stay in crisis-hit country</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-urges-lebanese-embrace-reconciliation-stay-crisis-hit-country</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-urges-lebanese-embrace-reconciliation-stay-crisis-hit-country</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Visiting Pope Leo XIV urged the Lebanese people on Sunday to embrace reconciliation and remain in their crisis-hit country, while calling on its leaders to put themselves fully at the service of their citizens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pope, bearing what he described as a message of peace, had previously visited Turkey, where he kicked off his first overseas tour since being elected leader of the world's 1.4 billion Catholics in May.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long hailed as a model of coexistence, multi-confessional Lebanon is nonetheless plagued by sectarian and political rifts, and has seen waves of emigration.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Operations restart at Iraq's Khor Mor field, transporting gas to power stations, ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/operations-restart-iraqs-khor-mor-field-transporting-gas-power-stations-ministry</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/operations-restart-iraqs-khor-mor-field-transporting-gas-power-stations-ministry</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD, Nov 30 (Reuters) - Operations restarted at Iraq's Khor Mor gas field, with the transmission of gas to power stations starting at 2:00 a.m. Sunday (2300 GMT Saturday), the Kurdish regional government's electricity ministry announced, days after a drone attack halted production and led to extensive power cuts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Khor Mor gas field, one of the largest in the Kurdistan region, provides supplies for regional power generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 07:01:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo taking peace message to Lebanon, target of Israeli strikes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-taking-peace-message-lebanon-target-israeli-strikes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-taking-peace-message-lebanon-target-israeli-strikes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Nov 30 (Reuters) - Pope Leo travels to Lebanon on Sunday, where he is expected to appeal for peace in a country that is a continued target of Israeli air strikes, on the second and final leg of his first overseas trip as leader of the Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first U.S. pope will arrive from Turkey, where he has been visiting for four days and warned that humanity's future was at risk because of the world's unusual number of bloody conflicts and condemned violence in the name of religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:36:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Dinosaur tartare' and holograms: Dubai AI chef sparks awe and ire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dinosaur-tartare-and-holograms-dubai-ai-chef-sparks-awe-and-ire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dinosaur-tartare-and-holograms-dubai-ai-chef-sparks-awe-and-ire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Dubai restaurant has opened that prides itself on having the world's "first AI chef", the latest ostentatious dive into new technology in a city obsessed with being on the cutting edge of the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Emirati city has become increasingly known for its growing culinary scene, with thousands of restaurants on offer from luxurious Michelin-starred eateries to greasy spoons serving up bona fide street food from across the Middle East and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 03:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OPEC+ likely to maintain current output levels</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/opec-likely-maintain-current-output-levels</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/opec-likely-maintain-current-output-levels</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ministers of the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries and allied nations (OPEC+) are expected to keep current output levels unchanged when they meet for online meetings on Sunday, analysts told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biannual ministerial meeting comes as uncertainty remains over how oil prices will develop in the near future, with traders looking for signs that indicate progress in ongoing negotiations on resolving the conflict in Ukraine, which could lead to the return of Russian crude to markets.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 02:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope to wrap up Turkey trip before heading to Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-wrap-turkey-trip-heading-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-wrap-turkey-trip-heading-lebanon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo XIV wraps up a four-day trip to Turkey Sunday after a warm welcome by its tiny Christian community, before heading to Lebanon with a message of peace for the crisis-mired nation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On his first overseas trip since being elected leader of the world's 1.4 billion Catholics, Leo met President Recep Tayyip Erdogan before travelling to Iznik for a celebration marking 1,700 years since the First Council of Nicaea, one of the early Church's most important gatherings. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 02:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US State Department stops processing visas for Afghan allies</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-state-department-stops-processing-visas-afghan-allies</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-state-department-stops-processing-visas-afghan-allies</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Nov 29 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump’s administration has ordered its diplomats worldwide to stop processing visas for Afghan nationals, according to a State Department cable seen by Reuters, effectively suspending the special immigration program for Afghans who helped the United States during its 20-year-long occupation of their home country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 20:36:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza death toll tops 70,000, health ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-death-toll-tops-70000-health-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-death-toll-tops-70000-health-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Nov 29 (Reuters) - The number of people confirmed killed in Israel's offensive in  the Gaza Strip has passed the 70,000 mark, the enclave's health ministry said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 301 people have been added to the toll since Thursday, taking it to 70,100, the ministry added. Two died in recent Israeli strikes, the rest were identified from remains buried for some time in the rubble, according to the statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 17:36:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prominent activist arrested as hundreds protest in Tunisia</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/prominent-activist-arrested-hundreds-protest-tunisia</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/prominent-activist-arrested-hundreds-protest-tunisia</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A prominent Tunisian activist was arrested on Saturday as hundreds protested in the capital against the curtailing of freedoms, an AFP journalist and lawyers said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protest in Tunis came a day after a mass appeal trial saw some 40 public figures, mainly critics of President Kais Saied, handed hefty sentences over plotting against the state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Poet and political figure Chaima Issa, who was handed a 20-year sentence during the trial on Friday, was arrested during the rally, lawyers and witnesses said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 17:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>