<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Morocco says evacuated 140,000 people due to severe weather</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/morocco-says-evacuated-140000-people-due-severe-weather</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/morocco-says-evacuated-140000-people-due-severe-weather</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Authorities have evacuated more than 140,000 people from their homes since heavy rainfall flooded several provinces in northern Morocco last week, the interior ministry said Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Authorities have not announced any casualties, and the national weather service forecast heavy rains and strong winds to continue on Thursday and Friday across the north.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The severe weather came after Morocco struggled with seven consecutive years of drought.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 18:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE plans compound for Palestinians in Israeli-held south Gaza, map shows</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-plans-compound-palestinians-israeli-held-south-gaza-map-shows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-plans-compound-palestinians-israeli-held-south-gaza-map-shows</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 5 (Reuters) - The United Arab Emirates has drafted plans to build a compound to house thousands of displaced Palestinians in a part of south Gaza under Israeli military control, according to a map seen by Reuters and people briefed on the plans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The planning map shows where the "UAE Temporary Emirates Housing Complex" would be constructed near Rafah, once a city of a quarter million people but now almost completely destroyed and depopulated by Israeli forces. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 17:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran, US prepare for Oman talks after deadly protest crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-prepare-oman-talks-after-deadly-protest-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-prepare-oman-talks-after-deadly-protest-crackdown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States were preparing for talks on Friday in Oman, with Washington looking to see if there is any prospect of diplomatic progress on the Iranian nuclear programme and other issues while refusing to rule out military action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talks, which were finally confirmed by both sides late Wednesday after hours of doubt over the location, timing and format, will be the first such encounter between the two foes since the US joined Israel's war against the Islamic republic in June with strikes on nuclear sites.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 16:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Famine spreading in Sudan's Darfur, warn UN-backed experts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/famine-spreading-sudans-darfur-warn-un-backed-experts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/famine-spreading-sudans-darfur-warn-un-backed-experts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Famine is spreading in Sudan's western Darfur region, UN-backed experts warned on Thursday, as a grinding war between the army and paramilitary forces has left millions hungry, displaced and cut off from aid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since April 2023, the conflict between Sudan's army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces has killed tens of thousands, displaced nearly 11 million and triggered one of the world's worst humanitarian crises.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 16:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazil's Lula likely to visit Washington in early March</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/brazils-lula-likely-visit-washington-early-march</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/brazils-lula-likely-visit-washington-early-march</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SAO PAULO, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva said on Thursday he is likely to travel to Washington in the first week of March for a meeting with his U.S. counterpart Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking in an interview with news outlet UOL, Lula said Brazil would be interested in being part of Trump's Board of Peace, provided discussions were limited to Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Gabriel Araujo; Writing by Isabel Teles)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 15:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Activists plan new, bigger flotilla to try to bring aid to Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/activists-plan-new-bigger-flotilla-try-bring-aid-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/activists-plan-new-bigger-flotilla-try-bring-aid-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tim Cocks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JOHANNESBURG, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Activists behind a flotilla intercepted at sea last year by Israel while trying to bring aid to Gaza will try again this year, expecting more than twice as many boats carrying up to 1,000 medics, they said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military halted the roughly 40 boats in the Global Sumud Flotilla last October as they attempted to reach blockaded Gaza, arresting Swedish activist Greta Thunberg and more than 450 other participants.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 15:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US, Russia to reestablish military-to-military talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-russia-reestablish-military-military-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-russia-reestablish-military-military-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 5 (Reuters) - The U.S. military said that Washington and Moscow on Thursday agreed to reestablish high level military-to-military dialogue, following talks in Abu Dhabi, a move which could signal a move towards normalizing some ties between the United States and Russia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United States halted military-to-military communication with Moscow just before Russia invaded Ukraine. The conflict, which began in 2022, is the deadliest war in Europe since World War Two and the biggest confrontation between Moscow and the West since the depths of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 14:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's IRGC seizes two tankers in Gulf over alleged oil smuggling</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</guid><description>What appeared to be a routine policing action followed two run-ins with the US Navy earlier this week, amid a massive buildup of US naval and air forces around Iran.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:53:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's IRGC seizes two tankers in Gulf over alleged oil smuggling</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</guid><description>What appeared to be a routine policing action followed two run-ins with the US Navy earlier this week, amid a massive buildup of US naval and air forces around Iran.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:53:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's IRGC seizes two tankers in Gulf over alleged oil smuggling</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</guid><description>What appeared to be a routine policing action followed two run-ins with the US Navy earlier this week, amid a massive buildup of US naval and air forces around Iran.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:53:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's IRGC seizes two tankers in Gulf over alleged oil smuggling</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-irgc-seizes-two-tankers-gulf-over-alleged-oil-smuggling</guid><description>What appeared to be a routine policing action followed two run-ins with the US Navy earlier this week, amid a massive buildup of US naval and air forces around Iran.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:53:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Irish attorney general raises concerns on sanctioning services in Israeli settlements</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irish-attorney-general-raises-concerns-sanctioning-services-israeli-settlements</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irish-attorney-general-raises-concerns-sanctioning-services-israeli-settlements</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBLIN, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Ireland's top government lawyer has raised several "significant" legal and practical issues in long-awaited advice on whether planned curbs on trade with Israeli settlements should be extended to services, a junior minister said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ireland has been preparing a law to curb trade with settlements in the Israeli-occupied West Bank, facing pressure at home to widen the scope of the ban from goods to services, while Israel and the United States want the bill scrapped.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What does Iran want from talks with the US?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/what-does-iran-want-talks-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/what-does-iran-want-talks-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States are holding talks on Friday in Oman, with Tehran pushing to focus squarely on its nuclear programme, while Washington's demands go beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two foes had held several rounds of Oman-mediated nuclear talks in 2025, but the Iran-Israel war, which saw the United States conduct strikes on Iranian nuclear sites, derailed diplomacy days before a meeting was due.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey is doing its best to prevent US-Iran conflict, Erdogan says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-doing-its-best-prevent-us-iran-conflict-erdogan-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-doing-its-best-prevent-us-iran-conflict-erdogan-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tuvan Gumrukcu and Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL/ DUBAI, Feb 5 (Reuters) - President Tayyip Erdogan said Turkey is working hard to prevent U.S.-Iran tensions from tipping the Middle East into a new conflict, as the two adversaries signal that disagreement over Tehran’s missile arsenal threatens to torpedo a deal.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 12:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany's Merz shares concerns over Iran escalation on Gulf trip</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/germanys-merz-shares-concerns-over-iran-escalation-gulf-trip</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/germanys-merz-shares-concerns-over-iran-escalation-gulf-trip</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DOHA, Feb 5 (Reuters) - German Chancellor Friedrich Merz said on Thursday that concerns about a further escalation in the conflict with Iran have characterised his talks during a trip to the Gulf region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"In all my conversations yesterday and today, great concern has been expressed about a further escalation in the conflict with Iran," he said during a press conference in Doha.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He called on Iran to end what he called an aggression and enter into talks, saying Germany would do everything it can to de-escalate the situation and work towards stability in the region.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 11:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey to stress need to update customs union with EU during commissioner's visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-stress-need-update-customs-union-eu-during-commissioners-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-stress-need-update-customs-union-eu-during-commissioners-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan will push for a speedy resumption of talks with the European Union to update their customs union during a visit to Turkey by the bloc's commissioner for enlargement, a Turkish Foreign Ministry source said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey has been an official candidate to join the EU since 1999, but its accession has been frozen for years over issues ranging from human rights to democratic backsliding. The sides have in recent months shown signs of increased engagement and economic cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US, Ukraine, Russia delegations agree to exchange 314 prisoners, Witkoff says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-ukraine-russia-delegations-agree-exchange-314-prisoners-witkoff-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-ukraine-russia-delegations-agree-exchange-314-prisoners-witkoff-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 5 (Reuters) - Delegations from the United States, Ukraine and Russia have agreed to exchange 314 prisoners, U.S. President Donald Trump's special envoy Steve Witkoff said in a post on X on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Discussions will continue, with additional progress anticipated in the coming weeks," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Shubham Kalia in BengaluruEditing by Bernadette Baum)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin dismisses Western claims that Epstein was Russian intelligence asset</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-dismisses-western-claims-epstein-was-russian-intelligence-asset</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-dismisses-western-claims-epstein-was-russian-intelligence-asset</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 5 (Reuters) - The Kremlin said on Thursday it did not want to waste time answering questions about unproven suggestions in Western media and by Poland's premier that late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein may have been some sort of Russian intelligence asset.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polish Prime Minister Donald Tusk said on Tuesday that Warsaw would launch an investigation into what it said were possible links between Epstein and Russia's intelligence services, and into any potential impact on Poland.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN rights chief appeals for $400 million as crises mount and funding shrinks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-rights-chief-appeals-400-million-crises-mount-and-funding-shrinks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-rights-chief-appeals-400-million-crises-mount-and-funding-shrinks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Feb 5 (Reuters) - U.N. human rights chief Volker Turk appealed for $400 million on Thursday to address mounting human rights needs in countries such as Sudan and Myanmar, after donor funding cuts drastically reduced the work of his office and left it in "survival mode".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.N. office is appealing for $100 million less than last year, after a significant scale back of its work in some areas due to a fall in contributions from countries including the U.S. and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Dmitriev says progress made on Ukraine peace deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-dmitriev-says-progress-made-ukraine-peace-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-dmitriev-says-progress-made-ukraine-peace-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 5 (Reuters) - Russian President Vladimir Putin's envoy Kirill Dmitriev said on Thursday that there was progress and a positive movement forward in negotiations on peace in Ukraine, as delegations from Russia, Ukraine and the United States prepared for talks in Abu Dhabi.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia invaded Ukraine in February 2022 after eight years of fighting in the east, triggering the deadliest war in Europe since World War Two and biggest confrontation between Moscow and the West since the depths of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>