<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Six ancient statues stolen from Syria's National Museum of Damascus</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/six-ancient-statues-stolen-syrias-national-museum-damascus</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/six-ancient-statues-stolen-syrias-national-museum-damascus</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS (Reuters) -Six ancient statues have been stolen from the National Museum of Damascus, which is one of the Middle East's oldest cultural institutions and houses a collection showing Syria's archaeological and artistic heritage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A source at the museum told Reuters that a thief broke a glass display case on Monday and apparently stayed inside the building until evening. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Authorities have launched an investigation, according to the head of internal security in Damascus, Osama Mohammad Khair Atkeh.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UNICEF says Israel blocking one million syringes needed to vaccinate Gaza children</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/unicef-says-israel-blocking-one-million-syringes-needed-vaccinate-gaza-children</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/unicef-says-israel-blocking-one-million-syringes-needed-vaccinate-gaza-children</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA (Reuters) -UNICEF said on Tuesday essential items including syringes to vaccinate children and bottles for baby formula are being denied entry into Gaza by Israel, preventing aid agencies from reaching those in need in the war-devastated territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As UNICEF undertakes a mass children's vaccination campaign with a fragile ceasefire in place, it said it faces serious challenges getting 1.6 million syringes and solar-powered fridges to store vaccine vials into Gaza. The syringes have awaited customs clearance since August, UNICEF said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada's G7 summit to tackle peace in Ukraine and Middle East</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/canadas-g7-summit-tackle-peace-ukraine-and-middle-east</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/canadas-g7-summit-tackle-peace-ukraine-and-middle-east</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maria  Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TORONTO (Reuters) -As the latest meeting of the Group of Seven’s foreign ministers begins in Canada on Tuesday, Canada's foreign minister Anita Anand said the agenda will focus on issues including Arctic security, the war in Ukraine and securing peace in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid the current era of "geopolitical volatility," Anand said her U.S. counterpart Marco Rubio has been "a very constructive member" of the G7 and commended the U.S. for its efforts to secure peace in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkish prosecutor seeks 2,000-year jail term for Istanbul mayor Imamoglu in graft case</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-prosecutor-seeks-2000-year-jail-term-istanbul-mayor-imamoglu-graft-case</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-prosecutor-seeks-2000-year-jail-term-istanbul-mayor-imamoglu-graft-case</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -A Turkish prosecutor has demanded a potential prison sentence of more than 2,000 years for Istanbul Mayor Ekrem Imamoglu, who has been jailed since March pending trial on corruption charges that he and his main opposition party deny.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The indictment, presented by the Istanbul Chief Prosecutor, accuses Imamoglu and 401 others of involvement in a graft network that allegedly caused 160 billion lira ($3.81 billion) in damages to the state over a 10-year period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;($1 = 41.9551 liras)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel fears Iran resuming ballistic missile project, eyes confrontation, destabilizing regime</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</guid><description>The Israeli security establishment is concerned over reports that Iran is adamant in avenging the Israeli and American strikes on its nuclear plants last summer, resuming and bolstering its ballistic missile project.</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 12:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel fears Iran resuming ballistic missile project, eyes confrontation, destabilizing regime</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</guid><description>The Israeli security establishment is concerned over reports that Iran is adamant in avenging the Israeli and American strikes on its nuclear plants last summer, resuming and bolstering its ballistic missile project.</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 12:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel fears Iran resuming ballistic missile project, eyes confrontation, destabilizing regime</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</guid><description>The Israeli security establishment is concerned over reports that Iran is adamant in avenging the Israeli and American strikes on its nuclear plants last summer, resuming and bolstering its ballistic missile project.</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 12:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel fears Iran resuming ballistic missile project, eyes confrontation, destabilizing regime</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-fears-iran-resuming-ballistic-missile-project-eyes-confrontation</guid><description>The Israeli security establishment is concerned over reports that Iran is adamant in avenging the Israeli and American strikes on its nuclear plants last summer, resuming and bolstering its ballistic missile project.</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 12:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thieves steal ancient gold from Syria's national museum, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/thieves-steal-ancient-gold-syrias-national-museum-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/thieves-steal-ancient-gold-syrias-national-museum-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Thieves made off with several ancient gold ingots from Syria's national museum in Damascus, a security source and another close to the institution's management said Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The museum was spared during Syria's destructive civil war that ran from 2011 to late last year, and houses priceless artefacts dating back to antiquity.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 12:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli parliament advances death penalty bill backed by Ben-Gvir</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-parliament-advances-death-penalty-bill-backed-ben-gvir</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-parliament-advances-death-penalty-bill-backed-ben-gvir</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -The Israeli parliament has advanced a bill that would mandate the death penalty for Palestinian militants convicted of killing Israeli citizens, with some lawmakers believing it would prevent future prisoner-release deals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a vote held late on Monday - the first of four needed for the measure to become law - the bill passed with 39 in favour and 16 against, out of 120 lawmakers. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 11:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkish, Egyptian foreign ministers to discuss Gaza ceasefire, post-war efforts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-egyptian-foreign-ministers-discuss-gaza-ceasefire-post-war-efforts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-egyptian-foreign-ministers-discuss-gaza-ceasefire-post-war-efforts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -The foreign ministers of Turkey and Egypt will discuss the Gaza ceasefire and international efforts to rebuild the enclave once the war is over during talks in Ankara on Wednesday, a Turkish foreign ministry source said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NATO member Turkey has been one of the most vocal critics of Israel's two-year assault on Gaza, calling it a genocide, which Israel denies. Along with Egypt and Qatar, it has helped mediate the fragile ceasefire, emerging as a crucial player and vowing to monitor the strict implementation of the accord.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 10:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At least 12 killed in suicide bombing in Pakistan's capital</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/least-12-killed-suicide-bombing-pakistans-capital</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/least-12-killed-suicide-bombing-pakistans-capital</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD (Reuters) -At least 12 people were killed in a suicide bombing outside a local court in Pakistan's capital Islamabad on Tuesday, the country's interior minister said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Asif Shahzad, writing by Shilpa Jamkhandikar; Editing by YP Rajesh)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 10:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel buries hostage officer killed in Gaza 11 years ago</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-buries-hostage-officer-killed-gaza-11-years-ago</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-buries-hostage-officer-killed-gaza-11-years-ago</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of Israelis bid farewell to army officer Hadar Goldin, who was laid to rest Tuesday in the central town of Kfar Saba after Hamas returned his remains more than a decade after his death in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Crowds packed the military cemetery, with some climbing onto rooftops to glimpse the funeral, while others filled the streets and watched on a large outdoor screen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blue-and-white Israeli flags fluttered in the wind, as mourners held the young lieutenant's portrait alongside a homemade banner reading: "We will remember forever."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 09:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says US sending contradictory messages on nuclear talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-says-us-sending-contradictory-messages-nuclear-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-says-us-sending-contradictory-messages-nuclear-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ABU DHABI (Reuters) -Iran's Deputy Foreign Minister said on Tuesday the U.S. was sending Tehran contradictory messages about nuclear talks through third countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran wants to reach "a peaceful nuclear agreement" but will not compromise on national security, Saeed Khatibzadeh told the 12th Abu Dhabi Strategic Debate. He reiterated Tehran's position that it does not seek nuclear bombs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Samia Nakhool and Parisa Hafezi, writing by Elwely Elwelly; Editing by Andrew Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 07:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Partition of Gaza a looming risk as Trump's plan falters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/partition-gaza-looming-risk-trumps-plan-falters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/partition-gaza-looming-risk-trumps-plan-falters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MANAMA (Reuters) -A de facto partition of Gaza between an area controlled by Israel and another ruled by Hamas is increasingly likely, multiple sources said, with efforts to advance U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the war beyond a ceasefire faltering.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Six European officials with direct knowledge of the efforts to implement the next phase of the plan told Reuters it was effectively stalled and that reconstruction now appeared likely to be limited to the Israel- controlled area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That could lead to years of separation, they warned.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 07:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France's Macron to meet Palestinian president Abbas</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/frances-macron-meet-palestinian-president-abbas</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/frances-macron-meet-palestinian-president-abbas</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;French President Emmanuel Macron will meet Palestinian president Mahmud Abbas in Paris on Tuesday to discuss the "full implementation" of the Gaza ceasefire agreement, the Elysee said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting comes a month into a fragile truce between Hamas and Israel, following two years of war triggered by the Palestinian militant group's October 7, 2023 attack against Israel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abbas, 89, is the longtime head of the Palestinian Authority, which exercises limited control over parts of the West Bank and is being considered to assume governance in Gaza under the deal.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 06:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What next after Iraq's general election?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/what-next-after-iraqs-general-election</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/what-next-after-iraqs-general-election</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iraqis head to the polls on Tuesday to elect a new parliament for a four-year term in a vote that will be closely watched in Washington and Tehran. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is a look at what could come next and what the regional impact could be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- What happens after the vote? -&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iraq's Supreme Court must first ratify the election results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later, the newly elected members of parliament should convene for a swearing-in ceremony and to choose their speaker, who by convention should be a member from the Sunni community.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 02:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraqis vote in general election at a crucial regional moment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iraqis-vote-general-election-crucial-regional-moment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iraqis-vote-general-election-crucial-regional-moment</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iraqis began voting for a new parliament on Tuesday at a pivotal time for the country and the wider region, in an election that both Iran and the United States will be closely watching.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iraq, which has long been a fertile land for proxy wars, has only recently regained a sense of stability, as it tries to move past decades of war since the US-led invasion that toppled Saddam Hussein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But even now, the country of 46 million people suffers from poor infrastructure, failing public services, mismanagement and endemic corruption.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 01:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraqis vote in election they expect to bring little reform</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iraqis-vote-election-they-expect-bring-little-reform</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iraqis-vote-election-they-expect-bring-little-reform</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Rasheed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD (Reuters) -Iraqis vote on Tuesday in a parliamentary election in which Prime Minister Mohammed Shia al-Sudani is seeking a second term and which a growing young electorate sees as a vehicle for established parties to divide up the country's oil wealth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sudani's bloc is forecast to win the most seats but fall short of a majority, potentially meaning months of post-election talks among Shi'ite and Sunni Muslim as well as Kurdish parties to divvy up government posts and pick a prime minister.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 00:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK pro-Palestinian commentator set to be released from US detention, his family says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uk-pro-palestinian-commentator-set-be-released-us-detention-his-family-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uk-pro-palestinian-commentator-set-be-released-us-detention-his-family-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON (Reuters) -British pro-Palestinian commentator Sami Hamdi, who is being held by U.S. immigration authorities, is set to be released, his family said on Monday, a fortnight after he was detained midway through a national speaking tour. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. Homeland Security officials detained Hamdi and revoked his visa on October 26, saying then that he would be deported rather than allowed to complete his speaking tour in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 23:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>