<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>US says 'key participant' in 2012 attack on Benghazi mission arrested</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-says-key-participant-2012-attack-benghazi-mission-arrested</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-says-key-participant-2012-attack-benghazi-mission-arrested</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the "key participants" behind the 2012 attack on the US mission in Benghazi that left the ambassador and three other Americans dead has been arrested, officials said Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attorney General Pam Bondi said the suspect, Zubayr al-Bakoush, has been brought to the United States and will face murder and other charges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a press conference, Bondi and FBI Director Kash Patel declined to say where Bakoush was arrested, saying only that it was "overseas."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 16:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands attend burial of slain son of Libya's Gaddafi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/thousands-attend-burial-slain-son-libyas-gaddafi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/thousands-attend-burial-slain-son-libyas-gaddafi</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands turned out on Friday for the burial of the slain son of former Libyan ruler Muammar Gaddafi in a town that still holds allegiance to the late longtime leader.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seif al-Islam Gaddafi, once seen by some as Libya's heir apparent, was shot dead in his home in the northwestern city of Zintan on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His burial in the town of Bani Walid, some 175 kilometres (110 miles) south of Tripoli, brought together thousands of Gaddafi loyalists, nearly 15 years after the ruler was toppled and killed in a 2011 NATO-backed uprising.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 16:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US arrests Benghazi suspect, Bondi says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-arrests-benghazi-suspect-bondi-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-arrests-benghazi-suspect-bondi-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 6 (Reuters) - The United States has arrested a person suspected of playing a role in the 2012 attack on the U.S. consulate in Benghazi, Libya. Attorney General Pam Bondi said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bondi said Zubayar al-Bakoush has been extradited to the United States and will face murder, arson and terrorism related charges.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 15:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Some UAE companies pull out of Saudi defence show as Gulf rift spills into business</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-some-uae-companies-pull-out-saudi-defence-show-gulf-rift-spills</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-some-uae-companies-pull-out-saudi-defence-show-gulf-rift-spills</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Federico Maccioni, Nazih Osseiran and Maha El Dahan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 6 (Reuters) - Some UAE companies have pulled out of a major defence show taking place in Saudi Arabia, two sources with direct knowledge of the matter told Reuters, the latest sign that a rift between the two Gulf oil powers is seeping into business interests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The World Defense Show is set to take place in the Saudi capital Riyadh from February 8-12. It was not immediately clear if all the UAE participants involved in the country pavilion had withdrawn.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 15:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Palestinians returning to Gaza, a bittersweet reunion</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinians-returning-gaza-bittersweet-reunion</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinians-returning-gaza-bittersweet-reunion</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ramadan Abed and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAZA/CAIRO, Feb 6 (Reuters) - Eatedal Rayyan waited for this moment for nearly two years: a reunion with her husband in Gaza, where she says yearning for family and homeland has persisted despite widespread destruction from the enclave's two-year war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rayyan, 29, left Gaza with her mother and three children after suffering a leg injury that doctors warned could need amputation if left untreated. She was one of tens of thousands who fled to Egypt in the early months of the conflict. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 14:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanese army must be given 'means' to disarm Hezbollah: French FM to AFP</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanese-army-must-be-given-means-disarm-hezbollah-french-fm-afp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanese-army-must-be-given-means-disarm-hezbollah-french-fm-afp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;French Foreign Minister Jean-Noel Barrot said Friday that Lebanon's army must be given the means to disarm militant group Hezbollah and replace a United Nations peacekeeping force after its mandate ends this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the final stop of a regional tour that has taken him to Syria and Iraq, Barrot was meeting senior officials in Beirut on Friday, with discussions expected to address preparations for a March conference in Paris in support of the Lebanese army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"France's vision for Lebanon is that of a strong, sovereign state holding a monopoly on arms," Barrot told AFP. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 14:30:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian FM says US-Iran nuclear talks in Oman 'a good start'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-fm-says-us-iran-nuclear-talks-oman-good-start</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-fm-says-us-iran-nuclear-talks-oman-good-start</guid><description>Iran's top diplomat, Abbas Araghchi, said the two sides agreed to continue talks but would first consult with their capitals.</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 14:02:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France and Bahrain sign bilateral deal on defence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-and-bahrain-sign-bilateral-deal-defence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-and-bahrain-sign-bilateral-deal-defence</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Feb 6 (Reuters) - France and Bahrain have signed a bilateral deal on defence which includes strategic information sharing, the office of French President Emmanuel Macron said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"This agreement will also open up new opportunities for industrial cooperation in defence, and strengthen solidarity between our two countries in a global and regional geopolitical context marked by increasing tensions," it said.      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Inti Landauro, editing by Bart Meijer)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 13:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Norway set to probe Epstein revelations as scandal reverberates round Europe</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-set-probe-epstein-revelations-scandal-reverberates-round-europe</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-set-probe-epstein-revelations-scandal-reverberates-round-europe</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Gwladys Fouche&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OSLO, Feb 6 (Reuters) - Norway looks set to launch an inquiry into its own foreign ministry over links to late U.S. sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, one of several European nations to feel the heat from a scandal that has yet to cause major political repercussions in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The release of an enormous cache of new files last week has revealed a host of new Epstein connections with politicians, royals and the ultra-rich.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 12:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sweden to make asylum seekers live in centres in further tightening of rules</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sweden-make-asylum-seekers-live-centres-further-tightening-rules</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sweden-make-asylum-seekers-live-centres-further-tightening-rules</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;STOCKHOLM, Feb 6 (Reuters) - Sweden's centre-right government said on Friday it planned to make all asylum seekers live in migrant reception centres while their cases are processed, in a further tightening of immigration regulations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People will have to prove that they have moved to the centres, or risk losing their benefits, and also agree to travel restrictions, Migration Minister Johan Forssell told reporters. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 11:37:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey edges towards curbing social media access to minors amid global push</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-edges-towards-curbing-social-media-access-minors-amid-global-push</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-edges-towards-curbing-social-media-access-minors-amid-global-push</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Can Sezer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Feb 6 (Reuters) - Turkey is laying the groundwork to restrict social media access for minorswith a parliamentary report this week calling for broad measures including age verification and content filtering, joining a growing list of countries seeking tighter controls.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 11:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin says it hopes US-Iran talks in Oman will yield results</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-says-it-hopes-us-iran-talks-oman-will-yield-results</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-says-it-hopes-us-iran-talks-oman-will-yield-results</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 6 (Reuters) - The Kremlin said on Friday that it hoped that negotiations between Iran and the United States in Oman would yield results and lead to a de-escalation and urged all sides to show restraint in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States started high-stakes negotiations on Friday to try to overcome sharp differences over Tehran's nuclear programme, with Oman shuttling between the sides, but a dispute over widening the agenda risked derailing diplomacy and triggering another Middle East conflict.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 10:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran expects more US talks after 'positive atmosphere' in Oman</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-expects-more-us-talks-after-positive-atmosphere-oman</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-expects-more-us-talks-after-positive-atmosphere-oman</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran on Friday said it expected to hold more negotiations with the United States, hailing a "positive atmosphere" during a day of indirect talks in Oman but warning against threats after Washington raised the spectre of new military action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With an American naval group led by an aircraft carrier in Middle Eastern waters, US and Iranian delegations held talks in Muscat mediated by the Gulf sultanate without publicly meeting face-to-face.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 09:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran, US to negotiate in Oman amid deep rifts and mounting war fears</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-negotiate-oman-amid-deep-rifts-and-mounting-war-fears</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-negotiate-oman-amid-deep-rifts-and-mounting-war-fears</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI/WASHINGTON, Feb 6 (Reuters) - Iran and the United States are set to hold high-stakes negotiations in Oman on Friday over Tehran's nuclear programme, but a dispute over the agenda suggests progress will be hard won amid the threat of a regional Middle East war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 04:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran, US prepare for Oman talks after deadly protest crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-prepare-oman-talks-after-deadly-protest-crackdown-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-us-prepare-oman-talks-after-deadly-protest-crackdown-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran and the United States were preparing for talks on Friday in Oman, with Washington looking to see if there was any prospect of diplomatic progress on the Iranian nuclear programme and other issues while refusing to rule out military action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talks -- finally confirmed by both sides late Wednesday after uncertainty over the location, timing and format -- will be the first such encounter between the two foes since the United States joined Israel's war against the Islamic republic in June with strikes on nuclear sites.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 21:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran filmmaker Panahi fears Iranians' interests will be 'sacrificed' in US talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-filmmaker-panahi-fears-iranians-interests-will-be-sacrificed-us-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-filmmaker-panahi-fears-iranians-interests-will-be-sacrificed-us-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dissident Iranian film director Jafar Panahi told AFP he believes ordinary Iranians risk being "sacrificed" in talks between Iran and the United States on Friday, with his country still "in shock" over a deadly crackdown on protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Panahi, Iran's best-known director, offered support for anti-government protests last month in which thousands of people were killed by security forces, according to rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 20:30:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Lebanon, a Hezbollah-run camp houses people escaping Syria</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanon-hezbollah-run-camp-houses-people-escaping-syria</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanon-hezbollah-run-camp-houses-people-escaping-syria</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;"They drove us out at gunpoint," says Lebanese citizen Zeinab Qataya, who fled her adopted home in Syria after the fall of Bashar al-Assad and returned to her country to live in a camp built by Hezbollah.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The construction of the Imam Ali Housing Compound has proved controversial, but Lebanese and Syrian families pushed out of villages just over the border in Syria say they now rely on the Iran-backed movement for safety.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 20:30:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran names Ali Shamkhani head of Defense Council: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-names-ali-shamkhani-head-defense-council-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-names-ali-shamkhani-head-defense-council-what-know</guid><description>Ali Shamkhani, a longtime security official, recently dismissed the idea of sending enriched uranium abroad and expressed a degree of hope about the upcoming negotiations with the US.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 20:20:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran names Ali Shamkhani head of Defense Council: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-names-ali-shamkhani-head-defense-council-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-names-ali-shamkhani-head-defense-council-what-know</guid><description>Ali Shamkhani, a longtime security official, recently dismissed the idea of sending enriched uranium abroad and expressed a degree of hope about the upcoming negotiations with the US.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 20:20:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran names Ali Shamkhani head of Defense Council: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-names-ali-shamkhani-head-defense-council-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-names-ali-shamkhani-head-defense-council-what-know</guid><description>Ali Shamkhani, a longtime security official, recently dismissed the idea of sending enriched uranium abroad and expressed a degree of hope about the upcoming negotiations with the US.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 20:20:22 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>