<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Factbox-Who is fighting in Yemen?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-who-fighting-yemen</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-who-fighting-yemen</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Yousef Saba&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 2 (Reuters) - Yemen's more than decade-long civil war has flared up after a United Arab Emirates-backed separatist movement swept through territory in the south, splintering the Saudi-led coalition that was created to fight the Iran-aligned Houthi group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Below are details of the key factions in the conflict in Yemen, which has caused one of the world's worst humanitarian crises:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;THE HOUTHIS&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan says he will discuss Ukraine, Gaza with Trump on Monday</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-says-he-will-discuss-ukraine-gaza-trump-monday</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-says-he-will-discuss-ukraine-gaza-trump-monday</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 2 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan said he would have a phone call with U.S. President Donald Trump on Monday to discuss peace efforts between Ukraine and Russia as well as issues surrounding Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to reporters in Istanbul on Friday, Erdogan also said Turkey's Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan will attend a meeting of the "Coalition of the Willing", a group of nations backing Ukraine, in Paris in coming days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Huseyin Hayatsever; Editing by Jonathan Spicer )&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump threatens Iran over protest deaths as unrest flares</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-threatens-iran-over-protest-deaths-unrest-flares</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-threatens-iran-over-protest-deaths-unrest-flares</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 2 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump threatened on Friday to come to the aid of protesters in Iran if security forces fire on them, days into unrest that has left several dead and posed the biggest internal threat to Iranian authorities in years. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are locked and loaded and ready to go," he said in a social media post. The United States struck Iranian nuclear facilities in June, joining an Israeli air campaign that targeted Tehran's atomic programme and military leadership. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 11:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US will 'come to their rescue' if Iran kills protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-us-will-come-their-rescue-if-iran-kills-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-us-will-come-their-rescue-if-iran-kills-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump said on Friday that the United States is "locked and loaded" to respond if Iran kills protesters, prompting Tehran to warn that intervention would destabilise the region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protesters and security forces clashed in several Iranian cities on Thursday, with six reported killed, the first deaths since the unrest escalated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shopkeepers in the capital Tehran went on strike Sunday over high prices and economic stagnation, actions that have since spread into a protest movement with political demands that has swept into other parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 11:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US will intervene if Iran violently suppresses peaceful protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-us-will-intervene-if-iran-violently-suppresses-peaceful-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-us-will-intervene-if-iran-violently-suppresses-peaceful-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 2 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump on Friday said that if Iran shoots and violently kills peaceful protesters, the United States of America will come to their rescue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are locked and loaded and ready to go," he said in a Truth Social post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This follows the deaths of several people as Iran's biggest protests in three years over economic hardship turned violent across multiple provinces.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi envoy says leader of Yemen separatist group STC blocked delegation's Aden landing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-envoy-says-leader-yemen-separatist-group-stc-blocked-delegations-aden</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-envoy-says-leader-yemen-separatist-group-stc-blocked-delegations-aden</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 2 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia's ambassador to Yemen said on Friday that Aidarus Al-Zubaidi, the leader of the UAE-backed Southern Transitional Council (STC), refused landing permission the previous day for a plane carrying a Saudi delegation to Aden.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The halt in flights at Aden international airport was the latest sign of a deepening crisis between Gulf powers Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates, whose rivalry is reshaping war-torn Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 07:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fresh clashes kill six in Iran cost-of-living protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fresh-clashes-kill-six-iran-cost-living-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fresh-clashes-kill-six-iran-cost-living-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Protesters and security forces clashed in several Iranian cities on Thursday, with six reported killed, the first deaths since the cost-of-living demonstrations broke out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests began on Sunday in Tehran, where shopkeepers went on strike over high prices and economic stagnation, and have since spread to other parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Iran's Fars news agency reported two people killed in clashes between security forces and protesters in the city of Lordegan, in the province of Chaharmahal and Bakhtiari, and three in Azna, in neighbouring Lorestan province.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 18:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Best of frenemies: Saudi, UAE rivalry bursts into view</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/best-frenemies-saudi-uae-rivalry-bursts-view</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/best-frenemies-saudi-uae-rivalry-bursts-view</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For years, the United Arab Emirates and Saudi Arabia projected geopolitical and economic power across the Gulf and beyond, seemingly in tandem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But a growing rivalry and struggle for influence has come to a head -- most recently in Yemen -- following years of divergence over a tangle of competing interests that reach from regional waterways to the corridors of power in Washington, analysts say. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 17:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemen’s Aden airport shuts as Saudi-UAE rift deepens</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemens-aden-airport-shuts-saudi-uae-rift-deepens</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemens-aden-airport-shuts-saudi-uae-rift-deepens</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 1 (Reuters) - Air traffic at Yemen's Aden international airport was halted on Thursday as tensions persisted between Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates, two Gulf powers whose rivalry is reshaping war-torn Yemen.    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Saudi-backed, internationally recognized Yemeni government ordered new restrictions on flights to and from the UAE, aiming to curb escalating tensions in Yemen, a Saudi source told Reuters. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 15:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Several reported killed in Iran protests over economic woes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/several-reported-killed-iran-protests-over-economic-woes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/several-reported-killed-iran-protests-over-economic-woes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Elwely Elwelly&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 1 (Reuters) - Several people were killed during unrest in Iran on Thursday, an Iranian news agency and a rights group reported, as the biggest protests to hit the country for three years over soaring inflation sparked violence in several provinces. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The semi-official Fars news agency cited a "source with knowledge" as saying several people were killed in clashes on Thursday morning between police and what it said were armed protesters in Lordegan in western Iran. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 14:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemen separatists say Saudi-backed forces to deploy in seized territories</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemen-separatists-say-saudi-backed-forces-deploy-seized-territories</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemen-separatists-say-saudi-backed-forces-deploy-seized-territories</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Separatists from Yemen's Southern Transitional Council said on Thursday that Saudi-aligned government forces would enter territories seized by the UAE-backed group, in a step that appeared unlikely to satisfy Riyadh after it repeatedly demanded their full withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A surprise offensive by the STC, in which the separatists took control of resource-rich Hadramawt and Mahra provinces last month, has brought the United Arab Emirates and Saudi Arabia, officially allies in Yemen, to a point of unprecedented tension.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 11:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands stage pro-Gaza rally in Istanbul</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-stage-pro-gaza-rally-istanbul</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-stage-pro-gaza-rally-istanbul</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands joined a New Year's Day rally for Gaza in Istanbul Thursday, waving Palestinian and Turkish flags and calling for an end to the violence in the tiny war-torn territory. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demonstrators gathered in freezing temperatures under cloudless blue skies to march to the city's Galata Bridge for a rally under the slogan: "We won't remain silent, we won’t forget Palestine," an AFP reporter at the scene said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 11:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel confirms ban on 37 NGOs in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-confirms-ban-37-ngos-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-confirms-ban-37-ngos-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel on Thursday said 37 humanitarian agencies supplying aid in Gaza had not met a deadline to meet "security and transparency standards", and would be banned from the territory, despite an international outcry. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The international NGOs, which had been ordered to disclose detailed information on their Palestinian staff, will now be required to cease operations by March 1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has warned that this will exacerbate the humanitarian crisis in the war-ravaged Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 10:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu among partygoers at Trump's New Year's Eve fete</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israels-netanyahu-among-partygoers-trumps-new-years-eve-fete</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israels-netanyahu-among-partygoers-trumps-new-years-eve-fete</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump hosted Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu at a glittering New Year's Eve party at his lavish Mar-a-Lago resort on Wednesday, according to social media.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netanyahu, who arrived at the US president's Palm Beach residence on Monday, was spotted alongside tuxedo-clad Trump Wednesday night in a social media post from conservative influencer Michael Solakiewicz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump had joked that the Israeli leader could attend the party during meetings Monday to discuss the fragile Gaza ceasefire and other regional geopolitical concerns in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 04:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN chief condemns Israeli law blocking electricity, water for UNRWA facilities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-chief-condemns-israeli-law-blocking-electricity-water-unrwa-facilities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-chief-condemns-israeli-law-blocking-electricity-water-unrwa-facilities</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jasper Ward&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dec 31 (Reuters) - United Nations Secretary General Antonio Guterres condemned on Wednesday a move by Israel to ban electricity or water to facilities owned by the U.N. Palestinian refugee agency, a U.N. spokesperson said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spokesperson said the move would "further impede" the agency's ability to operate and carry out activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 01:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU warns Yemen developments risk Gulf stability</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-warns-yemen-developments-risk-gulf-stability</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-warns-yemen-developments-risk-gulf-stability</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 31 (Reuters) - The European Union said on Wednesday that recent developments in the Yemeni provinces of Hadramout and Al Mahra threaten to bring new risks to the Gulf region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The EU calls for de-escalation and avoiding steps that further threaten stability of Yemen and the region," an EU spokesperson said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The EU reiterates its strong commitment to the unity, sovereignty, independence and territorial integrity of Yemen, as well as its support for the Presidential Leadership Council and the Government of Yemen," the spokesperson added.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 21:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US grants temporary licence to Russian-controlled Serbian oil firm NIS: Serbian minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-grants-temporary-licence-russian-controlled-serbian-oil-firm-nis-serbian</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-grants-temporary-licence-russian-controlled-serbian-oil-firm-nis-serbian</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The United States has granted a temporary licence to NIS, a majority-Russian owned Serbian oil company caught up in US sanctions against Moscow's invasion of Ukraine, a Serbian minister said on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washington's sanctions on the Petroleum Industry of Serbia (NIS), part of its crackdown on Russia's energy sector, forced Serbia's sole oil refinery, which supplies around 80 percent of the Serbian market, to shut down in early December. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 19:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel begins demolishing 25 buildings in West Bank camp</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-begins-demolishing-25-buildings-west-bank-camp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-begins-demolishing-25-buildings-west-bank-camp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli bulldozers began demolishing 25 buildings housing Palestinians in a refugee camp on Wednesday, in what the military said was an effort to root out armed groups in northern areas of the occupied West Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The buildings, home to some 100 families, are in the Nur Shams camp, a frequent site of clashes between Palestinian militants and Israeli forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israeli military bulldozers and cranes tore through the structures early Wednesday, sending thick plumes of dust into the air, an AFP journalist reported. Many residents watched from a distance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 19:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-UAE foreign policy in spotlight after Yemen escalation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/factbox-uae-foreign-policy-spotlight-after-yemen-escalation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/factbox-uae-foreign-policy-spotlight-after-yemen-escalation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Yousef Saba&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 31 - The United Arab Emirates has pursued an assertive foreign policy and carved its own sphere of influence across the Middle East and Africa, a strategy in the spotlight after a rare military escalation with Saudi Arabia in Yemen this week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abu Dhabi has used alliances with states or proxies, military intervention and financial support mainly to counter what it views as the destabilising threat of political Islam, specifically from groups linked to the Muslim Brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 14:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Oman says foreign minister met Saudi counterpart to discuss Yemen</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/oman-says-foreign-minister-met-saudi-counterpart-discuss-yemen</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/oman-says-foreign-minister-met-saudi-counterpart-discuss-yemen</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 31 (Reuters) - Oman's foreign minister met his Saudi counterpart in Riyadh on Wednesday to discuss finding a political solution to the crisis in Yemen, Oman's Foreign Ministry said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting came a day after a Saudi-led strike on Yemen's southern port of Mukalla, which raised tensions between Riyadh and the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, a Saudi-led coalition has clashed with UAE-backed southern separatists in Yemen. The UAE has said it is ending its remaining military mission there, highlighting a widening rift between the Gulf allies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 14:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>