<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Afghans say last path to safety shuts as US halts visas after DC shooting</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghans-say-last-path-safety-shuts-us-halts-visas-after-dc-shooting</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghans-say-last-path-safety-shuts-us-halts-visas-after-dc-shooting</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saeed  Shah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KABUL/ISLAMABAD (Reuters) -Afghans who fled the Taliban and have waited years for a U.S. resettlement decision say their last path to safety has shut since Washington froze all Afghan immigration cases following a shooting near the White House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services (USCIS) said late on Wednesday it had halted processing for Afghan nationals indefinitely, hours after an Afghan man shot and critically wounded two National Guard soldiers in Washington. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo, flying on Thanksgiving, given two pumpkin pies on papal plane</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-flying-thanksgiving-given-two-pumpkin-pies-papal-plane</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-flying-thanksgiving-given-two-pumpkin-pies-papal-plane</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ABOARD THE PAPAL FLIGHT TO ANKARA (Reuters) -Like many Americans on the annual holiday of Thanksgiving, Pope Leo was travelling on Thursday, flying from Rome to Turkey for his first overseas trip as leader of the Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the first U.S. pope may not have a chance to enjoy a meal with turkey, stuffing and the other traditional dishes this year, several journalists aboard his papal flight from Rome tried to make sure he had a taste of the annual feast.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says Lebanon-Cyprus maritime deal violates Turkish Cypriots' rights, is unacceptable</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-lebanon-cyprus-maritime-deal-violates-turkish-cypriots-rights</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-lebanon-cyprus-maritime-deal-violates-turkish-cypriots-rights</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -A maritime demarcation deal signed between Lebanon and Cyprus violates the rights of Turkish Cypriots on the island and is therefore unacceptable, Turkey said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lebanon and Cyprus on Wednesday signed the long-awaited deal, which aims to pave the way for potential exploration of offshore gas fields and deepen energy cooperation in the Mediterranean.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says Russia-Ukraine ceasefire needed first before discussing troop deployment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-russia-ukraine-ceasefire-needed-first-discussing-troop-deployment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-russia-ukraine-ceasefire-needed-first-discussing-troop-deployment</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -Turkey's defence ministry said on Thursday that a ceasefire between Ukraine and Russia must be achieved first before any discussions can take place on possible troop deployment for a potential reassurance force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, French President Emmanuel Macron said the force would have French, British and Turkish soldiers. Ankara, which has maintained cordial ties with both Moscow and Kyiv during the war, has said it was open to discussing such a deployment but only if its modalities were set.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 09:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela revokes flight rights for six airlines amid escalating US tensions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/venezuela-revokes-flight-rights-six-airlines-amid-escalating-us-tensions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/venezuela-revokes-flight-rights-six-airlines-amid-escalating-us-tensions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Venezuela has revoked operating rights for six major international airlines after they suspended flights to the country following a warning from the U.S. Federal Aviation Administration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Venezuela's civil aviation authority revoked permits for Iberia, TAP, Avianca, Latam Colombia, Turkish Airlines and Gol, with Caracas saying in a statement that the carriers had "joined actions of state terrorism promoted by the United States" by "unilaterally" halting commercial flights.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia lists Iran's Islamic Revolutionary Guard as state sponsor of terrorism</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-lists-irans-islamic-revolutionary-guard-state-sponsor-terrorism</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-lists-irans-islamic-revolutionary-guard-state-sponsor-terrorism</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY (Reuters) -Australia has listed Iran's Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps as a state sponsor of terrorism, Foreign Minister Penny Wong said on Thursday, following an intelligence assessment that it had orchestrated attacks against Australia's Jewish Community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Australia in August accused Iran of directing two antisemitic arson attacks in the cities of Sydney and Melbourne and gave Tehran's ambassador seven days to leave the country on Tuesday, its first such expulsion since World War Two.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Renju Jose in Sydney; Editing by Christian Schmollinger)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 03:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US must re-examine Afghan immigrants who came when Biden was president</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-must-re-examine-afghan-immigrants-who-came-when-biden-was-president</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-us-must-re-examine-afghan-immigrants-who-came-when-biden-was-president</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -President Donald Trump on Wednesday called for his government to re-examine Afghan immigrants who entered the United States during the former President Joe Biden's administration.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The president called the shooting of two National Guard members in Washington "an act of terror," saying the suspect came from Afghanistan in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"This heinous assault was an act of evil, an act of hatred and an act of terror," Trump said in pre-taped remarks from Florida, where he is spending the Thanksgiving holiday. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 03:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Schools but no books: Gaza's children return to makeshift classrooms</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/schools-no-books-gazas-children-return-makeshift-classrooms</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/schools-no-books-gazas-children-return-makeshift-classrooms</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;With no backpack, books or uniform, 11-year-old Layan Haji navigates the ruins of Gaza City and heads to a makeshift classroom after two years of war halted her education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the school is not what she is used to. Painted walls and students' artwork no longer adorn the walls and hallways -- instead, tents set up in a battered building serve as their temporary classrooms. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I walk for half an hour at least. The streets are devastated, full of ruins... It is difficult and sad," Haji said, wearing a torn shirt and patched trousers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 03:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope lands in Turkey to meet Erdogan on first overseas trip</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-lands-turkey-meet-erdogan-first-overseas-trip</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-lands-turkey-meet-erdogan-first-overseas-trip</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo XIV arrived in Turkey on Thursday for a four-day visit where he will hold talks with President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and meet Christian leaders on the first overseas trip of his papacy. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trip, which includes a second leg to Lebanon, begins in the Turkish capital Ankara, where the first American pope landed shortly after midday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I have very much been looking forward to this trip because of what it means for Christians, but it is also a great message to the whole world," he told reporters travelling with him on his plane, describing it as a "historic moment". &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 02:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemeni drugs seizure a 'landmark moment', say WADA</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/yemeni-drugs-seizure-landmark-moment-say-wada</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/yemeni-drugs-seizure-landmark-moment-say-wada</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The seizure of a large amount of performance-enhancing drugs in a raid by Yemeni law enforcement agents is "a landmark moment", the head of investigations for the World Anti-Doping Agency (WADA) has told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gunter Younger said the operation, which netted 447kg of both narcotics and performance-enhancing substances, mainly amphetamines, showed authorities were increasingly tracking the cross-border trade of prohibited substances.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 02:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo heading to Turkey for closely watched first overseas trip</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-heading-turkey-closely-watched-first-overseas-trip</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-heading-turkey-closely-watched-first-overseas-trip</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VATICAN CITY (Reuters) -Pope Leo begins his first trip outside Italy as Catholic leader on Thursday with a visit to Turkey, where he is expected to make appeals for peace in the Middle East and urge unity among long-divided Christian churches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first U.S. pope chose mainly Muslim Turkey as his first overseas destination to mark the 1,700th anniversary of a landmark early Church council there that produced the Nicene Creed, still used by most of the world's Christians today.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 01:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu accused of dodging blame as Israel confronts Oct 7 failures</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-accused-dodging-blame-israel-confronts-oct-7-failures</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-accused-dodging-blame-israel-confronts-oct-7-failures</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tension is escalating between Israel's political and military top brass over accountability for the failures behind the October 7, 2023 Hamas attack, with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu accused of sidestepping blame.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weekly protests against Netanyahu's leadership of the subsequent two-year war in Gaza and demanding the return of hostages became emblematic of the anger boiling within parts of Israeli society over how the attack and its fallout have been handled.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 20:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says to carry out French prisoner 'exchange' in 'next two months'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-says-carry-out-french-prisoner-exchange-next-two-months</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-says-carry-out-french-prisoner-exchange-next-two-months</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran will allow two French citizens held by the Islamic republic for over three years to return home in "exchange" for France freeing an Iranian citizen "in the next two months", Tehran's foreign minister said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with TV channel France 24 after talks in Paris with his French counterpart Jean-Noel Barrot, Abbas Araghchi said "an exchange was negotiated between us and France".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 18:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli army launches new operation in West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-army-launches-new-operation-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-army-launches-new-operation-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's military on Wednesday launched a new operation against Palestinian armed groups in the occupied West Bank, where a local governor told AFP that Israeli forces had raided several towns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military, police and internal security service said in a joint statement that they had begun "a broad counter-terrorism operation" in the north of the Palestinian territory after they received intelligence about "attempts to establish terrorist strongholds".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 18:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo lands in Turkey on first foreign visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-lands-turkey-first-foreign-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-lands-turkey-first-foreign-visit</guid><description>On his inaugural foreign visit to Turkey, Pope Leo will begin his tour with a meeting with the Turkish president.</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 17:18:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New finds in Turkey's southeast add to picture of Neolithic age</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-finds-turkeys-southeast-add-picture-neolithic-age</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-finds-turkeys-southeast-add-picture-neolithic-age</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ceyda Caglayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SANLIURFA, Turkey (Reuters) -Turkey unveiled dozens of new finds at a major archaeological site in southeast Turkey on Wednesday, giving fresh insight into an area seen as showing humanity's transition from hunter-gatherers to settled societies more than 11,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a plateau overlooking the fertile plains of what is often called the "cradle of civilisation", the UNESCO World Heritage Site of Gobeklitepe and nearby Karahantepe are transforming archaeologists' understanding of prehistoric times.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 16:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanese living abroad seek hope as they return for pope visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanese-living-abroad-seek-hope-they-return-pope-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanese-living-abroad-seek-hope-they-return-pope-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rachelle Mazraani is travelling from Sydney to Beirut for Pope Leo XIV's visit this week, one of many Lebanese at home and abroad who hope the trip will revive their struggling country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After visiting Turkey, Leo is to arrive in Lebanon on Sunday for a three-day trip that includes an open-air mass at Beirut's waterfront that organisers expect to draw 120,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He will also hold a special meeting with those aged 16 to 35 in Bkerke, north of Beirut, where the patriarchate of Lebanon's Maronite Church is located.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 16:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon’s citizenship offer for FIFA head sparks debate over equal rights</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanons-citizenship-offer-fifa-head-sparks-debate-over-equal-rights</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanons-citizenship-offer-fifa-head-sparks-debate-over-equal-rights</guid><description>Lebanon’s president has announced he will grant citizenship to FIFA President Gianni Infantino, sparking a wave of outrage.</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 15:21:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon’s citizenship offer for FIFA head sparks debate over equal rights</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanons-citizenship-offer-fifa-head-sparks-debate-over-equal-rights</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanons-citizenship-offer-fifa-head-sparks-debate-over-equal-rights</guid><description>Lebanon’s president has announced he will grant citizenship to FIFA President Gianni Infantino, sparking a wave of outrage.</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 15:21:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon’s citizenship offer for FIFA head sparks debate over equal rights</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanons-citizenship-offer-fifa-head-sparks-debate-over-equal-rights</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanons-citizenship-offer-fifa-head-sparks-debate-over-equal-rights</guid><description>Lebanon’s president has announced he will grant citizenship to FIFA President Gianni Infantino, sparking a wave of outrage.</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 15:21:15 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>