<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>EU warns Yemen developments risk Gulf stability</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-warns-yemen-developments-risk-gulf-stability</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-warns-yemen-developments-risk-gulf-stability</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 31 (Reuters) - The European Union said on Wednesday that recent developments in the Yemeni provinces of Hadramout and Al Mahra threaten to bring new risks to the Gulf region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The EU calls for de-escalation and avoiding steps that further threaten stability of Yemen and the region," an EU spokesperson said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The EU reiterates its strong commitment to the unity, sovereignty, independence and territorial integrity of Yemen, as well as its support for the Presidential Leadership Council and the Government of Yemen," the spokesperson added.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 21:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US grants temporary licence to Russian-controlled Serbian oil firm NIS: Serbian minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-grants-temporary-licence-russian-controlled-serbian-oil-firm-nis-serbian</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-grants-temporary-licence-russian-controlled-serbian-oil-firm-nis-serbian</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The United States has granted a temporary licence to NIS, a majority-Russian owned Serbian oil company caught up in US sanctions against Moscow's invasion of Ukraine, a Serbian minister said on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washington's sanctions on the Petroleum Industry of Serbia (NIS), part of its crackdown on Russia's energy sector, forced Serbia's sole oil refinery, which supplies around 80 percent of the Serbian market, to shut down in early December. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 19:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel begins demolishing 25 buildings in West Bank camp</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-begins-demolishing-25-buildings-west-bank-camp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-begins-demolishing-25-buildings-west-bank-camp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli bulldozers began demolishing 25 buildings housing Palestinians in a refugee camp on Wednesday, in what the military said was an effort to root out armed groups in northern areas of the occupied West Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The buildings, home to some 100 families, are in the Nur Shams camp, a frequent site of clashes between Palestinian militants and Israeli forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israeli military bulldozers and cranes tore through the structures early Wednesday, sending thick plumes of dust into the air, an AFP journalist reported. Many residents watched from a distance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 19:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-UAE foreign policy in spotlight after Yemen escalation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/factbox-uae-foreign-policy-spotlight-after-yemen-escalation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/factbox-uae-foreign-policy-spotlight-after-yemen-escalation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Yousef Saba&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 31 - The United Arab Emirates has pursued an assertive foreign policy and carved its own sphere of influence across the Middle East and Africa, a strategy in the spotlight after a rare military escalation with Saudi Arabia in Yemen this week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abu Dhabi has used alliances with states or proxies, military intervention and financial support mainly to counter what it views as the destabilising threat of political Islam, specifically from groups linked to the Muslim Brotherhood.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 14:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Oman says foreign minister met Saudi counterpart to discuss Yemen</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/oman-says-foreign-minister-met-saudi-counterpart-discuss-yemen</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/oman-says-foreign-minister-met-saudi-counterpart-discuss-yemen</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 31 (Reuters) - Oman's foreign minister met his Saudi counterpart in Riyadh on Wednesday to discuss finding a political solution to the crisis in Yemen, Oman's Foreign Ministry said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting came a day after a Saudi-led strike on Yemen's southern port of Mukalla, which raised tensions between Riyadh and the United Arab Emirates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, a Saudi-led coalition has clashed with UAE-backed southern separatists in Yemen. The UAE has said it is ending its remaining military mission there, highlighting a widening rift between the Gulf allies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 14:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel to ban 37 aid groups operating in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-ban-37-aid-groups-operating-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-ban-37-aid-groups-operating-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel plans to ban 37 aid organisations from operating in Gaza from Thursday unless they hand over detailed information on their Palestinian staff, despite mounting criticism from the United Nations and the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several NGOs have told AFP the new rules will have a major impact on food and medical shipments to Gaza, and humanitarian groups warn there is already not enough aid to cover the devastated territory's needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel's deadline for NGOs to provide the details expires at midnight on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 13:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Filmmaker Panahi says Iran protests 'to move history forward'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/filmmaker-panahi-says-iran-protests-move-history-forward</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/filmmaker-panahi-says-iran-protests-move-history-forward</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Award-winning Iranian filmmaker Jafar Panahi said Wednesday that protests which have gripped his country in recent days aimed "to move history forward".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Shared pain has now become a cry in the street," said the director who won the Cannes Film festival's top prize this year and has been nominated for an Oscar for his film "It Was Just an Accident".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"When there is nothing left to lose, fear falls away. Voices unite, the silence is broken, and there is no way back," he said on Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 13:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hoping for better year ahead, Gazans bid farewell to 'nightmare' of 2025</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hoping-better-year-ahead-gazans-bid-farewell-nightmare-2025</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hoping-better-year-ahead-gazans-bid-farewell-nightmare-2025</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As 2025 draws to a close, Palestinians in Gaza are marking the new year not with celebration, but with exhaustion, grief and a fragile hope that their "endless nightmare" might finally end.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For residents of the battered territory, daily life is a struggle for survival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Much of Gaza's infrastructure lies in ruins, electricity remains scarce and hundreds of thousands of people live in makeshift tents after being repeatedly displaced by the two years of fighting that began with Hamas's attack on Israel in October 2023.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 11:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran government building attacked as top prosecutor responds to protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-government-building-attacked-top-prosecutor-responds-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-government-building-attacked-top-prosecutor-responds-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A government building in southern Iran was attacked on Wednesday, authorities said, as the country's top prosecutor warned of a "decisive response" to any attempt to create instability after days of economic protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spontaneous protests, driven by dissatisfaction at Iran's economic stagnation, began on Sunday in Tehran's largest mobile phone market, where shopkeepers shuttered their businesses, and have since drawn in students across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 10:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World welcomes 2026 with fireworks after year of Trump and turmoil</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/world-welcomes-2026-fireworks-after-year-trump-and-turmoil</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/world-welcomes-2026-fireworks-after-year-trump-and-turmoil</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Revellers around the world toasted the start of 2026, bidding farewell on Wednesday to a volatile year when temperatures soared, US President Donald Trump upended global trade, and the brutal conflict in Ukraine raged on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While a fragile truce took hold in devastated Gaza, violence in Sudan continued unabated. A new American pope was installed at the Vatican, the world lost pioneering zoologist Jane Goodall, and Labubu dolls sparked a worldwide frenzy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 20:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Yemen strike shows depth of distrust between Saudi Arabia and UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/analysis-yemen-strike-shows-depth-distrust-between-saudi-arabia-and-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/analysis-yemen-strike-shows-depth-distrust-between-saudi-arabia-and-uae</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maha El Dahan and Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 30 (Reuters) - The withdrawal of Emirati forces from Yemen following a Saudi airstrike may help defuse a confrontation between the UAE and Saudi Arabia, but the incident has exposed simmering distrust between two Gulf oil powers with long-running differences.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The airstrike by a Saudi-led coalition early on Tuesday on the southern Yemeni port of Mukalla was followed by calls on all UAE forces to leave Yemen, and a statement from Riyadh that its national security was a red line.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 19:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran rocked with new protests as economic anger meets mounting foreign pressure</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</guid><description>The latest wave of protests is moving beyond markets and into universities, as Tehran trades warnings with Washington and Israel.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 18:52:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran rocked with new protests as economic anger meets mounting foreign pressure</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</guid><description>The latest wave of protests is moving beyond markets and into universities, as Tehran trades warnings with Washington and Israel.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 18:52:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran rocked with new protests as economic anger meets mounting foreign pressure</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</guid><description>The latest wave of protests is moving beyond markets and into universities, as Tehran trades warnings with Washington and Israel.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 18:52:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran rocked with new protests as economic anger meets mounting foreign pressure</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-rocked-new-protests-economic-anger-meets-mounting-foreign-pressure</guid><description>The latest wave of protests is moving beyond markets and into universities, as Tehran trades warnings with Washington and Israel.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 18:52:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump-Erdogan ties pay off for Turkey in 2025 as Ankara pushes for F-35s</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/trump-erdogan-ties-pay-turkey-2025-ankara-pushes-f-35s</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/trump-erdogan-ties-pay-turkey-2025-ankara-pushes-f-35s</guid><description>Leader-level diplomacy between Ankara and Washington produced selective gains but failed to break the deadlock over defense sanctions imposed for Turkey’s S-400 purchase.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 17:39:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What's next for Yemen as UAE withdraws, rift with Saudi Arabia grows?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</guid><description>The escalating conflict in Yemen poses challenges to both the Saudi-backed government and the UAE’s position in the country, but may benefit the Houthis.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 17:17:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What's next for Yemen as UAE withdraws, rift with Saudi Arabia grows?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</guid><description>The escalating conflict in Yemen poses challenges to both the Saudi-backed government and the UAE’s position in the country, but may benefit the Houthis.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 17:17:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What's next for Yemen as UAE withdraws, rift with Saudi Arabia grows?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</guid><description>The escalating conflict in Yemen poses challenges to both the Saudi-backed government and the UAE’s position in the country, but may benefit the Houthis.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 17:17:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What's next for Yemen as UAE withdraws, rift with Saudi Arabia grows?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/whats-next-yemen-uae-withdraws-rift-saudi-arabia-grows</guid><description>The escalating conflict in Yemen poses challenges to both the Saudi-backed government and the UAE’s position in the country, but may benefit the Houthis.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 17:17:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>