<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israeli president to honour Bondi Beach attack victims on Australia visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-president-honour-bondi-beach-attack-victims-australia-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-president-honour-bondi-beach-attack-victims-australia-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's President Isaac Herzog starts a tightly secured visit to Australia on Monday to honour the victims of an antisemitic gun attack on Sydney's Bondi Beach that killed 15 people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the head of state seeks to console the Jewish Australian community, his four-day trip has also sparked calls for pro-Palestinian protests in Sydney's streets, where the authorities promised a large police presence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 19:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's Nobel winner Narges Mohammadi faces a new prison term of more than seven years</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-nobel-winner-narges-mohammadi-faces-new-prison-term-more-seven-years</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-nobel-winner-narges-mohammadi-faces-new-prison-term-more-seven-years</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Iranian activist and Nobel Peace Prize winner Narges Mohammadi, who has been imprisoned repeatedly in her three-decade campaign for women's rights, was sentenced to a new prison term of 7-1/2 years, a group supporting her said on Sunday.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mohammadi, 53, was on a week-long hunger strike that ended on Sunday, the Narges Foundation said in a statement. It said Mohammadi told her lawyer, Mostafa Nili, in a phone call on Sunday from prison that she had received her sentence on Saturday. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel to take more West Bank powers and relax settler land buys, media say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-take-more-west-bank-powers-and-relax-settler-land-buys-media-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-take-more-west-bank-powers-and-relax-settler-land-buys-media-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Israel's security cabinet approved a series of steps on Sunday that would make it easier for settlers in the occupied West Bank to buy land while granting Israeli authorities more enforcement powers over Palestinians, Israeli media reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The West Bank is among the territories that the Palestinians seek for a future independent state. Much of it is under Israeli military control, with limited Palestinian self-rule in some areas run by the Western-backed Palestinian Authority (PA).  &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 16:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia orders 20 high-speed trains from Spain's Talgo</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/saudi-arabia-orders-20-high-speed-trains-spains-talgo</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/saudi-arabia-orders-20-high-speed-trains-spains-talgo</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MADRID, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia has ordered 20 new high-speed trains from Spain's Talgo SA, the company and Spain's transport minister said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Talgo said the deal adds 1.33 billion euros ($1.57 billion) to its order backlog, bringing it to a total of nearly 6 billion euros, a record. The contract also covers maintenance for the trains.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 15:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Morocco flood evacuees still shaken, waiting to return home</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/morocco-flood-evacuees-still-shaken-waiting-return-home</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/morocco-flood-evacuees-still-shaken-waiting-return-home</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It was through a call from her local mosque's loudspeakers that Kasia El Selami learnt it was time to flee as floodwaters rose in her Moroccan village of Ouled Ameur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Selami is among more than 150,000 people to have been evacuated over the past week as heavy rainfall battered provinces in Morocco's north.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We felt immense fear... especially for our children", said the 67-year-old while hanging a blanket by the tent in which she now lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 15:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran insists on right to enrichment, ready for confidence-building</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-insists-right-enrichment-ready-confidence-building</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-insists-right-enrichment-ready-confidence-building</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Recognition of Iran's right to enrich uranium is key for nuclear talks with the U.S. to succeed, Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;American and Iranian diplomats held indirect talks in Oman on Friday, aimed at reviving diplomacy amid a U.S. naval buildup near Iran and Tehran's vows of a harsh response if attacked. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Zero enrichment can never be accepted by us. Hence, we need to focus on discussions that accept enrichment inside Iran while building trust that enrichment is and will stay for peaceful purposes," Araqchi said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 10:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran defies US threats to insist on right to enrich uranium</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-defies-us-threats-insist-right-enrich-uranium</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-defies-us-threats-insist-right-enrich-uranium</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araghchi on Sunday ruled out Tehran ever giving up uranium enrichment in its negotiations with Washington, insisting it will not be intimidated by the threat of war with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Araghchi told a forum in Tehran attended by AFP that Iran had little trust in Washington and doubted that the US side was taking renewed negotiations seriously. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He later said Iran was consulting with its "strategic partners" China and Russia about the talks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 10:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia says man suspected of shooting top general has been detained in Dubai</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-says-man-suspected-shooting-top-general-has-been-detained-dubai</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-says-man-suspected-shooting-top-general-has-been-detained-dubai</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Russia's Federal Security Service (FSB) said on Sunday that the man suspected of shooting top Russian military intelligence officer Vladimir Alexeyev in Moscow has been detained in Dubai and handed over to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant General Vladimir Alexeyev, deputy head of the GRU, Russia's military intelligence arm, was shot several times in anapartment block in Moscow on Friday, investigators said. He underwent surgery after the shooting, Russian media said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 08:01:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Neglected killer: kala-azar disease surges in Kenya</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/neglected-killer-kala-azar-disease-surges-kenya</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/neglected-killer-kala-azar-disease-surges-kenya</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For nearly a year, repeated misdiagnoses of the deadly kala-azar disease left 60-year-old Harada Hussein Abdirahman's health deteriorating, as an outbreak in Kenya's arid regions claimed a record number of lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kala-azar is spread by sandflies and is one of the most dangerous neglected tropical diseases, with a fatality rate of 95 percent if untreated, causing fever, weight loss, and enlargement of the spleen and liver.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cases of kala-azar, also known as visceral leishmaniasis, have spiked in Kenya, from 1,575 in 2024 to 3,577 in 2025, according to the health ministry.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 02:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu expected to meet Trump in US on Wednesday and discuss Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-expected-meet-trump-us-wednesday-and-discuss-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-expected-meet-trump-us-wednesday-and-discuss-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 7 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu is expected to meet U.S. President Donald Trump on Wednesday in Washington, where they will discuss negotiations with Iran, Netanyahu's office said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian and U.S. officials held indirect nuclear talks in the Omani capital Muscat on Friday. Both sides said more talks were expected to be held again soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demonstrators in Berlin call for fall of Iran's Islamic republic</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/demonstrators-berlin-call-fall-irans-islamic-republic</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/demonstrators-berlin-call-fall-irans-islamic-republic</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Several thousand demonstrators rallied in Berlin on Saturday calling for an end to Iran's clerical-led government and its bloody repression of protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police said 10,000 people had attended one protest at the city's Brandenburg Gate organised by the MEK, an exiled opposition group considered "terrorist" by Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another demonstration, this one organised by supporters of Reza Pahlavi, the US-based son of the last shah of Iran, attracted 1,600 people, said police. They marched along a major avenue, carrying shah-era Iranian flags as well as US, German and Israeli ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 18:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Over 2,200 IS detainees transferred to Iraq from Syria: Iraqi official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/over-2200-detainees-transferred-iraq-syria-iraqi-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/over-2200-detainees-transferred-iraq-syria-iraqi-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iraq has so far received 2,225 Islamic State group detainees, whom the US military began transferring from Syria last month, an Iraqi official told AFP on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They are among up to 7,000 IS detainees whose transfer from Syria to Iraq the US Central Command (CENTCOM) announced last month, in a move it said was aimed at "ensuring that the terrorists remain in secure detention facilities".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, they had been held in prisons and camps administered by the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF) in northeast Syria.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 16:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands protest in Berlin in solidarity with Iranian uprisings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/thousands-protest-berlin-solidarity-iranian-uprisings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/thousands-protest-berlin-solidarity-iranian-uprisings</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maria Martinez&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Feb 7 (Reuters) - Thousands of people protested in Berlin on Saturday in support of Iranians' nationwide uprising, coinciding with the anniversary of Iran's 1979 anti-monarchy revolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rally follows nationwide protests in Iran, which started in December over economic hardships and quickly turned political and were repressed in the most violent crackdown since the 1979 Islamic Revolution. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around 8,000 were gathered at Berlin's Brandenburg Gate at 1300 GMT, the Berlin police told Reuters, adding that 20,000 had registered to attend. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 15:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Algeria begins to cancel air services agreement with UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/algeria-begins-cancel-air-services-agreement-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/algeria-begins-cancel-air-services-agreement-uae</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 7 (Reuters) - Algeria has begun the process of cancelling its air services agreement with the United Arab Emirates, signed in Abu Dhabi in May 2013, state media said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It gave no immediate reason for the move, but Algerian media outlets have strongly criticised the UAE in recent months, accusing it of attempting to sow regional discord.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 15:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>If US attacks, Iran says it will strike US bases in the region</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/if-us-attacks-iran-says-it-will-strike-us-bases-region</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/if-us-attacks-iran-says-it-will-strike-us-bases-region</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Feb 7 (Reuters) - Iran will strike U.S. bases in the Middle East if it is attacked by U.S. forces that have massed in the region, its foreign minister said on Saturday, insisting that this should not be seen as an attack on the countries hosting them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi spoke to Qatari Al Jazeera TV a day after Tehran and Washington pledged to continue indirect nuclear talks following what both sides described as positive discussions on Friday in Oman.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 12:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran FM looks to more nuclear talks, but warns US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-fm-looks-more-nuclear-talks-warns-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-fm-looks-more-nuclear-talks-warns-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araghchi said on Saturday he hoped talks with the United States would resume soon, while reiterating Tehran's red lines and warning against any American attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to excerpts published on his official Telegram channel during an interview with the Al Jazeera network, Araghchi said that Iran's missile programme was "never negotiable" in Friday's talks in Oman.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu is expected to raise the ballistic missiles programme in a meeting with US President Donald Trump in Washington next week.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 12:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US plans meeting for Gaza 'Board of Peace' in Washington on Feb 19, Axios reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-plans-meeting-gaza-board-peace-washington-feb-19-axios-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-plans-meeting-gaza-board-peace-washington-feb-19-axios-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 6 (Reuters) - The White House is planning the first leaders meeting for President Donald Trump's so-called "Board of Peace" in relation to Gaza on February 19, Axios reported on Friday, citing a U.S. official and diplomats from four countries that are on the board.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The plans for the meeting, which would also be a fundraising conference for Gaza reconstruction, are in early stages and could still change, Axios reported. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 04:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump signs order threatening tariffs on nations doing business with Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-signs-order-threatening-tariffs-nations-doing-business-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-signs-order-threatening-tariffs-nations-doing-business-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 6 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump signed an executive order on Friday that may impose a 25% tariff on countries that do business with Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The order comes as tensions between Iran and U.S. continue to simmer even as the two countries engaged in talks this week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Jasper Ward and Christian Martinez in Washington; editing by Michelle Nichols and Caitlin Webber)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 22:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France to rally aid for Lebanon as it warns truce gains remain fragile</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-rally-aid-lebanon-it-warns-truce-gains-remain-fragile</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-rally-aid-lebanon-it-warns-truce-gains-remain-fragile</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Feras Dalatey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feb 6 (Reuters) - France said on Friday that Lebanon's recovery remains precarious despite positive signs following a ceasefire and government transition, and it stood ready to support the country's reconstruction if it continues with reforms.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 22:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-Seven key Trump-Iran moments as tensions run high</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/factbox-seven-key-trump-iran-moments-tensions-run-high</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/factbox-seven-key-trump-iran-moments-tensions-run-high</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Costas Pitas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feb 6 (Reuters) - The United States and Iran on Friday were trying to reach a diplomatic solution to disputes between the two nations that have led to heightened tensions in the Middle East, and warnings from President Donald Trump that military options are at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Washington wants talks to include the nuclear program, ballistic missiles, support for armed groups and treatment of the Iranian people, Tehran has insisted on focusing exclusively on its disputed nuclear program and is seeking recognition of its right to enrich uranium.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 22:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>