<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan will soon decide whether to join Trump's Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-will-soon-decide-whether-join-trumps-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-will-soon-decide-whether-join-trumps-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan will soon decide whether to join U.S. President Donald Trump's Board of Peace initiative after having received an invitation, Turkey's foreign minister said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have received an invitation. Our President is being invited as a founding member, on behalf of Turkey (and) will likely make his decision on this matter very soon," Hakan Fidan said in a televised interview with state media.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Tuvan Gumrukcu; Editing by Jonathan Spicer)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US-led coalition negotiating Al-Hol camp handover, Syrian sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-led-coalition-negotiating-al-hol-camp-handover-syrian-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-led-coalition-negotiating-al-hol-camp-handover-syrian-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 20 (Reuters) - The U.S.-led coalition against the Islamic State was negotiating a handover of the Al-Hol camp, which houses IS-linked civilians, to Syrian authorities, three Syrian sources familiar with the matter said on Tuesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the sources, a Syrian official, said the talks were focused on a smooth transition of control from Kurdish security forces who had been holding the camp, to avoid any security risks or detainees fleeing. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Suleiman Al-Khalidi, Mahmoud Hasano and Khalil Ashawi; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US invited Israel to join board of peace, Israeli minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-invited-israel-join-board-peace-israeli-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-invited-israel-join-board-peace-israeli-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 20 (Reuters) - Israel foreign minister Gideon Saar said on Tuesday that Israel was invited by the United States to join the board of peace initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Omri Taasan; Editing by Andrew Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greece will cooperate with Israel on anti-drone systems, cybersecurity, Greek minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-will-cooperate-israel-anti-drone-systems-cybersecurity-greek-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-will-cooperate-israel-anti-drone-systems-cybersecurity-greek-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Greece will cooperate with Israel on anti-drone systems and cybersecurity, Greek Defence Minister Nikos Dendias said on Tuesday after meeting his Israeli counterpart in Athens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With strong economic and diplomatic ties, Greece and Israel operate an air training center on Greek territory and have held joint military drills in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Elefterios Papadimas; Writing by Angeliki Koutantou; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel orders Gaza families to move in first forced evacuation since ceasefire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-orders-gaza-families-move-first-forced-evacuation-ceasefire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-orders-gaza-families-move-first-forced-evacuation-ceasefire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Israeli forces have ordered dozens of Palestinian families in the southern Gaza Strip to leave their homes in the first forced evacuation since October's ceasefire, as residents and Hamas said on Tuesday the military was expanding the area under its control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Residents of Bani Suhaila, east of Khan Younis, said the leaflets were dropped on Monday on families living in tent encampments in the Al-Reqeb neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Talks between Damascus, Kurdish-led forces 'collapse': Kurdish official to AFP</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/talks-between-damascus-kurdish-led-forces-collapse-kurdish-official-afp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/talks-between-damascus-kurdish-led-forces-collapse-kurdish-official-afp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Negotiations have collapsed between the Syrian president and the chief of the country's Kurdish-led forces, a Kurdish official told AFP, as the army deployed reinforcements to flashpoint areas in the north.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed al-Sharaa and Mazloum Abdi, who heads the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF), were meeting to discuss a ceasefire agreement that included integrating the Kurds' administration into the state.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN rights council to hold emergency session on Iran, document shows</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-council-hold-emergency-session-iran-document-shows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-council-hold-emergency-session-iran-document-shows</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin and Emma Farge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 20 (Reuters) - The U.N. Human Rights Council will hold an emergency session on Iran in the coming days, with proponents aiming to discuss "alarming violence" used against protesters, a document showed on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An Iranian official said authorities have verified at least 5,000 deaths in the protests which are the biggest demonstrations since 2022, prompting U.N. rights chief Volker Turk to condemn the violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel begins demolitions at UNRWA headquarters in east Jerusalem</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-begins-demolitions-unrwa-headquarters-east-jerusalem</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-begins-demolitions-unrwa-headquarters-east-jerusalem</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli bulldozers began demolitions at the headquarters of the UN agency for Palestinian refugees in east Jerusalem on Tuesday, in what the organisation called an "unprecedented attack".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNRWA spokesman Jonathan Fowler said in a statement to AFP that Israeli forces "stormed into" the compound shortly after 7am (0500 GMT) and ousted security guards from the site, before bulldozers entered and began demolishing buildings.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's Sisi to meet Trump on the sidelines of Davos, presidency says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-sisi-meet-trump-sidelines-davos-presidency-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-sisi-meet-trump-sidelines-davos-presidency-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Egypt's President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi will meet U.S President Donald Trump on the sidelines of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Egypt's presidency said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be the first meeting between the two leaders since the U.S announced it was launching the second phase of its plan to end the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sisi and Trump met in the Red Sea resort of Sharm el-Sheikh in October during a summit convened by Egypt to sign a ceasefire deal aimed at ending the war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel demolishes buildings in UN Palestinian agency's East Jerusalem compound</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-demolishes-buildings-un-palestinian-agencys-east-jerusalem-compound</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-demolishes-buildings-un-palestinian-agencys-east-jerusalem-compound</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Pesha Magid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Israel demolished structures inside the U.N. Palestinian refugee agency's East Jerusalem compound on Tuesday after seizing the site last year, in an act condemned by the agency as a violation of international law. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Surrounded by Israeli forces, bulldozers razed several large buildings and other smaller structures inside the United Nations Relief and Works Agency's compound, where dozens of agency staff once worked. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump threatens 200% tariffs on French wines to get Macron on Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-threatens-200-tariffs-french-wines-get-macron-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-threatens-200-tariffs-french-wines-get-macron-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nandita Bose and Bo Erickson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/PARIS, Jan 20 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump threatened to hit French wines and champagnes with 200% tariffs in an apparent effort to cajole French President Emmanuel Macron into joining his Board of Peace initiative aimed at resolving global conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump's initiative, which would start by addressing Gaza and then expand to deal with other conflicts, raises questions about the role of the United Nations and a source close to Macron said the French president intended to decline the invitation to join.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey warning as PKK vows won't abandon Syria's Kurds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-warning-pkk-vows-wont-abandon-syrias-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-warning-pkk-vows-wont-abandon-syrias-kurds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turkey warned Tuesday it would not tolerate "provocations" as Kurds in the country prepared to protest over a military offensive targeting Kurds in Syria that has also angered the militant PKK. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syrian forces began an offensive nearly two weeks ago, pushing the Kurdish-led SDF forces out of Aleppo. Over the weekend,they advanced deep into the northeastern area held by Kurdish forces for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Pakistan's 'combat tested' jets boost weapons sales</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-pakistans-combat-tested-jets-boost-weapons-sales</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-pakistans-combat-tested-jets-boost-weapons-sales</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saad Sayeed and Ariba Shahid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Pakistan's defence manufacturing industry is running red hot since its jets, drones and missiles earned the coveted 'combat tested' tag in a conflict with India last year, attracting a slew of interested buyers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Islamabad has held talks with 13 countries, six to eight of which are in an advanced stage, for deals involving JF-17 jets made jointly with China as well as training aircraft, drones, and weapons systems, said three Pakistani sources who have knowledge of defence sales.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Canada's Carney aims to lead new global trading order less reliant on US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-canadas-carney-aims-lead-new-global-trading-order-less-reliant-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-canadas-carney-aims-lead-new-global-trading-order-less-reliant-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Promit Mukherjee, Andrew Mills and Federico Maccioni&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OTTAWA/DOHA/DUBAI, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney is trying to foster a new global trading order by working more closely with China and inking smaller trade deals, but faces constraints from Canada's still overwhelming economic dependency on the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump shares messages from France's Macron offering G7 meeting after Davos</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-shares-messages-frances-macron-offering-g7-meeting-after-davos</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-shares-messages-frances-macron-offering-g7-meeting-after-davos</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 20 (Reuters) - French President Emmanuel Macron told U.S President Donald Trump that he could set up a meeting after Davos in Paris on Thursday afternoon, according to screenshots of messages sent by Macron to Trump that were posted by the U.S. president on Truth Social. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Macron also invited Trump to have dinner in Paris on Thursday, according to the screenshots. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump's reply, if any, was not part of the screenshot. The White House did not respond to a request for comment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Chandni Shah in Bengaluru; Editing by Christian Schmollinger)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ASEAN will not certify Myanmar election or send observers, Malaysia says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/asean-will-not-certify-myanmar-election-or-send-observers-malaysia-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/asean-will-not-certify-myanmar-election-or-send-observers-malaysia-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KUALA LUMPUR, Jan 20 (Reuters) - The 11-member Association of Southeast Asian Nations will not send observers to army-ruled Myanmar's ongoing three-stage election and will therefore not endorse the poll, Malaysia's foreign minister said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Myanmar has been ravaged by conflict since the military staged a coup against a civilian government in 2021. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Content to die': Afghanistan's hunger crisis worsened by winter, aid cuts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/content-die-afghanistans-hunger-crisis-worsened-winter-aid-cuts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/content-die-afghanistans-hunger-crisis-worsened-winter-aid-cuts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KABUL, Jan 20 (Reuters) - In the dull glow of a single bulb lighting their tent on the outskirts of Kabul, Samiullah and his wife Bibi Rehana sit down to dry bread and tea, their only meal of the day, accompanied by their five children and three-month-old grandchild.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have reached a point where we are content with death," said 55-year-old Samiullah, whose family, including two older sons aged 18 and 20 and their wives, is among the millions deported by neighbouring Iran and Pakistan in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria says 120 Islamic State detainees escaped prison; Kurdish website said 1,500 escaped</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-says-120-islamic-state-detainees-escaped-prison-kurdish-website-said-1500</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-says-120-islamic-state-detainees-escaped-prison-kurdish-website-said-1500</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Syria's Interior Ministry said on Tuesday that about 120 Islamic State detainees escaped from Shaddadi prison, after the Kurdish website Rudaw reported that a spokesperson for the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, Farhad Shami, said around 1,500 Islamic State members had escaped.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria offensive leaves Turkey's Kurds on edge</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-offensive-leaves-turkeys-kurds-edge</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-offensive-leaves-turkeys-kurds-edge</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turkey's Kurds are hoping that Ankara's bid to end the decades-long PKK conflict won't be hurt by Damascus' lightning offensive against Kurdish fighters in northern Syria that was backed by Turkey. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A close ally of the new post Bashar al-Assad Syrian leadership, Ankara has been engaged in dialogue with the jailed founder of the Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK) Abdullah Ocalan whose fighters fought a four-decade insurgency that cost some 50,000 lives. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 21:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump demands end to clashes with Kurds in call with Syria's Sharaa</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-demands-end-clashes-kurds-call-syrias-sharaa</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-demands-end-clashes-kurds-call-syrias-sharaa</guid><description>US President Donald Trump called Syria’s interim president, Ahmed al-Sharaa, and secured a pledge from the leader to not enter al-Hasakeh as Syrian forces clashed with the Kurdish-led SDF.</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 21:05:06 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>