<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Iran's traders, frustrated by economic losses, turn against clerics</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-traders-frustrated-economic-losses-turn-against-clerics</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-traders-frustrated-economic-losses-turn-against-clerics</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 12 (Reuters) - Iran's bazaar merchants, the trader class who were the financial backbone of the 1979 Islamic Revolution, have turned against the clerics they helped bring to power, fuelling unrest over an economy that has morphed into full-blown anti-government protests.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Reza Pahlavi: Iran's ex-crown prince dreaming of homecoming</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/reza-pahlavi-irans-ex-crown-prince-dreaming-homecoming</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/reza-pahlavi-irans-ex-crown-prince-dreaming-homecoming</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Reza Pahlavi, who as a boy was groomed to be the next shah of imperial Iran but has spent nearly five decades in exile, has emerged as a rallying figure in the protests shaking the Islamic republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The chant of "Pahlavi will come back!" has become a mantra for many of the protesters, while the US-based 65-year-old has urged nightly actions in video messages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pahlavi's prominence in the protest movement has surprised some observers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey cautions against foreign intervention in Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-cautions-against-foreign-intervention-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-cautions-against-foreign-intervention-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 12 (Reuters) - Turkey said on Monday that any foreign intervention in neighbouring Iran would lead to greater crises in the country and the region, and it called for U.S. and Iranian negotiations to resolve existing problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran is facing its biggest demonstrations since 2022 and U.S. President Donald Trump has threatened to get involved if force is used against protesters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NATO member Turkey does not wish to see chaos in Iran despite "certain problems within Iranian society and government", Omer Celik, spokesperson for Turkey's ruling AK Party, said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Pakistan and Indonesia closing in on jets and drones defence deal, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-pakistan-and-indonesia-closing-jets-and-drones-defence-deal-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-pakistan-and-indonesia-closing-jets-and-drones-defence-deal-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saad Sayeed, Ananda Teresia and Ariba Shahid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD/JAKARTA Jan 12 (Reuters) - Indonesia's defence minister met Pakistan's air force chief in Islamabad to discuss a potential deal that includes the sale of combat jets and killer drones to Jakarta, three security officials with knowledge of the meeting on Monday said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The talks come as Pakistan's defence industry moves forward with a series of defence procurement negotiations, including deals with Libya's National Army and Sudan's army, and looks to establish itself as a sizable regional player. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Israel poised to launch defence privatisations in months, says government official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-israel-poised-launch-defence-privatisations-months-says-government</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-israel-poised-launch-defence-privatisations-months-says-government</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 12 (Reuters) - Israel plans to begin the long-awaited privatisation of two of its largest defence companies as early as the second quarter of this year, a senior government official said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Roi Kahlon, director of the Government Companies Authority, said union and regulatory issues should be resolved in the next few months to allow initial public offerings by Israel Aerospace Industries (IAI) and Rafael Advanced Defense Systems in the second quarter.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>School resumes in tents under shadow of Gaza's 'yellow line'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/school-resumes-tents-under-shadow-gazas-yellow-line</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/school-resumes-tents-under-shadow-gazas-yellow-line</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mahmoud Issa  and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAZA/CAIRO Jan 12 (Reuters) - She spends her lessons in the wintry cold on the floor of a crowded tent, her teacher interrupted by regular gunfire and explosions from Israeli-controlled territory less than 1,000 metres away. But Toulin Al-Hindi, 7, is grateful to be in school at last after more than two years of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:01:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli-backed group kills a senior Hamas police officer in Gaza, threatens more attacks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-backed-group-kills-senior-hamas-police-officer-gaza-threatens-more</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-backed-group-kills-senior-hamas-police-officer-gaza-threatens-more</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 12 (Reuters) - An Israeli-backed Palestinian militia said on Monday it had killed a senior Hamas police officer in the southern Gaza Strip, an incident which Hamas blamed on "Israeli collaborators".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A statement from the Hamas-run interior ministry said gunmen opened fire from a passing car, killing Mahmoud Al-Astal, head of the criminal police unit in Khan Younis, in the south of the enclave. It described the attackers as "collaborators with the occupation".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran government stages mass rallies as alarm grows over protest toll</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-government-stages-mass-rallies-alarm-grows-over-protest-toll</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-government-stages-mass-rallies-alarm-grows-over-protest-toll</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian authorities on Monday sought to regain control of the streets with mass nationwide rallies in the wake of protests on a scale unprecedented in recent years, as alarm grew over a deadly crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The foreign minister said Iran was ready for both war and talks after repeated threats from Washington to intervene militarily over the crackdown on protests, which activists fear has left at least hundreds dead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:30:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'I know the pain': ex-refugee takes over as UNHCR chief</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/i-know-pain-ex-refugee-takes-over-unhcr-chief</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/i-know-pain-ex-refugee-takes-over-unhcr-chief</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Barham Salih has known torture and the wrenching loss of exile. Four decades after his own ordeal, he has taken the helm of the UN refugee agency as it grapples with a funding shortfall and ever-rising needs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A former Iraqi president, Salih, 65, became the first former head of state to run the United Nations High Commission for Refugees (UNHCR) at the start of the year. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It is a profound moral and legal responsibility," Salih told AFP during his first trip in the new role -- to Kakuma refugee camp in Kenya.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says weighing tough response to Iran crackdown, says Tehran called to negotiate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-weighing-tough-response-iran-crackdown-says-tehran-called-negotiate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-weighing-tough-response-iran-crackdown-says-tehran-called-negotiate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi, Rami Ayyub and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) Jan 12 - President Donald Trump said the U.S. may meet Iranian officials and was in contact with the opposition, as he weighed a range of strong responses including military options to escalating unrest posing one of the biggest challenges to clerical rule since the 1979 Islamic Revolution&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump said Iran called to negotiate its nuclear programme, which Israel and the U.S. bombed in a 12-day war in June. Trump has warned Iran's leaders that the United States would attack if security forces open fire on protesters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 06:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian arts festival decision to bar Palestinian author after Bondi attack spurs boycott</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/australian-arts-festival-decision-bar-palestinian-author-after-bondi-attack-spurs</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/australian-arts-festival-decision-bar-palestinian-author-after-bondi-attack-spurs</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kirsty Needham&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Jan 12 (Reuters) - A top Australian arts festival has seen the withdrawal of dozens of writers in a backlash against its decision to bar an Australian Palestinian author after the Bondi Beach mass shooting, as moves to curb antisemitism spur free speech concerns.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The shooting which killed 15 people at a Jewish Hanukkah celebration at Sydney's Bondi Beach on December 14 sparked nationwide calls to tackle antisemitism. Police say the alleged gunmen were inspired by the Islamic State militant group.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says he will talk to Musk about restoring internet in Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-will-talk-musk-about-restoring-internet-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-will-talk-musk-about-restoring-internet-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Rachael Levy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, D.C., Jan 11 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said on Sunday that he plans to speak with billionaire entrepreneur Elon Musk about restoring internet in Iran, where authorities blacked out service amid ongoing anti-government protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"He's very good at that kind of thing, he's got a very good company," Trump told reporters in response to a question about whether he would engage with Musk's SpaceX company, which offers a satellite internet service called Starlink that has been used in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 01:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says he and US military weighing 'strong options' on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-and-us-military-weighing-strong-options-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-and-us-military-weighing-strong-options-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 11 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump said on Sunday he is weighing a range of responses to escalating unrest in Iran, including possible military options, as massive protests continue to roil the country. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting By Jarrett Renshaw; Editing by Tom Hogue)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deaths from Iran protests reach more than 500, rights group says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/deaths-iran-protests-reach-more-500-rights-group-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/deaths-iran-protests-reach-more-500-rights-group-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi, Rami Ayyub and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI/JERUSALEM, Jan 11 (Reuters) - Unrest in Iran has killed more than 500 people, a rights group said on Sunday, as Tehran threatened to target U.S. military bases if President Donald Trump carries out threats to intervene on behalf of protesters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the Islamic Republic's clerical establishment facing the biggest demonstrations since 2022, Trump has repeatedly threatened to intervene if force is used on protesters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 20:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Some US senators skeptical about military options for Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/some-us-senators-skeptical-about-military-options-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/some-us-senators-skeptical-about-military-options-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Matt Tracy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 11 (Reuters) - Some U.S. lawmakers in both major parties on Sunday questioned whether military action against Iran is the best approach for the United States as Iranian authorities face growing turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump in recent days has left open the possibility of American intervention in Iran, where the biggest anti-government protests in years have led to the Revolutionary Guards blaming unrest on terrorists and vowing to safeguard the governing system.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 19:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demonstrators in London, Paris, Istanbul back Iran protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/demonstrators-london-paris-istanbul-back-iran-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/demonstrators-london-paris-istanbul-back-iran-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Demonstrators rallied in London, Paris and Istanbul on Sunday in support of protests in Iran that have been countered with a deadly crackdown by the country's security forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;London demonstrations, initially in front of the Iranian embassy and later in front of the British prime minister's residence, grew to several thousand as the day progressed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We want revolution, change the regime," Afsi, a 38-year-old Iranian, who declined to give her last name, told AFP at the rally in front of Downing Street.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 19:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran protest deaths rise to more than 500, rights group says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-deaths-rise-more-500-rights-group-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-deaths-rise-more-500-rights-group-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 11 (Reuters) - Deaths from two weeks of protests in Iran have risen to more than 500, U.S.-based rights group HRANA said on Sunday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its latest spreadsheet - based on activists inside and outside Iran - showed 490 protesters and 48 security personnel killed, plus 10,000 arrests. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters could not independently confirm the figures and Iranian authorities have not given tolls from the unrest it blames on "rioters" being encouraged by foreign powers.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 17:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump briefing on Iran options planned for Tuesday, WSJ reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-briefing-iran-options-planned-tuesday-wsj-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-briefing-iran-options-planned-tuesday-wsj-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 11 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump is scheduled to be briefed by senior officials in his administration on Tuesday on specific options to respond to the protests in Iran, the Wall Street Journal reported on Sunday, citing U.S. officials. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting will be a discussion about possible next steps including military strikes, deploying secretive cyber weapons against Iranian military and civilian sites, placing more sanctions on Iran's government and boosting anti-government sources online, the Journal reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White House said it had no comment on the report.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 17:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey bars Iranians from protesting outside Istanbul consulate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-bars-iranians-protesting-outside-istanbul-consulate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-bars-iranians-protesting-outside-istanbul-consulate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turkey on Sunday prevented Iranian nationals from protesting outside Iran's consulate in Istanbul, with the area cordoned off and crowds blocked by police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran has been roiled by street protests since December 28 that have taken hold nationwide, challenging the theocratic government that has ruled the country since the 1979 revolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey, a majority Sunni Muslim country, shares a border of around 500 kilometres (300 miles) and three land crossings with its Shiite neighbour Iran. It hosts more than 74,000 Iranians with residence permits and around 5,000 refugees.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 16:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians in Kurdish area of Aleppo pick up pieces after clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-kurdish-area-aleppo-pick-pieces-after-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-kurdish-area-aleppo-pick-pieces-after-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Residents of a Kurdish neighbourhood in Syria's second city of Aleppo passed through government checkpoints Sunday to find blackened walls, destroyed vehicles and debris-littered streets as they returned home after days of deadly clashes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While they picked up the pieces in the city's Ashrafiyeh neighbourhood, the city's only other Kurdish-majority district Sheikh Maqsud still remained off limits after suffering the worst of the fighting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many locals like wheelchair-bound Abdul Qader Satar returned to Ashrafiyeh on Sunday to inspect their homes after days of violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 16:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>