<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Dutch appeals court rejects bid to stop arms exports to Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dutch-appeals-court-rejects-bid-stop-arms-exports-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dutch-appeals-court-rejects-bid-stop-arms-exports-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;THE HAGUE (Reuters) -A Dutch appeals court on Thursday confirmed a decision to throw out a case brought by pro-Palestinian groups to stop the Netherlands exporting weapons to Israel and trading with Israeli settlements in occupied Palestinian territories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court said it was up to the state to decide what actions to take and not judges.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Young Iraqis run for parliament to challenge sectarian rule, push reform</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/young-iraqis-run-parliament-challenge-sectarian-rule-push-reform</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/young-iraqis-run-parliament-challenge-sectarian-rule-push-reform</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Rasheed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD (Reuters) -Anwar Ibrahim, 25, is so frustrated with Iraq's sectarian politics that he is running for parliament, joining a wave of young Iraqis challenging an entrenched elite at elections next week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I believe young people and technocrats should be given the space to participate in the management of the state, and that we should put an end to the domination of certain parties,” said Ibrahim, a pro-democracy activist.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-US military to establish presence at Damascus airbase, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-us-military-establish-presence-damascus-airbase-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-us-military-establish-presence-damascus-airbase-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Suleiman Al-Khalidi and Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AMMAN/DAMASCUS (Reuters) -The United States is preparing to establish a military presence at an airbase in Damascus to help enable a security pact that Washington is brokering between Syria and Israel, six sources familiar with the matter told Reuters. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. plans for the presence in the Syrian capital, which have not previously been reported, would be a sign of Syria's strategic realignment with the U.S. following the fall last year of longtime leader Bashar al-Assad, an ally of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah rejects any negotiations between Lebanon and Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-rejects-any-negotiations-between-lebanon-and-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-rejects-any-negotiations-between-lebanon-and-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hezbollah lashed out on Thursday against the prospect of any political negotiations between Lebanon and Israel, and insisted that it has a right to defend itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A source close to Hezbollah's political leadership told AFP the declaration followed recent US and Egyptian pressure on Lebanon's leaders to open direct negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lebanon and Israel are still technically in a state of war, but all the recent armed conflicts with Israel were fought by Hezbollah, not the Lebanese military.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians furious at major hike in electricity prices</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrians-furious-major-hike-electricity-prices</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrians-furious-major-hike-electricity-prices</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In his workshop near the Syrian capital, Ghassan Aama is at a loss following a recent decision to massively hike electricity prices, even as much of the country continues to face extensive outages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last month, the energy ministry raised prices by at least 60 times compared to the previous tariff, sending shockwaves through a population already reeling from decades of sanctions and 14 years of war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We were surprised to see electricity prices rise, as our income is limited," said Aama, a blacksmith.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghanistan and Pakistan return to Istanbul for more peace talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-and-pakistan-return-istanbul-more-peace-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-and-pakistan-return-istanbul-more-peace-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Asif Shahzad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD/KABUL (Reuters) -Afghanistan and Pakistan will resume peace talks in Istanbul on Thursday, both nations said, after a previous round ended without agreeing a lasting truce.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Militaries from the South Asian neighbours clashed last month, with dozens killed in the worst such violence since the Taliban returned to power in Kabul in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Probe into Thales defence group looking at Indonesian contract</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/probe-thales-defence-group-looking-indonesian-contract</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/probe-thales-defence-group-looking-indonesian-contract</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A French-British investigation into alleged bribery at France-based defence giant Thales is examining a contract with Indonesia, an AFP investigation has showed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In November last year, Britain's Serious Fraud Office (SFO) said it had launched a joint investigation with its French counterparts into "suspected bribery and corruption" at the multinational, which denies any wrongdoing.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 09:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurdish leader Barzani pushes for leverage with Baghdad in Iraq vote</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kurdish-leader-barzani-pushes-leverage-baghdad-iraq-vote</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kurdish-leader-barzani-pushes-leverage-baghdad-iraq-vote</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD Reuters) -Masoud Barzani, the Iraqi Kurdish leader who first took up arms against Saddam Hussein as a teenage guerrilla, remains a towering figure in Kurdish politics as Iraq heads into its November 11 election.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though he no longer holds an official post, Barzani’s Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP) is urging a strong Kurdish turnout to safeguard regional interests and strengthen its hand in fraught negotiations with Baghdad.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 08:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah says Lebanon is bound by ceasefire but group rejects negotiations with Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-says-lebanon-bound-ceasefire-group-rejects-negotiations-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-says-lebanon-bound-ceasefire-group-rejects-negotiations-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Lebanon's Hezbollah said on Thursday that the group had "a legitimate right to resist (Israeli) occupation", adding that the group would support the Lebanese army. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hezbollah also said that, while Lebanon was bound by a ceasefire, it was not obligated to be drawn into political negotiations with Israel. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Tala Ramadan, Nayera Abdallah and Maya Gebeily; Editing by Alex Richardson)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 08:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Opium farming in Afghanistan shrank by a fifth in 2025, UN survey finds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/opium-farming-afghanistan-shrank-fifth-2025-un-survey-finds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/opium-farming-afghanistan-shrank-fifth-2025-un-survey-finds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;VIENNA (Reuters) -The total area of land in Afghanistan on which opium poppy is grown shrank 20% this year, according to a U.N. estimate issued on Thursday, a further drop since farming of the raw material for heroin collapsed in 2023 after the Taliban banned it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) said its annual survey of opium poppy cultivation in Afghanistan, long the world's dominant producer, had found the harvest had shrunk even faster, falling an estimated 32% to 296 tons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 06:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>SDF commander Hemo: Syria’s Kurds prepare for threat of war as Damascus talks falter</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</guid><description>As US-brokered talks stall, Kurdish forces are preparing contingencies while continuing dialogue with Damascus to secure Syria’s future, SDF commander Sipan Hemo told Al-Monitor in an exclusive interview.</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 20:10:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>SDF commander Hemo: Syria’s Kurds prepare for threat of war as Damascus talks falter</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</guid><description>As US-brokered talks stall, Kurdish forces are preparing contingencies while continuing dialogue with Damascus to secure Syria’s future, SDF commander Sipan Hemo told Al-Monitor in an exclusive interview.</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 20:10:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>SDF commander Hemo: Syria’s Kurds prepare for threat of war as Damascus talks falter</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</guid><description>As US-brokered talks stall, Kurdish forces are preparing contingencies while continuing dialogue with Damascus to secure Syria’s future, SDF commander Sipan Hemo told Al-Monitor in an exclusive interview.</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 20:10:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>SDF commander Hemo: Syria’s Kurds prepare for threat of war as Damascus talks falter</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sdf-commander-hemo-syrias-kurds-prepare-threat-war-damascus-talks-falter</guid><description>As US-brokered talks stall, Kurdish forces are preparing contingencies while continuing dialogue with Damascus to secure Syria’s future, SDF commander Sipan Hemo told Al-Monitor in an exclusive interview.</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 20:10:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US to share draft UN resolution on Gaza with most of Security Council</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-share-draft-un-resolution-gaza-most-security-council</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-share-draft-un-resolution-gaza-most-security-council</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) -The United States will share a draft resolution on President Donald Trump's peace plan for Gaza with the 10 elected members of the United Nations Security Council later on Wednesday, a U.S. official said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representatives for Egypt, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and the United Arab Emirates will join the U.S., "showing clear regional support," the official added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 19:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey, Hamas team discuss next Gaza plan phases, security sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-hamas-team-discuss-next-gaza-plan-phases-security-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-hamas-team-discuss-next-gaza-plan-phases-security-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -Turkey's MIT intelligence agency chief met Hamas' negotiating team head Khalil Al-Hayya on Wednesday and they discussed the path to be followed in implementing the next phases of the Gaza ceasefire plan, Turkish security sources said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They said MIT chief Ibrahim Kalin met the Hamas delegation in Istanbul and they also discussed steps to ensure smooth operation of the ceasefire process and how to overcome existing problems. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ece Toksabay; Writing by Daren Butler; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 18:00:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Attack on funeral in Sudan's Kordofan region kills 40: UN</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/attack-funeral-sudans-kordofan-region-kills-40-un</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/attack-funeral-sudans-kordofan-region-kills-40-un</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;An attack on a funeral in the strategic city of El-Obeid in Sudan's central Kordofan region killed 40 people, the UN said Wednesday, as paramilitaries looked poised to launch an offensive there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations' humanitarian office did not specify when the attack took place or who was behind it, but said that the situation in Kordofan was worsening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The war in Sudan has killed tens of thousands of people and displaced millions more, with the fighting spreading to new areas in recent days, sparking fears of an even greater humanitarian catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 18:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>With new pact, Israel and India boost defense ties, eye $905M aircraft deal: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-pact-israel-and-india-boost-defense-ties-eye-905m-aircraft-deal-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-pact-israel-and-india-boost-defense-ties-eye-905m-aircraft-deal-what-know</guid><description>The new defense pact and potential defense deal come as Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar visits Delhi this week.</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 17:24:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>With new pact, Israel and India boost defense ties, eye $905M aircraft deal: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-pact-israel-and-india-boost-defense-ties-eye-905m-aircraft-deal-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-pact-israel-and-india-boost-defense-ties-eye-905m-aircraft-deal-what-know</guid><description>The new defense pact and potential defense deal come as Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar visits Delhi this week.</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 17:24:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>With new pact, Israel and India boost defense ties, eye $905M aircraft deal: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-pact-israel-and-india-boost-defense-ties-eye-905m-aircraft-deal-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/new-pact-israel-and-india-boost-defense-ties-eye-905m-aircraft-deal-what-know</guid><description>The new defense pact and potential defense deal come as Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar visits Delhi this week.</description><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 17:24:52 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>