<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Greeks march to mark anniversary of 1973 student revolt against junta</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/greeks-march-mark-anniversary-1973-student-revolt-against-junta</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/greeks-march-mark-anniversary-1973-student-revolt-against-junta</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS (Reuters) -Thousands of Greeks marched through Athens on Monday to mark the anniversary of a violently quashed student uprising in 1973 that helped topple the military junta that then ruled the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The annual march to the embassy of the United States, which many Greeks accuse of supporting the 1967-1974 military dictatorship, often becomes a focal point for protests against government policies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 16:01:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council to vote on US resolution on Trump's Gaza plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-vote-us-resolution-trumps-gaza-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-vote-us-resolution-trumps-gaza-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Simon Lewis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON -The UN Security Council was set to vote later on Monday on a U.S.-drafted resolution endorsing President Donald Trump's peace plan for Gaza and authorizing an international stabilization force for the Palestinian enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel and the Palestinian militantgroup Hamas agreed last month to the first phase ofTrump's 20-point plan for Gaza - aceasefire in their two-year war and a hostage-release deal - but a UN resolution is seen as vital to legitimize a transitional governance body and to reassure countries considering sending troops to Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 16:01:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian militant faction says Israel killed a local leader in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-militant-faction-says-israel-killed-local-leader-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-militant-faction-says-israel-killed-local-leader-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -The Palestinian Resistance Committees (PRC), an allied faction of Hamas, said on Monday that one of its local armed leaders was killed by what it described as an Israeli undercover force near Deir Al-Balah city in the central Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The group said Waseem Abdel-Hadi, a commander of its armed wing, was killed in what it called a “cowardly and treacherous assassination operation".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 15:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany lifts Israel arms embargo: What changed in Berlin?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/germany-lifts-israel-arms-embargo-what-changed-berlin</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/germany-lifts-israel-arms-embargo-what-changed-berlin</guid><description>With the ceasefire in place, even though violated at times, Berlin decided to lift the partial arms embargo it imposed on Israel.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:38:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia's MBS on 'comeback tour' in first US visit since Khashoggi murder</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</guid><description>President Donald Trump will host Saudi Arabia's de facto leader for talks focused on deepening US-Saudi ties, Gaza diplomacy and reciprocal investments.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:14:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia's MBS on 'comeback tour' in first US visit since Khashoggi murder</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</guid><description>President Donald Trump will host Saudi Arabia's de facto leader for talks focused on deepening US-Saudi ties, Gaza diplomacy and reciprocal investments.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:14:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia's MBS on 'comeback tour' in first US visit since Khashoggi murder</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</guid><description>President Donald Trump will host Saudi Arabia's de facto leader for talks focused on deepening US-Saudi ties, Gaza diplomacy and reciprocal investments.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:14:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia's MBS on 'comeback tour' in first US visit since Khashoggi murder</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-arabias-mbs-comeback-tour-first-us-visit-khashoggi-murder</guid><description>President Donald Trump will host Saudi Arabia's de facto leader for talks focused on deepening US-Saudi ties, Gaza diplomacy and reciprocal investments.</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:14:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Berlin to lift suspension of Israel weapons sales, but says ceasefire must hold</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/berlin-lift-suspension-israel-weapons-sales-says-ceasefire-must-hold</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/berlin-lift-suspension-israel-weapons-sales-says-ceasefire-must-hold</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Andreas Rinke&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BERLIN (Reuters) -Germany on Monday moved to resume weapons sales to Israel that had been suspended since August over the war in Gaza, but said the decision is subject to the observance of the ceasefire and the large-scale provision of humanitarian aid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Germany, the second-largest exporter of arms to Israel after the United States, announced a suspension of some arms exports to Israel in August, amid mounting popular pressure over the war. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Emirates orders 65 more Boeing 777X planes despite delays</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/emirates-orders-65-more-boeing-777x-planes-despite-delays</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/emirates-orders-65-more-boeing-777x-planes-despite-delays</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Emirates, the Middle East's biggest airline, topped up its order of Boeing 777X planes on Monday despite years of delays, delivering a vote of confidence to the US manufacturer at the Dubai Airshow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The order of 65 777-9s, valued at $38 billion including engines, came despite last month's announcement that delivery was now due in 2027 -- seven years behind the original schedule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emirates, already the biggest customer for the Boeing 777, now has 270 777X, 10 777 freighters and 35 Boeing 787s on order.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurdish PKK militants say have left key area in north Iraq</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kurdish-pkk-militants-say-have-left-key-area-north-iraq</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kurdish-pkk-militants-say-have-left-key-area-north-iraq</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Kurdish militant PKK said Monday its forces had withdrawn from a key border area in northern Iraq in a move aimed at shoring up the peace process with Turkey. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pull out comes six months after the Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK) formally renounced its armed struggle against Turkey, drawing a line under four decades of violence that had claimed some 50,000 lives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"As of the evening of November 16, our forces.. in the Zap region have been withdrawn," the group said in a statement published by Firat news agency. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 09:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leaders of divided Cyprus to meet on November 20, officials say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/leaders-divided-cyprus-meet-november-20-officials-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/leaders-divided-cyprus-meet-november-20-officials-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;NICOSIA (Reuters) -Leaders of ethnically-split Cyprus will meet on November 20, officials said on Monday, marking their first encounter since the election of a new Turkish Cypriot leader last month. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkish Cypriot leader Tufan Erhurman and Greek Cypriot leader Nikos Christodoulides will meet at the residence of the envoy to the United Nations peacekeeping force on the island. The announcement of the meeting was issued simultaneously by the Greek and Turkish Cypriot sides.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 07:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi crown prince visits US with defence, AI and nuclear on the agenda</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-crown-prince-visits-us-defence-ai-and-nuclear-agenda</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-crown-prince-visits-us-defence-ai-and-nuclear-agenda</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timour Azhari and Matt Spetalnick&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;RIYADH/WASHINGTON (Reuters) -A visit by Saudi Arabia's de facto ruler to the White House for talks on Tuesday with U.S. President Donald Trump aims to deepen decades-old cooperation on oil and security while broadening ties in commerce, technology and potentially even nuclear energy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 05:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>From pariah to power player: Saudi's MbS reclaims world stage in US visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pariah-power-player-saudis-mbs-reclaims-world-stage-us-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pariah-power-player-saudis-mbs-reclaims-world-stage-us-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI (Reuters) -On his first White House visit since the killing of Saudi critic Jamal Khashoggi sparked global outrage, Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman is on a mission to reclaim his place on the world stage and prove to President Donald Trump that backing his forceful leadership was worth the gamble.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 05:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says Republicans drafting bill to sanction countries that trade with Russia</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-republicans-drafting-bill-sanction-countries-trade-russia</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-republicans-drafting-bill-sanction-countries-trade-russia</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -President Donald Trump said on Sunday that Republicans are working on legislation that will impose sanctions on any country doing business with Russia, and he said Iran may get added to that list.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"As you know, I suggested it, so any country that does business with Russia will be very severely sanctioned," Trump told reporters. "They may add Iran to that," he added.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Nandita Bose and Daphne Psaledakis in Washington; Editing by Leslie Adler)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 03:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran girls kick down social barriers with karate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-girls-kick-down-social-barriers-karate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-girls-kick-down-social-barriers-karate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As the referee's whistle signalled the start of the match, two five-year-old Iranian girls faced off, delivering a closely watched karate bout to a captivated audience -- a sign of the changing attitude toward martial arts in the Islamic Republic in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two young opponents, clad in crisp white karategi with coloured belts and protective headgear, circled each other on the tatami, the floor covering used for practising Japanese martial arts.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 03:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council set to vote on international force for Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-set-vote-international-force-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-set-vote-international-force-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The UN Security Council is set to vote Monday on a US-drafted resolution bolstering Donald Trump's Gaza peace plan, especially the deployment of an international force, as Washington warns that a failure to act could lead to renewed fighting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft, which has been revised several times as a result of high-stakes negotiations, "endorses" the plan, which allowed for a fragile ceasefire between Israel and Hamas to take hold on October 10 in the war-wracked Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 03:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia rules out co-hosting climate summit with Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-rules-out-co-hosting-climate-summit-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-rules-out-co-hosting-climate-summit-turkey</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Christine Chen and Renju Jose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY (Reuters) -Prime Minister Anthony Albanese said on Monday that Australia would not co-host the COP31 climate summit with Turkey amid an ongoing stalemate between the two countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey has proposed jointly leading next year's U.N. climate summit with Australia and the discussions on the hosting standoff remain unresolved, Turkish diplomatic sources told Reuters on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 01:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain reviews human rights laws in major shake-up of asylum policy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/britain-reviews-human-rights-laws-major-shake-asylum-policy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/britain-reviews-human-rights-laws-major-shake-asylum-policy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alistair Smout&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LONDON (Reuters) -Britain will overhaul its approach to human rights laws to make it easier to deport migrants who arrive in the country illegally as part of a major shake-up of asylum policy to be set out on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interior minister Shabana Mahmood will outline changes to how the European Convention on Human Rights will be interpreted by courts, the government said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"These reforms will block endless appeals, stop last minute claims and scale up removals of those with no right to be here," Prime Minister Keir Starmer said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 22:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey proposed joint leadership for COP31 to end hosting standoff with Australia, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-proposed-joint-leadership-cop31-end-hosting-standoff-australia-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-proposed-joint-leadership-cop31-end-hosting-standoff-australia-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -Turkey has proposed jointly leading next year's U.N. climate summit with Australia, though the two sides have not yet reached an agreement and the discussions on the hosting standoff remain unresolved, Turkish diplomatic sources said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Australia and Turkey both submitted bids in 2022 to host COP31 and neither has withdrawn, leading to an attention-sapping impasse that must be overcome at this year's COP30 meeting currently taking place in Belem, Brazil. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 13:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>