<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>World Bank, in letter to US, backs draft UN resolution on Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/world-bank-letter-us-backs-draft-un-resolution-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/world-bank-letter-us-backs-draft-un-resolution-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) -The World Bank backs language in a U.S.-drafted United Nations Security Council resolution on Gaza that would authorize a two-year mandate for a transitional governance body,according to a letter to the United States seen by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 19:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jared Kushner arrives in Israel for Gaza talks with Netanyahu, source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/jared-kushner-arrives-israel-gaza-talks-netanyahu-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/jared-kushner-arrives-israel-gaza-talks-netanyahu-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump's influential son-in-law, Jared Kushner, arrived in Israel on Sunday for talks with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on implementing the U.S. plan to end the Gaza war, a source familiar with the matter said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kushner was expected to meet with Netanyahu on Monday, said the source, speaking on condition of anonymity as the meeting had not been formally announced. The White House and Netanyahu's office did not immediately respond to a Reuters request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Killed on sight': Sudanese fleeing El-Fasher recall ethnic attacks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/killed-sight-sudanese-fleeing-el-fasher-recall-ethnic-attacks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/killed-sight-sudanese-fleeing-el-fasher-recall-ethnic-attacks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As he fled the Sudanese city of El-Fasher in terror, Hassan Osman said he saw ethnic attacks by paramilitary forces, with civilians targeted for their tribe and skin colour. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rapid Support Forces (RSF), which have been at war with the army since April 2023, captured the last military stronghold in western Darfur on October 26. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports of mass killings, ethnic violence, abductions and sexual assaults have since emerged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AFP spoke to three survivors of the battle for El-Fasher, who are now seeking shelter in the nearby town of Tawila. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 17:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel confirms remains returned are officer Goldin killed in 2014 Gaza war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-confirms-remains-returned-are-officer-goldin-killed-2014-gaza-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-confirms-remains-returned-are-officer-goldin-killed-2014-gaza-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel said the remains it received on Sunday from Hamas were those of Lieutenant Hadar Goldin, an Israeli officer killed more than a decade ago in the 2014 Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Goldin was the 24th deceased hostage whose remains have been returned by Hamas since the start of the ceasefire on October 10 that has halted the latest war in Gaza, which broke out in October 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said forensic experts had confirmed the remains were of Goldin.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 15:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel receives remains of deceased hostage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-receives-remains-deceased-hostage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-receives-remains-deceased-hostage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -Israel on Sunday received the remains of a deceased hostage held in Gaza that Palestinian militant group Hamas said were of an Israeli soldier killed in the territory more than a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said in a statement the remains were handed over to Israeli forces in the Palestinian territory by the Red Cross.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has not yet been formal identification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hamas' armed wing had said it would hand over the body of Hadar Goldin, a military officer killed in an ambush in Gaza during the 2014 Israel-Hamas war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 14:01:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mamdani’s New York victory exposes fault lines in Jewish Democratic politics</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/mamdanis-new-york-victory-exposes-fault-lines-jewish-democratic-politics</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/mamdanis-new-york-victory-exposes-fault-lines-jewish-democratic-politics</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Helen Coster and James Oliphant&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NEW YORK (Reuters) -Zohran Mamdani’s election as New York’s next mayor exposed a deepening rift between traditional Democratic Jewish voters and younger progressives — one that could reshape politics for years in the metropolitan area with the world’s largest Jewish population outside Israel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mamdani, a 34-year-old democratic socialist, handily defeated Andrew Cuomo, the Democratic former governor of New York who ran as an independent, while beating back accusations of antisemitism over his support of Palestinians in the conflict in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 11:36:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkish delegation to meet in Pakistan aiming to seal peace deal with Afghanistan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-delegation-meet-pakistan-aiming-seal-peace-deal-afghanistan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-delegation-meet-pakistan-aiming-seal-peace-deal-afghanistan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -Turkey's foreign and defence ministers and intelligence chief plan to travel to Pakistan this week to discuss its stop-start talks with Afghanistan over a ceasefire in place in South Asia, President Tayyip Erdogan said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to an official readout on Sunday of his comments on a return flight from Baku, where he met Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif, Erdogan said the tripartite visit aim to seal a permanent ceasefire and peace between the nations as soon as possible. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 09:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US sanctions official says time is right to cut Iran's Hezbollah funding</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-sanctions-official-says-time-right-cut-irans-hezbollah-funding</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-sanctions-official-says-time-right-cut-irans-hezbollah-funding</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Spicer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -The United States seeks to take advantage of a "moment" in Lebanon in which it can cut Iranian funding to Hezbollah and press the group to disarm, the U.S. Treasury Department's top sanctions official said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a late Friday interview, John Hurley, the undersecretary for terrorism and financial intelligence, said Iran has managed to funnel about $1 billion to Hezbollah this year despite a raft of Western sanctions that have battered its economy. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 07:01:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Before talks with Trump, Saudi Arabia doubles down on terms for Israel ties</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-talks-trump-saudi-arabia-doubles-down-terms-israel-ties</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-talks-trump-saudi-arabia-doubles-down-terms-israel-ties</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI (Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump has been talking up the prospects of Saudi Arabia agreeing to normalise ties with Israel, but it is unlikely to happen when Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman visits the White House this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The establishment of diplomatic relations between Israel and Saudi Arabia after decades of enmity could shake up the political and security landscape in the Middle East, potentially strengthening U.S. influence in the region.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 06:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian president arrives in US for landmark visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrian-president-arrives-us-landmark-visit-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrian-president-arrives-us-landmark-visit-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria's President Ahmed al-Sharaa arrived in the United States on Saturday for a landmark official visit, his country's state news agency reported, a day after Washington removed him from a terrorism blacklist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sharaa, whose rebel forces ousted longtime ruler Bashar al-Assad late last year, is due to meet US President Donald Trump at the White House on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's the first such visit by a Syrian president since the country's independence in 1946, according to analysts.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 05:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian president arrives in US for landmark visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrian-president-arrives-us-landmark-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrian-president-arrives-us-landmark-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria's President Ahmed al-Sharaa arrived in the United States on Saturday for a landmark official visit, his country's state news agency reported, a day after Washington removed him from a terrorism blacklist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sharaa, whose rebel forces ousted longtime ruler Bashar al-Assad late last year, is due to meet US President Donald Trump at the White House on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's the first such visit by a Syrian president since the country's independence in 1946, according to analysts.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 00:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria carries out pre-emptive operations against Islamic State cells</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-carries-out-pre-emptive-operations-against-islamic-state-cells</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-carries-out-pre-emptive-operations-against-islamic-state-cells</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Syria has carried out nationwide pre-emptive operations targeting Islamic State cells, a spokesperson for the Interior Ministry said on Saturday.        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syrian security forces carried out 61 raids, with 71 people arrested and explosives and weapons seized, the spokesperson told state-run Al Ekhbariya TV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The raids come ahead of a trip by Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa to Washington to meet with U.S. President Donald Trump and join an anti Islamic State U.S.-led coalition. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 21:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli settlers attack Palestinians, journalists at West Bank olive harvest, witnesses say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-settlers-attack-palestinians-journalists-west-bank-olive-harvest</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-settlers-attack-palestinians-journalists-west-bank-olive-harvest</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -Israeli settlers attacked a group of Palestinian villagers, activists and journalists on Saturday who had gathered during an attempt to harvest olives near a settler outpost in the Israeli-occupied West Bank, witnesses said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two Reuters employees - a journalist and a security adviser accompanying her - were among those injured in the attack by the men who wielded sticks and clubs and hurled large rocks, in an area close to the Palestinian village of Beita.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 20:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel identifies latest hostage body, as families await five more</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-identifies-latest-hostage-body-families-await-five-more</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-identifies-latest-hostage-body-families-await-five-more</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel identified on Saturday the latest hostage remains sent back from Gaza by Palestinian militants, leaving only five more bodies to be returned under the US-brokered truce that halted the two-year war.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military identified the body handed over on Friday as that of volunteer ambulance driver Lior Rudaeff, who was killed in the October 7, 2023 Hamas attack that triggered the Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 12:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Syria’s south, Bedouins uprooted by sectarian clashes see little hope of return</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrias-south-bedouins-uprooted-sectarian-clashes-see-little-hope-return</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrias-south-bedouins-uprooted-sectarian-clashes-see-little-hope-return</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Laila Bassam and Tom Perry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NAWA, Syria (Reuters) -As sectarian violence swept through Syria's southern Sweida province in July, the Sbeih family say they were taken by Druze gunmen and held in a school with other Bedouin tribe members. When their guards disappeared after three nights, they tried to escape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shots were fired, and the Bedouins scattered. Faisal Sbeih and his wife, Fasl, were separated. Three family members were killed, they said, including their 20-year-old daughter, Malak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She had been due to marry the next day.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US forces working with Israel on Gaza aid, Israeli official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-forces-working-israel-gaza-aid-israeli-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-forces-working-israel-gaza-aid-israeli-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emily Rose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -U.S. forces are taking part in overseeing and coordinating aid transfer into the Gaza Strip together with Israel as part of U.S. President Donald Trump's ceasefire plan, an Israeli security official said on Saturday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Washington Post on Friday reported that the U.S.-led  Civil-Military Coordination Center (CMCC) will replace Israel in overseeing aid into Gaza. It cited a U.S. official and people familiar with the matter as saying Israel was part of the process but that CMCC would decide what aid enters Gaza and how.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghanistan, Pakistan peace talks collapse, ceasefire continues, Taliban says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-pakistan-peace-talks-collapse-ceasefire-continues-taliban-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-pakistan-peace-talks-collapse-ceasefire-continues-taliban-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Peace negotiations between Afghanistan and Pakistan broke down, although a ceasefire continues between the South Asian neighbours, a Taliban spokesperson said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zabihullah Mujahid said negotiations had failed due to Islamabad insisting that Afghanistan assume responsibility for Pakistan's internal security, a demand he described as beyond Afghanistan's "capacity".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, he said, "The ceasefire that has been established has not been violated by us so far, and it will continue to be observed."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 08:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A third Tunisian opposition leader launches hunger strike in prison</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/third-tunisian-opposition-leader-launches-hunger-strike-prison</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/third-tunisian-opposition-leader-launches-hunger-strike-prison</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS (Reuters) -Jailed Tunisian opposition leader Rached Ghannouchi, 84, began a hunger strike, joining two prominent politicians who are protesting what they call “unjust imprisonment,” lawyers said on Saturday, marking the latest escalation in a standoff with President Kais Saied.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the country's opposition leaders are in jail and some parties have accused Saied of turning Tunisia into an “open-air prison” while using the judiciary to cement his authoritarian rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 03:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US accuses Iran in plot to kill Israeli ambassador in Mexico</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-accuses-iran-plot-kill-israeli-ambassador-mexico</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-accuses-iran-plot-kill-israeli-ambassador-mexico</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The United States and Israel on Friday accused Iran of trying to kill Israel's ambassador to Mexico, with Tehran rejecting the claim as a "big lie" and the Mexican government saying it was unaware of the plot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The purported assassination attempt came as tensions soared to new highs between Israel and Iran, which have each attacked the other's territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel said Mexican authorities had intervened to stop the attempt to kill its ambassador, Einat Kranz-Neiger, but Mexico's foreign ministry later said it had "received no information" on the alleged incident.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 01:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey issues genocide arrest warrant against Netanyahu</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-issues-genocide-arrest-warrant-against-netanyahu</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-issues-genocide-arrest-warrant-against-netanyahu</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turkey announced Friday that it had issued arrest warrants for genocide against Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and senior officials in his government over the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcement was met with a firm rebuttal from Israel. Foreign Minister Gideon Saar said Israel "firmly rejects, with contempt" the charges, calling them "the latest PR stunt by the tyrant (Turkish President Recep Tayyip) Erdogan".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Istanbul prosecutor's office said in a statement that a total of 37 suspects were targeted by the arrest warrants, without providing a full list.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 22:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>