<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>US to start UN negotiations on Thursday on international Gaza force mandate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-start-un-negotiations-thursday-international-gaza-force-mandate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-start-un-negotiations-thursday-international-gaza-force-mandate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) -The United Nations Security Council on Thursday will start negotiations on a U.S.-drafted resolution to endorse President Donald Trump's Gaza peace plan, said a senior U.S. government official, and authorize a two-year mandate for a transitional governance body and international stabilization force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. formally circulated the draft resolution to the 15 council members late on Wednesday and has said it has regional support from Egypt, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Turkey, and the United Arab Emirates for the text.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff says will announce new country to enter the Abraham Accords on Thursday night</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/witkoff-says-will-announce-new-country-enter-abraham-accords-thursday-night</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/witkoff-says-will-announce-new-country-enter-abraham-accords-thursday-night</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -U.S. special envoy Steve Witkoff said that a new country would be announced on Thursday night as entering the Abraham Accords that have normalized relations between Israel and Muslim-majority nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Witkoff told a business forum in Florida that he would be returning to Washington for the announcement, declining to say which country it would be. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Simon Lewis, Editing by Franklin Paul)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel launches airstrikes on south Lebanon, says it's targeting Hezbollah</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-airstrikes-south-lebanon-says-its-targeting-hezbollah</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-airstrikes-south-lebanon-says-its-targeting-hezbollah</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT (Reuters) -The Israeli military carried out heavy airstrikes on southern Lebanon on Thursday after issuing evacuation orders for several locations, saying Lebanese armed group Hezbollah was trying to rebuild its military capabilities there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The orders and strikes came despite a ceasefire deal agreed a year ago that was meant to end more than a year of fighting between Israel and Iran-backed Hezbollah, and after months of Lebanese army efforts to clear Hezbollah sites in the south.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fleetwod and Lowry lift each other into Abu Dhabi lead</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fleetwod-and-lowry-lift-each-other-abu-dhabi-lead</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fleetwod-and-lowry-lift-each-other-abu-dhabi-lead</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Friends Tommy Fleetwood and Shane Lowry shared the lead in the Abu Dhabi Championship after they were paired together on Thursday and both shot eight-under-par opening rounds of 64.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pair shared the lead with New Zealander Kazuma Kobori, South African Richard Sterne and Frenchman Adrien Saddier at the start of the last event of the DP Tour before the season-ending World Championship in Dubai.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lowry and Fleetwood, both previous winners of the event, were drawn in a group that also included a third Ryder Cup player Rasmus Hojgaard.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 16:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tight UK security ahead of match against Israeli club</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tight-uk-security-ahead-match-against-israeli-club</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tight-uk-security-ahead-match-against-israeli-club</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;More than 700 police deployed across the UK city of Birmingham Thursday for protests planned ahead of a football match between Maccabi Tel Aviv and Aston Villa, with visiting Israeli fans barred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK government last month vowed to reverse the ban on Maccabi fans attending the Europa League match in the city in central England that has a significant Muslim population after widespread criticism of the decision taken by local safety advisors and police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Israeli club later announced it would decline any tickets for its fans, citing safety concerns.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan's RSF agrees to U.S. proposal for humanitarian ceasefire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudans-rsf-agrees-us-proposal-humanitarian-ceasefire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudans-rsf-agrees-us-proposal-humanitarian-ceasefire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Sudan's paramilitary Rapid Support Forces agreed to a proposal from the United States for a humanitarian ceasefire, they said on Thursday in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The war erupted in April 2023 when the Sudanese army and the RSF, then partners in power, clashed over plans to integrate their forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Khalid Abdelaziz and Nafisa Eltahir; Writing by Enas Alashray; Editing by Alex Richardson)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mediators propose deal to get Hamas fighters out of Gaza's Israeli zone, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/mediators-propose-deal-get-hamas-fighters-out-gazas-israeli-zone-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/mediators-propose-deal-get-hamas-fighters-out-gazas-israeli-zone-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -Hamas fighters holed up in the Israeli-held Rafah area of Gaza would surrender their arms in exchange for passage to other areas of the enclave under a proposal to resolve an issue seen as a risk to the month-old truce, according to two sources familiar with the talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the U.S.-brokered ceasefire took effect in Gaza on October 10, the Rafah area has been the scene of at least two attacks on Israeli forces which Israel has blamed on Hamas; the militant group has denied responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 14:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria advances Qatar-backed $7B power project amid soaring electricity prices</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</guid><description>According to the state-run Syrian Arab News Agency, the plants will use a combination of natural gas and solar energy.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 14:08:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria advances Qatar-backed $7B power project amid soaring electricity prices</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</guid><description>According to the state-run Syrian Arab News Agency, the plants will use a combination of natural gas and solar energy.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 14:08:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria advances Qatar-backed $7B power project amid soaring electricity prices</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</guid><description>According to the state-run Syrian Arab News Agency, the plants will use a combination of natural gas and solar energy.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 14:08:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria advances Qatar-backed $7B power project amid soaring electricity prices</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syria-advances-qatar-backed-7b-power-project-amid-soaring-electricity-prices</guid><description>According to the state-run Syrian Arab News Agency, the plants will use a combination of natural gas and solar energy.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 14:08:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greek court charges more coast guard officers over 2023 migrant shipwreck, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/greek-court-charges-more-coast-guard-officers-over-2023-migrant-shipwreck-sources</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/greek-court-charges-more-coast-guard-officers-over-2023-migrant-shipwreck-sources</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Renee Maltezou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ATHENS (Reuters) -A Greek prosecutor has extended charges to four more senior coast guard officers over one of the Mediterranean's deadliest accidents, a 2023 shipwreck in which hundreds drowned off the southwestern town of Pylos, legal sources said on Thursday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The charges follow an appeal by lawyers representing the victims, the sources told Reuters. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 14:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dutch appeals court rejects bid to stop arms exports to Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dutch-appeals-court-rejects-bid-stop-arms-exports-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dutch-appeals-court-rejects-bid-stop-arms-exports-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;THE HAGUE (Reuters) -A Dutch appeals court on Thursday confirmed a decision to throw out a case brought by pro-Palestinian groups to stop the Netherlands exporting weapons to Israel and trading with Israeli settlements in occupied Palestinian territories.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court said it was up to the state to decide what actions to take and not judges.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Young Iraqis run for parliament to challenge sectarian rule, push reform</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/young-iraqis-run-parliament-challenge-sectarian-rule-push-reform</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/young-iraqis-run-parliament-challenge-sectarian-rule-push-reform</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Rasheed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD (Reuters) -Anwar Ibrahim, 25, is so frustrated with Iraq's sectarian politics that he is running for parliament, joining a wave of young Iraqis challenging an entrenched elite at elections next week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I believe young people and technocrats should be given the space to participate in the management of the state, and that we should put an end to the domination of certain parties,” said Ibrahim, a pro-democracy activist.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-US military to establish presence at Damascus airbase, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-us-military-establish-presence-damascus-airbase-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-us-military-establish-presence-damascus-airbase-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Suleiman Al-Khalidi and Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AMMAN/DAMASCUS (Reuters) -The United States is preparing to establish a military presence at an airbase in Damascus to help enable a security pact that Washington is brokering between Syria and Israel, six sources familiar with the matter told Reuters. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. plans for the presence in the Syrian capital, which have not previously been reported, would be a sign of Syria's strategic realignment with the U.S. following the fall last year of longtime leader Bashar al-Assad, an ally of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel strikes Hezbollah targets in Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-strikes-hezbollah-targets-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-strikes-hezbollah-targets-lebanon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel struck Hezbollah targets in southern Lebanon on Thursday as the group rejected the prospect of direct political talks between the countries and vowed to defend itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military confirmed a new series of strikes had begun after warning civilians to evacuate certain buildings in three Lebanese villages: Taybeh, Tayr Debba and Aita al-Jabal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An Israeli strike had already killed one person, according to the Lebanese health ministry. The Israeli military said it had targeted a Hezbollah construction team.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians furious at major hike in electricity prices</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrians-furious-major-hike-electricity-prices</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrians-furious-major-hike-electricity-prices</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In his workshop near the Syrian capital, Ghassan Aama is at a loss following a recent decision to massively hike electricity prices, even as much of the country continues to face extensive outages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last month, the energy ministry raised prices by at least 60 times compared to the previous tariff, sending shockwaves through a population already reeling from decades of sanctions and 14 years of war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We were surprised to see electricity prices rise, as our income is limited," said Aama, a blacksmith.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghanistan and Pakistan return to Istanbul for more peace talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-and-pakistan-return-istanbul-more-peace-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-and-pakistan-return-istanbul-more-peace-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Asif Shahzad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD/KABUL (Reuters) -Afghanistan and Pakistan will resume peace talks in Istanbul on Thursday, both nations said, after a previous round ended without agreeing a lasting truce.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Militaries from the South Asian neighbours clashed last month, with dozens killed in the worst such violence since the Taliban returned to power in Kabul in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Probe into Thales defence group looking at Indonesian contract</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/probe-thales-defence-group-looking-indonesian-contract</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/probe-thales-defence-group-looking-indonesian-contract</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A French-British investigation into alleged bribery at France-based defence giant Thales is examining a contract with Indonesia, an AFP investigation has showed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In November last year, Britain's Serious Fraud Office (SFO) said it had launched a joint investigation with its French counterparts into "suspected bribery and corruption" at the multinational, which denies any wrongdoing.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 09:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurdish leader Barzani pushes for leverage with Baghdad in Iraq vote</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kurdish-leader-barzani-pushes-leverage-baghdad-iraq-vote</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kurdish-leader-barzani-pushes-leverage-baghdad-iraq-vote</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD Reuters) -Masoud Barzani, the Iraqi Kurdish leader who first took up arms against Saddam Hussein as a teenage guerrilla, remains a towering figure in Kurdish politics as Iraq heads into its November 11 election.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though he no longer holds an official post, Barzani’s Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP) is urging a strong Kurdish turnout to safeguard regional interests and strengthen its hand in fraught negotiations with Baghdad.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 08:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>