<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan says Israeli decision to recognise Somaliland unacceptable, illegal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkeys-erdogan-says-israeli-decision-recognise-somaliland-unacceptable-illegal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkeys-erdogan-says-israeli-decision-recognise-somaliland-unacceptable-illegal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Dec 30 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan said on Tuesday that Israel's decision to formally recognise of the self-declared Republic of Somaliland was an illegal and unacceptable step, adding that it was trying to drag the horn of Africa into destabilisation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a press conference alongside Somali counterpart Hassan Sheikh Mohamud in Istanbul, Erdogan also said Turkey was planning on starting offshore energy drilling off the coast of Somalia in 2026 as per a bilateral agreement, adding that it was adding two new drilling vessels to its fleet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 16:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spain exempts Airbus from Israeli tech ban</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/spain-exempts-airbus-israeli-tech-ban</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/spain-exempts-airbus-israeli-tech-ban</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MADRID, Dec 30 (Reuters) - Spain has granted Airbus exceptional permission to produce aircraft and drones using Israeli technology at its Spanish plants even though it banned military and dual-use products from Israel two months ago over its war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Approved last Tuesday by the cabinet and defended by several ministers this week, the exemption reflects the pressure from companies and domestic interests that some of Europe's toughest critics of Israel's recent war have faced as they attempt to impose trade sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE says it ends mission of counterterrorism units in Yemen voluntarily</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/uae-says-it-ends-mission-counterterrorism-units-yemen-voluntarily</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/uae-says-it-ends-mission-counterterrorism-units-yemen-voluntarily</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Dec 30 (Reuters) - The United Arab Emirates' defence ministry said on Monday it has ended the mission of its counterterrorism units in Yemen voluntarily, state news agency WAM reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It said the decision came after a comprehensive assessment following recent developments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Menna Alaa El-Din and Muhammad Al Gebaly; Editing by Andrew Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A war within a war: Yemen's latest conflict</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/war-within-war-yemens-latest-conflict</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/war-within-war-yemens-latest-conflict</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Yemen has been fighting a crippling war with itself since Iran-backed Houthi rebels ousted the government in 2014, triggering a Saudi-led military intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, a new conflict is brewing within the conflict, involving rival armed factions loosely grouped under the government but separately backed by the United Arab Emirates and Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confrontation could tear apart the already-fractured government and threaten slow-moving peace negotiations with the Houthis, including a UN-brokered ceasefire that has largely held since 2022.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 14:30:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US, partner forces killed or captured nearly 25 Islamic State operatives since strikes in Syria</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-partner-forces-killed-or-captured-nearly-25-islamic-state-operatives-strikes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-partner-forces-killed-or-captured-nearly-25-islamic-state-operatives-strikes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 30 (Reuters) - The United States and its partner forces killed or captured nearly 25 Islamic State operatives since it launched retaliatory strikes in Syria earlier this month, the U.S. military said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. carried out large-scale strikes against dozens of Islamic State targets in Syria on Dec. 19 in retaliation for an attack on American personnel.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 14:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria imposes curfew in Latakia days after protests turn violent, state media says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-imposes-curfew-latakia-days-after-protests-turn-violent-state-media-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-imposes-curfew-latakia-days-after-protests-turn-violent-state-media-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 30 (Reuters) - Syrian security forces imposed a curfew on Latakia city, a bastion of the country's Alawite minority, state media reported on Tuesday, days after four people were killed in protests that spiralled into violence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syria has been rocked by several episodes of sectarian bloodshed since longtime leader Bashar al-Assad, who hails from the Muslim Alawite community, was ousted by a rebel offensive last year and replaced by a Sunni-led government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;State media said the curfew was set to last from 5 p.m. (1400 GMT) on Tuesday until 6 a.m. (0300 GMT) on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 12:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's government offers dialogue to protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-government-offers-dialogue-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/irans-government-offers-dialogue-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Elwely Elwelly&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 30 (Reuters) - Iran's government said on Tuesday it would seek dialogue with protest leaders after demonstrations in Tehran and other cities over a plunge in the currency's value that has accelerated inflation, with the central bank chief resigning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Protests, which included shopkeepers in Tehran's Grand Bazaar, were held on Sunday and Monday according to Iranian state media, the latest demonstrations in the Islamic Republic where bouts of unrest have repeatedly erupted in recent years. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 11:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran threats, flattery, unresolved gaps: What Trump really gave Netanyahu at Mar-a-Lago</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</guid><description>At their meeting at Mar-a-Lago, President Donald Trump heaped compliments on Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu but offered few concrete achievements.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 11:33:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran threats, flattery, unresolved gaps: What Trump really gave Netanyahu at Mar-a-Lago</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</guid><description>At their meeting at Mar-a-Lago, President Donald Trump heaped compliments on Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu but offered few concrete achievements.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 11:33:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran threats, flattery, unresolved gaps: What Trump really gave Netanyahu at Mar-a-Lago</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</guid><description>At their meeting at Mar-a-Lago, President Donald Trump heaped compliments on Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu but offered few concrete achievements.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 11:33:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran threats, flattery, unresolved gaps: What Trump really gave Netanyahu at Mar-a-Lago</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-threats-flattery-unresolved-gaps-what-trump-really-gave-netanyahu-mar-lago</guid><description>At their meeting at Mar-a-Lago, President Donald Trump heaped compliments on Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu but offered few concrete achievements.</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 11:33:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>From brothers to rivals: Key moments in Saudi-UAE relations​</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/brothers-rivals-key-moments-saudi-uae-relations</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/brothers-rivals-key-moments-saudi-uae-relations</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Yousef Saba&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 30 - A Saudi airstrike on what it said was a UAE-linked weapons shipment in Yemen on Tuesday marked the most significant escalation between Riyadh and Abu Dhabi to date. Once the twin pillars of regional security, the two Gulf heavyweights have seen their interests diverge on everything from oil quotas to geopolitical influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is a timeline of how the relationship has evolved:&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia says national security is a red line as UAE forces asked to leave Yemen</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-arabia-says-national-security-red-line-uae-forces-asked-leave-yemen</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-arabia-says-national-security-red-line-uae-forces-asked-leave-yemen</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Yomna Ehab, Nayera Abdallah and Maha El Dahan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dec 30 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia said on Tuesday its national security was a red line and backed a call for UAE forces to leave Yemen within 24 hours, hours after a Saudi-led coalition carried out an airstrike on the southern Yemeni port of Mukalla.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 10:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Students join demonstrations after Iran shopkeepers protest</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/students-join-demonstrations-after-iran-shopkeepers-protest</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/students-join-demonstrations-after-iran-shopkeepers-protest</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian students staged street protests in Tehran on Tuesday, a day after the capital's shopkeepers demonstrated against economic hardship and won a message of understanding from the president himself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Ilna, a news agency associated with Iran's labour movement, protests erupted at seven Tehran colleges that are among the country's most prestigious, and at the technology university in the central city of Isfahan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 09:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Facing Alawite backlash, Syria’s new leaders take controversial steps to win loyalty</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/facing-alawite-backlash-syrias-new-leaders-take-controversial-steps-win-loyalty</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/facing-alawite-backlash-syrias-new-leaders-take-controversial-steps-win-loyalty</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QARDAHA, Syria, Dec 30 (Reuters) - He carried no weapons and helped keep government security forces alive, but Khairallah Dib still needed a promise of amnesty to come out of hiding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He had been lying low for weeks after Alawite fighters staged a March insurrection against Syria’s new Islamist-led rulers. The uprising by loyalists of ousted President Bashar al-Assad killed more than 200 Syrian security forces and triggered days of vengeance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 07:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi-backed head of Yemen's presidential council tells UAE to leave</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-backed-head-yemens-presidential-council-tells-uae-leave</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-backed-head-yemens-presidential-council-tells-uae-leave</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Yomna Ehab and Nayera Abdallah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dec 30 (Reuters) - The head of Yemen's presidential council called on Tuesday for all United Arab Emirates forces to leave the country within 24 hours, shortly after an air strike by the Saudi-led coalition at the southern port of Mukalla.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The coalition said the strike targeted foreign military support for the UAE-backed southern separatists, whose offensive this month pitted the Southern Transitional Council (STC) against Saudi-supported Yemeni government troops, bringing the two Gulf allies closer than ever to an all-out conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 07:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey detains 110 suspects in operation targeting Islamic State after deadly clash</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-detains-110-suspects-operation-targeting-islamic-state-after-deadly-clash</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-detains-110-suspects-operation-targeting-islamic-state-after-deadly-clash</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Dec 30 (Reuters) - Turkish police detained 110 suspects in an operation against Islamic State on Tuesday, a day after three police officers and six militants were killed in a gunfight in northwest Turkey, the Istanbul chief prosecutor’s office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police conducted an eight-hour siege at a house in the town of Yalova, on the Sea of Marmara coast south of Istanbul, a week after more than 100 suspected IS members were detained in connection with alleged plans to carry out Christmas and New Year attacks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 06:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump, top aides asked Netanyahu to change policy in occupied West Bank, Axios says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/trump-top-aides-asked-netanyahu-change-policy-occupied-west-bank-axios-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/trump-top-aides-asked-netanyahu-change-policy-occupied-west-bank-axios-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 29 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trumpand his top advisers asked Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahuto change Israel's policies in the occupied West Bank during their meeting, Axios said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters could not immediately confirm the report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;International pressure has been mounting on Israel to curb settlers' attacks on Palestinians in the West Bank. Home to 2.7 million Palestinians, the West Bank has long been at the heart of plans for a future Palestinian state alongside Israel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 04:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia condemns 'dangerous' UAE moves in Yemen after striking shipment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-arabia-condemns-dangerous-uae-moves-yemen-after-striking-shipment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-arabia-condemns-dangerous-uae-moves-yemen-after-striking-shipment</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia declared a UAE-backed separatist advance in Yemen a threat to the kingdom's national security on Tuesday and called Abu Dhabi's actions "highly dangerous", as the rivalry between the Gulf monarchies boiled over into an open dispute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strongly worded foreign ministry statement came hours after the Saudi-led coalition fighting in Yemen said it had struck a United Arab Emirates weapons shipment destined for separatist forces.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 03:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pentagon announces $8.6 billion Boeing contract for F-15 jets for Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pentagon-announces-86-billion-boeing-contract-f-15-jets-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/pentagon-announces-86-billion-boeing-contract-f-15-jets-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Dec 29 (Reuters) - Boeing was given an $8.6 billion contract for the F-15 Israel Program, the Pentagon said on Monday, after U.S. President Donald Trump met Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu in Florida.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"This contract provides for the design, integration, instrumentation, test, production, and delivery of 25 new F-15IA aircraft for the Israeli Air Force with an option for an additional 25 F-15IA aircraft," the Pentagon said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 23:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>