<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Germany's Merz to visit Israel, meet PM Netanyahu</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/germanys-merz-visit-israel-meet-pm-netanyahu</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/germanys-merz-visit-israel-meet-pm-netanyahu</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN (Reuters) -German Chancellor Friedrich Merz will travel to Israel on December 6 and 7 for his first official visit since taking office, a German government spokesperson said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Merz is scheduled to meet Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on December 7 to discuss bilateral relations, the ceasefire in Gaza and other international issues, and will also visit the Yad Vashem memorial and hold talks with local representatives from society, the spokesperson added during a regular government press conference.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 12:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN condemns 'brazen' West Bank killings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-condemns-brazen-west-bank-killings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-condemns-brazen-west-bank-killings</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA (Reuters) -The U.N. human rights rights office said on Friday it was appalled by the killing of two Palestinian men by Israeli security forces in the occupied West Bank, saying the incident appeared to amount to summary executions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We're appalled by the brazen killing by Israeli border police yesterday of two Palestinian men in Jenin in the occupied West Bank in yet another apparent summary execution," Jeremy Laurence told a U.N. briefing in Geneva.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 11:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli forces kill 13 in southern Syria operation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-forces-kill-13-southern-syria-operation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-forces-kill-13-southern-syria-operation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli forces killed 13 people on Friday in an operation in southern Syria, the deadliest since Bashar al-Assad's fall from power nearly a year ago, which they said was targeting an Islamist group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since an Islamist coalition overthrew longtime ruler Assad in December of last year, Israel has conducted hundreds of strikes as well as incursions into Syria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli army said an exchange of fire in the operation to detain militants in the Syrian village of Beit Jin left six Israeli soldiers wounded, with three of them in a serious condition.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 11:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ten people killed during Israeli raid in southern Syria, Syrian state media reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ten-people-killed-during-israeli-raid-southern-syria-syrian-state-media-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ten-people-killed-during-israeli-raid-southern-syria-syrian-state-media-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/DAMASCUS (Reuters) -Ten people were killed by Israeli fire in a village in southern Syria on Friday, Syrian state media reported, while the Israeli military said five soldiers were wounded in a clash during an operation to apprehend members of a militant group there.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey not 'hostile' to Christians, Constantinople patriarch says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-not-hostile-christians-constantinople-patriarch-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-not-hostile-christians-constantinople-patriarch-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Muslim-majority Turkey, which is hosting Pope Leo XIV on his first overseas trip as pontiff, is not "a hostile environment" for Christians, the Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople told AFP in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It is simplistic to see adversaries everywhere and to imagine the pope's visit as taking sides in a hostile environment," said Patriarch Bartholomew I, leader of the world's 260 million Orthodox Christians.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 07:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo to meet Middle East Christian leaders in bid for unity</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-meet-middle-east-christian-leaders-bid-unity</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-meet-middle-east-christian-leaders-bid-unity</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -Pope Leo will meet in Turkey on Friday with Christian leaders from across the Middle East, and is expected to urge unity among denominations divided for centuries during his first overseas trip as leader of the global Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first U.S. pope will attend a celebration for the 1,700th anniversary of a landmark early Church council, held in modern Turkey. It produced the Nicene Creed, still used by most of the world's 2.6 billion Christians today.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 06:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>National Guard member dies as ambush in US capital becomes political flashpoint</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/national-guard-member-dies-ambush-us-capital-becomes-political-flashpoint</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/national-guard-member-dies-ambush-us-capital-becomes-political-flashpoint</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jeff Mason and Jasper Ward&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PALM BEACH, Florida/WASHINGTON (Reuters) -     A National Guard member died on Thursday after being shot near the White House in an ambush that investigators say was carried out by an Afghan national, an attack President Donald Trump blamed on Biden-era immigration vetting failures as he ordered a sweeping review of asylum cases.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 03:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli forces shoot dead two Palestinians apparently surrendering in West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-forces-shoot-dead-two-palestinians-apparently-surrendering-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-forces-shoot-dead-two-palestinians-apparently-surrendering-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Israeli army and police said Thursday they were investigating the circumstances in which two Palestinians were shot dead in the occupied West Bank while seemingly surrendering to Israeli forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The incident in Jenin in the northern West Bank, a stronghold of Palestinian armed groups, was filmed from several angles, including by AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian Authority named the two men killed as 37-year-old Yussef Ali Asa'sa and 26-year-old Al-Muntasir Billah Mahmud Abdullah.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 23:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli forces kill two Palestinians in West Bank who appeared to be surrendering</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-forces-kill-two-palestinians-west-bank-who-appeared-be-surrendering</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-forces-kill-two-palestinians-west-bank-who-appeared-be-surrendering</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ali Sawafta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JENIN (Reuters) -Israeli security forces shot two Palestinian men on Thursday who appeared to be surrendering and unarmed during a raid in the Israeli-occupied West Bank, Palestine TV news footage showed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the footage, the men are seen exiting a building surrounded by armed Israeli forces in the northern West Bank city of Jenin, lifting their shirts and lying on the ground in an apparent surrender. The forces then appeared to direct the men back inside the building before opening fire at close range.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 19:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ogier recovers in Rally Saudi Arabia to boost title hopes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ogier-recovers-rally-saudi-arabia-boost-title-hopes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ogier-recovers-rally-saudi-arabia-boost-title-hopes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sebastien Ogier bounced back from a mediocre first full day at the season-closing Rally Saudi Arabia to share the honours in Thursday's final stage and boost his hopes of landing a ninth World Rally Championship. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Frenchman, who described the conditions as "terrible", hit the same time as M-Sport Ford driver Martins Sesks in the final stage to close the day in seventh place overall, 44.2 seconds behind leader Adrien Fourmaux.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 19:30:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nobel winner says 'permanently' barred from leaving Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/nobel-winner-says-permanently-barred-leaving-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/nobel-winner-says-permanently-barred-leaving-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian Nobel Peace Prize winner Narges Mohammadi on Thursday said she was permanently barred from leaving Iran, in a birthday message to her teenage twins who she has not seen for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mohammadi, 53, had been in prison for over three years until her release in December last year for a limited period on medical leave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her legal team has warned she could be re-arrested and sent back to jail at any time, and she is not able to leave the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 19:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What we know about Afghan national suspected of shooting two Guardsmen near White House</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/what-we-know-about-afghan-national-suspected-shooting-two-guardsmen-near-white</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/what-we-know-about-afghan-national-suspected-shooting-two-guardsmen-near-white</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Julia Harte and Lucia Mutikani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-From battlefields in Afghanistan to a scenic home in the Pacific Northwest, Rahmanullah Lakanwal had followed a promising path before Wednesday, when U.S. authorities say he shottwo National Guard soldiers blocks from the White House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lakanwal, 29, drove across the country from his homein the state of Washington, said Jeanine Pirro, U.S. Attorney for Washington, D.C., at a news conference on Thursday. He lived in Bellingham, acoastal city near Canada's border, with his wife and five children.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 17:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Relaxed' Norris raring to go in Qatar after Las Vegas disqualification</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/relaxed-norris-raring-go-qatar-after-las-vegas-disqualification</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/relaxed-norris-raring-go-qatar-after-las-vegas-disqualification</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Lando Norris insisted Thursday he was feeling calm and composed ahead of the Qatar Grand Prix where he could win his first drivers' world championship title.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unperturbed by the double disqualification of himself and McLaren team-mate and title rival Oscar Piastri in Las Vegas last weekend, the 26-year-old Briton told reporters he was completely at ease ahead of this weekend's showdown. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I feel as relaxed now as I was before when I was 35 points behind and I feel the same when I'm 24 points ahead," Norris said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 17:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel launches new strikes in south Lebanon on ceasefire anniversary</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-new-strikes-south-lebanon-ceasefire-anniversary-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-new-strikes-south-lebanon-ceasefire-anniversary-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military carried out a fresh series of strikes against Hezbollah in southern Lebanon on Thursday, exactly a year into a ceasefire with the militant group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lebanon's state-run National News Agency said Israeli aircraft launched "a series of raids on Al-Mahmoudiya and Al-Jarmak", just north of the Litani River.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The November 27, 2024 ceasefire sought to end over a year of hostilities between the two sides.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 17:00:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sally Rooney says UK ban on Palestine Action could force her books off shelves</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sally-rooney-says-uk-ban-palestine-action-could-force-her-books-shelves</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sally-rooney-says-uk-ban-palestine-action-could-force-her-books-shelves</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON (Reuters) -Irish novelist Sally Rooney said Britain's decision to ban pro-Palestinian group Palestine Action as a terrorist organisation could stop her receiving royalties and even lead to her books being withdrawn from sale due to her support for the group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bestselling author said in a witness statement made public on Thursday, the second day of a legal bid to overturn the ban, that production company Element Pictures had expressed concern that paying her royalties could be a crime.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 15:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon slams Iran over Hezbollah comments as one-year ceasefire wobbles</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</guid><description>Relations between Iran and Lebanon have been strained since Hezbollah, Tehran’s main proxy in the region, emerged weakened from last year’s war with Israel.</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:32:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon slams Iran over Hezbollah comments as one-year ceasefire wobbles</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</guid><description>Relations between Iran and Lebanon have been strained since Hezbollah, Tehran’s main proxy in the region, emerged weakened from last year’s war with Israel.</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:32:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon slams Iran over Hezbollah comments as one-year ceasefire wobbles</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</guid><description>Relations between Iran and Lebanon have been strained since Hezbollah, Tehran’s main proxy in the region, emerged weakened from last year’s war with Israel.</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:32:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon slams Iran over Hezbollah comments as one-year ceasefire wobbles</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/lebanon-slams-iran-over-hezbollah-comments-one-year-ceasefire-wobbles</guid><description>Relations between Iran and Lebanon have been strained since Hezbollah, Tehran’s main proxy in the region, emerged weakened from last year’s war with Israel.</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:32:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel launches new strikes in south Lebanon on ceasefire anniversary</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-new-strikes-south-lebanon-ceasefire-anniversary</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-new-strikes-south-lebanon-ceasefire-anniversary</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military said it had carried out another series of strikes against Hezbollah in southern Lebanon on Thursday, exactly a year into the ceasefire with the militant group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lebanon's state-run National News Agency said Israeli aircraft launched "a series of raids on Al-Mahmoudiya and Al-Jarmak in the Jezzine area".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military "struck and dismantled Hezbollah terror infrastructure in several areas in southern Lebanon", it said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>