<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Somali regions reject Mogadishu's move to cut ties with UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/somali-regions-reject-mogadishus-move-cut-ties-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/somali-regions-reject-mogadishus-move-cut-ties-uae</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Giulia Paravicini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NAIROBI, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Three self-governing regions in Somalia that have close relations with the United Arab Emirates have dismissed a decision this week by the central government to sever ties with the UAE, a longterm sponsor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Monday Somalia annulled all agreements with the UAE, including in the field of security, accusing the Gulf country, which has trained and funded Somalia's army and invested in its ports, of undermining Somalia's national sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas to elect first leader since Sinwar killed by Israel, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/hamas-elect-first-leader-sinwar-killed-israel-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/hamas-elect-first-leader-sinwar-killed-israel-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Hamas is expected to elect a new leader this month, two sources in the group told Reuters, filling the role left vacant since Israel killed Yahya Sinwar in 2024 despite concerns that a successor could suffer the same fate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khalil Al-Hayya and Khaled Meshaal are seen as frontrunners for the helm at a vital moment for the militant Islamist group, battered by two years of war ignited by its October 7, 2023 attack on Israel and facing international demands to disarm.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran ex-empress urges security forces to join protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-ex-empress-urges-security-forces-join-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-ex-empress-urges-security-forces-join-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The former empress of Iran, widow of the shah deposed by the Islamic revolution, on Tuesday urged the Iranian security forces to support protests shaking the clerical leadership that ousted her husband.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Farah Pahlavi, 87, echoing calls made by her son the former crown prince Reza Pahlavi, said she believed "light will triumph over darkness" despite a crackdown by authorities that activists fear has left hundreds dead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU to 'swiftly' propose further sanctions on Iran, von der Leyen says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-swiftly-propose-further-sanctions-iran-von-der-leyen-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-swiftly-propose-further-sanctions-iran-von-der-leyen-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Jan 13 (Reuters) - The EU will "swiftly" propose further sanctions on those responsible for the repression of demonstrations in Iran, European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The rising number of casualties in Iran is horrifying. I unequivocally condemn the excessive use of force and continued restriction of freedom, " von der Leyen said on social media platform X.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Further sanctions on those responsible for the repression will be swiftly proposed."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Six dead as Gaza’s displaced struggle to hold ground in torrential rain</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/six-dead-gazas-displaced-struggle-hold-ground-torrential-rain</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/six-dead-gazas-displaced-struggle-hold-ground-torrential-rain</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Dawoud Abu Elkas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/GAZA, Jan 13 (Reuters) - A rainstorm swept across the Gaza Strip on Tuesday, flooding hundreds of tents, collapsing homes sheltering families displaced by two years of war and killing at least six people, local health officials said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medics said five people, including two women and a girl, died when homes collapsed near Gaza City’s beach, while a one-year-old boy died of extreme cold in a tent in Deir Al-Balah in central Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan 'lost all sources of revenue' in the war: finance minister to AFP</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudan-lost-all-sources-revenue-war-finance-minister-afp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudan-lost-all-sources-revenue-war-finance-minister-afp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Widespread destruction, massive military spending and plummeting oil and gold revenues have left Sudan's economy in "very difficult times", army-aligned finance minister Gibril Ibrahim said, nearly three years into the army's war with rival paramilitary forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with AFP from his office in Port Sudan, Ibrahim said the government is eyeing deals for Red Sea ports and private investment to help rebuild infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Why Iran’s clerical regime still holds as protests rage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-why-irans-clerical-regime-still-holds-protests-rage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-why-irans-clerical-regime-still-holds-protests-rage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Despite Iran's nationwide protests and years of external pressure, there are as yet no signs of fracture in the Islamic Republic's security elite that could bring an end to one of the world's most resilient regimes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adding to the stress on Iran's clerical rulers, U.S. President Donald Trump has repeatedly threatened military action over Tehran's severe crackdown on the protests, which follow an Israeli and U.S. bombing campaign last year against Iran's nuclear program and key officials.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN rights office says hundreds killed in Iran protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-office-says-hundreds-killed-iran-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-office-says-hundreds-killed-iran-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emma Farge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 13 (Reuters) - The U.N. human rights chief said on Tuesday that he was "horrified" by mounting violence by Iran's security forces against peaceful protesters, with the U.N. citing its own sources as saying that hundreds have been killed so far.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Islamic Republic's clerical authorities are facing the biggest demonstrations since 2022 and on Sunday a rights group said that unrest has killed more than 500 people. An Iranian official indicated on Tuesday it was higher, at around 2,000.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's Iran tariff threat risks reopening China rift</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-iran-tariff-threat-risks-reopening-china-rift</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-iran-tariff-threat-risks-reopening-china-rift</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joe Cash&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIJING, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Donald Trump's threat to slap a 25% tariff on countries that trade with Iran risks reopening old wounds with Beijing, Tehran's top partner, challenging Chinese leader Xi Jinping's global image and resolve to defend China's commercial interests.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Despite criticism, DJ priest hits a high note with some Lebanese</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/despite-criticism-dj-priest-hits-high-note-some-lebanese</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/despite-criticism-dj-priest-hits-high-note-some-lebanese</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Jan 13 (Reuters) - In a packed Beirut nightclub, electronic beats pulsed alongside projected videos of popes in white robes as Catholic priest Father Guilherme Peixoto spun tracks on the turntable.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The performance drew 2,000 attendees, but it also sparked opposition from some Christians in Lebanon, the first time the man known as Padre Guilherme to his 2.6 million Instagram followers says he has faced such vocal objection. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Over 100 children killed in Gaza since ceasefire, UNICEF says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/over-100-children-killed-gaza-ceasefire-unicef-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/over-100-children-killed-gaza-ceasefire-unicef-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 13 (Reuters) - The U.N. children's agency said on Tuesday that over 100 children have been killed in Gaza since the October ceasefire, including victims of drone and quadcopter attacks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“More than 100 children have been killed in Gaza since the ceasefire of early October," UNICEF spokesperson James Elder told reporters at a U.N. briefing by video link from Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Survival remains conditional, whilst the bombings and the shootings haveslowed, have reduced during the ceasefire, they have not stopped."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>About 2,000 killed in Iran protests, official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/about-2000-killed-iran-protests-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/about-2000-killed-iran-protests-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Around 2,000 people were killed in Iran protests, an Iranian official told Reuters on Tuesday, blaming "terrorists" for the deaths of civilians and security personnel. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian MP warns of greater unrest, urging government to address grievances</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-mp-warns-greater-unrest-urging-government-address-grievances</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-mp-warns-greater-unrest-urging-government-address-grievances</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 13 - An Iranian parliamentarian said on Tuesday the government will face even bigger protests unless it addresses people's grievances, after more than two weeks of nationwide demonstrations that have challenged the legitimacy of the country's clerical rulers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has responded to the wave of unrest over  dire economic conditions with a crackdown that a rights group says has killed hundreds and led to the arrest of thousands.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:01:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The West Bank soccer field slated for demolition by Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-soccer-field-slated-demolition-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-soccer-field-slated-demolition-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BETHLEHEM, West Bank, Jan 12 (Reuters) - Israeli authorities have ordered the demolition of a soccer field in a crowded refugee camp in the occupied West Bank, eliminating one of the few spaces where Palestinian children are able to run and play.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"If the field gets demolished, this will destroy our dreams and our future. We cannot play any other place but this field, the camp does not have spaces," said Rital Sarhan, 13, who plays on a girls' soccer team in the Aida refugee camp near Bethlehem.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:01:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Somaliland: Horn of Africa territory at heart of geopolitical scramble</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/somaliland-horn-africa-territory-heart-geopolitical-scramble</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/somaliland-horn-africa-territory-heart-geopolitical-scramble</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Since Israel recognised Somaliland last month, the self-declared republic on the Gulf of Aden has become central to a struggle over military access, ports and regional influence across the Red Sea corridor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somaliland sits astride one of the world's most strategic maritime choke points, flanked by multiple conflicts in the Horn of Africa and the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It declared independence from Somalia in 1991 but had never been recognised internationally until Israel's move.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump hits Iran trade partners with tariffs as protest toll soars</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-hits-iran-trade-partners-tariffs-protest-toll-soars</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-hits-iran-trade-partners-tariffs-protest-toll-soars</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump announced a 25-percent tariff on any country doing business with Iran, ramping up pressure as a rights group estimated a crackdown on protests has killed at least 648 people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian authorities insisted they have regained control after successive nights of mass protests nationwide since Thursday that have posed one of the biggest challenges to the clerical leadership since the 1979 Islamic revolution ousted the shah.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's leadership is in its 'final days and weeks', Germany's Merz says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-leadership-its-final-days-and-weeks-germanys-merz-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-leadership-its-final-days-and-weeks-germanys-merz-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BENGALURU, Jan 13 (Reuters) - German Chancellor Friedrich Merz said on Tuesday he assumes Iran's leadership is in its "final days and weeks" as it faces widespread protests. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demonstrations in Iran have evolved from complaints about dire economic hardships to calls for the fall of the clerical establishment in the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I assume that we are now witnessing the final days and weeks of this regime," Merz said during a trip to India, questioning the Iranian leadership's legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In 'big trouble'? The factors determining Iran's future</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/big-trouble-factors-determining-irans-future</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/big-trouble-factors-determining-irans-future</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Over two weeks of protests mark the most serious challenge in years to Iran's theocratic leadership in their scale and nature but it is too early to predict the immediate demise of the Islamic republic, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The demonstrations moved from protesting economic grievances to demanding a wholesale change from the clerical system that has ruled Iran since the 1979 revolution that ousted the shah. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 03:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian writers festival in turmoil over decision to bar Palestinian author</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/australian-writers-festival-turmoil-over-decision-bar-palestinian-author</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/australian-writers-festival-turmoil-over-decision-bar-palestinian-author</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kirsty Needham&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Jan 13 (Reuters) - The director of one of Australia's top writers festivals resigned on Tuesday saying she could not be party to silencing a Palestinian author and warning government moves to ban protests and slogans in the aftermath of the Bondi mass shooting threatened free speech.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 01:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump has options on Iran, but first must define goal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-has-options-iran-first-must-define-goal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-has-options-iran-first-must-define-goal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump has options to intervene in protest-hit Iran that range from low to high risk, but choosing his course depends on him deciding his ultimate goal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been 10 days since Trump said the United States was "locked and loaded" and ready to "come to the rescue" if Iran's clerical state kills demonstrators who have taken to the streets in major numbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since then, Trump has kept threatening a military option, even as hundreds of people have died, according to rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 23:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>