<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Syrian security forces use gunfire to disperse rival protests in Alawite heartland</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrian-security-forces-use-gunfire-disperse-rival-protests-alawite-heartland</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrian-security-forces-use-gunfire-disperse-rival-protests-alawite-heartland</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LATAKIA, Syria (Reuters) -Syrian security forces used gunfire on Tuesday to break up two rival groups of demonstrators in the coastal town of Latakia, heartland of the country's Alawite minority, witnesses and officials said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syria has been rocked by several episodes of sectarian violence since longtime leader Bashar al-Assad, who hails from the Muslim Alawite minority, was ousted by a rebel offensive last year and replaced by a Sunni-led government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 15:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Floods swamp homeless Palestinians' tents in Gaza as winter looms</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/floods-swamp-homeless-palestinians-tents-gaza-winter-looms</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/floods-swamp-homeless-palestinians-tents-gaza-winter-looms</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GAZA/CAIRO (Reuters) -Heavy rain caused flooding in the Gaza Strip on Tuesday, swamping the tents of thousands of homeless Palestinians facing the prospect of harsh winter storms without sturdy shelter. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The large majority of Gaza's 2 million people were forced from their homes during Israel's two-year ground and air war in the small, crowded enclave triggered by Hamas' October 2023 attack, with many now living in tents and other basic shelters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 14:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians protest after attacks on Alawite minority</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrians-protest-after-attacks-alawite-minority</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrians-protest-after-attacks-alawite-minority</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of people demonstrated on Tuesday across Syria's coastal Alawite heartland in protest against recent attacks targeting the minority community, AFP correspondents said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests are the biggest in the Alawite region since the fall last December of longtime Syrian ruler Bashar al-Assad, who hails from the community, following an Islamist-led offensive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since then, the community has been the target of attacks, and hundreds of people were killed in sectarian massacres in the area in March.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 13:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan's warring factions have not yet accepted peace plan, Trump advisor says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudans-warring-factions-have-not-yet-accepted-peace-plan-trump-advisor-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudans-warring-factions-have-not-yet-accepted-peace-plan-trump-advisor-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Federico Maccioni&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ABU DHABI (Reuters) -The United States presented the warring Sudanese army and paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) with a strong text for a peace plan but neither side has accepted it, senior U.S. envoy Massad Boulos said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump said last week he would intervene to stop the devastating conflict, which broke out in April 2023 and has spread famine and ethnic killings across the country and threatened a split, the second in its history.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 11:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli strikes have killed at least 127 civilians in Lebanon since ceasefire, UN says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-strikes-have-killed-least-127-civilians-lebanon-ceasefire-un-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-strikes-have-killed-least-127-civilians-lebanon-ceasefire-un-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA (Reuters) -The U.N. human rights office said on Tuesday that at least 127 civilians had been killed in Lebanon in strikes by the Israel military since a ceasefire nearly a year ago, and called for an investigation and for the truce to be respected.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 10:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE's Gargash welcomes US efforts to end Sudan war, condemns atrocities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uaes-gargash-welcomes-us-efforts-end-sudan-war-condemns-atrocities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uaes-gargash-welcomes-us-efforts-end-sudan-war-condemns-atrocities</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ABU DHABI (Reuters) -Anwar Gargash, the diplomatic adviser to the United Arab Emirates' president, said on Tuesday the UAE welcomed U.S.  efforts to end war in Sudan and condemned "atrocities" committed by both Sudan's army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump said on Wednesday he would work to help end the war in Sudan after Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman asked him to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Federico Maccioni, Writing by Ahmed Elimam, editing by Andrew Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 10:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghanistan says 9 children killed in Pakistani air strikes, vows to respond</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-says-9-children-killed-pakistani-air-strikes-vows-respond</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/afghanistan-says-9-children-killed-pakistani-air-strikes-vows-respond</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Afghanistan's Taliban administration said on Tuesday that nine children and a woman were killed in Pakistani air strikes and vowed to respond, ratcheting up tensions between the South Asian neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bombardment overnight reported by Kabul followed a series of attacks in Pakistan that Islamabad blames on militants based in Afghanistan. Pakistan did not immediately respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 10:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinians fear new Israeli settlement will wreck their town</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinians-fear-new-israeli-settlement-will-wreck-their-town</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinians-fear-new-israeli-settlement-will-wreck-their-town</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a town near Jerusalem, a growing number of houses and businesses are receiving demolition and evacuation notices, and Palestinian residents link the drive to Israel's approval of a major new settlement project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"This is a project of total destruction for the economy and the people. It will affect everyone," said Yahya Abu Ghaliyeh, whose home in Al-Eizariya town was demolished by Israeli authorities earlier this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, the 37-year-old's car wash business is also due for demolition.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 10:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As it prepares for Hezbollah’s retaliation, Israel anticipates limited fighting in Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</guid><description>After Israel killed Hezbollah military commander Ali Tabatabai, the militant group faces demands for retaliation from its base.</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 09:26:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As it prepares for Hezbollah’s retaliation, Israel anticipates limited fighting in Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</guid><description>After Israel killed Hezbollah military commander Ali Tabatabai, the militant group faces demands for retaliation from its base.</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 09:26:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As it prepares for Hezbollah’s retaliation, Israel anticipates limited fighting in Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</guid><description>After Israel killed Hezbollah military commander Ali Tabatabai, the militant group faces demands for retaliation from its base.</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 09:26:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As it prepares for Hezbollah’s retaliation, Israel anticipates limited fighting in Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/it-prepares-hezbollahs-retaliation-israel-anticipates-limited-fighting-lebanon</guid><description>After Israel killed Hezbollah military commander Ali Tabatabai, the militant group faces demands for retaliation from its base.</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 09:26:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian economy suffers worst-ever collapse after Israel-Hamas conflict, UN says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-economy-suffers-worst-ever-collapse-after-israel-hamas-conflict-un</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-economy-suffers-worst-ever-collapse-after-israel-hamas-conflict-un</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA (Reuters) -The two-year Gaza war and economic restrictions have triggered an unprecedented collapse in the Palestinian economy, wiping out decades of growth, a United Nations report said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Extensive damage to infrastructure, productive assets and public services has reversed decades of socioeconomic progress in the Occupied Palestinian Territory," according to the report by the United Nations trade and development agency (UNCTAD).&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 09:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US Army Secretary Driscoll meets Russian delegation in Abu Dhabi, official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-army-secretary-driscoll-meets-russian-delegation-abu-dhabi-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-army-secretary-driscoll-meets-russian-delegation-abu-dhabi-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -U.S. Army Secretary Dan Driscoll held talks with Russian officials in Abu Dhabi on Monday, a U.S. official told Reuters, the latest effort by President Donald Trump's administration to broker a peace agreement between Russia and Ukraine. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting comes after U.S. and Ukrainian officials sought to narrow the gaps between them over a plan to end the war in Ukraine, agreeing to modify a U.S. proposal that Kyiv and its European allies saw as a Kremlin wish list.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 08:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-Why are tensions flaring again between Afghanistan and Pakistan?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/explainer-why-are-tensions-flaring-again-between-afghanistan-and-pakistan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/explainer-why-are-tensions-flaring-again-between-afghanistan-and-pakistan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saeed  Shah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD (Reuters) -Tensions flared between Afghanistan and Pakistan on Tuesday as the Taliban accused Pakistani forces of air strikes in eastern Afghanistan, which killed 9 children and a woman, and injured four others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no immediate comment from Islamabad. The bombardment followed a series of recent attacks in Pakistan, in which Islamabad says the militants came from Afghanistan. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 08:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-From Paul VI to Leo XIV: A history of the pope's overseas tours</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/factbox-paul-vi-leo-xiv-history-popes-overseas-tours</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/factbox-paul-vi-leo-xiv-history-popes-overseas-tours</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VATICAN CITY (Reuters) -Pope Leo will embark on his first trip outside Italy on Thursday, travelling to Turkey and Lebanon. Here is a history of papal foreign visits, which have become a major part of the agenda for the leader of the world's 1.4 billion Catholics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;POPE PAUL VI (1963 to 1978)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 08:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo to take peace message to Turkey, Lebanon on first overseas trip</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-take-peace-message-turkey-lebanon-first-overseas-trip</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-take-peace-message-turkey-lebanon-first-overseas-trip</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VATICAN CITY (Reuters) -Pope Leo will embark on his first trip outside Italy as the leader of the Catholic Church on Thursday, travelling to Turkey and Lebanon, where he is expected to make appeals for peace in the region and urge unity among long-divided Christian churches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leo, the first U.S. pope, will give his first speeches to foreign governments and visit some sensitive cultural sites as part of a crowded itinerary during the November 27 to December 2 trip.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 08:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At tomb of Lebanon's miracle saint, faithful await the pope</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tomb-lebanons-miracle-saint-faithful-await-pope</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tomb-lebanons-miracle-saint-faithful-await-pope</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Charbel Matar says a Lebanese saint saved his life when he was a child. Now, he is among pilgrims of all faiths who visit Saint Charbel's tomb, soon to be graced by Pope Leo XIV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"My family and I have great faith in Saint Charbel and always visit him," said Matar, 69, at the Saint Maron Monastery in Annaya in the mountains of north Lebanon. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I almost died when I was five. He performed a miracle and saved me from death, and kept me alive for 64 more years," said Matar, whose parents changed his name from Roger to Charbel to honour the saint.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 06:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas attack victims sue Binance for allegedly allowing payments to militant group</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-attack-victims-sue-binance-allegedly-allowing-payments-militant-group</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-attack-victims-sue-binance-allegedly-allowing-payments-militant-group</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Stempel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Victims of Hamas' October 2023 attack on Israel sued Binance and its founder Changpeng Zhao, accusing them of facilitating millions of dollars in payments to the group and other U.S.-designated terrorist groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a complaint made public on Monday, the world's largest cryptocurrency exchange laundered money for Hamas even after pleading guilty in November 2023 and paying a $4.32 billion criminal penalty for violating federal anti-money-laundering and sanctions laws.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 21:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump administration to consider whether to label Muslim Brotherhood chapters as terrorist</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-administration-consider-whether-label-muslim-brotherhood-chapters-terrorist</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-administration-consider-whether-label-muslim-brotherhood-chapters-terrorist</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -President Donald Trump on Monday signed an executive order directing his administration to determine whether to designate certain chapters of the Muslim Brotherhood, such as those in Lebanon, Egypt, and Jordan, as foreign terrorist organizations and specially-designated global terrorists, the White House said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"President Trump is confronting the Muslim Brotherhood’s transnational network, which fuels terrorism and destabilization campaigns against U.S. interests and allies in the Middle East," according to a White house fact sheet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 21:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>