<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Syria deal could remove main obstacle to Turkey-PKK peace, Turkish officials say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-deal-could-remove-main-obstacle-turkey-pkk-peace-turkish-officials-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-deal-could-remove-main-obstacle-turkey-pkk-peace-turkish-officials-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ece Toksabay and Daren Butler&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Jan 19 (Reuters) - A deal under which Kurdish forces abandoned long-held territory in Syria to the Syrian government could pave the way for Turkey to advance its stalled effort to end its decades-long conflict with the PKK, Turkish politicians and officials said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Trump's 'Board of Peace'?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/what-trumps-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/what-trumps-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump's government has asked countries to pay $1 billion for a permanent spot on his "Board of Peace" aimed at resolving conflicts, according to its charter seen by AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The board was originally conceived to oversee the rebuilding of war-torn Gaza, but the charter does not appear to limit its role to the occupied Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What exactly will it do? And who has been invited?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- To what end? -&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace will be chaired by Trump, according to its founding charter.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian army deploys in former Kurdish-held areas under ceasefire deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-deploys-former-kurdish-held-areas-under-ceasefire-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-deploys-former-kurdish-held-areas-under-ceasefire-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria's army deployed in formerly Kurdish-led areas in the country's east and north on Monday after a ceasefire announced a day earlier, as Syria's president and the Kurds' leader were set to hold talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The leader of the Syrian Kurdish forces said Sunday he agreed to the deal with Damascus to avoid broader war, integrating the Kurds' administration and his fighters into the state after months of stalled negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurdish-led force says armed group attacks Syria prison holding thousands of Islamic State members</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-led-force-says-armed-group-attacks-syria-prison-holding-thousands-islamic</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-led-force-says-armed-group-attacks-syria-prison-holding-thousands-islamic</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 19 (Reuters) - The Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces said on Monday that an "armed group" was attacking Shaddadi prison in Hasaka in Syria's northeast where it said thousands of Islamic State militants were being held.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SDF had said earlier in the day it was clashing with Syrian government forces near Al-Aqtan prison on the outskirts of the city of Raqqa that also held IS detainees. Raqqa was once the seat of a short-lived IS-declared "caliphate" in the region.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 13:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump to charge $1bn for permanent 'peace board' membership</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-charge-1bn-permanent-peace-board-membership</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-charge-1bn-permanent-peace-board-membership</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump's government has asked countries to pay $1.0 billion for a permanent spot on his "Board of Peace" aimed at resolving conflicts, according to its charter, seen Monday by AFP. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White House has asked various world leaders to sit on the board, chaired by Trump himself, including Russian President Vladimir Putin, Hungarian premier Viktor Orban and Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 13:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemen humanitarian crisis to worsen in 2026 amid funding cuts, says UN</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemen-humanitarian-crisis-worsen-2026-amid-funding-cuts-says-un</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemen-humanitarian-crisis-worsen-2026-amid-funding-cuts-says-un</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 19 (Reuters) - The U.N. warned on Monday that the humanitarian situation in Yemen is worsening and that gains made to tackle malnutrition and health would go into reverse due to funding cuts.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The context is very concerning... We are expecting things to be much worse in 2026," Julien Harneis, U.N. Resident and Humanitarian Coordinator for Yemen, told reporters in Geneva.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Influential Israeli minister Smotrich calls for US-led centre for Gaza to be shuttered</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/influential-israeli-minister-smotrich-calls-us-led-centre-gaza-be-shuttered</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/influential-israeli-minister-smotrich-calls-us-led-centre-gaza-be-shuttered</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 19 (Reuters) - Israeli Finance Minister Bezalel Smotrich urged Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on Monday to shut a U.S.-led multinational coordinating centre that supports President Donald Trump’s plan to end the Gaza war. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washington established the Civil Military Coordination Centre (CMCC) last October as a centre for civilian and military personnel from other countries to work alongside U.S. and Israeli officials on post-war Gaza planning.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian troops consolidate hold after abrupt Kurdish withdrawal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-troops-consolidate-hold-after-abrupt-kurdish-withdrawal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-troops-consolidate-hold-after-abrupt-kurdish-withdrawal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Karam al-Masri  and Khalil Ashawi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;RAQQA/ Syria, Jan 19 (Reuters) - Syrian government troops tightened their grip on Monday across a swathe of northern and eastern territory abruptly abandoned the previous day by Kurdish forces, in a dramatic shift that consolidated President Ahmed al-Sharaa's rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After days of fighting with government forces, the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF), once the main U.S. allies in Syria, agreed on Sunday to withdraw from two Arab-majority provinces they had controlled for years, including oil fields.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran to consider lifting internet ban; state TV hacked</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-consider-lifting-internet-ban-state-tv-hacked</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-consider-lifting-internet-ban-state-tv-hacked</guid><description>Iran will decide on restoring internet in the coming days, with service resuming "as soon as security conditions are appropriate".</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey sees Syria–Kurdish forces deal as "historic turning point", security sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-sees-syria-kurdish-forces-deal-historic-turning-point-security-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-sees-syria-kurdish-forces-deal-historic-turning-point-security-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 19 (Reuters) - Turkish security sources said on Monday that an integration deal between Syria's government and Kurdish forces marked an "historic turning point" ahead of which Turkey's intelligence agency played an intensive role to ensure restraint by parties on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fight against Islamic State in Syria would continue uninterrupted, the sources said, adding that establishing stability and security in Syria was critically important for Turkey's goal of eliminating terrorism at home.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Khartoum markets back to life but 'nothing like before'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/khartoum-markets-back-life-nothing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/khartoum-markets-back-life-nothing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The hustle and bustle of buyers and sellers has returned to Khartoum's central market, but "it's nothing like before", fruit vendor Hashim Mohamed told AFP, streets away from where war first broke out nearly three years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On April 15, 2023, central Khartoum awoke to battles between the Sudanese army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF), who had been allies since 2021, when they ousted civilians from a short-lived transitional government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their war has since killed tens of thousands and displaced millions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President of Kazakhstan to join Donald Trump's 'Board of Peace,' spokesperson says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/president-kazakhstan-join-donald-trumps-board-peace-spokesperson-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/president-kazakhstan-join-donald-trumps-board-peace-spokesperson-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tamara Vaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ASTANA, Jan 19 (Reuters) - Kazakh President Kassym-Jomart Tokayev will join the "Board of Peace" proposed by U.S. President Donald Trump after accepting an invitation to do so and wants to contribute to bringing about a stable Middle East peace, his spokesperson said on Monday.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The board would be chaired for life by Trump and would start by addressing the Gaza conflict and then be expanded to deal with other conflicts, according to a copy of the letter and draft charter seen by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands march in US to back Iranian anti-government protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-march-us-back-iranian-anti-government-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-march-us-back-iranian-anti-government-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands in the United States staged large demonstrations Sunday denouncing the Iranian government's deadly crackdown on anti-government protesters in the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several thousand people marched in Los Angeles, home to the world's largest Iranian diaspora, while several hundred others gathered in New York, AFP journalists in both cities reported. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US protesters could be seen carrying signs condemning a "New Holocaust," a "genocide in the making," and the "terror" of the Iranian government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian president cancels Germany visit, Merz meeting</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-president-cancels-germany-visit-merz-meeting</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-president-cancels-germany-visit-merz-meeting</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 18 (Reuters) - Syria's President Ahmed al-Sharaa has cancelled his visit to Berlin on Monday and Tuesday, a German government spokesperson told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al-Sharaa had been scheduled to meet with German Chancellor Friedrich Merz and President Frank-Walter Steinmeier. Talks with German business leaders were also planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ceasefire was agreed on Sunday after days of fierce clashes between Syrian government troops and U.S.-backed Kurdish fighters.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Andreas Rinke, Writing by Rachel More, Editing by Alexander Smith)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 19:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>India gets Trump's invite to join Board of Peace on Gaza, source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/india-gets-trumps-invite-join-board-peace-gaza-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/india-gets-trumps-invite-join-board-peace-gaza-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;NEW DELHI, Jan 18 (Reuters) - India has received an invitation from U.S. President Donald Trump to join his "Board of Peace" initiative that is aimed at resolving global conflicts, beginning with Gaza, a senior Indian government official said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was not clear whether India would join the initiative. Its foreign ministry did not immediately respond to a request for comment.  &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 17:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian government, SDF agree on immediate ceasefire on all fronts, state media say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-sdf-agree-immediate-ceasefire-all-fronts-state-media-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-sdf-agree-immediate-ceasefire-all-fronts-state-media-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 18 (Reuters) - The Syrian government and the U.S.-backed Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF) have agreed on an immediate ceasefire on all fronts, Syrian state media reported on Sunday, after days of fighting as the army advanced into Kurdish-held territories in the northeast.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Jaidaa Taha and Ahmed Tolba, Editing by Louise Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 16:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bowing to US pressure, Syrian military advances, Kurdish-led SDF agrees to Sharaa's terms</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bowing-us-pressure-syrian-military-advances-kurdish-led-sdf-agrees-sharaas-terms</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bowing-us-pressure-syrian-military-advances-kurdish-led-sdf-agrees-sharaas-terms</guid><description>Syrian government forces rapidly retook Raqqa and key eastern territories from the US-backed SDF, prompting a ceasefire agreement that effectively restores Damascus’s control over much of Syria’s oil-rich northeast.</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:39:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurdish commander calls on US to 'intervene forcefully' in Syria clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-commander-calls-us-intervene-forcefully-syria-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-commander-calls-us-intervene-forcefully-syria-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Feras Dalatey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS, Jan 18 (Reuters) - The U.S. should intervene more forcefully to end a Syrian offensive that has gained key territory from Kurdish fighters in recent days, the head of the main Kurdish forces told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government troops launched an offensive on Saturday into territory run for the last decade by semi-autonomous Kurdish authorities in the northeast of Syria, capturing towns on both sides of the Euphrates River as well asthe country's largest oilfield and a gas field, officials and security sources said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian forces advance deeper into the US‑backed, Kurdish‑controlled northeast</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-advance-deeper-us-backed-kurdish-controlled-northeast</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-advance-deeper-us-backed-kurdish-controlled-northeast</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mahmoud Hasano and Khalil Ashawi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TABQA, Jan 18 (Reuters) - Syrian government troops are pushing towards Raqqa and Hasakah in the northeast of the country, the last strongholds of the U.S.-backed autonomous Kurdish-led administration, government officials and security sources said on Sunday.    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They had earlier taken control of the Deir al-Zor's main oil and gas fields east of the Euphrates River — a key source of revenue for the Kurdish-led forces — dealing a major blow to the group.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World leaders show caution on Trump's broader 'board of peace' amid fears for U.N</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/world-leaders-show-caution-trumps-broader-board-peace-amid-fears-un</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/world-leaders-show-caution-trumps-broader-board-peace-amid-fears-un</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By John Irish and Andreas Rinke&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 18 (Reuters) - Governments reacted cautiously on Sunday to U.S. President Donald Trump's invitation to join his "Board of Peace" initiative aimed at resolving conflicts globally, a plan that diplomats said could harm the work of the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only Hungary, whose leader is a close Trump ally, gave an unequivocal acceptance in response to the invitations, which have been addressed to some 60 nations and began arriving in European capitals on Saturday, according to diplomats.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>