<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Explainer-What's next for Trump's Gaza plan after Rafah reopening?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/explainer-whats-next-trumps-gaza-plan-after-rafah-reopening</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/explainer-whats-next-trumps-gaza-plan-after-rafah-reopening</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 2 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the Gaza war was given a boost on Monday with the reopening of the enclave's Rafah crossing with Egypt. But difficult questions remain unaddressed, including whether Hamas will disarm. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump's plan, now in its second phase, has been shaken by repeated Israeli attacks that have killed hundreds in Gaza, as well as resistance by Hamas militants to lay down their weapons. Israeli officials say they are preparing for a return to war if Hamas refuses to disarm. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 08:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran examines diplomacy with US, hopes for results in coming days, official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-examines-diplomacy-us-hopes-results-coming-days-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-examines-diplomacy-us-hopes-results-coming-days-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 2 (Reuters) - Details of various diplomatic processes to manage tensions with the U.S. are being examined by Iran, Iranian foreign ministry spokesperson Esmaeil Baghaei said on Monday, adding that Tehran hoped for results in the coming days. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid a military buildup by the U.S. Navy near Iran, U.S. President Donald Trump told reporters last week that Iran was "seriously talking" with Washington, hours after Tehran's top security official Ali Larijani said on X that arrangements for negotiations were underway.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 08:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel expected to reopen Gaza's Rafah border crossing to Egypt, with limits</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-expected-reopen-gazas-rafah-border-crossing-egypt-limits</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-expected-reopen-gazas-rafah-border-crossing-egypt-limits</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Haseeb Alwazeer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAZA, Feb 2 (Reuters) - Israel was expected to reopen the border between Gaza and Egypt on Monday for people on foot, a move that would allow Palestinians to leave the enclave and let back in those who want to return after fleeing Israel's war in the enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reopening of the Rafah border crossing will be limited, with Israel demanding security checks for Palestinians entering and exiting. Israel and Egypt were expected to impose caps on the number of travellers. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 07:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia does not want a global conflict, Medvedev says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-does-not-want-global-conflict-medvedev-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-does-not-want-global-conflict-medvedev-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Guy Faulconbridge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 2 (Reuters) - Dmitry Medvedev, a senior Kremlin security official, said in remarks released for publication on Monday that the world was getting very dangerous, but that Russia did not want a global conflict.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia's 2022 invasion of Ukraine triggered the biggest confrontation between the West and Moscow since the depths of the Cold War, though U.S. President Donald Trump's envoys are trying to negotiate an end to the war with Russia and Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 06:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Top US, Israeli generals meet at Pentagon amid soaring Iran tensions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/top-us-israeli-generals-meet-pentagon-amid-soaring-iran-tensions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/top-us-israeli-generals-meet-pentagon-amid-soaring-iran-tensions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 1 (Reuters)  - The top U.S. and Israeli generals held talks at the Pentagon on Friday amid soaring tensions with Iran, two U.S. officials told Reuters on Sunday, speaking on condition of anonymity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The officials did not offer details about the closed-door discussions between U.S. General Dan Caine, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and Eyal Zamir, the Israeli armed forces chief of staff. The meeting has not been previously reported.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 17:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelenskiy says new trilateral talks set for Feb 4-5 in Abu Dhabi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/zelenskiy-says-new-trilateral-talks-set-feb-4-5-abu-dhabi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/zelenskiy-says-new-trilateral-talks-set-feb-4-5-abu-dhabi</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Feb 1 (Reuters) - A new round of U.S.-brokered trilateral talks between Ukraine and Russia will take place in Abu Dhabi on Feb. 4 and 5, Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said on Sunday, adding that Kyiv was ready for a "substantive discussion".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Our negotiating team has just delivered a report. The dates for the next trilateral meetings have been set – February 4 and 5 in Abu Dhabi," he wrote on X.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Ukraine is ready for a substantive discussion, and we are interested in ensuring that the outcome brings us closer to a real and dignified end to the war."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 11:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan forces kill 145 militants after attacks in Balochistan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pakistan-forces-kill-145-militants-after-attacks-balochistan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pakistan-forces-kill-145-militants-after-attacks-balochistan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt; (Corrects to add missing word in headline)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Ariba Shahid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KARACHI, Feb 1 (Reuters) - Pakistan's security forces killed 145 militants over 40 hours after coordinated attacks across Balochistan, the chief minister of the southwestern province said on Sunday, as the authorities battle one of the deadliest flare-ups in years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The attacks underscore the persistence of insurgents in the resource-rich province bordering Iran and Afghanistan, where separatist militant groups have stepped up assaults on security forces, civilians and infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Preparations underway for full reopening of Gaza's Rafah crossing, officials say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/preparations-underway-full-reopening-gazas-rafah-crossing-officials-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/preparations-underway-full-reopening-gazas-rafah-crossing-officials-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maayan Lubell and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/CAIRO Feb 1 (Reuters) - Preparations to reopen Gaza's main border crossing in Rafah were underway on Sunday though it was uncertain any Palestinians would pass through it before the day's end, Israeli and Palestinian officials said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the war, the Rafah border crossing with Egypt was the only direct exit point for most Palestinians in Gaza to reach the outside world as well as a key entry point for aid into the territory. It has been largely shut since May 2024. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tehran warns of regional conflict if US attacks Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tehran-warns-regional-conflict-if-us-attacks-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tehran-warns-regional-conflict-if-us-attacks-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 1 (Reuters) - Iran's Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei said that if the U.S. attacked Iran it would become a regional conflict, state media reported on Sunday, amid heightened tensions between Washington and Tehran.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. has built up its naval presence in the Middle East  after President Donald Trump repeatedly threatened Iran with intervention if it did not agree to a nuclear deal or failed to stop killing protesters. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-US special envoy for Iraq Mark Savaya no longer in the post, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-us-special-envoy-iraq-mark-savaya-no-longer-post-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-us-special-envoy-iraq-mark-savaya-no-longer-post-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Andrea Shalal, Timour Azhari and Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/RIYADH, Jan 31 (Reuters) - Mark Savaya, named by U.S. President Donald Trump as special envoy for Iraq in October, is no longer in that role, sources familiar with the move said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move comes amid growing tensions between Washington and Baghdad over Washington's push to curb Iranian influence in Iraqi politics.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 07:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump hopeful of Iran deal after Tehran warns of regional war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-hopeful-iran-deal-after-tehran-warns-regional-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-hopeful-iran-deal-after-tehran-warns-regional-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump on Sunday said he was hopeful of agreeing a deal with Iran after the country's supreme leader warned that any US attack on the Islamic republic would trigger a regional war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the Iranian authorities' deadly response to anti-government protests that peaked last month, Trump has threatened military action and ordered the dispatch of an aircraft carrier group to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian supreme leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei on Sunday likened the recent protests to a "coup", warning that a US attack would trigger a broad conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 07:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran considers EU armies as 'terrorist groups' in retaliatory move</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-considers-eu-armies-terrorist-groups-retaliatory-move</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-considers-eu-armies-terrorist-groups-retaliatory-move</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 1 (Reuters) - Iran considers as "terrorist groups" the armies of EU countries that listed the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps on the bloc's list of terrorist organisations, Parliament Speaker Mohammad Baqer Qalibaf said on Sunday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU marked a symbolic shift in its approach to Iran's leadership on Thursday by designating the Revolutionary Guards as a terrorist organisation, following what turned out to be the Islamic Republic's bloodiest crackdown of protests since its establishment in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 07:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says partially reopening Gaza's Rafah crossing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-says-partially-reopening-gazas-rafah-crossing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-says-partially-reopening-gazas-rafah-crossing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel partially reopened the Rafah crossing between the devastated Gaza Strip and Egypt on Sunday, following months of appeals from aid groups, though access is limited to pedestrians.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;COGAT, the Israeli defence ministry body coordinating Palestinian civilian affairs, made no mention of allowing in a long hoped-for surge of aid, and clarified that the passage of individuals through the gateway in both directions was expected to begin Monday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 03:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Sudan's old port of Suakin, dreams of a tourism revival</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudans-old-port-suakin-dreams-tourism-revival</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudans-old-port-suakin-dreams-tourism-revival</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The mayor of Suakin dreams of a rebirth for his town, an ancient Red Sea port spared by the wars that have marked Sudan's history but reduced to ruins by the ravages of time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was called the 'White City'," for its unique buildings made of coral stone taken from the seabed, said mayor Abu Mohamed El-Amin Artega, who is also the leader of the Artega tribe, part of eastern Sudan's Beja ethnic group.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 02:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Qatari PM meets Iran's Larijani in Tehran, discusses easing regional tensions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/qatari-pm-meets-irans-larijani-tehran-discusses-easing-regional-tensions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/qatari-pm-meets-irans-larijani-tehran-discusses-easing-regional-tensions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 31 (Reuters) - Qatari Prime Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman al-Thani met with top Iranian security official Ali Larijani in Tehran and reviewed efforts to de-escalate tensions in the region, Qatar's foreign ministry said on Saturday in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Hatem Maher; Writing by Enas Alashray; editing by Diane Craft)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 21:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq's Shi'ite bloc reaffirms backing for Maliki despite Trump's warnings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraqs-shiite-bloc-reaffirms-backing-maliki-despite-trumps-warnings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraqs-shiite-bloc-reaffirms-backing-maliki-despite-trumps-warnings</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 31 (Reuters) - Iraq's alliance of Shi'ite political blocs, the Coordination Framework, reaffirmed on Saturday its support for former premier Nouri al-Maliki to lead the next government, despite a warning from U.S. President Donald Trump that Washington would no longer help Iraq if Maliki returned to power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bloc, which holds a majority in parliament, picked Maliki, Iraq's first elected prime minister after a U.S.-led invasion toppled Saddam Hussein in 2003, as its nominee for the post following an election.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 20:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan says 92 militants killed after attacks in Balochistan, security officials say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-says-92-militants-killed-after-attacks-balochistan-security-officials</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-says-92-militants-killed-after-attacks-balochistan-security-officials</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saleem Ahmed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QUETTA, Pakistan, Jan 31 (Reuters) - At least 92 militants were killed on Saturday battling Pakistan's security forces in multiple cities across the southwestern province of Balochistan, four security officials told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pakistan's military said in a statement sent by text message that 15 security personnel were also killed during clearance operations, while militants targeted civilians in several areas, killing at least 18 people, including women and children.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 19:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says progress made towards US talks despite attack jitters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-progress-made-towards-us-talks-despite-attack-jitters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-progress-made-towards-us-talks-despite-attack-jitters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's top security official said Saturday that progress had been made towards negotiations with the United States, even as the Islamic republic's army chief warned Washington against launching military strikes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump confirmed the two sides were talking, while keeping the threat of an attack in the foreground.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washington has deployed warships led by the USS Abraham Lincoln aircraft carrier off Iran's shores, after Trump threatened to intervene in the wake of Tehran's deadly crackdown on anti-government protests.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 19:00:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Protesters in Copenhagen rally for Danish veterans after Trump remarks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/protesters-copenhagen-rally-danish-veterans-after-trump-remarks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/protesters-copenhagen-rally-danish-veterans-after-trump-remarks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Soren  Jeppesen and Tom Little&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;COPENHAGEN, Jan 31 (Reuters) - Hundreds of Danes gathered outside the U.S. Embassy in Copenhagen on Saturday in support of veterans who said they had been insulted by President Donald Trump's comment that European allies had kept "off the front lines" in the Afghanistan war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Denmark, with a population less than 2% the size of the United States, was one of the major combat allies in the U.S.-led war in Afghanistan, losing 44 service members killed, a per capita death toll on par with that of the Americans themselves. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 18:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explosion occurs at Iran's southern port of Bandar Abbas, Iranian media reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explosion-occurs-irans-southern-port-bandar-abbas-iranian-media-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explosion-occurs-irans-southern-port-bandar-abbas-iranian-media-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 31 (Reuters) - An explosion occurred at Iran's southern port of Bandar Abbas on Saturday, Iranian media reported, without giving a cause for the blast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The semi-official Tasnim news agency said that social media reports alleging that a Revolutionary Guard navy commander was targeted in the explosion were "completely false".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian media said the blast was being investigated but gave no further information. Iranian authorities could not immediately be contacted for comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>