<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israeli police raid UN refugee agency UNRWA's East Jerusalem compound</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israeli-police-raid-un-refugee-agency-unrwas-east-jerusalem-compound</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israeli-police-raid-un-refugee-agency-unrwas-east-jerusalem-compound</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Pesha Magid and Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 8 (Reuters) - Israeli authorities entered the U.N. Palestinian refugee agency's East Jerusalem offices on Monday and raised Israel's flag, in a raid they said was ordered over unpaid taxes but was condemned by the agency as a challenge to international law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA), which has been accused of bias by Israel, has not used the building since the start of this year after Israel ordered it to vacate all its premises and cease its operations. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 16:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU countries agree positions on new asylum, migrant returns policy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-countries-agree-positions-new-asylum-migrant-returns-policy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-countries-agree-positions-new-asylum-migrant-returns-policy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Julia Payne&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Dec 8 (Reuters) - EU countries on Monday agreed their final negotiating positions for several proposed migration laws on new asylum rules, a common EU list of "safe countries of origin" and an EU-wide policy for illegal migrant returns, statements from the Council of the European Union said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite strong criticism from more than 200 organisations, the key elements of the European Commission's proposals will likely become law.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 15:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Big hopes for Africa': Defence firms scramble for drone market at Egypt arms expo</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/big-hopes-africa-defence-firms-scramble-drone-market-egypt-arms-expo</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/big-hopes-africa-defence-firms-scramble-drone-market-egypt-arms-expo</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Dziadosz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Dec 8 (Reuters) - Quadcopters, electromagnetic rifles and an AI-powered navigation system were among the wares displayed at one of Africa and the Middle East’s biggest arms expos, as defence companies jostle to break into regional markets increasingly defined by drone warfare.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 14:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli prime minister to meet Trump on December 29, Israel says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israeli-prime-minister-meet-trump-december-29-israel-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israeli-prime-minister-meet-trump-december-29-israel-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 8 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu will meet U.S. President Donald Trump on December 29, an Israeli government spokesperson said on Monday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Maayan Lubell; Writing by Elwely Elwelly)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 14:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Congo President Tshisekedi accuses Rwanda of violating peace deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/congo-president-tshisekedi-accuses-rwanda-violating-peace-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/congo-president-tshisekedi-accuses-rwanda-violating-peace-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KINSHASA, Dec 8 (Reuters) - Congolese President Felix Tshisekedi said in a speech to lawmakers on Monday that Rwanda is already violating its commitments under a peace deal mediated by Washington, undermining efforts to end fighting in the east.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ange Adihe Kasongo; Writing by Ayen Deng Bior; Editing by Robbie Corey-Boulet)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mother of last Gaza hostage says Israel won't heal until he's back</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/mother-last-gaza-hostage-says-israel-wont-heal-until-hes-back</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/mother-last-gaza-hostage-says-israel-wont-heal-until-hes-back</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michal Yaakov Itzaki  and Rami Amichay&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MEITAR, Israel, Dec 8 (Reuters) - The mother of the last hostage in Gaza says Israel will not heal until he or his remains are brought home, and that the next phase of a peace plan should not proceed until he is back.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police officer Ran Gvili was one of 251 hostages seized and taken to Gaza by the Palestinian militant group Hamas in its attack on southern Israel on October 7, 2023.      &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU looking at options for boosting Lebanon's internal security forces, document says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-looking-options-boosting-lebanons-internal-security-forces-document-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eu-looking-options-boosting-lebanons-internal-security-forces-document-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Lili Bayer, John Irish and Maya Gebeily&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Dec 8 (Reuters) - The European Union is studying options for strengthening Lebanon’s Internal Security Forces to help free up the Lebanese army to focus on disarming the armed group Hezbollah, according to a document seen by Reuters on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A 2024 truce between Lebanon and Israel remains fragile, with Israel carrying out regular strikes on Lebanese territory that it says are targeting Hezbollah’s efforts to rearm.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Global leaders commit $1.9 billion to eradicate polio amid funding cuts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/global-leaders-commit-19-billion-eradicate-polio-amid-funding-cuts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/global-leaders-commit-19-billion-eradicate-polio-amid-funding-cuts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 8 (Reuters) - Global leaders pledged $1.9 billion to advance polio eradication on Monday, accelerating efforts to protect 370 million children from polio each year amid significant funding cuts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The budget of the Global Polio Eradication Initiative, a partnership that includes the World Health Organization and the Gates Foundation, is expected to take a 30% cut in 2026 and has a funding gap of $1.7 billion up to 2029.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan's paramilitary RSF says it took control of strategic Heglig oilfield</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/sudans-paramilitary-rsf-says-it-took-control-strategic-heglig-oilfield</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/sudans-paramilitary-rsf-says-it-took-control-strategic-heglig-oilfield</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 8 (Reuters) - Sudan's paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) said on Monday it had taken control of the strategic Heglig oilfield in the South Kordofan province.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heglig, which lies along Sudan's southern border, houses the main processing facility for South Sudanese oil, which makes up much of the revenue for South Sudan's government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government forces and workers at the Heglig oil field withdrew from the area on Sunday to avoid clashes that could have damaged the oil facilities, government sources told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tens of thousands celebrate as Syria marks one year since Assad's ouster</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/tens-thousands-celebrate-syria-marks-one-year-assads-ouster</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/tens-thousands-celebrate-syria-marks-one-year-assads-ouster</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tens of thousands took to the streets across Syria on Monday to celebrate a year since the toppling of longtime ruler Bashar al-Assad, with President Ahmed al-Sharaa urging people to unite to rebuild the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sharaa's Islamist-led alliance launched a lightning offensive in late November last year and took Damascus on December 8 after nearly 14 years of war, ending more than five decades of Assad family rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran opens trial of dual national accused of spying for Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-opens-trial-dual-national-accused-spying-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-opens-trial-dual-national-accused-spying-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 8 (Reuters) - The trial of a dual national holding European citizenship has begun in Iran, the semi-official Tasnim news agency reported on Monday, saying they were indicted for "intelligence cooperation and espionage in favour of the Zionist regime (Israel)."  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Alborz provincial attorney general, the defendant - whose identity has not been disclosed - entered Iran about a month before the 12-day war in June, during which Israel and the U.S. struck Iranian nuclear facilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 09:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian refugee returns set to slow as donor support fades</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syrian-refugee-returns-set-slow-donor-support-fades</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syrian-refugee-returns-set-slow-donor-support-fades</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Dec 8 (Reuters) - More than 3 million Syrians have returned home since the collapse of Bashar al-Assad's rule a year ago but a decline in global funding could deter others, the U.N. refugee agency said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some 1.2 million refugees in addition to 1.9 million internally displaced people have gone back home following the civil war that ended with Assad's overthrow, but millions more are yet to return, according to UNHCR. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agency said much more support was needed to ensure the trend continues.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 07:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A year after Assad's fall, families of missing detainees languish without answers</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/year-after-assads-fall-families-missing-detainees-languish-without-answers</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/year-after-assads-fall-families-missing-detainees-languish-without-answers</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS, Dec 8 (Reuters) - A year after dictator Bashar al-Assad's ouster in Syria, little has changed in Amina Beqai's desperate quest. She types her missing husband's name yet again into an internet search box, hoping for answers to a 13-year-old question. In vain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beqai has nowhere else to turn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A National Commission for Missing Persons established in May has been gathering evidence of enforced disappearances under Assad, but has yet to offer families any clues on the estimated 150,000 people who vanished in his notorious prisons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 06:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN cuts its aid appeal for 2026 despite soaring need</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-cuts-its-aid-appeal-2026-despite-soaring-need</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-cuts-its-aid-appeal-2026-despite-soaring-need</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Dec 8 (Reuters) - The United Nations on Monday appealed for an aid budget only half the size of what it had hoped for this year, acknowledging a plunge in donor funding at a time when humanitarian needs have never been greater.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By its own admission, the $23 billion U.N. appeal will shut out tens of millions of people in urgent need of help as falling support has forced it to prioritise only the most desperate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funding cuts come on top of other challenges for aid agencies that include security risks to staff in conflict zones and lack of access. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 05:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria to mark one year since Assad toppled</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-mark-one-year-assad-toppled</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-mark-one-year-assad-toppled</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS, Dec 8 (Reuters) - Syrians will mark the first anniversary of the overthrow of Bashar al-Assad and his iron-fisted rule on Monday, as the fractured nation struggles to find stability and recover after years of war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Official celebrations are planned for the central Umayyad Square in Damascus, which has already been packed with jubilant gatherings ahead of December 8, and elsewhere around the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 03:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas official says group needs guarantees on war's end and statehood to disarm</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</guid><description>Senior Hamas official Basem Naim stopped short of pledging that Hamas would not fire on international troops, but said the militant group has "no problem” with the stabilization force.</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 17:18:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas official says group needs guarantees on war's end and statehood to disarm</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</guid><description>Senior Hamas official Basem Naim stopped short of pledging that Hamas would not fire on international troops, but said the militant group has "no problem” with the stabilization force.</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 17:18:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas official says group needs guarantees on war's end and statehood to disarm</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</guid><description>Senior Hamas official Basem Naim stopped short of pledging that Hamas would not fire on international troops, but said the militant group has "no problem” with the stabilization force.</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 17:18:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas official says group needs guarantees on war's end and statehood to disarm</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/hamas-official-says-group-needs-guarantees-wars-end-and-statehood-disarm</guid><description>Senior Hamas official Basem Naim stopped short of pledging that Hamas would not fire on international troops, but said the militant group has "no problem” with the stabilization force.</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 17:18:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu says he will not quit politics if he receives a pardon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-says-he-will-not-quit-politics-if-he-receives-pardon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-says-he-will-not-quit-politics-if-he-receives-pardon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 7 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said on Sunday that he would not retire from politics if he receives a pardon from the country's president in his years-long corruption trial.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Asked by a reporter if planned on retiring from political life if he receives a pardon, Netanyahu replied: "no".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netanyahu last month asked President Isaac Herzog for a pardon, with lawyers for the prime minister arguing that frequent court appearances were hindering Netanyahu's ability to govern and that a pardon would be good for the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 15:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>