<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Turkey helping in talks over Hamas fighters holed up in Gaza, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-helping-talks-over-hamas-fighters-holed-gaza-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-helping-talks-over-hamas-fighters-holed-gaza-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Turkey is working with the United States and Arab mediators to secure safe passage for Hamas fighters who are holed up in tunnels in the Israel-controlled area of Gaza, a Palestinian source, a Hamas official and Turkish officials said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fate of about 200 fighters has complicated efforts to shift Gaza ceasefire talks, being conducted between Israel and the Palestinians militant group, to the next phase that aims to secure a permanent end to the two-year-old war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 16:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli hostage says faith sustained him in Hamas captivity</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-hostage-says-faith-sustained-him-hamas-captivity</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-hostage-says-faith-sustained-him-hamas-captivity</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;HOLON, Israel (Reuters) -Released Israeli hostage Bar Kupershtein says he managed to survive two years in a cramped Hamas tunnel in Gaza with no sunlight, little food and regular beatings, by clinging to his belief that he was in God's hands the entire time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kupershtein, 23, was released on October 13 along with 19 other hostages in exchange for some 2,000 Palestinian convicts and detainees, as part of the Gaza ceasefire between Israel and Hamas that has largely halted two years of devastating war.    &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Sudanese who told the world what happened in El-Fasher</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudanese-who-told-world-what-happened-el-fasher</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/sudanese-who-told-world-what-happened-el-fasher</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;"Sixteen killed." "Seven killed." "Thirty-one killed." "People are eating cowhide to survive." "The bombs are getting closer." "They're shooting people trying to run away."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These were the grim updates shared with AFP's veteran Sudan correspondent Abdelmoneim Abu Idris Ali by people trapped in the 18-month-long siege of El-Fasher, a city overrun by the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) two weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout the siege and ensuing battle, it was thanks to ordinary civilians that AFP and other news organisations were able to form a picture of what was happening there.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's foreign reserves exceed $50B mark for first time: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</guid><description>The stronger reserve position signals that Egypt has largely emerged from its worst economic crunch in decades.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:19:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's foreign reserves exceed $50B mark for first time: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</guid><description>The stronger reserve position signals that Egypt has largely emerged from its worst economic crunch in decades.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:19:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's foreign reserves exceed $50B mark for first time: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</guid><description>The stronger reserve position signals that Egypt has largely emerged from its worst economic crunch in decades.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:19:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's foreign reserves exceed $50B mark for first time: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypts-foreign-reserves-exceed-50b-mark-first-time-what-know</guid><description>The stronger reserve position signals that Egypt has largely emerged from its worst economic crunch in decades.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:19:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi goes on trial for deadly German Christmas market attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-goes-trial-deadly-german-christmas-market-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-goes-trial-deadly-german-christmas-market-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Saudi doctor went on trial in Germany Monday accused of driving an SUV through a Christmas market, killing six people and wounding more than 300 in a rampage that shocked the nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taleb Jawad al-Abdulmohsen, a 51-year-old psychiatrist, was arrested next to the battered rental vehicle after the attack on December 20, 2024 in the eastern city of Magdeburg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prosecutor Matthias Boettcher told the court that the accused wanted "to kill a large number of people" by driving the two-tonne vehicle "deliberately into a mass of pedestrians".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:00:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US Secretary of State Rubio heads to Canada for G7 meeting on Ukraine, Gaza, trade</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-secretary-state-rubio-heads-canada-g7-meeting-ukraine-gaza-trade</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-secretary-state-rubio-heads-canada-g7-meeting-ukraine-gaza-trade</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -U.S. Secretary of State Marco Rubio will travel to Canada's Niagara region this week to join the Group of Seven foreign ministers' meeting, his office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rubio intends to discuss U.S. President Donald Trump's efforts to bring peace to Ukraine and Gaza, security in Haiti and Sudan, maritime security, critical minerals and global supply chains with his G7 counterparts from France, Germany, Italy, Japan and Britain.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting will take place on Tuesday and Wednesday in Niagara, Ontario.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey’s Fidan heads to US as Trump hosts Sharaa, Gaza talks continue</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</guid><description>Fidan's surprise visit coincides with Syrian president’s historic White House talks and ongoing Gaza ceasefire negotiations.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:17:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey’s Fidan heads to US as Trump hosts Sharaa, Gaza talks continue</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</guid><description>Fidan's surprise visit coincides with Syrian president’s historic White House talks and ongoing Gaza ceasefire negotiations.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:17:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey’s Fidan heads to US as Trump hosts Sharaa, Gaza talks continue</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</guid><description>Fidan's surprise visit coincides with Syrian president’s historic White House talks and ongoing Gaza ceasefire negotiations.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:17:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey’s Fidan heads to US as Trump hosts Sharaa, Gaza talks continue</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-fidan-heads-us-trump-hosts-sharaa-gaza-talks-continue</guid><description>Fidan's surprise visit coincides with Syrian president’s historic White House talks and ongoing Gaza ceasefire negotiations.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:17:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kushner in Israel as trapped Hamas fighters issue bedevils Gaza truce progress</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kushner-israel-trapped-hamas-fighters-issue-bedevils-gaza-truce-progress</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kushner-israel-trapped-hamas-fighters-issue-bedevils-gaza-truce-progress</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/CAIRO (Reuters) -U.S. mediators are meeting Israel's prime minister on Monday with attention turning to the second, far more complex, phase of the Gaza ceasefire deal and the immediate problem of a standoff over a group of Hamas fighters still holed up in tunnels. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting between U.S. President Donald Trump's son-in-law Jared Kushner and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu comes a month after Washington and regional states pressed Israel and Hamas to a truce after two years of devastating war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US envoy Kushner and Netanyahu discuss phase two of Gaza truce</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-envoy-kushner-and-netanyahu-discuss-phase-two-gaza-truce</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-envoy-kushner-and-netanyahu-discuss-phase-two-gaza-truce</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US envoy Jared Kushner and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu held talks Monday on the second phase of the Gaza ceasefire, as Washington intensified its efforts to ensure the fragile truce endures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The truce, in effect for exactly a month now, has largely halted the war that erupted after Hamas's surprise attack on Israel on October 7, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the ongoing first stage, a series of prisoner and hostage exchanges took place over recent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Lukoil declares force majeure at Iraqi oilfield following sanctions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-lukoil-declares-force-majeure-iraqi-oilfield-following-sanctions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-lukoil-declares-force-majeure-iraqi-oilfield-following-sanctions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Rasheed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD (Reuters) -Lukoil has declared force majeure at Iraq's giant West Qurna-2 oilfield, four sources with knowledge of the matter said on Monday, after Western sanctions on the Russian oil major hampered its operations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lukoil did not immediately respond to a Reuters request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United States and Britain imposed sanctions on Lukoil -  Russia's second-largest oil company - last month. And Iraq has since halted all cash and crude payments to the company, three of the sources said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE rules out joining Gaza stabilization force for now, backs peace efforts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uae-rules-out-joining-gaza-stabilization-force-now-backs-peace-efforts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uae-rules-out-joining-gaza-stabilization-force-now-backs-peace-efforts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maha El Dahan and Jana Choukeir&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI (Reuters) -The United Arab Emirates does not yet see a clear framework for the proposed international stability force in Gaza and, under the current circumstances, will not take part, a senior Emirati official said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anwar Gargash, diplomatic adviser to the UAE president, said Abu Dhabi would continue to support political efforts toward peace and remain a leading provider of humanitarian aid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The region remains fragile, yet there is reason for cautious optimism", he told the Abu Dhabi Strategic Debate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel pushes Lebanon army to search more intrusively for Hezbollah arms, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-pushes-lebanon-army-search-more-intrusively-hezbollah-arms-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-pushes-lebanon-army-search-more-intrusively-hezbollah-arms-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maya Gebeily and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT/JERUSALEM (Reuters) -Israel is pressing Lebanon's army to be more aggressive in disarming the Iranian-backed militant group Hezbollah by searching private homes in the south for weaponry, three Lebanese security officials and two Israeli officials have said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The demand has emerged in recent weeks and been rejected by Lebanon's military leadership, who fear it would ignite civil strife and derail a disarmament strategy seen by the army as cautious but effective, the Lebanese security officials told Reuters. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime watchdog FATF to visit Turkey after 'grey list' exit, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/crime-watchdog-fatf-visit-turkey-after-grey-list-exit-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/crime-watchdog-fatf-visit-turkey-after-grey-list-exit-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ebru Tuncay and Can Sezer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -A team from the international crime watchdog FATF will evaluate Turkey this month after removing it from its "grey list" last year for progress made in fighting money laundering and the funding of terrorist activity, five sources said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey has to show it is meeting commitments or it risks returning to the grey list of countries that require special scrutiny, which would dent its improving financial credentials.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Syria foiled Islamic State plots on President Sharaa's life, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-syria-foiled-islamic-state-plots-president-sharaas-life-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-syria-foiled-islamic-state-plots-president-sharaas-life-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS (Reuters) -Syria has foiled two separate Islamic State plots to assassinate President Ahmed al-Sharaa, two senior officials said, adding a personal dimension to the leader's plans to join a U.S.-led coalition to fight the militant group that he has long battled. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sources, a senior Syrian security official and a senior Middle Eastern official, said the plots on Sharaa's life were foiled over the last few months and underlined the direct threat he faces as he tries to consolidate power in a country ruined by 14 years of civil war. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>