<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Syrian president cancels Germany visit, Merz meeting</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-president-cancels-germany-visit-merz-meeting</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-president-cancels-germany-visit-merz-meeting</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 18 (Reuters) - Syria's President Ahmed al-Sharaa has cancelled his visit to Berlin on Monday and Tuesday, a German government spokesperson told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Al-Sharaa had been scheduled to meet with German Chancellor Friedrich Merz and President Frank-Walter Steinmeier. Talks with German business leaders were also planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ceasefire was agreed on Sunday after days of fierce clashes between Syrian government troops and U.S.-backed Kurdish fighters.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Andreas Rinke, Writing by Rachel More, Editing by Alexander Smith)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 19:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>India gets Trump's invite to join Board of Peace on Gaza, source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/india-gets-trumps-invite-join-board-peace-gaza-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/india-gets-trumps-invite-join-board-peace-gaza-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;NEW DELHI, Jan 18 (Reuters) - India has received an invitation from U.S. President Donald Trump to join his "Board of Peace" initiative that is aimed at resolving global conflicts, beginning with Gaza, a senior Indian government official said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was not clear whether India would join the initiative. Its foreign ministry did not immediately respond to a request for comment.  &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 17:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian government, SDF agree on immediate ceasefire on all fronts, state media say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-sdf-agree-immediate-ceasefire-all-fronts-state-media-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-sdf-agree-immediate-ceasefire-all-fronts-state-media-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 18 (Reuters) - The Syrian government and the U.S.-backed Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF) have agreed on an immediate ceasefire on all fronts, Syrian state media reported on Sunday, after days of fighting as the army advanced into Kurdish-held territories in the northeast.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Jaidaa Taha and Ahmed Tolba, Editing by Louise Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 16:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bowing to US pressure, Syrian military advances, Kurdish-led SDF agrees to Sharaa's terms</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bowing-us-pressure-syrian-military-advances-kurdish-led-sdf-agrees-sharaas-terms</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bowing-us-pressure-syrian-military-advances-kurdish-led-sdf-agrees-sharaas-terms</guid><description>Syrian government forces rapidly retook Raqqa and key eastern territories from the US-backed SDF, prompting a ceasefire agreement that effectively restores Damascus’s control over much of Syria’s oil-rich northeast.</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:39:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurdish commander calls on US to 'intervene forcefully' in Syria clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-commander-calls-us-intervene-forcefully-syria-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-commander-calls-us-intervene-forcefully-syria-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Feras Dalatey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS, Jan 18 (Reuters) - The U.S. should intervene more forcefully to end a Syrian offensive that has gained key territory from Kurdish fighters in recent days, the head of the main Kurdish forces told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government troops launched an offensive on Saturday into territory run for the last decade by semi-autonomous Kurdish authorities in the northeast of Syria, capturing towns on both sides of the Euphrates River as well asthe country's largest oilfield and a gas field, officials and security sources said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian forces advance deeper into the US‑backed, Kurdish‑controlled northeast</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-advance-deeper-us-backed-kurdish-controlled-northeast</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-advance-deeper-us-backed-kurdish-controlled-northeast</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mahmoud Hasano and Khalil Ashawi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TABQA, Jan 18 (Reuters) - Syrian government troops are pushing towards Raqqa and Hasakah in the northeast of the country, the last strongholds of the U.S.-backed autonomous Kurdish-led administration, government officials and security sources said on Sunday.    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They had earlier taken control of the Deir al-Zor's main oil and gas fields east of the Euphrates River — a key source of revenue for the Kurdish-led forces — dealing a major blow to the group.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World leaders show caution on Trump's broader 'board of peace' amid fears for U.N</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/world-leaders-show-caution-trumps-broader-board-peace-amid-fears-un</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/world-leaders-show-caution-trumps-broader-board-peace-amid-fears-un</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By John Irish and Andreas Rinke&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 18 (Reuters) - Governments reacted cautiously on Sunday to U.S. President Donald Trump's invitation to join his "Board of Peace" initiative aimed at resolving conflicts globally, a plan that diplomats said could harm the work of the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only Hungary, whose leader is a close Trump ally, gave an unequivocal acceptance in response to the invitations, which have been addressed to some 60 nations and began arriving in European capitals on Saturday, according to diplomats.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan receives US invitation to join Board of Peace on Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-receives-us-invitation-join-board-peace-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-receives-us-invitation-join-board-peace-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 18 (Reuters) - Pakistan's Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif has received U.S. President Donald Trump's invitation to join the Board of Peace for Gaza, a spokesperson for Pakistan's ministry of foreign affairs said in a statement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Pakistan will remain engaged with international efforts for peace and security in Gaza, leading to a lasting solution to the Palestine issue in accordance with United Nations resolutions," the statement added.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ananya Palyekar in Bengaluru, Editing by Louise Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 13:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Limited internet briefly returns in Iran after protest blackout</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/limited-internet-briefly-returns-iran-after-protest-blackout</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/limited-internet-briefly-returns-iran-after-protest-blackout</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Limited internet access briefly returned in Iran before dropping again, a monitor said Sunday, 10 days into a communications blackout that rights groups said aimed to mask a protest crackdown that killed thousands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran's president warned that an attack on the country's supreme leader would be a declaration of war -- an apparent response to US counterpart Donald Trump saying it was time to look for new leadership in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 13:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's Gaza peace board charter seeks $1 billion for extended membership, document shows</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-gaza-peace-board-charter-seeks-1-billion-extended-membership-document</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-gaza-peace-board-charter-seeks-1-billion-extended-membership-document</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Jan 18 (Reuters) - A draft charter sent to about 60 countries by the U.S. administration calls for members to contribute $1 billion in cash if they want their membership to last more than three years, according to the document seen by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Each Member State shall serve a term of no more than three years from this Charter’s entry into force, subject to renewal by the Chairman," the document, first reported by Bloomberg News, shows.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian forces seize major oil, gas fields in eastern Syria, security sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-seize-major-oil-gas-fields-eastern-syria-security-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-seize-major-oil-gas-fields-eastern-syria-security-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 18 (Reuters) - Syrian troops fighting U.S.-backed Kurdish-led forces seized the Omar oil field, the country’s largest, and the Conoco gas field in the eastern Deir Zor province as allied Arab tribal forces advanced in the oil-rich area along the border with Iraq, officials and security sources said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The takeover of the oil fields that lie east of the Euphrates River — a main source of revenue for the Kurdish-led forces — was a major blow to the group, which officials said had deprived the state of resources used by the militia.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 10:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria's leader agrees truce with Kurds after govt troops advance</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-leader-agrees-truce-kurds-after-govt-troops-advance</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-leader-agrees-truce-kurds-after-govt-troops-advance</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa on Sunday announced a deal with the chief of Kurdish-led forces that includes a ceasefire, after government troops advanced across Kurdish-held areas of the country's north and east.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syrian Kurdish leader Mazloum Abdi said he agreed to the deal to avoid a broader war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He made the decision after deadly clashes in the Syrian city of Raqa Sunday between Kurdish-led forces and local fighters loyal to Damascus, and fighting this month between the Kurds and government forces.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian official says verified deaths in Iran protests reaches at least 5,000</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-official-says-verified-deaths-iran-protests-reaches-least-5000</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-official-says-verified-deaths-iran-protests-reaches-least-5000</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 18 (Reuters) - An Iranian official in the region said on Sunday the authorities had verified at least 5,000 people had been killed in protests in Iran, including about 500 security personnel, blaming "terrorists and armed rioters" for killing "innocent Iranians".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jordan says King Abdullah received invitation to join Gaza peace board</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/jordan-says-king-abdullah-received-invitation-join-gaza-peace-board</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/jordan-says-king-abdullah-received-invitation-join-gaza-peace-board</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 18 (Reuters) - Jordan's foreign ministry said on Sunday that King Abdullah received an invitation from U.S. President Donald Trump to join the so-called "Board of Peace" for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The foreign ministry said it was currently reviewing related documents within the country's internal legal procedures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The board is set to supervise the temporary governance of Gaza, which has been under a shaky ceasefire since October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Menna Alaa El-Din and Muhammad Al Gebaly;Editing by Elaine Hardcastle)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump wants nations to pay $1 billion to stay on his peace board, report says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-wants-nations-pay-1-billion-stay-his-peace-board-report-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-wants-nations-pay-1-billion-stay-his-peace-board-report-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 17 (Reuters) - The Trump administration wants nations to pay $1 billion to stay on his peace board, Bloomberg News reported on Saturday, citing a draft charter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;United States President Donald Trump would serve as its inaugural chairman and each member state shall serve a term of no more than three years from this charter's entry into force, subject to renewal by the chairman, the report said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters could not immediately verify the report.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:01:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands march in France to back Iranian protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-march-france-back-iranian-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-march-france-back-iranian-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of people rallied in France on Saturday in a show of support for demonstrators in Iran risking their lives to demand an end to theocratic rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests in Iran over past weeks are the largest since the "Woman, Life, Freedom" street movement in 2022-2023, sparked by the death in custody of an Iranian Kurdish woman arrested for allegedly not following a required dress code. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Woman, Life, Freedom," chanted marchers in the French capital, some holding portraits of deceased Iranian protesters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 19:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq takes full control of air base after US withdrawal, defence ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraq-takes-full-control-air-base-after-us-withdrawal-defence-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraq-takes-full-control-air-base-after-us-withdrawal-defence-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD, Jan 17 (Reuters) - U.S. forces have withdrawn from Iraq's Ain al-Asad Airbase, which housed U.S.-led forces in Western Iraq, and the Iraqi army has assumed full control, the Iraqi defence ministry said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2024, Washington and Baghdad reached an understanding on plans for the withdrawal of U.S.-led coalition forces from Iraq and a move towards a bilateral security relationship.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian army extends hold over north Syria, Kurds report clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-extends-hold-over-north-syria-kurds-report-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-extends-hold-over-north-syria-kurds-report-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria's army has seized swathes of the country's north, dislodging Kurdish forces from territory over which they held effective autonomy for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government appeared to be extending its grip on Kurdish-run areas after President Ahmed al-Sharaa issued a decree declaring Kurdish a "national language" and granting the minority group official recognition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Kurds have said Friday's announcement fell short of their aspirations, while the implementation of a March deal -- intended to see Kurdish forces integrated into the state -- has stalled.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says US Gaza executive board composition against its policy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-says-us-gaza-executive-board-composition-against-its-policy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-says-us-gaza-executive-board-composition-against-its-policy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV, Jan 17 (Reuters) - Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said on Saturday that this week's Trump administration announcement on the composition of a Gaza executive board was not coordinated with Israel and ran counter to government policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It said Foreign Minister Gideon Saar would raise the issue with U.S. Secretary of State Marco Rubio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The statement did not specify what part of the board's composition contradicted Israeli policy. An Israeli government spokesperson declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel objects to line-up of Trump panel for post-war Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-objects-line-trump-panel-post-war-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-objects-line-trump-panel-post-war-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel said on Saturday it objected to the line-up of a Gaza panel that will operate under US President Donald Trump's Board of Peace, which oversees post-war governance in the Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The panel, known as the Gaza executive board, notably includes Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan and a Qatari official and was announced by the White House on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace began to take shape on Saturday as the leaders of Egypt, Turkey, Argentina and Canada were asked to join. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 15:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>