<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Five takeaways from Davos 2026</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/five-takeaways-davos-2026</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/five-takeaways-davos-2026</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAVOS, Switzerland, Jan 23 (Reuters) - World leaders and business executives departed from Davos after an eventful World Economic Forum annual meeting which was dominated by U.S. President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here's what we learned:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GEOPOLITICS&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Europe learned the value of standing up to Trump. His claim to Greenland crossed all of its red lines on territorial sovereignty and Europe's resistance, possibly helped by the ensuing fall on financial markets, was seen as one reason he backed off.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkish court rejects bid by Erdogan rival to overcome block to his presidential run</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkish-court-rejects-bid-erdogan-rival-overcome-block-his-presidential-run</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkish-court-rejects-bid-erdogan-rival-overcome-block-his-presidential-run</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Jan 23 (Reuters) - A Turkish court rejected on Friday a lawsuit from jailed Istanbul Mayor Ekrem Imamoglu challenging the cancellation of his university degree, his legal team said, in a further blow to his plans to run for the presidency in the next election.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Imamoglu, who is President Tayyip Erdogan's main political rival, has been in jail since last March, pending trial on corruption charges. He received a separate prison sentence in July for insulting and threatening the city’s chief prosecutor.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU concerned about Trump 'concentration of powers' over 'Board of Peace', document says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-concerned-about-trump-concentration-powers-over-board-peace-document-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-concerned-about-trump-concentration-powers-over-board-peace-document-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Lili Bayer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Jan 23 (Reuters) - The European Union’s foreign policy arm has raised questions about U.S. President Donald Trump’s broad powers over his new Board of Peace, according to an internal document seen by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump has urged world leaders to join hisBoard of Peace initiative aimed at resolving conflicts globally, but many Western heads of government have been reluctant to take part.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN urges Iran to end 'brutal repression'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-urges-iran-end-brutal-repression</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-urges-iran-end-brutal-repression</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The United Nations called Friday on Iranian authorities to immediately end their "brutal repression", after a crackdown on nationwide protests left thousands dead, including children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at an urgent UN Human Rights Council meeting on the situation in Iran, UN rights chief Volker Turk voiced alarm at the authorities' crushing of recent demonstrations, describing how security forces used "live ammunition" against protesters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US targets Iran's 'shadow fleet' over crackdown on protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-targets-irans-shadow-fleet-over-crackdown-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-targets-irans-shadow-fleet-over-crackdown-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 23 (Reuters) - The United States on Friday imposed sanctions on nine vessels of what is known as the shadow fleet and eight related firms, the U.S. Treasury Department said in a statement, as Washington sought to escalate pressure on Iran over the recent killing of protesters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Treasury said the vessels and their respective owners or management firms, which include entities based in India, Oman and the United Arab Emirates, have collectively transported hundreds of millions of dollars’ worth of Iranian oil and petroleum products to foreign markets.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Merz says Berlin cannot accept Trump's Board of Peace plan in current form</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/merz-says-berlin-cannot-accept-trumps-board-peace-plan-current-form</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/merz-says-berlin-cannot-accept-trumps-board-peace-plan-current-form</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ROME, Jan 23 (Reuters) - German Chancellor Friedrich Merz said on Friday he would be ready to join U.S. President Donald Trump's Board of Peace initiative for the sake of Gaza but could not accept the plan in its current form. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"In the form in which the peace board is currently set up, we cannot accept its governance structures in Germany for constitutional reasons," Merz said in a joint news conference with Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni in Rome. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S., in control of oil dollars, heaps pressure on Iraq over Iranian influence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-control-oil-dollars-heaps-pressure-iraq-over-iranian-influence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-control-oil-dollars-heaps-pressure-iraq-over-iranian-influence</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maha El Dahan, Timour Azhari and Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI/WASHINGTON, Jan 23 - Washington has threatened senior Iraqi politicians with sanctions targeting the Iraqi state — including potentially its critical supply of oil revenue sourced via the Federal Reserve Bank of New York — should Iran-backed armed groups be included in the next government, four sources told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian cleric says Iran may target US investments in region if attacked</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-cleric-says-iran-may-target-us-investments-region-if-attacked</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-cleric-says-iran-may-target-us-investments-region-if-attacked</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 23 (Reuters) - An influential Iranian cleric warned on Friday that Iran may target U.S.-linked investments in the region in retaliation for any U.S. attack on the Islamic Republic, Iranian news agencies reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump said on Thursday that the United States had an "armada" heading toward Iran but hoped he would not have to use it, as he renewed warnings to Tehran against killing protesters or restarting its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Israel aims to ensure more Palestinians are let out of Gaza than back in</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-israel-aims-ensure-more-palestinians-are-let-out-gaza-back</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-israel-aims-ensure-more-palestinians-are-let-out-gaza-back</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV, Jan 23 (Reuters) - Israel wants to restrict the number of Palestinians entering Gaza through the border crossing with Egypt to ensure that more are allowed out than in, three sources briefed on the matter said ahead of the border's expected opening next week.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Europeans among 150 IS detainees transferred from Syria to Iraq</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/europeans-among-150-detainees-transferred-syria-iraq</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/europeans-among-150-detainees-transferred-syria-iraq</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Europeans were among 150 senior Islamic State group detainees transferred this week by the US military from Kurdish custody in Syria to Iraq, whose premier urged EU countries to repatriate their nationals.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They were among an estimated 7,000 jihadists due to be moved across the border to Iraq as the Kurdish-led force that has held them for years relinquishes swathes of territory to the advancing Syrian army.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>West Bank education centre could close in days due to Israeli seizure threat, says UNRWA</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-education-centre-could-close-days-due-israeli-seizure-threat-says-unrwa</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/west-bank-education-centre-could-close-days-due-israeli-seizure-threat-says-unrwa</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 23 (Reuters) - A training centre for hundreds of Palestinians in the occupied West Bank could be closed within days by Israeli authorities, jeopardising the education of students, the U.N. Palestinian refugee agency said on Friday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;  The Kalandia Training Centre, which teaches 350 young male students from across the West Bank skills such as plumbing and vehicle maintenance, could be shut, as the land it sits on is at risk of expropriation by Israeli authorities, UNRWA said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under fire at home over Board of Peace, Netanyahu hints Trump could OK Gaza war restart</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</guid><description>According to diplomatic sources, Netanyahu believes that at some point Israel will receive a green light from the Trump administration to resume fighting in Gaza, though his coalition partners do not seem reassured.</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:25:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under fire at home over Board of Peace, Netanyahu hints Trump could OK Gaza war restart</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</guid><description>According to diplomatic sources, Netanyahu believes that at some point Israel will receive a green light from the Trump administration to resume fighting in Gaza, though his coalition partners do not seem reassured.</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:25:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under fire at home over Board of Peace, Netanyahu hints Trump could OK Gaza war restart</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</guid><description>According to diplomatic sources, Netanyahu believes that at some point Israel will receive a green light from the Trump administration to resume fighting in Gaza, though his coalition partners do not seem reassured.</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:25:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under fire at home over Board of Peace, Netanyahu hints Trump could OK Gaza war restart</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/under-fire-home-over-board-peace-netanyahu-hints-trump-could-ok-gaza-war-restart</guid><description>According to diplomatic sources, Netanyahu believes that at some point Israel will receive a green light from the Trump administration to resume fighting in Gaza, though his coalition partners do not seem reassured.</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:25:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's NATO front line comments 'deeply disappointing', UK minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-nato-front-line-comments-deeply-disappointing-uk-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trumps-nato-front-line-comments-deeply-disappointing-uk-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 23 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump's comments that NATO troops stayed off the front line in Afghanistan were "deeply disappointing", a British minister said on Friday, noting that many European soldiers had died supporting American-led operations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Criticising NATO in a Fox News interview on Thursday, Trump said the United States had "never needed" the alliance and that its allies stayed "a little off the front lines" in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli Bedouin say hope for better life crushed after deadly crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-bedouin-say-hope-better-life-crushed-after-deadly-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-bedouin-say-hope-better-life-crushed-after-deadly-crackdown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When the Israeli Bedouin village of Tarabin al-Sana backed Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's party in the last elections, they expected their lives would improve. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Three years later, the small community in the Negev has been left stunned after a two-week crackdown during which police shot dead a 36-year-old father of six.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israeli police set up roadblocks, fired tear gas and searched homes in scenes reminiscent of military raids on Palestinian towns in the occupied West Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tarabin's residents, however, are Israeli citizens.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-Who is leading Russia's delegation at the Ukraine talks in Abu Dhabi?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-who-leading-russias-delegation-ukraine-talks-abu-dhabi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-who-leading-russias-delegation-ukraine-talks-abu-dhabi</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 23 (Reuters) - Russian Admiral Igor Kostyukov is set to head Moscow's team at trilateral security talks with the U.S. and Ukraine on Friday in Abu Dhabi, as part of efforts to reach a deal to end the war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What do we know about Kostyukov?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAREER IN MILITARY INTELLIGENCE&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kostyukov is the director of Russia's military intelligence organisation, known as the GRU. Born in 1961, he received a naval education and went on to serve as a military diplomat, which included a posting as a military attache to the Russian embassy in Greece in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian government says it controls prison in Raqqa with Islamic State-linked detainees</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-says-it-controls-prison-raqqa-islamic-state-linked-detainees</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-government-says-it-controls-prison-raqqa-islamic-state-linked-detainees</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 23 (Reuters) - Syria's Interior Ministry said on Friday it had taken over al-Aktan prison in the city of Raqqa in northeastern Syria, a facility that was formerly under the control of Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prison has been holding detainees linked to the militant group Islamic State, and witnessed clashes in its vicinity this week between advancing Syrian government forces and the SDF.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelenskiy says territorial issue to be discussed at trilateral talks in UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/zelenskiy-says-territorial-issue-be-discussed-trilateral-talks-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/zelenskiy-says-territorial-issue-be-discussed-trilateral-talks-uae</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Anna Pruchnicka&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Jan 23 (Reuters) - President Volodymyr Zelenskiy said on Friday that the vital question of territory in Ukraine's war with Russia would be discussed at U.S.-brokered trilateral talks in Abu Dhabi on Friday and Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kyiv is under mounting U.S. pressure to secure a peace deal in the nearly four-year-old war with Moscow, which has demanded Ukraine give up its entire eastern area of Donbas before it stops fighting.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>