<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Iran protest deaths rise to more than 500, rights group says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-deaths-rise-more-500-rights-group-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-deaths-rise-more-500-rights-group-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 11 (Reuters) - Deaths from two weeks of protests in Iran have risen to more than 500, U.S.-based rights group HRANA said on Sunday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its latest spreadsheet - based on activists inside and outside Iran - showed 490 protesters and 48 security personnel killed, plus 10,000 arrests. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters could not independently confirm the figures and Iranian authorities have not given tolls from the unrest it blames on "rioters" being encouraged by foreign powers.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 17:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump briefing on Iran options planned for Tuesday, WSJ reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-briefing-iran-options-planned-tuesday-wsj-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-briefing-iran-options-planned-tuesday-wsj-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 11 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump is scheduled to be briefed by senior officials in his administration on Tuesday on specific options to respond to the protests in Iran, the Wall Street Journal reported on Sunday, citing U.S. officials. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting will be a discussion about possible next steps including military strikes, deploying secretive cyber weapons against Iranian military and civilian sites, placing more sanctions on Iran's government and boosting anti-government sources online, the Journal reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The White House said it had no comment on the report.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 17:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey bars Iranians from protesting outside Istanbul consulate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-bars-iranians-protesting-outside-istanbul-consulate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-bars-iranians-protesting-outside-istanbul-consulate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turkey on Sunday prevented Iranian nationals from protesting outside Iran's consulate in Istanbul, with the area cordoned off and crowds blocked by police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran has been roiled by street protests since December 28 that have taken hold nationwide, challenging the theocratic government that has ruled the country since the 1979 revolution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey, a majority Sunni Muslim country, shares a border of around 500 kilometres (300 miles) and three land crossings with its Shiite neighbour Iran. It hosts more than 74,000 Iranians with residence permits and around 5,000 refugees.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 16:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians in Kurdish area of Aleppo pick up pieces after clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-kurdish-area-aleppo-pick-pieces-after-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-kurdish-area-aleppo-pick-pieces-after-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Residents of a Kurdish neighbourhood in Syria's second city of Aleppo passed through government checkpoints Sunday to find blackened walls, destroyed vehicles and debris-littered streets as they returned home after days of deadly clashes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While they picked up the pieces in the city's Ashrafiyeh neighbourhood, the city's only other Kurdish-majority district Sheikh Maqsud still remained off limits after suffering the worst of the fighting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many locals like wheelchair-bound Abdul Qader Satar returned to Ashrafiyeh on Sunday to inspect their homes after days of violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 16:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria govt forces take control of Aleppo's Kurdish neighbourhoods</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-govt-forces-take-control-aleppos-kurdish-neighbourhoods</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-govt-forces-take-control-aleppos-kurdish-neighbourhoods</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria's government was in full control of Aleppo on Sunday after taking over the city's Kurdish neighbourhoods and evacuating fighters there to Kurdish autonomous areas following days of deadly clashes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Residents of the Ashrafiyeh neighbourhood, the first of two areas to fall to the Syrian army, began returning to their homes to inspect the damage, finding shrapnel and broken glass littering the streets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The violence started earlier this week after negotiations stalled on integrating the Kurds' de facto autonomous administration and forces into the country's new government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 14:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli fire kills three people in Gaza, tension rises</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-three-people-gaza-tension-rises</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-three-people-gaza-tension-rises</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 11 (Reuters) - Israeli fire killed at least three Palestinians in two separate incidents across the enclave, local health authorities said, as tension rises over continued violence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medics said one Palestinian was killed in the Tuffah neighbourhood in Gaza City, in an area under Palestinian control, while two others were killed in the town of Bani Suhaila east of Khan Younis, an area Israel still occupies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no comment from the Israeli military on the two incidents. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Son of Iran's toppled shah seeks a role as protests expand</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/son-irans-toppled-shah-seeks-role-protests-expand</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/son-irans-toppled-shah-seeks-role-protests-expand</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 11 (Reuters) - In a nation where opposition to almost half a century of clerical rule has long been fragmented, the son of the last shah of Iran has become a prominent voice spurring on protesters staging the biggest anti-government demonstrations in years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reza Pahlavi, 65, has sought to speak as a national leader despite living outside Iran since before his father was toppled in the 1979 Islamic Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 11:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Confronting protests, Iran vows to strike back if U.S. attacks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/confronting-protests-iran-vows-strike-back-if-us-attacks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/confronting-protests-iran-vows-strike-back-if-us-attacks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi, Rami Ayyub and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI/JERUSALEM, Jan 11 (Reuters) - Tehran threatened on Sunday to retaliate against Israel and U.S. military bases in the event of U.S. strikes on Iran, issuing the warning as Israeli sources said Israel was on high alert for the possibility of any U.S. intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Gaza hospital, patients cling to MSF as Israel orders it out</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/gaza-hospital-patients-cling-msf-israel-orders-it-out</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/gaza-hospital-patients-cling-msf-israel-orders-it-out</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At a hospital in Gaza, wards are filled with patients fearing they will be left without care if Doctors Without Borders (MSF) is forced out under an Israeli ban due to take effect in March.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last month, Israel announced it would prevent 37 aid organisations, including MSF, from operating in Gaza from March 1 for failing to provide detailed information on their Palestinian staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"They stood by us throughout the war," said 10-year-old Adam Asfour, his left arm pinned with metal rods after he was wounded by shrapnel in a bombing in September.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 08:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran protest death toll rises as alarm grows over crackdown 'massacre'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-death-toll-rises-alarm-grows-over-crackdown-massacre</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protest-death-toll-rises-alarm-grows-over-crackdown-massacre</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At least 192 protesters have been killed in Iran's  biggest movement against the Islamic republic in more than three years, a rights group said Sunday, as warnings grew that authorities were committing a "massacre" to quell the demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests, initially sparked by anger over the rising cost of living, have now become a movement against the theocratic system in place in Iran since the 1979 revolution and have already lasted two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 08:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel on high alert for possibility of US intervention in Iran, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-high-alert-possibility-us-intervention-iran-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-high-alert-possibility-us-intervention-iran-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 11 (Reuters) - Israel is on high alert for the possibility of any U.S. intervention in Iran as authorities there confront the biggest anti-government protests in years, according to three Israeli sources with knowledge of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump has repeatedly threatened to intervene in recent days and warned Iran’s rulers against using force against demonstrators. On Saturday, Trump said the U.S. stands “ready to help”.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 06:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rubio and Netanyahu discuss Iran, Syria and Gaza, Axios reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rubio-and-netanyahu-discuss-iran-syria-and-gaza-axios-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/rubio-and-netanyahu-discuss-iran-syria-and-gaza-axios-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 10 (Reuters) - U.S. Secretary of State Marco Rubio spoke over the phone with Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on Saturday, Axios reporter Barak Ravid said on X, adding they discussed protests in Iran along with Gaza and Syria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ravid cited a U.S. source.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Kanishka Singh in Washington; Editing by Andrea Ricci)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 02:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Last SDF fighters leave Syria's Aleppo, Ekhbariya TV reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/last-sdf-fighters-leave-syrias-aleppo-ekhbariya-tv-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/last-sdf-fighters-leave-syrias-aleppo-ekhbariya-tv-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 11 (Reuters) - The last Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces fighters have left Aleppo, Syrian state-run Ekhbariya TV said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SDF head said the group had reached an understanding on a ceasefire and the evacuation of trapped civilians and fighters from Aleppo's Ashrafiyya and Sheikh Maksoud neighborhoods to northern and eastern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Yomna EhabEditing by Rod Nickel)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 00:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bangladesh seeks to join international force in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bangladesh-seeks-join-international-force-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bangladesh-seeks-join-international-force-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 10 (Reuters) - Bangladesh said on Saturday it has told the United States that it wants to join the international stabilization force that would be deployed in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bangladesh said its national security adviser, Khalilur Rahman, met U.S. diplomats Allison Hooker and Paul Kapur in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 23:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Protester put pre-Islamic revolution Iran flag on London embassy: witnesses</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/protester-put-pre-islamic-revolution-iran-flag-london-embassy-witnesses</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/protester-put-pre-islamic-revolution-iran-flag-london-embassy-witnesses</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A protester briefly replaced the flag of the Islamic Republic of Iran on its London embassy with a former flag, flown before 1979, during a demonstration Saturday, witnesses told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A video posted to social media showed a man on the balcony of the embassy, near Hyde Park, replace the country's current flag with one used during the rule of the ousted shah to cheers from hundreds of demonstrators below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flag -- tri-coloured, with a lion and sun, surrounded by a wreath and crown -- was a ceremonial one used in Iran before the Islamic revolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 18:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt announces results of last seats in parliament vote that gave Sisi strong majority</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypt-announces-results-last-seats-parliament-vote-gave-sisi-strong-majority</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypt-announces-results-last-seats-parliament-vote-gave-sisi-strong-majority</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 10 - Egypt’s National Elections Authority declared the results on Saturday of the last 49 seats in a parliamentary election that began more than three months ago and gave President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi the super-majority he needs to amend the constitution. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The results of the final seats had been held up by reruns of voting in constituencies where initial results had been annulled.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 16:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemen's main separatist group denies disbanding</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemens-main-separatist-group-denies-disbanding</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/yemens-main-separatist-group-denies-disbanding</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 10 (Reuters) - Yemen's main separatist group, the Southern Transitional Council, denied on Saturday it was disbanding, according to a statement posted on X.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The statement comes amid conflicting remarks by members on the UAE-backed group's fate, reflecting a feud between Gulf powers Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates that was blown into the open by a separatist advance last month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Menna Alaa El-Din and Jaidaa Taha. Editing by Mark Potter)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 10:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's army vows to protect public property as Tehran seeks to quell growing unrest</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-army-vows-protect-public-property-tehran-seeks-quell-growing-unrest</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-army-vows-protect-public-property-tehran-seeks-quell-growing-unrest</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 10 (Reuters) - The Iranian army said on Saturday it would safeguard strategic infrastructure and public property and urged Iranians to thwart "the enemy's plots", as the clerical establishment steps up efforts to quell the country's biggest protests in years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Iranian military statement came after U.S. President Donald Trump issued a new warning to Iran's leaders on Friday, and after Secretary of State Marco Rubio on Saturday declared: "The United States supports the brave people of Iran."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>China, Russia, Iran start 'BRICS Plus' naval exercises in South African waters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/china-russia-iran-start-brics-plus-naval-exercises-south-african-waters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/china-russia-iran-start-brics-plus-naval-exercises-south-african-waters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tim Cocks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JOHANNESBURG, Jan 10 (Reuters) - China, Russia and Iran began a week of joint naval exercises in South Africa's waters on Saturday in what the host country described as a BRICS Plus operation to "ensure the safety of shipping and maritime economic activities".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BRICS Plus is an expansion of a geopolitical bloc originally comprising Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa - and seen by members as a counterweight to U.S. and Western economic dominance - to include six other countries.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fresh protests in Iran as internet blackout persists</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fresh-protests-iran-internet-blackout-persists</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fresh-protests-iran-internet-blackout-persists</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Anti-government chants filled the streets of Iran's capital on Saturday night, as protesters pressed the biggest movement against the Islamic republic in more than three years&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;despite a deadly crackdown under cover of an internet blackout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran has blamed the United States for the demonstrations, which ignited in Tehran two weeks ago over economic hardship and have since fanned nationwide with calls for ousting the clerical authorities. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rights groups have reported dozens of deaths and expressed alarm on Saturday that authorities were intensifying the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 09:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>