<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>South Africa to probe unexpected arrival of Palestinian group</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/south-africa-probe-unexpected-arrival-palestinian-group</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/south-africa-probe-unexpected-arrival-palestinian-group</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Sfundo  Parakozov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JOHANNESBURG (Reuters) -South Africa granted entry to 130 Palestinians without travel papers after initially barring them but said it will examine accusations that an unregistered organisation arranged their trip "in an irregular and irresponsible manner".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;South Africa has long supported Palestinian aspirations to statehood and filed a case against Israel at the International Court of Justice in 2023 accusing it of genocide in the Gaza war. Israel has denied the accusations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 14:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tens of thousands of displaced people missing in Sudan's Darfur, UN says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tens-thousands-displaced-people-missing-sudans-darfur-un-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tens-thousands-displaced-people-missing-sudans-darfur-un-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emma Farge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA (Reuters) -Tens of thousands of people who have fled the Sudanese city of al-Fashir are unaccounted for, the U.N. refugee agency said on Friday, raising concerns for their safety after reports of rape, killings and other abuses from escapees.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Famine-stricken al-Fashir was the final stronghold of the Sudanese army in the vast, western Darfur region before it fell to the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces on October 26 after an 18-month siege.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 14:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU considers training 3,000 Palestinian police officers from Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/eu-considers-training-3000-palestinian-police-officers-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/eu-considers-training-3000-palestinian-police-officers-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Lili Bayer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS (Reuters) -European Union foreign ministers will discuss next week a proposal for the bloc to take the lead in training 3,000 Palestinian police officers with the aim of later deploying them in Gaza, according to a document seen by Reuters on Friday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a paper produced by the bloc’s diplomatic arm ahead of the gathering of ministers on November 20, officials outlined options for contributing to the implementation of a 20-point plan for Gaza proposed by U.S. President Donald Trump. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 12:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greece in talks to buy anti-aircraft, artillery systems from Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/greece-talks-buy-anti-aircraft-artillery-systems-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/greece-talks-buy-anti-aircraft-artillery-systems-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS (Reuters) -Greece is in talks with Israel to buy modern missile systems that would be used for a planned anti-aircraft defence dome, two officials with knowledge of the plan told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Athens has said it will spend about 28 billion euros ($33 billion) by 2036 to modernise its armed forces as it emerges from a 2009-2018 debt crisis and tries to keep pace with its historic rival Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 11:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesia says its Gaza peacekeepers would focus on health, infrastructure tasks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/indonesia-says-its-gaza-peacekeepers-would-focus-health-infrastructure-tasks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/indonesia-says-its-gaza-peacekeepers-would-focus-health-infrastructure-tasks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JAKARTA (Reuters) -Indonesia has trained up to 20,000 troops to take on health and construction-related tasks during a planned peacekeeping operation in the war-torn enclave of Gaza, the defence minister said on Friday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The world's most populous Muslim nation, Indonesia is among the countries with which the United States has discussed plans for a multinational stabilisation force in Gaza, which include Azerbaijan, Egypt and Qatar. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Human Rights Council begins emergency session on Sudan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-human-rights-council-begins-emergency-session-sudan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-human-rights-council-begins-emergency-session-sudan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA (Reuters) -A special session on the situation in al-Fashir, Sudan, opened on Friday at the U.N. Human Rights Council in Geneva following grave concerns about mass killings during the fall of the city to paramilitary forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;States will consider a draft resolution which requests a U.N. fact-finding mission to conduct an urgent inquiry into recent violations allegedly committed by the Rapid Support Forces and their allies in al-Fashir, as well as identifying the perpetrators.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 08:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas quietly reasserts control in Gaza as post-war talks grind on</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-quietly-reasserts-control-gaza-post-war-talks-grind</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-quietly-reasserts-control-gaza-post-war-talks-grind</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -From regulating the price of chicken to levying fees on cigarettes, Hamas is seeking to widen control over Gaza as U.S. plans for its future slowly take shape, Gazans say, adding to rivals' doubts over whether it will cede authority as promised.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 08:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia proposes its own UN resolution on Gaza in challenge to US draft</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/russia-proposes-its-own-un-resolution-gaza-challenge-us-draft</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/russia-proposes-its-own-un-resolution-gaza-challenge-us-draft</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Simon Lewis and Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -Russia on Thursday proposed its own draft of a U.N. resolution on Gaza in a challenge to a U.S. effort to pass its own text at the Security Council that would endorse President Donald Trump's Gaza peace plan, according to a copy of the draft seen by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. formally circulated the draft resolution to the 15 Council members last week and has said it has regional support for its resolution that would authorize a two-year mandate for a transitional governance body and international stabilization force.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 23:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran asks UN to hold US accountable for directing Israel's summer strikes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-asks-un-hold-us-accountable-directing-israels-summer-strikes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-asks-un-hold-us-accountable-directing-israels-summer-strikes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jasper Ward&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araghchi called for the United Nations to impose "appropriate measures" against the United States and Israel over military strikes in June against Iran's nuclear sites.Araghchi said that President Donald Trump and other U.S. officials bear "criminal responsibility" for the strikes after Trump's statement last week that he directed Israel's initial attack on Iran on June 13. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 22:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US officials raise concerns over Saudi Arabia's bid for F-35 jets, the New York Times reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-officials-raise-concerns-over-saudi-arabias-bid-f-35-jets-new-york-times</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-officials-raise-concerns-over-saudi-arabias-bid-f-35-jets-new-york-times</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -A Pentagon intelligence report raises concerns over Saudi Arabia's bid to buy F-35 jets from the United States, warning that China could acquire the aircraft's technology if the sale proceeds, the New York Times reported on Thursday, citing people familiar with the assessment. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Jasper Ward; Writing by Katharine Jackson)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 21:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Saudi to bolster trade with Lebanon after drug smuggling curbed</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-saudi-bolster-trade-lebanon-after-drug-smuggling-curbed</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-saudi-bolster-trade-lebanon-after-drug-smuggling-curbed</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;RIYADH (Reuters) -Saudi Arabia plans imminently to boost commercial ties with Lebanon after Lebanese authorities demonstrated "efficacy" in curbing drug smuggling to the kingdom over the past months, a senior Saudi official said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ties between Riyadh and Beirut have been strained for years due to the power of Iran-backed Hezbollah over Lebanese political and security affairs, but the kingdom sees an opening after the group was severely weakened by war with Israel last year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 21:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Like a horror movie': 770 km of fear for those fleeing Sudan's El-Fasher</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/horror-movie-770-km-fear-those-fleeing-sudans-el-fasher</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/horror-movie-770-km-fear-those-fleeing-sudans-el-fasher</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Survivors of the bloody takeover of El-Fasher walked for days through the desert, past bodies and armed men who humiliated them, desperate to escape the Sudanese city now overrun by paramilitary forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several gave harrowing accounts to AFP, describing scenes of terror as nearly 100,000 people fled the last army stronghold in western Darfur after its fall to Sudan's Rapid Support Forces (RSF) on October 26.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 20:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada spy agency says it foiled potentially 'lethal threats' by Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/canada-spy-agency-says-it-foiled-potentially-lethal-threats-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/canada-spy-agency-says-it-foiled-potentially-lethal-threats-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;OTTAWA (Reuters) -Canada's domestic spy agency this year foiled potentially lethal threats by Iran directed against people whom Tehran sees as enemies, the agency's head said in a rare speech on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dan Rogers, director of the Canadian Security Intelligence Service, also said his agents had blocked attempts by Russia to  illegally acquire Canadian goods and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rogers, appointed in February, spoke as he presented an annual update on security challenges facing Canada. CSIS directors seldom appear in public.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 19:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After 13 hours, 150 Gazans allowed to enter South Africa: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</guid><description>The group were reportedly stranded for several hours after opting to leave the war-torn Palestinian enclave.</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:44:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After 13 hours, 150 Gazans allowed to enter South Africa: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</guid><description>The group were reportedly stranded for several hours after opting to leave the war-torn Palestinian enclave.</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:44:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After 13 hours, 150 Gazans allowed to enter South Africa: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</guid><description>The group were reportedly stranded for several hours after opting to leave the war-torn Palestinian enclave.</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:44:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After 13 hours, 150 Gazans allowed to enter South Africa: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-13-hours-150-gazans-allowed-enter-south-africa-what-know</guid><description>The group were reportedly stranded for several hours after opting to leave the war-torn Palestinian enclave.</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:44:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>YouTube superstar MrBeast opens pop-up park in Saudi Arabia</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/youtube-superstar-mrbeast-opens-pop-park-saudi-arabia</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/youtube-superstar-mrbeast-opens-pop-park-saudi-arabia</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MrBeast, the world's most followed YouTuber with over 450 million subscribers, opened a temporary amusement park in Riyadh on Thursday, the latest celebrity drawn to Saudi Arabia as it aspires to become a major entertainment hub.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eager for a chance to meet the social media star, families and teenagers gathered at "Beast Land", a venue featuring obstacle course-like challenges similar to those in his popular videos where contestants compete for massive pay days.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian Authority says Israel killed two teens in West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-authority-says-israel-killed-two-teens-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/palestinian-authority-says-israel-killed-two-teens-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian Authority said Thursday that Israeli soldiers had killed two 15-year-olds in the occupied West Bank, while Israel called them "terrorists" attempting to carry out an attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Settler violence has surged in recent weeks across the West Bank, drawing international condemnation and even rare criticism from within the Israeli military and government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says two-state solution is most realistic option for Cyprus</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-two-state-solution-most-realistic-option-cyprus</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkey-says-two-state-solution-most-realistic-option-cyprus</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -President Tayyip Erdogan said on Thursday that Turkey believes the most realistic way to resolve political deadlock over Cyprus is to have two states on the ethnically-split island.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Erdogan was speaking alongside Tufan Erhurman, the newly-elected Turkish Cypriot president who has pledged to explore a federal solution - long supported by the United Nations - to end the island's nearly 50-year-old division.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 16:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>