<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>France to increase visas for Iranian seeking refuge amid crackdown, minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-increase-visas-iranian-seeking-refuge-amid-crackdown-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-increase-visas-iranian-seeking-refuge-amid-crackdown-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Feb 11 (Reuters) - France will increase the number of visas for Iranians seeking asylum as a result of the recent crackdown by Iranian authorities, Foreign Minister Jean-Noel Barrot said on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking in parliament, Barrot said Paris wanted to support the Iranian people by any means possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"In particular by welcoming opponents persecuted by the regime who are seeking asylum and refuge in France. We will increase our humanitarian visas for asylum purposes for these individuals whom we must protect," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli court ordered prisons to give Palestinian detainees more food. They are still hungry</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-court-ordered-prisons-give-palestinian-detainees-more-food-they-are-still</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-court-ordered-prisons-give-palestinian-detainees-more-food-they-are-still</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;NABLUS, West Bank, Feb 11 (Reuters) - Five months after Israel's Supreme Court ruled that its prisons were failing to provide enough food for Palestinian detainees and ordered conditions be improved, emaciated prisoners are still emerging with tales of extreme hunger and abuse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samer Khawaireh, 45, told Reuters that all he was given to eatin Israel's Megiddo and Nafha prisons was ten thin pieces of bread over the course of a day, with a bit of hummus and tahini. Twice a week some tuna. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US firm involved in defunct Gaza aid scheme recruits new officers, website shows</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-firm-involved-defunct-gaza-aid-scheme-recruits-new-officers-website-shows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-firm-involved-defunct-gaza-aid-scheme-recruits-new-officers-website-shows</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Pesha Magid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 11 (Reuters) - The U.S. security firm that deployed armed military veterans to Gaza to guard aid sites run by a now-defunct distribution operation is seeking to hire Arabic-speaking contractors with combat experience, according to job listings on its website.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 13:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Poland and Italy say they will not join Trump's Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/poland-and-italy-say-they-will-not-join-trumps-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/poland-and-italy-say-they-will-not-join-trumps-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WARSAW, Feb 11 (Reuters) - Poland and Italy will not join U.S. President Donald Trump's Board of Peace, Warsaw and Rome said on Wednesday, adding to the list of Washington's allies remaining on the sidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially designed to cement Gaza's ceasefire, Trump sees the Board of Peace taking a wider role in resolving global conflicts which some countries fear means it could become a rival to the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This along with the fact that Russia and Belarus were invited to join means many Western countries have taken a cautious approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 13:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN says Israel's West Bank plans would accelerate 'dispossession of Palestinians'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-says-israels-west-bank-plans-would-accelerate-dispossession-palestinians</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-says-israels-west-bank-plans-would-accelerate-dispossession-palestinians</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's plans to tighten control over the occupied West Bank, paving the way for further settlement expansion, are a step towards consolidating illegal annexation, the UN rights chief said Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The plans include allowing Jewish Israelis to buy West Bank land directly, and extending greater Israeli control over areas where the Palestinian Authority exercises power. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Volker Turk, the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights, said the decisions by Israel's security cabinet were the latest in a string of measures to annex Palestinian lands.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 13:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says it won't negotiate over its missile capabilities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-says-it-wont-negotiate-over-its-missile-capabilities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-says-it-wont-negotiate-over-its-missile-capabilities</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 11 (Reuters) - Iran's missile capabilities are its red line and are not a subject to be negotiated, an adviser to Iran's supreme leader said on Wednesday, as Tehran and Washington eye a new round of talks to avert conflict. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. and Iranian diplomats held indirect talks last week in Oman, amid a regional naval buildup by the U.S. threatening Iran. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The Islamic Republic's missile capabilities are non-negotiable," Ali Shamkhani said according to state media while appearing in a march commemorating the 47th anniversary of the Islamic Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 11:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Autopsies show migrants in shipwreck off Greece died of head injuries, not drowning</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/autopsies-show-migrants-shipwreck-greece-died-head-injuries-not-drowning</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/autopsies-show-migrants-shipwreck-greece-died-head-injuries-not-drowning</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Yannis Souliotis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Feb 11 (Reuters) - Most of the 15 Afghan migrants who were killed off the Greek island of Chios last week when their dinghy collided with a coast guard vessel died of head injuries, not from drowning, autopsy results seen by Reuters show.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A criminal investigation has been opened into the February 3 collision - one of Greece's deadliest migrant accidents in years - in which a coast guard vessel struck a dinghy carrying about 39 people, causing it to capsize.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 11:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia says US restrictions on its role in Venezuela's oil business are discrimination</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-says-us-restrictions-its-role-venezuelas-oil-business-are-discrimination</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-says-us-restrictions-its-role-venezuelas-oil-business-are-discrimination</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Dmitry Antonov and Vladimir Soldatkin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 11 (Reuters) - Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov said on Wednesday that new U.S. restrictions on the role of Russia and other countries in Venezuela's oil business were blatant discrimination and the Kremlin said it would clarify the matter with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Treasury Department on Tuesday issued a general license to facilitate the exploration and production of oil and gas in Venezuela. The license did not authorise transactions involving Russian, Chinese and Iranian nationals or entities.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 11:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkish and Greek leaders set for talks on migration, maritime borders</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkish-and-greek-leaders-set-talks-migration-maritime-borders</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkish-and-greek-leaders-set-talks-migration-maritime-borders</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Feb 11 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan will host Greek Prime Minister Kyriakos Mitsotakis on Wednesday for talks likely to focus on migration and longstanding maritime disputes, as the NATO allies and historic rivals try to build on warming ties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fifteen migrants died in a shipwreck off the Greek island of Chios last week after their boat collided with a Greek coastguard vessel and sank in the Aegean Sea off the Turkish coast. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Qatar Emir and Trump discuss regional de-escalation, royal court says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/qatar-emir-and-trump-discuss-regional-de-escalation-royal-court-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/qatar-emir-and-trump-discuss-regional-de-escalation-royal-court-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 11 (Reuters) - Qatar's Emir Sheikh Tamim bin Hamad al-Thani and U.S. President Donald Trump discussed in a phone call efforts for regional de-escalation and stability, the Emiri Diwan said on Wednesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The call comes ahead of a meeting between Trump and Benjamin Netanyahu where the Israeli prime minister is expected to press him to widen U.S. talks with Iran to include curbs on Tehran's missile arsenal and other security threats beyond its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Nayera Abdallah and Jana Choukeir; Editing by Andrew Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 08:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Takeaways from six previous Trump-Netanyahu meetings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/takeaways-six-previous-trump-netanyahu-meetings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/takeaways-six-previous-trump-netanyahu-meetings</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 11 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu will meet President Donald Trump on Wednesday to discuss renewed U.S. nuclear negotiations with Iran amid concern that failed talks could spark a wider conflict.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are the takeaways from the six previous meetings of the two leaders, mostly focused on Iran and Gaza, since Trump's White House return in January 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* February 4, 2025: In a shock announcement, Trump says the U.S. wants to take over the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 07:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu expected to press Trump over Iran diplomacy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-expected-press-trump-over-iran-diplomacy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-expected-press-trump-over-iran-diplomacy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/JERUSALEM, Feb 11 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump will host Benjamin Netanyahu at the White House on Wednesday where the Israeli prime minister is expected to press him to widen U.S. talks with Iran to include curbs on Tehran’s missile arsenal and other security threats that go beyond its nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 06:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan appoints new justice and interior ministers</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkeys-erdogan-appoints-new-justice-and-interior-ministers</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkeys-erdogan-appoints-new-justice-and-interior-ministers</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Feb 11 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan replaced the country's justice and interior ministers in a mini reshuffle on Wednesday, with Istanbul chief prosecutor Akin Gurlek taking the role of justice minister, the Official Gazette said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It said Gurlek replaced Yilmaz Tunc as justice minister, while Erdogan appointed Erzurum provincial governor Mustafa Ciftci as interior minister in place of Ali Yerlikaya.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Ezgi Erkoyun; Editing by Daren Butler)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 04:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu to push Trump on Iran missiles in White House talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/netanyahu-push-trump-iran-missiles-white-house-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/netanyahu-push-trump-iran-missiles-white-house-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu will push Donald Trump on Wednesday to take a tougher stance in nuclear talks with Iran, after rushing to Washington to stiffen the US president's resolve.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump said on the eve of the hastily arranged White House meeting -- set to begin at 11:00 am (1600 GMT)-- that he was weighing sending a second US "armada" to the Middle East to pressure Tehran to reach a nuclear deal.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 04:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Anti-Khamenei slogans in Tehran on eve of revolution anniversary: social media footage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/anti-khamenei-slogans-tehran-eve-revolution-anniversary-social-media-footage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/anti-khamenei-slogans-tehran-eve-revolution-anniversary-social-media-footage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Some residents of the Iranian capital Tehran on Tuesday chanted slogans against the Islamic republic and supreme leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei on the eve of the most significant annual commemoration of the 1979 Islamic revolution, according to footage posted on social media.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran was rocked by protests last month opposing the Islamic republic, which were put down by what activists condemned as an unprecedented crackdown by the authorities, with thousands shot dead by security forces.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 23:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Erdogan taps Istanbul prosecutor as justice minister in cabinet reshuffle</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</guid><description>Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan on Tuesday appointed Istanbul Chief Public Prosecutor Akin Gurlek, who has been overseeing the ongoing investigation against Turkey’s main opposition party as justice minister.</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 21:17:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Erdogan taps Istanbul prosecutor as justice minister in cabinet reshuffle</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</guid><description>Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan on Tuesday appointed Istanbul Chief Public Prosecutor Akin Gurlek, who has been overseeing the ongoing investigation against Turkey’s main opposition party as justice minister.</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 21:17:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Erdogan taps Istanbul prosecutor as justice minister in cabinet reshuffle</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</guid><description>Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan on Tuesday appointed Istanbul Chief Public Prosecutor Akin Gurlek, who has been overseeing the ongoing investigation against Turkey’s main opposition party as justice minister.</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 21:17:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Erdogan taps Istanbul prosecutor as justice minister in cabinet reshuffle</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/erdogan-taps-istanbul-prosecutor-justice-minister-cabinet-reshuffle</guid><description>Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan on Tuesday appointed Istanbul Chief Public Prosecutor Akin Gurlek, who has been overseeing the ongoing investigation against Turkey’s main opposition party as justice minister.</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 21:17:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>100 non-Syrian Kurds return to PKK’s Qandil stronghold under SDF-Damascus deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/100-non-syrian-kurds-return-pkks-qandil-stronghold-under-sdf-damascus-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/100-non-syrian-kurds-return-pkks-qandil-stronghold-under-sdf-damascus-deal</guid><description>The transfer of non-Syrian PKK fighters to Iraq’s Qandil Mountains follows a US-brokered SDF-Damascus deal aimed at easing tensions and preserving Kurdish forces under national army oversight.</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 19:13:44 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>