<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Iran deaths went beyond protesters, hitting bystanders too, witnesses say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-deaths-went-beyond-protesters-hitting-bystanders-too-witnesses-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-deaths-went-beyond-protesters-hitting-bystanders-too-witnesses-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Art student Arash was walking home through the streets of Tehran when a shotgun blast ended his life. He had not shouted slogans, joined protesters or raised a fist. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A friend, speaking by telephone from the Iranian capital, described the moment in a voice cracking with grief: Arash fell instantly, lifeless on the pavement. He was 22.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Olympics-No formal communication yet with Trump on LA 2028 Games, says IOC</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/olympics-no-formal-communication-yet-trump-la-2028-games-says-ioc</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/olympics-no-formal-communication-yet-trump-la-2028-games-says-ioc</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LAUSANNE, Switzerland, Jan 21 (Reuters) - The International Olympic Committee has not yet had any formal communication with the White House and U.S. President Donald Trump on preparations for the Los Angeles 2028 Summer Olympics, IOC President Kirsty Coventry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump marked the end of a turbulent first year in office on Tuesday, havingrocked international diplomatic waters with his case for acquiring Greenland as an Arctic guard post against Russia and China, and threatening a trade war with Europeans who oppose him.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of jailed journalists fell from record high in 2025, CPJ report says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/number-jailed-journalists-fell-record-high-2025-cpj-report-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/number-jailed-journalists-fell-record-high-2025-cpj-report-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - The number of journalists jailed worldwide declined in 2025 but remains near record highs, the Committee to Protect Journalists said in a report on Wednesday that warned about ongoing threats to press freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The group said 330 journalists were behind bars as of December 1, down from a record high of 384 reported at the end of 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report said there were 50 journalists imprisoned in China, the most of any single country, followed by Myanmar with 30 and Israel with 29. It said that all of the journalists imprisoned in Israel were Palestinian.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria says seven soldiers killed in a drone attack by Kurdish forces</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-says-seven-soldiers-killed-drone-attack-kurdish-forces</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-says-seven-soldiers-killed-drone-attack-kurdish-forces</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - Seven Syrian soldiers were killed in a drone attack by the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces in northeastern Syria's Hasakah province, Syria's Defence Ministry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The drone attack took place in the countryside against an explosives workshop that was being secured by the army, the state news agency reported. The SDF has pulled back from a swathe of northern and eastern Syria this week, handing over territory to the army.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ahmed ElimamEditing by Peter Graff)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Drone attacks shock city in central Sudan as war inches closer</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/drone-attacks-shock-city-central-sudan-war-inches-closer</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/drone-attacks-shock-city-central-sudan-war-inches-closer</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Eltayeb Siddig&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EL OBEID, Sudan, Jan 21 - Drone strikes have intensified in and around al-Obeid in central Sudan as the country's devastating civil war closes in on the army-controlled city, causing significant civiliandeaths in at least two cases, residents say.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The city is one of Sudan's most important and the capital of North Kordofan state, part of the wider Kordofan region that stands between the RSF's Darfur stronghold and the army-controlled eastern half of the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan to join Trump's 'Board of Peace' on Gaza, says foreign office</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-gaza-says-foreign-office</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-join-trumps-board-peace-gaza-says-foreign-office</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Asif Shahzad and Ariba Shahid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Pakistan will join U.S. President Donald Trump's "Board of Peace" to help achieve lasting peace in Gaza, its foreign ministry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pakistan hoped "concrete steps will be taken towards the implementation of a permanent ceasefire" as well as to boost aid and Gaza's reconstruction, the ministry said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The announcement came after Pakistani army chief Field Marshal Asim Munir flew to Davos, three Pakistani officials told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fate of IS detainees uncertain as Damascus reins in Kurds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fate-detainees-uncertain-damascus-reins-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/fate-detainees-uncertain-damascus-reins-kurds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Syrian government's attempt to wrest back control of Kurdish-held areas has thrown into doubt the fate of thousands of suspected Islamic State group jihadists detained there, with Western observers worried many could take advantage of the chaos to escape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces spearheaded the battle against IS in Syria, backed by a US-led coalition, after it declared a "caliphate" in swathes of Syria and neighbouring Iraq in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's foreign minister to represent Erdogan on 'Board of Peace', source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-foreign-minister-represent-erdogan-board-peace-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-foreign-minister-represent-erdogan-board-peace-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan will represent Turkey's president on U.S. President Donald Trump's international "Board of Peace" initiative, a Turkish source told Reuters on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump had sent an invitation to President Tayyip Erdogan to become a member of the board, an initiative that initially aimed to end the conflict in Gaza but that Trump has said will resolve conflicts globally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump is due to preside over a ceremony marking the "Board of Peace" on Thursday at the annual meeting of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli fire kills five Palestinians as Trump seeks to advance Gaza peace deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-five-palestinians-trump-seeks-advance-gaza-peace-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-five-palestinians-trump-seeks-advance-gaza-peace-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Israeli fire killed five Palestinians, including two boys, in central and southern Gaza, local health authorities said, and the Israeli military said it had "eliminated" a Palestinian militant who posed a threat to soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel and Hamas have traded blame for many breaches of the October ceasefire after two years of war that devastated Gaza and caused a humanitarian disaster, and remain at odds over the next steps in U.S. President Donald Trump's 20-point peace plan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan says Kurdish forces in Syria must lay down arms and disband now</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-says-kurdish-forces-syria-must-lay-down-arms-and-disband-now</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-says-kurdish-forces-syria-must-lay-down-arms-and-disband-now</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan said on Wednesday that Kurdish forces in northern Syria must lay down weapons and disband now to avoid further bloodshed, after Damascus struck a ceasefire with the group and gave them four days to agree on integrating into the central state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syria's Turkey-backed government forces seized swathes of territory from the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF) in northeast Syria this week, as part of President Ahmed al-Sharaa's efforts to bring all the country under central government authority. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria accuses Kurdish force of truce breach as army enters IS-linked camp</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-accuses-kurdish-force-truce-breach-army-enters-linked-camp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-accuses-kurdish-force-truce-breach-army-enters-linked-camp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria on Wednesday accused Kurdish-led forces of breaching a ceasefire after seven soldiers were killed in a strike, while authorities entered a camp holding suspected relatives of Islamic State jihadists.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government announced a new truce with the Kurds on Tuesday after taking swathes of north and east Syria that had long been under the control of Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF). &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Widow of Iran's last shah says 'no turning back' after protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/widow-irans-last-shah-says-no-turning-back-after-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/widow-irans-last-shah-says-no-turning-back-after-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The widow of Iran's last shah has told AFP there is "no turning back" after a wave of protests against the country's clerical authorities, saying she is convinced the Iranian people will emerge victorious. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driven into exile with her husband in January 1979 during a popular revolution that brought the Islamic republic to power, Farah Pahlavi said her "desire" and "need today are to return to Iran", in an exclusive interview with AFP.  &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italy won't take part in Trump's "Board of Peace", Corriere says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/italy-wont-take-part-trumps-board-peace-corriere-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/italy-wont-take-part-trumps-board-peace-corriere-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ROME, Jan 21 (Reuters) - Italy won't take part in U.S. President Donald Trump's "Board of Peace" initiative, daily Corriere della Sera reported on Wednesday, citing concern that joining such a group led by a single country's leader would violate Italy's constitution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump's plan has so far drawn cautious reactions from Western allies, as diplomats say it could undermine the work of the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Trump is due to preside over a ceremony celebrating the new group in Davos, Switzerland, site of the World Economic Forum.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu accepts invitation to join Trump's Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israels-netanyahu-accepts-invitation-join-trumps-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israels-netanyahu-accepts-invitation-join-trumps-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 21 (Reuters) - Israel's Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on Wednesday accepted U.S. President Donald Trump's invitation to join the so-called "Board of Peace", an initiative that aims initially to end the conflict in Gaza but which could then be expanded to tackle conflicts elsewhere, Netanyahu office posted on X.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Nayera Abdallah; Editing by Tom Hogue)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says he had a 'very good call' with Turkish President Erdogan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-had-very-good-call-turkish-president-erdogan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-had-very-good-call-turkish-president-erdogan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 20 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said on Tuesday he had a "very good call" with Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan, without elaborating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier on Tuesday, Trump told reporters during a briefing at the White House that he was going to have "a very important call" with Erdogan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was a very good call," Trump said Tuesday evening, as he left the White House to go to the World Economic Forum in Switzerland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Trevor Hunnicutt; writing by Kanishka Singh; Editing by Nia Williams)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 02:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN report declares global state of 'water bankruptcy'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-report-declares-global-state-water-bankruptcy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-report-declares-global-state-water-bankruptcy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The world is entering an era of "global water bankruptcy" with rivers, lakes and aquifers depleting faster than nature can replenish them, a United Nations research institute said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It argues that decades of overuse, pollution, environmental destruction and climate pressure had pushed many water systems so beyond the point of recovery that a new classification was required.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says 'you got to let the UN continue' when asked about so-called 'Board of Peace'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-you-got-let-un-continue-when-asked-about-so-called-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-you-got-let-un-continue-when-asked-about-so-called-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Trevor Hunnicutt and Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 20 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said on Tuesday "you got to let the U.N. continue" when asked about his plans for a so-called "Board of Peace" that has alarmed international experts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Governments around the world have reacted cautiously to Trump's invitation to join that initiative that the U.S. president says aims to resolve conflicts globally, a plan that diplomats said could harm the work of the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump praises Syria's Sharaa after truce reached with SDF</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-syrias-sharaa-after-truce-reached-sdf</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-syrias-sharaa-after-truce-reached-sdf</guid><description>The Trump administration’s Syria envoy said Tuesday that Washington believed Damascus could handle the country’s continued fight against ISIS, signaling a major shift in the US' policy toward the Kurdish forces.</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:53:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump praises Syria's Sharaa after truce reached with SDF</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-syrias-sharaa-after-truce-reached-sdf</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-syrias-sharaa-after-truce-reached-sdf</guid><description>The Trump administration’s Syria envoy said Tuesday that Washington believed Damascus could handle the country’s continued fight against ISIS, signaling a major shift in the US' policy toward the Kurdish forces.</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:53:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump praises Syria's Sharaa after truce reached with SDF</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-syrias-sharaa-after-truce-reached-sdf</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-praises-syrias-sharaa-after-truce-reached-sdf</guid><description>The Trump administration’s Syria envoy said Tuesday that Washington believed Damascus could handle the country’s continued fight against ISIS, signaling a major shift in the US' policy toward the Kurdish forces.</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:53:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>