<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>New Gaza administration committee starts police recruitment drive</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-gaza-administration-committee-starts-police-recruitment-drive</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-gaza-administration-committee-starts-police-recruitment-drive</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Pesha Magid and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/CAIRO, Feb 19 (Reuters) - A U.S.-backed Palestinian committee established to take over the civil administration of Gaza opened applications for a police force for the strip on Thursday, ahead of the inaugural meeting of President Donald Trump's Board of Peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump is expected to announce a multi-billion-dollar reconstruction plan for Gaza and detail plans for a U.N.-authorized stabilization force for the Palestinian enclave at the meeting in Washington. Establishing security in Gaza is one of many formidable hurdles.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Facing US warnings, Iran defends right to nuclear enrichment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/facing-us-warnings-iran-defends-right-nuclear-enrichment-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/facing-us-warnings-iran-defends-right-nuclear-enrichment-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's atomic energy chief on Thursday said "no country can deprive Iran of the right" to nuclear enrichment, following fresh US warnings that there were "many reasons" to strike the Islamic republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two foes recently resumed indirect talks, after US President Donald Trump repeatedly threatened military action against Iran, at first over a deadly crackdown on protesters last month then more recently over its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MSF will keep operating in Gaza 'as long as we can': mission head</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/msf-will-keep-operating-gaza-long-we-can-mission-head</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/msf-will-keep-operating-gaza-long-we-can-mission-head</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The head of Doctors Without Borders in the Palestinian territories told AFP the charity would continue working in Gaza for as long as possible, following an Israeli decision to end its activities there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In early February, Israel announced it was terminating all the activities in Gaza by the medical charity, known by its French acronym MSF, after it failed to provide a list of its Palestinian staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MSF has slammed the move, which takes effect on March 1, as a "pretext" to obstruct aid.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia warns of escalating Iran tensions amid U.S. military build up</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-warns-escalating-iran-tensions-amid-us-military-build</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-warns-escalating-iran-tensions-amid-us-military-build</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Russia warned against an "unprecedented escalation of tension" around Iran on Thursday and urged restraint amid a U.S. military build-up in the region that a senior American official said should be complete by mid-March. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. threats to bomb Iran, with the two sides far apart in talks on Tehran's nuclear programme, have pushed up oil prices and a Russian corvette on Thursday joined planned Iranian naval drills in the Gulf of Oman, a vital sea route for global energy. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN says Israeli actions raise 'ethnic cleansing' fears in West Bank, Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-says-israeli-actions-raise-ethnic-cleansing-fears-west-bank-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-says-israeli-actions-raise-ethnic-cleansing-fears-west-bank-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's increased attacks and forcible transfers of Palestinians "raise concerns over ethnic cleansing" in the Gaza Strip and West Bank, the United Nations said Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cumulative impact of Israel's military conduct during the war in Gaza and blockade of the territory, has inflicted living conditions "increasingly incompatible with Palestinians' continued existence as a group in Gaza", said the UN human rights office.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia urges restraint as US builds up military assets near Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-urges-restraint-us-builds-military-assets-near-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-urges-restraint-us-builds-military-assets-near-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Russia said on Thursday that it was seeing an unprecedented escalation of tension around Iran as the United States moved military assets into the Middle East, and the Kremlin urged both Tehran and "other parties" to exercise prudence and restraint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. has deployed warships near Iran, while also holding talks with Tehran on limiting its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli forces and Hamas committed atrocity crimes in Gaza, UN report says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-forces-and-hamas-committed-atrocity-crimes-gaza-un-report-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-forces-and-hamas-committed-atrocity-crimes-gaza-un-report-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Israeli forces, Hamas and other Palestinian armed groups have both committed serious violations of international humanitarian law in Gaza and carried out atrocity crimes, a U.N. report published on Thursday said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intensified Israeli attacks and the forcible transfer of Palestinians appeared aimed at a permanent demographic shift in Gaza "raising concerns over ethnic cleansing," the report by the U.N. human rights office said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PKK militant group source says Turkish approval of peace roadmap is important step</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pkk-militant-group-source-says-turkish-approval-peace-roadmap-important-step</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pkk-militant-group-source-says-turkish-approval-peace-roadmap-important-step</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD, Feb 19 (Reuters) - A Turkish parliamentary commission's approval of a report setting out a roadmap for legal reforms alongside the disbandment of the Kurdistan Workers Party (PKK) militant group is an important step and the beginning of a fundamental change in Turkish policy, a PKK source told Reuters on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The commission voted overwhelmingly on Wednesday to approve the report, advancing a peace process designed to end decades of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Facing US warnings, Iran defends right to nuclear enrichment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/facing-us-warnings-iran-defends-right-nuclear-enrichment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/facing-us-warnings-iran-defends-right-nuclear-enrichment</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's atomic energy chief on Thursday said "no country can deprive Iran of the right" to nuclear enrichment, following fresh US warning that there were "many reasons" to strike the Islamic republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two foes recently resumed indirect talks, after US President Donald Trump repeatedly threatened military action against Iran, at first over a deadly crackdown on protesters last month then more recently over its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>British couple held in Iran sentenced to 10 years</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/british-couple-held-iran-sentenced-10-years</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/british-couple-held-iran-sentenced-10-years</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A British couple detained in Iran since January 2025 have been sentenced to 10 years in jail for espionage, their family announced on Thursday, triggering condemnation from the UK government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lindsay and Craig Foreman, both in their 50s, were arrested while travelling through the country on an around-the-world motorcycle journey, according to relatives, and have consistently denied Tehran's spying claims.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 09:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK condemns 10-year sentence for British couple in Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uk-condemns-10-year-sentence-british-couple-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uk-condemns-10-year-sentence-british-couple-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - British foreign minister Yvette Cooper on Thursday condemned as "totally unjustifiable" the 10-year sentence given to a British couple in Iran for spying, saying the government would continue to press for their release.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Craig and Lindsay Foreman had been charged with espionage after Iran accused them of gathering information in several parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We will pursue this case relentlessly with the Iranian government until we see Craig and Lindsay Foreman safely returned to the UK and reunited with their family," Cooper said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 08:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas tightens grip in Gaza as Trump pushes peace plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hamas-tightens-grip-gaza-trump-pushes-peace-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hamas-tightens-grip-gaza-trump-pushes-peace-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/JERUSALEM, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Hamas is cementing its hold over Gaza by placing loyalists in key government roles, collecting taxes and paying salaries, according to an Israeli military assessment seen by Reuters and sources in the Palestinian enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hamas’ continuing influence over key Gaza power structures has fuelled widespread scepticism about the prospects of U.S. President Donald Trump’s peace plan, which requires the militant group to give up its weapons in exchange for an Israeli military withdrawal from the territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 06:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian police probe threatening letter to country's largest mosque ahead of Ramadan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australian-police-probe-threatening-letter-countrys-largest-mosque-ahead-ramadan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australian-police-probe-threatening-letter-countrys-largest-mosque-ahead-ramadan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Australian police said on Thursday they had launched an investigation after a threatening letter was sent to the country’s largest mosque, the third such incident in the lead-up to the Muslim fasting month of Ramadan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The letter sent to Lakemba Mosque in Sydney’s west on Wednesday contained a drawing of a pig and a threat to kill the "Muslim race", local media reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police said they had taken the letter for forensic testing, and would continue to patrol religious sites including the mosque, as well as community events.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 06:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump to preside over first meeting of Board of Peace with many Gaza questions unresolved</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-preside-over-first-meeting-board-peace-many-gaza-questions-unresolved</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-preside-over-first-meeting-board-peace-many-gaza-questions-unresolved</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steve Holland, Simon Lewis and Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump will preside over the first meeting of his Board of Peace on Thursday with unresolved questions on the future of Gaza hanging over an event expected to include representatives from more than 45 nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The disarmament of Hamas militants, the size of the reconstruction fund and the flow of humanitarian aid to the war-battered populace of Gaza are among the major questions likely to test the effectiveness of the board in the weeks and months ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Lavrov warns against any new US strike on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-lavrov-warns-against-any-new-us-strike-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-lavrov-warns-against-any-new-us-strike-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 18 (Reuters) - Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov, in an interview made public on Wednesday, said that any new U.S. strike on Iran would have serious consequences and called for restraint to find a solution to enable Iran to pursue a peaceful nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lavrov's interview with Saudi Arabia's Al-Arabiya television was aired a day after U.S. and Iranian negotiators held indirect talks in Geneva to head off a new mounting crisis between Washington and Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 01:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump kicks off his 'Board of Peace,' with eye on Gaza and beyond</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-kicks-his-board-peace-eye-gaza-and-beyond</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-kicks-his-board-peace-eye-gaza-and-beyond</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump on Thursday gathers allies to inaugurate the "Board of Peace," his new institution focused on progress on Gaza but whose ambitions reach much further.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around two dozen world leaders or other senior officials have come to Washington for the meeting -- including several of Trump's authoritarian-leaning friends and virtually none of the European democrats that traditionally sign on to US initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 01:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran expected to submit written proposal for resolving standoff with US, senior US official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-expected-submit-written-proposal-resolving-standoff-us-senior-us-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-expected-submit-written-proposal-resolving-standoff-us-senior-us-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 18 (Reuters) - Iran is expected to submit a written proposal on how to avoid its standoff with the United States in the wake of U.S.-Iran talks in Geneva on Tuesday, a senior U.S. official told Reuters on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Top national security advisers met in the White House Situation Room to discuss Iran and were told all U.S. forces deployed to the region should be in place by mid-March, the official said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State Marco Rubio will meet Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu in Israel on the weekend of February 28, the official said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 22:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In new flip, Trump attacks UK on base deal as US mulls Iran attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-flip-trump-attacks-uk-base-deal-us-mulls-iran-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-flip-trump-attacks-uk-base-deal-us-mulls-iran-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump, shifting his tone yet again, warned Britain on Wednesday not to "give away" a key Indian Ocean base, saying it would be vital if the United States attacks Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump, who is considering strikes on the Islamic republic, lashed out hours after the State Department offered the latest US support to British Prime Minister Keir Starmer's deal to return the Chagos Islands to Mauritius.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the agreement, Britain would instead pay to lease the strategic joint US-UK base at Diego Garcia for a century.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 21:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel conducting 'gradual de facto annexation' of W.Bank: UN official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-conducting-gradual-de-facto-annexation-wbank-un-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-conducting-gradual-de-facto-annexation-wbank-un-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A top UN official warned Wednesday that steps by Israel to tighten control of areas of the West Bank administered by the Palestinian Authority amount to "gradual de facto annexation."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since last week, Israel has approved a series of initiatives backed by far-right ministers to consolidate control over the West Bank where the Palestinians exercise limited autonomy under past deals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 21:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US withdrawing all forces from Syria, WSJ reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-withdrawing-all-forces-syria-wsj-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-withdrawing-all-forces-syria-wsj-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 18 (Reuters) - The United States is in the process of withdrawing all of its roughly 1,000 troops from Syria, the Wall Street Journal reported on Wednesday, citing three U.S. officials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters could not immediately verify the report.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, the U.S. military said it completed a withdrawal from a strategic base in Syria, handing it over to Syrian forces, in the latest sign of strengthening U.S.-Syrian ties that could enable an even larger American drawdown.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>