<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israel to partially reopen Gaza's Rafah crossing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-partially-reopen-gazas-rafah-crossing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-partially-reopen-gazas-rafah-crossing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel is set to partially reopen the Rafah crossing between the war-devastated Gaza Strip and Egypt on Sunday, following months of urging from humanitarian organisations, though access will be limited to the movement of people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reopening comes amid ongoing violence in the Palestinian territory, with Gaza's civil defence agency reporting dozens killed in Israeli attacks on Saturday, while the Israeli military said it was retaliating against ceasefire violations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 03:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Sudan's old port of Suakin, dreams of a tourism revival</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudans-old-port-suakin-dreams-tourism-revival</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudans-old-port-suakin-dreams-tourism-revival</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The mayor of Suakin dreams of a rebirth for his town, an ancient Red Sea port spared by the wars that have marked Sudan's history but reduced to ruins by the ravages of time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was called the 'White City'," for its unique buildings made of coral stone taken from the seabed, said mayor Abu Mohamed El-Amin Artega, who is also the leader of the Artega tribe, part of eastern Sudan's Beja ethnic group.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 02:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Qatari PM meets Iran's Larijani in Tehran, discusses easing regional tensions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/qatari-pm-meets-irans-larijani-tehran-discusses-easing-regional-tensions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/qatari-pm-meets-irans-larijani-tehran-discusses-easing-regional-tensions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 31 (Reuters) - Qatari Prime Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman al-Thani met with top Iranian security official Ali Larijani in Tehran and reviewed efforts to de-escalate tensions in the region, Qatar's foreign ministry said on Saturday in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Hatem Maher; Writing by Enas Alashray; editing by Diane Craft)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 21:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq's Shi'ite bloc reaffirms backing for Maliki despite Trump's warnings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraqs-shiite-bloc-reaffirms-backing-maliki-despite-trumps-warnings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraqs-shiite-bloc-reaffirms-backing-maliki-despite-trumps-warnings</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 31 (Reuters) - Iraq's alliance of Shi'ite political blocs, the Coordination Framework, reaffirmed on Saturday its support for former premier Nouri al-Maliki to lead the next government, despite a warning from U.S. President Donald Trump that Washington would no longer help Iraq if Maliki returned to power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bloc, which holds a majority in parliament, picked Maliki, Iraq's first elected prime minister after a U.S.-led invasion toppled Saddam Hussein in 2003, as its nominee for the post following an election.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 20:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan says 92 militants killed after attacks in Balochistan, security officials say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-says-92-militants-killed-after-attacks-balochistan-security-officials</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-says-92-militants-killed-after-attacks-balochistan-security-officials</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saleem Ahmed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QUETTA, Pakistan, Jan 31 (Reuters) - At least 92 militants were killed on Saturday battling Pakistan's security forces in multiple cities across the southwestern province of Balochistan, four security officials told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pakistan's military said in a statement sent by text message that 15 security personnel were also killed during clearance operations, while militants targeted civilians in several areas, killing at least 18 people, including women and children.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 19:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says progress made towards US talks despite attack jitters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-progress-made-towards-us-talks-despite-attack-jitters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-progress-made-towards-us-talks-despite-attack-jitters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's top security official said Saturday that progress had been made towards negotiations with the United States, even as the Islamic republic's army chief warned Washington against launching military strikes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump confirmed the two sides were talking, while keeping the threat of an attack in the foreground.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washington has deployed warships led by the USS Abraham Lincoln aircraft carrier off Iran's shores, after Trump threatened to intervene in the wake of Tehran's deadly crackdown on anti-government protests.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 19:00:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Protesters in Copenhagen rally for Danish veterans after Trump remarks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/protesters-copenhagen-rally-danish-veterans-after-trump-remarks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/protesters-copenhagen-rally-danish-veterans-after-trump-remarks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Soren  Jeppesen and Tom Little&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;COPENHAGEN, Jan 31 (Reuters) - Hundreds of Danes gathered outside the U.S. Embassy in Copenhagen on Saturday in support of veterans who said they had been insulted by President Donald Trump's comment that European allies had kept "off the front lines" in the Afghanistan war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Denmark, with a population less than 2% the size of the United States, was one of the major combat allies in the U.S.-led war in Afghanistan, losing 44 service members killed, a per capita death toll on par with that of the Americans themselves. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 18:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explosion occurs at Iran's southern port of Bandar Abbas, Iranian media reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explosion-occurs-irans-southern-port-bandar-abbas-iranian-media-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explosion-occurs-irans-southern-port-bandar-abbas-iranian-media-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 31 (Reuters) - An explosion occurred at Iran's southern port of Bandar Abbas on Saturday, Iranian media reported, without giving a cause for the blast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The semi-official Tasnim news agency said that social media reports alleging that a Revolutionary Guard navy commander was targeted in the explosion were "completely false".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian media said the blast was being investigated but gave no further information. Iranian authorities could not immediately be contacted for comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza civil defence says Israeli strikes kill 32</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/gaza-civil-defence-says-israeli-strikes-kill-32</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/gaza-civil-defence-says-israeli-strikes-kill-32</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli air strikes killed 32 people including children in Gaza on Saturday, according to the Palestinian territory's civil defence agency, as the military said it had attacked in response to a Hamas ceasefire violation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a US-brokered truce entering its second phase earlier this month, violence in the Palestinian territory has continued, with both Israel and Hamas accusing each other of violating the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 12:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands flee northwest Pakistan after mosques warn of possible military action</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-flee-northwest-pakistan-after-mosques-warn-possible-military-action</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-flee-northwest-pakistan-after-mosques-warn-possible-military-action</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Muhammad Amin Afridi  and Saad Sayeed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BARA/KARACHI, Pakistan, Jan 31 (Reuters) - Tens of thousands of people have fled a remote mountainous region in northwestern Pakistan in recent weeks, residents said, after warnings broadcast from mosques urged families to evacuate ahead of a possible military action against Islamist militants.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 09:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli strikes kill 12 in Gaza, health ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-strikes-kill-12-gaza-health-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-strikes-kill-12-gaza-health-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;GAZA, Jan 31 (Reuters) - Israeli airstrikes in Gaza killed at least 12 people, the Palestinian health ministry said, with children reported to be among the fatalities in the latest violence rattling a tenuous ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One airstrike hit an apartment in Gaza City killing three children and two women, according to a family member and the official Palestinian news agency WAFA. Another airstrike hit a tent in Khan Younis, further south, according to WAFA.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 09:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran president says Trump, Netanyahu, Europe stirred tensions in protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-president-says-trump-netanyahu-europe-stirred-tensions-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-president-says-trump-netanyahu-europe-stirred-tensions-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 31 (Reuters) - Iranian President Masoud Pezeshkian said on Saturday that U.S., Israeli and European leaders had exploited Iran's economic problems, incited unrest and provided people with the means to "tear the nation apart” in recent protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two-week long nationwide protests, which began in late December over an economic crisis marked by soaring inflation and rising living costs, have abated after a bloody crackdown by the clerical authorities that U.S.-based rights group HRANA says has killed at least 6,563, including 6,170 protesters and 214 security forces.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisia extends state of emergency by 11 months until Dec 31</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/tunisia-extends-state-emergency-11-months-until-dec-31</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/tunisia-extends-state-emergency-11-months-until-dec-31</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TUNIS, Jan 30 (Reuters) - Tunisian President Kais Saied has extended a long-running state of emergency by 11 months until December 31, the official gazette showed on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The North African country has been under a state of emergency since 2015 after an attack in which several presidential guards were killed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Tarek Amara; Editing by Chris Reese)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 22:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Will EU’s terror listing of besieged Iran's IRGC backfire?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</guid><description>The EU designation could ultimately render the IRGC an even more aggressive and defiant organization aboard, and a more assertive rights violator at home.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:35:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Will EU’s terror listing of besieged Iran's IRGC backfire?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</guid><description>The EU designation could ultimately render the IRGC an even more aggressive and defiant organization aboard, and a more assertive rights violator at home.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:35:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Will EU’s terror listing of besieged Iran's IRGC backfire?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</guid><description>The EU designation could ultimately render the IRGC an even more aggressive and defiant organization aboard, and a more assertive rights violator at home.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:35:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Will EU’s terror listing of besieged Iran's IRGC backfire?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/will-eus-terror-listing-besieged-irans-irgc-backfire</guid><description>The EU designation could ultimately render the IRGC an even more aggressive and defiant organization aboard, and a more assertive rights violator at home.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 20:35:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria to close camps housing thousands linked to Islamic State</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-close-camps-housing-thousands-linked-islamic-state</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-close-camps-housing-thousands-linked-islamic-state</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 30 (Reuters) - Syria plans to permanently close two displacement camps in the northeast that hold civilians, including foreigners, linked to Islamic State militants, a government official said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The al-Hol and Roj camps hold more than 28,000 people, mostly Syrians and Iraqis, according to the U.N. About 6,000 foreigners are housed in al-Hol and a further 2,000 in Roj. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A charity that has worked in both camps, the Swiss-based Global Community Engagement and Resilience Fund, told Reuters it understands Damascus aims to empty and shut the sites within a year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 18:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Putin meets Iran’s top security official as Trump says Tehran wants deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/putin-meets-irans-top-security-official-trump-says-tehran-wants-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/putin-meets-irans-top-security-official-trump-says-tehran-wants-deal</guid><description>President Donald Trump said on Friday that Iran is seeking a nuclear deal but declined to specify a timeline for negotiations.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 18:27:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Putin meets Iran’s top security official as Trump says Tehran wants deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/putin-meets-irans-top-security-official-trump-says-tehran-wants-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/putin-meets-irans-top-security-official-trump-says-tehran-wants-deal</guid><description>President Donald Trump said on Friday that Iran is seeking a nuclear deal but declined to specify a timeline for negotiations.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 18:27:50 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>