<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Residents of north Lebanon city lose neighbours, livelihoods in building collapse</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/residents-north-lebanon-city-lose-neighbours-livelihoods-building-collapse</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/residents-north-lebanon-city-lose-neighbours-livelihoods-building-collapse</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rubble is all that remains of the building once home to Adnan Mardash's grocery shop in north Lebanon's Tripoli after it collapsed, killing 14 people and shining a spotlight on the impoverished city's neglect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mardash, 54, said he shut the small ground-floor store where he worked for more than three decades and went to his nearby home shortly before the disaster on Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Our neighbours and loved ones died... people lost their livelihoods," said the father of four, who has no other income.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MBZ hosts Sisi as Saudi Arabia and UAE jockey for regional influence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mbz-hosts-sisi-saudi-arabia-and-uae-jockey-regional-influence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mbz-hosts-sisi-saudi-arabia-and-uae-jockey-regional-influence</guid><description>Economic ties between Egypt and the UAE are strengthening thanks to large Emirati investments in the North African country.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:34:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>International outrage grows over Israel's plans for West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/international-outrage-grows-over-israels-plans-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/international-outrage-grows-over-israels-plans-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;International outrage was growing on Monday at Israeli plans to tighten the country's grip over the occupied West Bank, with the United Nations chief saying he was "gravely concerned".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, Saudi Arabia and seven other Muslim-majority countries condemned the new Israeli measures, which pave the way for more settlements in the occupied Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US issues fresh guidance to vessels transiting Strait of Hormuz as Iran tensions simmer</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-issues-fresh-guidance-vessels-transiting-strait-hormuz-iran-tensions-simmer</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-issues-fresh-guidance-vessels-transiting-strait-hormuz-iran-tensions-simmer</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 9 (Reuters) - The United States issued fresh guidance on Monday to commercial vessels transiting the Strait of Hormuz, a key shipping lane for Middle East oil supplies, as tensions simmered between Washington and Tehran over Iran’s nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran has in the past threatened to close down the Strait of Hormuz, a portion of which lies within its territorial waters, and has at times seized commercial ships and oil tankers moving through the area alleging smuggling.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 17:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Uber snaps up Getir in Turkey as Mubadala exits battered delivery bet</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uber-snaps-getir-turkey-mubadala-exits-battered-delivery-bet</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uber-snaps-getir-turkey-mubadala-exits-battered-delivery-bet</guid><description>For Uber, the $335 million deal marks a fresh bet on a populous growth market and comes at quite the discount — as recently as 2022, Getir was valued at nearly $12 billion.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 16:49:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Syria, Sharaa's brothers take spotlight with Saudi, Russian dealings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-sharaas-brothers-take-spotlight-saudi-russian-dealings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-sharaas-brothers-take-spotlight-saudi-russian-dealings</guid><description>Hazem al-Sharaa is playing a key role in Syria’s economic development and ties with the Gulf, while Maher al-Sharaa is involved in diplomacy with Russia, though another brother has reportedly fallen out of favor with the president.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 16:41:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran steps up arrests while remaining positive on US talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-steps-arrests-while-remaining-positive-us-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-steps-arrests-while-remaining-positive-us-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran stepped up its crackdown on Monday after recent protests, making more arrests while holding the door open to Washington for further nuclear negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The arrests -- including that of Javad Emam, the spokesperson for the main reformist coalition -- came after Iranian and US officials held talks in Oman that both sides painted as positive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Iran heaped more jail time on Nobel Peace Prize winner Narges Mohammadi, and on Monday arrested Hossein Karoubi, the son of prominent dissident Mehdi Karoubi.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 16:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's army chief says 'no plans to withdraw' from Syria</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkeys-army-chief-says-no-plans-withdraw-syria</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkeys-army-chief-says-no-plans-withdraw-syria</guid><description>Turkey’s military chief said that Ankara has no plans to withdraw troops from northern Syria despite recent Damascus-SDF agreements.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 15:41:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Norway police investigate diplomat couple over suspected Epstein corruption</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-police-investigate-diplomat-couple-over-suspected-epstein-corruption</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-police-investigate-diplomat-couple-over-suspected-epstein-corruption</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Terje Solsvik and Johan Ahlander&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OSLO/STOCKHOLM, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Norwegian police are investigating two high-profile diplomats in a corruption probe announced on Monday, part of a widening scandal in the Nordic country and across Europe over prominent figures' ties to the late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mona Juul, who resigned from her post as ambassador to Jordan and Iraq on Sunday, is suspected of gross corruption while her husband, former government minister Terje Roed-Larsen, is suspected of complicity in gross corruption, police said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 15:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arab states criticise Israel as it expands powers in occupied West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arab-states-criticise-israel-it-expands-powers-occupied-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arab-states-criticise-israel-it-expands-powers-occupied-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ali Sawafta and Emily Rose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;RAMALLAH/JERUSALEM, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates led regional states on Monday in condemning Israel's move to ease settlement expansion and widen its powers in the West Bank, a step critics said went in the direction of annexing occupied land.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunday's decisions by Israel's security cabinet will make it easier for Jewish settlers to buy land in the West Bank and give Israeli authorities more power to act in areas supposedly under full Palestinian control, two senior Israeli ministers said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-What is the two-state solution to the Israel-Palestinian conflict?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/explainer-what-two-state-solution-israel-palestinian-conflict</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/explainer-what-two-state-solution-israel-palestinian-conflict</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 9, (Reuters) - Israel has taken steps to help settlers acquire land in the occupied West Bank and widen its powers in parts of the territory where Palestinians have some self-rule - measures they said aimed to undermine the two-state solution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It marks the latest blow to the idea of establishing a Palestinian state co-existing peacefully alongside Israel in territory Israel captured in the 1967 Middle East war. Long backed by world powers, this vision formed the bedrock of the U.S.-backed peace process ushered in by the 1993 Oslo Accords. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arms production to air defense: Inside $350M Egypt-Turkey military pact</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arms-production-air-defense-inside-350m-egypt-turkey-military-pact</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arms-production-air-defense-inside-350m-egypt-turkey-military-pact</guid><description>Ankara and Cairo's military framework agreement goes beyond arms sales, reflecting a gradual strategic convergence that includes intelligence sharing in third countries.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:18:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudanese nomads trapped as war fuels banditry and ethnic splits</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-nomads-trapped-war-fuels-banditry-and-ethnic-splits</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-nomads-trapped-war-fuels-banditry-and-ethnic-splits</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Eltayeb Siddig&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NEAR AL-OBEID, Sudan, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Gubara al-Basheer and his family used to traverse Sudan's desert with their camels and livestock, moving freely between markets, water sources, and green pastures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But since war erupted in 2023, he and other Arab nomads have been stuck in the desert outside the central Sudanese city of al-Obeid, threatened by marauding bandits and ethnic tensions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 13:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prince William meets Saudi leader on visit overshadowed by Epstein scandal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/prince-william-meets-saudi-leader-visit-overshadowed-epstein-scandal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/prince-william-meets-saudi-leader-visit-overshadowed-epstein-scandal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Britain's Prince William met Saudi Arabia's de facto leader Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman on Monday, kicking off a visit aimed at deepening economic cooperation but overshadowed by his disgraced uncle Andrew's links to Jeffrey Epstein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The official Saudi Press Agency (SPA) released images of Prince Mohammed giving the heir to the British throne a private tour of the At-Turaif UNESCO World Heritage Site at Diriyah, the first capital of the Saudi state, before a meeting between the two royals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says killed four militants exiting Gaza tunnel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-says-killed-four-militants-exiting-gaza-tunnel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-says-killed-four-militants-exiting-gaza-tunnel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's military said Monday it had killed four armed militants who emerged from a tunnel in southern Gaza and attacked its troops, accusing the suspects of a "blatant violation" of the ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a US-brokered truce that entered its second phase last month, violence has continued in the Palestinian territory, with Israel and Hamas trading accusations. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gaza's health officials said that six people were killed on Monday by Israeli fire in several incidents separate to the one in Rafah, including four killed in an air strike on an apartment in Gaza City.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK's Prince William and Kate 'deeply concerned' about Epstein revelations</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uks-prince-william-and-kate-deeply-concerned-about-epstein-revelations</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uks-prince-william-and-kate-deeply-concerned-about-epstein-revelations</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Britain's Prince William and his wife Kate said on Monday they were deeply concerned by the revelations in the Jeffrey Epstein files amid further damning disclosures about the heir-to-the-throne's uncle Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mountbatten-Windsor, the younger brother of King Charles who had already been cast out of the royal inner circle over his close relationship with Epstein, has faced fresh scrutiny since the recent publication of millions of new documents relating to the late convicted U.S. sex offender.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:01:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US Vice President Vance heads to Armenia, Azerbaijan to push peace, trade</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-vice-president-vance-heads-armenia-azerbaijan-push-peace-trade</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-vice-president-vance-heads-armenia-azerbaijan-push-peace-trade</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Lucy Papachristou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TBILISI, Feb 9 (Reuters) - U.S. Vice President JD Vance will visit Armenia and Azerbaijan this week to push a Washington-brokered peace agreement that could transform energy and trade routes in the strategic South Caucasus region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His two-day trip to Armenia, which begins later on Monday, comes just six months after the Armenian and Azerbaijani leaders signed an agreement at the White House seen as the first step towards peace after nearly 40 years of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Adviser to Iran's Supreme Leader to visit Oman on Tuesday after US-Iranian talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/adviser-irans-supreme-leader-visit-oman-tuesday-after-us-iranian-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/adviser-irans-supreme-leader-visit-oman-tuesday-after-us-iranian-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Ali Larijani, an adviser to Iran's Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei and secretary of its national security council, will visit Oman on Tuesday following indirect U.S.-Iranian talks there, the semi-official Tasnim news agency reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. and Iranian diplomats engaged through Omani mediation in the Gulf Arab state last week in an effort to revive diplomacy amid a U.S. naval buildup near Iran and Tehran's vows of a harsh response if attacked.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain's Prince William to meet Saudi crown prince on official visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/britains-prince-william-meet-saudi-crown-prince-official-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/britains-prince-william-meet-saudi-crown-prince-official-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Britain's Prince William will meet Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman during a three-day visit to Saudi Arabia starting on Monday, an official trip on behalf of the government to deepen ties with the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The royal's visit follows a 2025 trip to Saudi by Britain's finance minister, which London said had unlocked trade and investment agreements worth 6.4 billion pounds ($8.71 billion). &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sydney police pepper spray protesters during rallies against Israeli president's visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sydney-police-pepper-spray-protesters-during-rallies-against-israeli-presidents</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sydney-police-pepper-spray-protesters-during-rallies-against-israeli-presidents</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sydney police used pepper spray on protesters on Monday as a rally against a visit to Australia by Israel's President Isaac Herzog turned violent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The head of state's tightly secured, four-day visit was aimed at consoling Australia's Jewish community in the wake of the December shooting at Sydney's Bondi Beach that killed 15 people at a Hanukkah festival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But he was met with protests in Australia's two largest cities on Monday evening, with a Sydney rally turning violent as police hit protesters and members of the media, including AFP, with pepper spray.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>