<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Soccer-Turkey orders arrest of 17 referees, club president in betting probe</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/soccer-turkey-orders-arrest-17-referees-club-president-betting-probe</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/soccer-turkey-orders-arrest-17-referees-club-president-betting-probe</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -Turkish prosecutors said on Friday they had ordered the detention of 21 people, including 17 referees and the chairman of an unnamed Super Lig club as part of an investigation into alleged betting on soccer matches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far 18 of the 21 suspects have been detained, state-owned Anadolu news agency reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move comes a week after the Turkish Football Federation (TFF) suspended 149 referees and assistant referees after an investigation found the officials working in the country's professional leagues were betting on football matches.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 06:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says Iran has been asking if US sanctions can be lifted</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-iran-has-been-asking-if-us-sanctions-can-be-lifted</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-says-iran-has-been-asking-if-us-sanctions-can-be-lifted</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump said on Thursday that Iran has been asking if U.S. sanctions against the country can be lifted.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Iran has been asking if the sanctions could be lifted. Iran has got very heavy U.S. sanctions, and it makes it really hard for them to do what they'd like to be able to do. And I'm open to hearing that, and we'll see what happens, but I would be open to it," Trump told reporters late on Thursday at the White House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran's mission to the United Nations in New York did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 02:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kazakhstan to join Abraham Accords as Trump pushes Mideast peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kazakhstan-join-abraham-accords-trump-pushes-mideast-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kazakhstan-join-abraham-accords-trump-pushes-mideast-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Kazakhstan said Thursday it will join the Abraham Accords between Israel and mainly Muslim nations, in a largely symbolic move aimed at boosting US President Donald Trump's push for Middle East peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The central Asian republic has had diplomatic ties with Israel for decades, unlike the four Arab states that normalized relations with Israel under the original accords signed in Trump's first term.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But with Trump aiming to shore up his fragile Gaza ceasefire deal, Washington is pushing to get as much support as possible behind a wider peace initiative.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 21:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Freed Israeli hostage says he faced sexual violence in Gaza captivity, TV reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/freed-israeli-hostage-says-he-faced-sexual-violence-gaza-captivity-tv-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/freed-israeli-hostage-says-he-faced-sexual-violence-gaza-captivity-tv-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -An Israeli hostage who was released in October has told an Israeli television channel he was subjected to sexual violence during his two-year captivity in Gaza by Palestinian militants -- the first male hostage to publicly make such an accusation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rom Braslavski, 21, who was abducted from the Nova music festival on October 7, 2023, made the allegation in an interview with Channel 13's Hazinor programme. Excerpts of the interview, broadcast late on Thursday, were shared with Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 20:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council removes sanctions on Syria's president and interior minister</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-removes-sanctions-syrias-president-and-interior-minister</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-removes-sanctions-syrias-president-and-interior-minister</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) -The United Nations Security Council removed sanctions on Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa, who is due to meet U.S. President Donald Trump at the White House on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S.-drafted resolution on Thursday also lifted sanctions on Syrian Interior Minister Anas Khattab. It received 14 votes in favor, while China abstained.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washington has been urging the 15-member Security Council for months to ease Syria sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 20:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council votes to lift sanctions on Syrian president</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-votes-lift-sanctions-syrian-president</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-votes-lift-sanctions-syrian-president</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Security Council voted in favor of a US resolution on Thursday to lift sanctions on Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa, ahead of his White House visit next week. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"(The Council) decides that Ahmed al-Sharaa...and (Interior Minister) Anas Hasan Khattab are delisted from the ISIL and Al-Qaida Sanctions List," said the resolution, approved by 14 council members. China abstained.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 20:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pirates board tanker off Somalia in biggest escalation since 2024</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pirates-board-tanker-somalia-biggest-escalation-2024</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pirates-board-tanker-somalia-biggest-escalation-2024</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Saul and Renee Maltezou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ATHENS (Reuters) -Pirates boarded a Malta-flagged products tanker off Somalia on Thursday, but the crew took refuge in a fortified safe room and remain in control of the vessel, maritime security sources said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A burst of armed attacks on vessels in the region - including the first involving suspected Somali pirates in a year - has reignited concerns for shipping lanes used to transport critical energy and goods to global markets.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Our brother-in-law': Arab world embraces New York's new mayor</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/our-brother-law-arab-world-embraces-new-yorks-new-mayor</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/our-brother-law-arab-world-embraces-new-yorks-new-mayor</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The newly elected mayor of New York City, Zohran Mamdani, is married to Rama Duwaji, a woman of Syrian descent. For many in Syria, that practically makes him family.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That he's also a Muslim and a supporter of the Palestinian cause doesn't hurt either, and his election victory has inspired warm feelings and an outpouring of humour in the Arab world.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I love how Syrians are now calling Zohran Mamdani our brother-in-law," wrote Karam Nachar, editor-in-chief of Al Jumhuriya, an independent Syrian media outlet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US to start UN negotiations on Thursday on international Gaza force mandate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-start-un-negotiations-thursday-international-gaza-force-mandate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-start-un-negotiations-thursday-international-gaza-force-mandate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) -The United Nations Security Council on Thursday will start negotiations on a U.S.-drafted resolution to endorse President Donald Trump's Gaza peace plan, said a senior U.S. government official, and authorize a two-year mandate for a transitional governance body and international stabilization force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. formally circulated the draft resolution to the 15 council members late on Wednesday and has said it has regional support from Egypt, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Turkey, and the United Arab Emirates for the text.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff says will announce new country to enter the Abraham Accords on Thursday night</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/witkoff-says-will-announce-new-country-enter-abraham-accords-thursday-night</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/witkoff-says-will-announce-new-country-enter-abraham-accords-thursday-night</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON (Reuters) -U.S. special envoy Steve Witkoff said that a new country would be announced on Thursday night as entering the Abraham Accords that have normalized relations between Israel and Muslim-majority nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Witkoff told a business forum in Florida that he would be returning to Washington for the announcement, declining to say which country it would be. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Simon Lewis, Editing by Franklin Paul)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council votes to lift sanctions on Syria's Sharaa</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-votes-lift-sanctions-syrias-sharaa</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/un-security-council-votes-lift-sanctions-syrias-sharaa</guid><description>The move comes days before Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa is due to visit the White House.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:20:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel launches airstrikes on south Lebanon, says it's targeting Hezbollah</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-airstrikes-south-lebanon-says-its-targeting-hezbollah</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-launches-airstrikes-south-lebanon-says-its-targeting-hezbollah</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT (Reuters) -The Israeli military carried out heavy airstrikes on southern Lebanon on Thursday after issuing evacuation orders for several locations, saying Lebanese armed group Hezbollah was trying to rebuild its military capabilities there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The orders and strikes came despite a ceasefire deal agreed a year ago that was meant to end more than a year of fighting between Israel and Iran-backed Hezbollah, and after months of Lebanese army efforts to clear Hezbollah sites in the south.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran doubles down on Venezuela support as Trump ups threats: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</guid><description>Iran is seeking to boost ties with Venezuela and has expressed solidarity following US strikes targeting drug smugglers off the country's coast, though their energy relationship has declined in recent years.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 16:34:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran doubles down on Venezuela support as Trump ups threats: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</guid><description>Iran is seeking to boost ties with Venezuela and has expressed solidarity following US strikes targeting drug smugglers off the country's coast, though their energy relationship has declined in recent years.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 16:34:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran doubles down on Venezuela support as Trump ups threats: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</guid><description>Iran is seeking to boost ties with Venezuela and has expressed solidarity following US strikes targeting drug smugglers off the country's coast, though their energy relationship has declined in recent years.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 16:34:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran doubles down on Venezuela support as Trump ups threats: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iran-doubles-down-venezuela-support-trump-ups-threats-what-know</guid><description>Iran is seeking to boost ties with Venezuela and has expressed solidarity following US strikes targeting drug smugglers off the country's coast, though their energy relationship has declined in recent years.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 16:34:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fleetwod and Lowry lift each other into Abu Dhabi lead</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fleetwod-and-lowry-lift-each-other-abu-dhabi-lead</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/fleetwod-and-lowry-lift-each-other-abu-dhabi-lead</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Friends Tommy Fleetwood and Shane Lowry shared the lead in the Abu Dhabi Championship after they were paired together on Thursday and both shot eight-under-par opening rounds of 64.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pair shared the lead with New Zealander Kazuma Kobori, South African Richard Sterne and Frenchman Adrien Saddier at the start of the last event of the DP Tour before the season-ending World Championship in Dubai.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lowry and Fleetwood, both previous winners of the event, were drawn in a group that also included a third Ryder Cup player Rasmus Hojgaard.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 16:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tight UK security ahead of match against Israeli club</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tight-uk-security-ahead-match-against-israeli-club</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tight-uk-security-ahead-match-against-israeli-club</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;More than 700 police deployed across the UK city of Birmingham Thursday for protests planned ahead of a football match between Maccabi Tel Aviv and Aston Villa, with visiting Israeli fans barred.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UK government last month vowed to reverse the ban on Maccabi fans attending the Europa League match in the city in central England that has a significant Muslim population after widespread criticism of the decision taken by local safety advisors and police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Israeli club later announced it would decline any tickets for its fans, citing safety concerns.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah rejects talks with Israel as attacks spark fear of renewed war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-rejects-talks-israel-attacks-spark-fear-renewed-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-rejects-talks-israel-attacks-spark-fear-renewed-war</guid><description>Hezbollah’s response to President Joseph Aoun’s call for talks with Israel have further deepened divisions in the country.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:29:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah rejects talks with Israel as attacks spark fear of renewed war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-rejects-talks-israel-attacks-spark-fear-renewed-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-rejects-talks-israel-attacks-spark-fear-renewed-war</guid><description>Hezbollah’s response to President Joseph Aoun’s call for talks with Israel have further deepened divisions in the country.</description><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:29:57 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>