<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>'Tehran' TV series producer Dana Eden found dead in Athens</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tehran-tv-series-producer-dana-eden-found-dead-athens</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/tehran-tv-series-producer-dana-eden-found-dead-athens</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TV producer Dana Eden, who co-created the hit Israeli spy thriller series "Tehran", has been found dead in a hotel room in central Athens, Greek police told AFP on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The body of the 52-year-old was found late Sunday in her hotel room near Syntagma Square, in the heart of the Greek capital, the force said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"An autopsy has been ordered, the surveillance cameras have been reviewed, and everything seems to indicate it was a suicide," a police spokesperson said&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 13:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italy says it stands ready to train police in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/italy-says-it-stands-ready-train-police-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/italy-says-it-stands-ready-train-police-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ROME, Feb 16 (Reuters) - Italy stands ready to help train police forces in Gaza and elsewhere in the Palestinian territories, its foreign minister said on Monday, as Rome aims to play a role in stabilizing the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are ready to train a new Gaza police force, and we are also ready to train a Palestinian police force," Foreign Minister Antonio Tajani told a news conference in Rome.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 13:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran FM in Geneva for US talks, as Guards begin drills in Hormuz Strait</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-fm-geneva-us-talks-guards-begin-drills-hormuz-strait</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-fm-geneva-us-talks-guards-begin-drills-hormuz-strait</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's foreign minister arrived in Geneva ahead of a second round of negotiations with the United States, as the Revolutionary Guards on Monday begin military drills in the strategic Strait of Hormuz.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Tehran, "indirect" Iran–US nuclear talks mediated by Oman will be held on Tuesday, although Washington has previously pushed for other topics to be discussed including Iran's ballistic missiles and support for regional proxies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 13:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU Commission to attend Trump's Board of Peace meeting as observer</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eu-commission-attend-trumps-board-peace-meeting-observer</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eu-commission-attend-trumps-board-peace-meeting-observer</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Feb 16 (Reuters) - EU Commissioner Dubravka Suica will travel to Washington this week to attend a meeting of the Board of Peace, as set up by U.S President Donald Trump, in her capacity as an observer, a spokesperson for the EU Commission said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 12:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French police raid Arab World Institute in Epstein-linked probe into Jack Lang</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/french-police-raid-arab-world-institute-epstein-linked-probe-jack-lang</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/french-police-raid-arab-world-institute-epstein-linked-probe-jack-lang</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Feb 16 (Reuters) - French police on Monday searched the Arab World Institute in Paris in connection with an investigation into its former head, ex culture minister Jack Lang, and his ties with the convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors opened a preliminary investigation into alleged tax fraud against Lang and his daughter Caroline following the release of documents by the U.S. Department of Justice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Arab World Institute said it could not comment immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 11:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thirty four Australians released from Syrian camp holding IS-affiliated families</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/thirty-four-australians-released-syrian-camp-holding-affiliated-families</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/thirty-four-australians-released-syrian-camp-holding-affiliated-families</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Orhan Qereman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ROJ CAMP, Syria, Feb 16 (Reuters) - Syrian Kurdish forces on Monday released 34 Australians who were detained in a camp holding families of suspected Islamic State militants in northern Syria, saying they would be flown to Australia from Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hukmiya Mohamed, a co-director of Roj camp, told Reuters that the 34 Australians had been handed to members of their families who had come to Syria for the release. They were put on small buses for Damascus ahead of their departure from the country. A military vehicle escorted the buses.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 11:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli producer of 'Tehran' TV series found dead in Athens hotel, police officials say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-producer-tehran-tv-series-found-dead-athens-hotel-police-officials-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-producer-tehran-tv-series-found-dead-athens-hotel-police-officials-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Feb 16 (Reuters) - The Israeli producer of hit spy thriller "Tehran" was found dead on Sunday at a hotel room in Athens, Greek police officials said while a probe into the incident is underway.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The body of the 52-year-old woman, identified as Dana Eden, was found after a relative made several failed attempts to reach her. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The case is being treated as suicide based on evidence and testimonies, the police officials said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Greek investigators found pills at the scene. A coroner also found bruises on the victim's neck. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 10:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesia readies 1,000 troops for potential peacekeeping force in Gaza in early April</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/indonesia-readies-1000-troops-potential-peacekeeping-force-gaza-early-april</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/indonesia-readies-1000-troops-potential-peacekeeping-force-gaza-early-april</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JAKARTA, Feb 16 (Reuters) - Indonesia is readying 1,000 troops for potential deployment in Gaza by early April as part of a proposed multinational peacekeeping force, its army spokesperson said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final deployment decision will be made by Indonesian President Prabowo Subianto, spokesperson Donny Pramono said, adding that a total of 8,000 soldiers will be ready for deployment by June. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The departure schedule remains entirely subject to the political decisions of the state and applicable international mechanisms," he said in a text message to Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 09:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's foreign minister will meet IAEA chief ahead of nuclear talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-foreign-minister-will-meet-iaea-chief-ahead-nuclear-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-foreign-minister-will-meet-iaea-chief-ahead-nuclear-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 16 (Reuters) - Iran's foreign minister Abbas Araqchi said he will meet the UN nuclear watchdog chief on Monday, ahead of U.S.-Iran nuclear talks to tackle their dispute over Tehran's nuclear programme and avert conflict as U.S. warships deploy to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two sides held indirect talks earlier this month in Oman.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I am in Geneva with real ideas to achieve a fair and equitable deal. What is not on the table: submission before threats," Araqchi said on X.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 09:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's foreign minister says he will meet IAEA director on Monday</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-foreign-minister-says-he-will-meet-iaea-director-monday</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-foreign-minister-says-he-will-meet-iaea-director-monday</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 16 (Reuters) - Iran's foreign minister Abbas Araqchi said he will meet with the director of the UN nuclear watchdog on Monday, the day before a second round of U.S.-Iran nuclear talks in Geneva. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran and the U.S. renewed negotiations earlier this month to tackle their decades-long dispute over Tehran's nuclear programme and avert a new military confrontation as U.S. warships, including a second aircraft carrier, are deploying to the region. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 07:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Art and the deal: market slump pushes galleries to the Gulf</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/art-and-deal-market-slump-pushes-galleries-gulf</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/art-and-deal-market-slump-pushes-galleries-gulf</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;With global sales mired in a slump, art dealers have turned to buyers in the oil-rich Gulf, where culture sector spending is on the rise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Art Basel, which runs elite fairs in Miami, Hong Kong, Paris and Switzerland, held its Gulf debut in Qatar earlier this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The second you land here, you see the ambition. It's basically the future," Andisheh Avini, a senior director at New York-based Gagosian Gallery, told AFP at the Doha fair. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 02:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New anti-government chants in Tehran after giant rallies abroad: reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-anti-government-chants-tehran-after-giant-rallies-abroad-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-anti-government-chants-tehran-after-giant-rallies-abroad-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Some residents of Tehran on Sunday chanted slogans against the clerical leadership from balconies and windows, reports said, a day after Iranians abroad staged giant opposition rallies in Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Islamic republic under supreme leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei was shaken by a protest movement that peaked in January and which according to rights groups was repressed by security forces in a crackdown that left thousands dead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 01:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu: Deal with Iran must dismantle nuclear infrastructure, not just stop enrichment process</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/netanyahu-deal-iran-must-dismantle-nuclear-infrastructure-not-just-stop</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/netanyahu-deal-iran-must-dismantle-nuclear-infrastructure-not-just-stop</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 15 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said on Sunday he told U.S. President Donald Trump last week that any deal with Iran must include the dismantling of Iran's nuclear infrastructure, not just stopping the enrichment process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the annual Conference of Presidents of Major American Jewish Organizations, Netanyahu also said Israel still needs to "complete the job" of destroying all tunnels in Gaza. Israel, he said, has already dismantled 150 km (93 miles) of an estimated 500 km.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump told Netanyahu in December he would support Israeli strikes on Iran's missile program, CBS News reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-told-netanyahu-december-he-would-support-israeli-strikes-irans-missile</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-told-netanyahu-december-he-would-support-israeli-strikes-irans-missile</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 15 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump told Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu during their meeting in Florida in December that he would support Israeli strikes on Iran's ballistic missile program if the U.S. and Iran could not reach a deal, CBS News reported on Sunday, citing two sources familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ryan Patrick Jones in Toronto; Editing by Chris Reese)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Separate talks on Iran and Ukraine-Russia set for Tuesday in Geneva, source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/separate-talks-iran-and-ukraine-russia-set-tuesday-geneva-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/separate-talks-iran-and-ukraine-russia-set-tuesday-geneva-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PALM BEACH, Florida, Feb 13 (Reuters) - Two sets of diplomatic negotiations, on Ukraine and Iran, are set to take place in Geneva on Tuesday, a source briefed on the matter told Reuters on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A U.S. delegation including envoys Steve Witkoff and Jared Kushner will meet with the Iranians on Tuesday morning, the source said. Representatives from Oman will be on hand and mediate the U.S.-Iran contacts, the source said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Witkoff and Kushner will then participate in trilateral talks with representatives from Russia and Ukraine in the afternoon, the source said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MSF suspends some Gaza hospital work over presence of gunmen, suspected weapons transfers, group says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/msf-suspends-some-gaza-hospital-work-over-presence-gunmen-suspected-weapons</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/msf-suspends-some-gaza-hospital-work-over-presence-gunmen-suspected-weapons</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 14 (Reuters) - Medecins Sans Frontieres has halted "non-critical" medical activities at a major hospital in southern Gaza following reports from patients and its own staff of armed men inside the facility and concerns over the movement of weapons within it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MSF's statement appeared to mark the first time that an international humanitarian group in Gaza has publicly reported the presence of armed men in a hospital or the possible use of such a facility for moving weapons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU should 'bring to life' mutual defence pact, von der Leyen says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eu-should-bring-life-mutual-defence-pact-von-der-leyen-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/eu-should-bring-life-mutual-defence-pact-von-der-leyen-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MUNICH, Feb 14 (Reuters) - The European Union should "bring to life" a mutual defence pact anchored in its founding treaty, European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen said at the Munich Security Conference on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Mutual defence is not an optional task for the European Union. It is an obligation within our own treaty," von der Leyen said in a speech at the conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It is our collective commitment to stand by each other in case of aggression, or in simple terms: one for all and all for one. And this is Europe's meaning."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Son of Iran's last shah urges US military intervention in Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/son-irans-last-shah-urges-us-military-intervention-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/son-irans-last-shah-urges-us-military-intervention-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MUNICH, Feb 14 (Reuters) - Iranian opposition figure Reza Pahlavi on Saturday said U.S. military intervention in Iran could save lives and urged President Donald Trump's administration not to spend too long negotiating with Tehran's clerical rulers on a nuclear deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The exiled son of Iran's toppled shah told Reuters in an interview that there were signs that the Iranian government was on the brink of collapse and that an attack could weaken it or accelerate its fall.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hariri signals Future Movement's return to Lebanon elections</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hariri-signals-future-movements-return-lebanon-elections</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hariri-signals-future-movements-return-lebanon-elections</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Feb 14 (Reuters) - Former Lebanese Prime Minister Saad al-Hariri, one of the country's best-known politicians, indicated on Saturday that his party would contestupcoming elections, four years after he stepped back from public office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a speech marking the 21st anniversary of the assassination of his father Rafik, who was also prime minister, Saad told supporters in Beirut that others would “hear our voice, and count our votes” when elections take place.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>African Union summit clouded by Saudi-UAE rivalry in Horn of Africa</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/african-union-summit-clouded-saudi-uae-rivalry-horn-africa</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/african-union-summit-clouded-saudi-uae-rivalry-horn-africa</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON/NAIROBI, Feb 14 (Reuters) - A feud between Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates across the Horn of Africa is overshadowing this weekend’s African Union summit, though most of the continent’s leaders will try to avoid taking sides, nine diplomats and experts said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What began as a rivalry in Yemen has spread across the Red Sea into a region riven with conflicts - from war in Somalia and Sudan to rivalry between Ethiopia and Eritrea and a divided Libya.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>