<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Top Iranian adviser visits mediator Oman, as Iran and US prepare for talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/top-iranian-adviser-visits-mediator-oman-iran-and-us-prepare-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/top-iranian-adviser-visits-mediator-oman-iran-and-us-prepare-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jana Choukeir and Elwely Elwelly&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 10 - A top adviser to Iran's Supreme Leader discussed ways to reach a "balanced and just" agreement with the United States during talks in Oman on Tuesday, as Washington and Tehran prepare to resume negotiations aimed at averting a new conflict.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oman facilitated talks between Iran and the U.S. last week, which a spokesperson for Iran's foreign ministry said had allowed Tehran to gauge Washington's seriousness and showed enough consensus for diplomacy to continue.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 11:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Indonesia says proposed Gaza peacekeeping force could total 20,000 troops</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/indonesia-says-proposed-gaza-peacekeeping-force-could-total-20000-troops</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/indonesia-says-proposed-gaza-peacekeeping-force-could-total-20000-troops</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JAKARTA, Feb 10 (Reuters) - A proposed multinational peacekeeping force for Gaza could total about 20,000 troops, with Indonesia estimating it could contribute up to 8,000, President Prabowo Subianto’s spokesman said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spokesman said, however, that no deployment terms or areas of operation had been agreed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel PM to meet Trump with Iran missiles high on agenda</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-pm-meet-trump-iran-missiles-high-agenda</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-pm-meet-trump-iran-missiles-high-agenda</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said Tuesday the top priority in his talks with US President Donald Trump would be the ongoing negotiations with Iran, as he presses for a tougher US approach to Tehran's ballistic missile programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far, Iran has rejected expanding the scope of its talks with the US beyond the issue of its nuclear programme, though Washington also wants Tehran's ballistic missile programme and its support for regional militant groups on the table.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says nuclear talks gauged 'seriousness' of U.S</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-says-nuclear-talks-gauged-seriousness-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-says-nuclear-talks-gauged-seriousness-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 10 (Reuters) - Nuclear talks with the United States allowed Tehran to gauge Washington's seriousness and showed enough consensus to continue on the diplomatic track, Iran's foreign ministry spokesperson said on Tuesday.    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. and Iranian diplomats held talks through Omani mediators in Oman last week in an effort to revive diplomacy, after U.S. President Donald Trump positioned a naval flotilla in the region, raising fears of new military action.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin says no date yet for next round of Ukraine talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-says-no-date-yet-next-round-ukraine-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/kremlin-says-no-date-yet-next-round-ukraine-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 10 (Reuters) - The Kremlin said on Tuesday there was no date set yet for the next round of peace talks on Ukraine, but said the negotiations were likely to happen soon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Russia, Ukraine and the United States met last week in Abu Dhabi for a second round of trilateral talks. They yielded no major breakthrough though 314 prisoners of war were exchanged, the first such swap since October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dmitry Antonov; Writing by Lucy Papachristou; editing by Guy Faulconbridge)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines sees signs of cooperation from China despite sea disputes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/philippines-sees-signs-cooperation-china-despite-sea-disputes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/philippines-sees-signs-cooperation-china-despite-sea-disputes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MANILA, Feb 10 (Reuters) - The Philippines' ambassador to Washington said on Tuesday that the country is seeing some signs that China is willing to work with Manila and "isolate" theSouth China Sea disputes which havehurt relations between the two nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ambassador Jose Manuel Romualdez told reporters that the Philippines' relationship with China cannot be purely defined based on territorial disputes over the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Karen Lema; Editing by David Stanway)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 03:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump opposes Israeli annexation of West Bank, White House official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-opposes-israeli-annexation-west-bank-white-house-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-opposes-israeli-annexation-west-bank-white-house-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 9 (Reuters) - A White House official on Monday reiterated U.S. President Donald Trump's opposition toward Israel annexing the West Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"A stable West Bank keeps Israel secure and is in line with this administration’s goal to achieve peace in the region," the official said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Costas Pitas)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Immigration judge rejects Trump effort to deport pro-Palestinian Tufts student</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/immigration-judge-rejects-trump-effort-deport-pro-palestinian-tufts-student</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/immigration-judge-rejects-trump-effort-deport-pro-palestinian-tufts-student</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nate Raymond&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BOSTON, Feb 9 (Reuters) - An immigration judge has rejected the Trump administration's efforts to deport Tufts University PhD student Rumeysa Ozturk, who was arrested last year as part of its targeting of pro-Palestinian campus activists, her lawyers said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for the Turkish student detailed the immigration judge's decision in a filing with the New York-based 2nd U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals, which had been reviewing a ruling that led to her release from immigration custody in May.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian leaders urge calm after Sydney clashes during Israeli President Herzog's visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australian-leaders-urge-calm-after-sydney-clashes-during-israeli-president</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australian-leaders-urge-calm-after-sydney-clashes-during-israeli-president</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Renju Jose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Feb 10 (Reuters) - Australian leaders on Tuesday urged calm and called on protests to remain peaceful after clashes between police and demonstrators opposing Israeli President Isaac Herzog's visit to Australia erupted in Sydney.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police said 27 people were arrested, including 10 for allegedly assaulting officers, after violence broke out on Monday evening when people failed to leave a planned protest site in central Sydney and police moved to clear access for pedestrians.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 23:36:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian woman hospitalized following seizure in US ICE detention</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-woman-hospitalized-following-seizure-us-ice-detention</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-woman-hospitalized-following-seizure-us-ice-detention</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 9 (Reuters) - A Palestinian woman, who lost dozens of family members in the Gaza war, has been hospitalized following a seizure in U.S. immigration detention, the Department of Homeland Security said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On February 6, 2026, at about 8:45 p.m., "medical staff at the Prairieland Detention Center in Alvarado, Texas, notified ICE that detainee Leqaa Kordia was admitted to Texas Health Huguley Hospital in Burleson, Texas, for further evaluation following a seizure," a DHS spokesperson said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 22:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mideast’s AI startups capture record $858M in funding during 2025, doubling share</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</guid><description>The growth represents a sizable jump from recent years, when local AI companies captured just a sliver of dealmaking, and Magnitt now predicts funding for MENA’s AI startups will easily surpass $1 billion in 2026.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mideast’s AI startups capture record $858M in funding during 2025, doubling share</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</guid><description>The growth represents a sizable jump from recent years, when local AI companies captured just a sliver of dealmaking, and Magnitt now predicts funding for MENA’s AI startups will easily surpass $1 billion in 2026.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mideast’s AI startups capture record $858M in funding during 2025, doubling share</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</guid><description>The growth represents a sizable jump from recent years, when local AI companies captured just a sliver of dealmaking, and Magnitt now predicts funding for MENA’s AI startups will easily surpass $1 billion in 2026.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mideast’s AI startups capture record $858M in funding during 2025, doubling share</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mideasts-ai-startups-capture-record-858m-funding-during-2025-doubling-share</guid><description>The growth represents a sizable jump from recent years, when local AI companies captured just a sliver of dealmaking, and Magnitt now predicts funding for MENA’s AI startups will easily surpass $1 billion in 2026.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Residents of north Lebanon city lose neighbours, livelihoods in building collapse</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/residents-north-lebanon-city-lose-neighbours-livelihoods-building-collapse</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/residents-north-lebanon-city-lose-neighbours-livelihoods-building-collapse</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Rubble is all that remains of the building once home to Adnan Mardash's grocery shop in north Lebanon's Tripoli after it collapsed, killing 14 people and shining a spotlight on the impoverished city's neglect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mardash, 54, said he shut the small ground-floor store where he worked for more than three decades and went to his nearby home shortly before the disaster on Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Our neighbours and loved ones died... people lost their livelihoods," said the father of four, who has no other income.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MBZ hosts Sisi as Saudi Arabia and UAE jockey for regional influence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mbz-hosts-sisi-saudi-arabia-and-uae-jockey-regional-influence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/mbz-hosts-sisi-saudi-arabia-and-uae-jockey-regional-influence</guid><description>Economic ties between Egypt and the UAE are strengthening thanks to large Emirati investments in the North African country.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:34:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>International outrage grows over Israel's plans for West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/international-outrage-grows-over-israels-plans-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/international-outrage-grows-over-israels-plans-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;International outrage was growing on Monday at Israeli plans to tighten the country's grip over the occupied West Bank, with the United Nations chief saying he was "gravely concerned".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, Saudi Arabia and seven other Muslim-majority countries condemned the new Israeli measures, which pave the way for more settlements in the occupied Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US issues fresh guidance to vessels transiting Strait of Hormuz as Iran tensions simmer</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-issues-fresh-guidance-vessels-transiting-strait-hormuz-iran-tensions-simmer</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-issues-fresh-guidance-vessels-transiting-strait-hormuz-iran-tensions-simmer</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 9 (Reuters) - The United States issued fresh guidance on Monday to commercial vessels transiting the Strait of Hormuz, a key shipping lane for Middle East oil supplies, as tensions simmered between Washington and Tehran over Iran’s nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran has in the past threatened to close down the Strait of Hormuz, a portion of which lies within its territorial waters, and has at times seized commercial ships and oil tankers moving through the area alleging smuggling.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 17:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Uber snaps up Getir in Turkey as Mubadala exits battered delivery bet</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uber-snaps-getir-turkey-mubadala-exits-battered-delivery-bet</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uber-snaps-getir-turkey-mubadala-exits-battered-delivery-bet</guid><description>For Uber, the $335 million deal marks a fresh bet on a populous growth market and comes at quite the discount — as recently as 2022, Getir was valued at nearly $12 billion.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 16:49:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Syria, Sharaa's brothers take spotlight with Saudi, Russian dealings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-sharaas-brothers-take-spotlight-saudi-russian-dealings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-sharaas-brothers-take-spotlight-saudi-russian-dealings</guid><description>Hazem al-Sharaa is playing a key role in Syria’s economic development and ties with the Gulf, while Maher al-Sharaa is involved in diplomacy with Russia, though another brother has reportedly fallen out of favor with the president.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 16:41:59 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>