<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Kushner in Israel as trapped Hamas fighters issue bedevils Gaza truce progress</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kushner-israel-trapped-hamas-fighters-issue-bedevils-gaza-truce-progress</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/kushner-israel-trapped-hamas-fighters-issue-bedevils-gaza-truce-progress</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/CAIRO (Reuters) -U.S. mediators are meeting Israel's prime minister on Monday with attention turning to the second, far more complex, phase of the Gaza ceasefire deal and the immediate problem of a standoff over a group of Hamas fighters still holed up in tunnels. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting between U.S. President Donald Trump's son-in-law Jared Kushner and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu comes a month after Washington and regional states pressed Israel and Hamas to a truce after two years of devastating war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US envoy Kushner in Jerusalem to press Gaza truce</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-envoy-kushner-jerusalem-press-gaza-truce</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-envoy-kushner-jerusalem-press-gaza-truce</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US envoy Jared Kushner met with Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu in Jerusalem on Monday as Washington pressed efforts to ensure the fragile Gaza ceasefire holds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The truce, in effect since October 10, has largely halted the war that erupted after Hamas's surprise attack on Israel on October 7, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of its first stage, a series of prisoner and hostage exchanges have taken place in recent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netanyahu's office confirmed his meeting with Kushner but did not provide further details.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Lukoil declares force majeure at Iraqi oilfield following sanctions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-lukoil-declares-force-majeure-iraqi-oilfield-following-sanctions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-lukoil-declares-force-majeure-iraqi-oilfield-following-sanctions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Rasheed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD (Reuters) -Lukoil has declared force majeure at Iraq's giant West Qurna-2 oilfield, four sources with knowledge of the matter said on Monday, after Western sanctions on the Russian oil major hampered its operations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lukoil did not immediately respond to a Reuters request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United States and Britain imposed sanctions on Lukoil -  Russia's second-largest oil company - last month. And Iraq has since halted all cash and crude payments to the company, three of the sources said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE rules out joining Gaza stabilization force for now, backs peace efforts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uae-rules-out-joining-gaza-stabilization-force-now-backs-peace-efforts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/uae-rules-out-joining-gaza-stabilization-force-now-backs-peace-efforts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maha El Dahan and Jana Choukeir&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI (Reuters) -The United Arab Emirates does not yet see a clear framework for the proposed international stability force in Gaza and, under the current circumstances, will not take part, a senior Emirati official said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Anwar Gargash, diplomatic adviser to the UAE president, said Abu Dhabi would continue to support political efforts toward peace and remain a leading provider of humanitarian aid.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The region remains fragile, yet there is reason for cautious optimism", he told the Abu Dhabi Strategic Debate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel pushes Lebanon army to search more intrusively for Hezbollah arms, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-pushes-lebanon-army-search-more-intrusively-hezbollah-arms-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-pushes-lebanon-army-search-more-intrusively-hezbollah-arms-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maya Gebeily and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT/JERUSALEM (Reuters) -Israel is pressing Lebanon's army to be more aggressive in disarming the Iranian-backed militant group Hezbollah by searching private homes in the south for weaponry, three Lebanese security officials and two Israeli officials have said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The demand has emerged in recent weeks and been rejected by Lebanon's military leadership, who fear it would ignite civil strife and derail a disarmament strategy seen by the army as cautious but effective, the Lebanese security officials told Reuters. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime watchdog FATF to visit Turkey after 'grey list' exit, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/crime-watchdog-fatf-visit-turkey-after-grey-list-exit-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/crime-watchdog-fatf-visit-turkey-after-grey-list-exit-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ebru Tuncay and Can Sezer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -A team from the international crime watchdog FATF will evaluate Turkey this month after removing it from its "grey list" last year for progress made in fighting money laundering and the funding of terrorist activity, five sources said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey has to show it is meeting commitments or it risks returning to the grey list of countries that require special scrutiny, which would dent its improving financial credentials.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Syria foiled Islamic State plots on President Sharaa's life, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-syria-foiled-islamic-state-plots-president-sharaas-life-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/exclusive-syria-foiled-islamic-state-plots-president-sharaas-life-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS (Reuters) -Syria has foiled two separate Islamic State plots to assassinate President Ahmed al-Sharaa, two senior officials said, adding a personal dimension to the leader's plans to join a U.S.-led coalition to fight the militant group that he has long battled. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sources, a senior Syrian security official and a senior Middle Eastern official, said the plots on Sharaa's life were foiled over the last few months and underlined the direct threat he faces as he tries to consolidate power in a country ruined by 14 years of civil war. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>African Union calls for urgent action in insurgency-hit Mali</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/african-union-calls-urgent-action-insurgency-hit-mali</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/african-union-calls-urgent-action-insurgency-hit-mali</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAMAKO (Reuters) -The African Union has called for an urgent international response, including intelligence-sharing, to address worsening security conditions in Mali, where insurgents are imposing a fuel blockade and kidnapping foreigners.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An Al Qaeda-linked jihadist group active in West Africa's Sahel region has blocked fuel imports since September, attacking convoys of tankers and creating a shortage that forced schools and businesses to shut.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>IAEA inspectors visited Iranian nuclear sites last week, foreign ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iaea-inspectors-visited-iranian-nuclear-sites-last-week-foreign-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/iaea-inspectors-visited-iranian-nuclear-sites-last-week-foreign-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI (Reuters) -Inspectors of the U.N. nuclear watchdog IAEA visited Iranian nuclear sites last week, Iran's foreign ministry spokesperson said on Monday, according to state media, a week after the IAEA urged Iran to "seriously improve" cooperation.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IAEA has carried out about a dozen inspections in Iran since hostilities with Israel in June, but last week highlighted it had not been given access to nuclear facilities such as Fordow, Natanz and Isfahan, which were bombed by the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 10:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt begins voting in parliamentary elections</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-begins-voting-parliamentary-elections</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/egypt-begins-voting-parliamentary-elections</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Egyptians head to the polls on Monday to elect a new parliament, which critics say will only further cement President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi's grip on power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The opening of polling stations at 9:00 am (0700 GMT) marks the start of a weeks-long process to fill 568 of the 596 seats in the lower house, with some provinces not voting for another two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The remaining 28 lawmakers will be appointed directly by Sisi, the former army chief who seized power after ousting late Islamist president Mohamed Morsi in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 08:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump to meet Sharaa at White House, capping major turnaround for Syria</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-meet-sharaa-white-house-capping-major-turnaround-syria</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/trump-meet-sharaa-white-house-capping-major-turnaround-syria</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steve Holland and Timour Azhari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/RIYADH (Reuters) -Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa's White House meeting with U.S. President Donald Trump on Monday caps a stunning year for the rebel-turned-ruler who toppled a longtime autocratic leader and has since toured the world as he seeks to end Syria's international isolation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 06:36:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi belly dancers break taboos behind closed doors</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-belly-dancers-break-taboos-behind-closed-doors</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/saudi-belly-dancers-break-taboos-behind-closed-doors</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a fitness studio in Saudi Arabia, dozens of women sway to Arabic music as they practise belly dancing -- an activity that many feel compelled to keep secret.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite their enthusiasm, none of them would give their real name or show their faces on camera, underlining the stigma and cultural prejudices surrounding the ancient dance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Arab communities, belly dancing has played many roles. It is a form of artistic expression, popular entertainment and a staple of classic Egyptian cinema.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 02:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Shoigu leads large Russian delegation to Egypt for military talks, RIA reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/shoigu-leads-large-russian-delegation-egypt-military-talks-ria-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/shoigu-leads-large-russian-delegation-egypt-military-talks-ria-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Russian Security Council secretary Sergei Shoigu arrived in Cairo on Sunday leading a large delegation of senior arms and nuclear officials for military talks with Egypt's leadership, RIA news agency reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shoigu is due to meet President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi, Egypt's national security adviser, foreign and defence ministers, as well as other senior security and intelligence officials, RIA reported.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 23:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World Bank, in letter to US, backs draft UN resolution on Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/world-bank-letter-us-backs-draft-un-resolution-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/world-bank-letter-us-backs-draft-un-resolution-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS (Reuters) -The World Bank backs language in a U.S.-drafted United Nations Security Council resolution on Gaza that would authorize a two-year mandate for a transitional governance body,according to a letter to the United States seen by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 19:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jared Kushner arrives in Israel for Gaza talks with Netanyahu, source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/jared-kushner-arrives-israel-gaza-talks-netanyahu-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/jared-kushner-arrives-israel-gaza-talks-netanyahu-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -U.S. President Donald Trump's influential son-in-law, Jared Kushner, arrived in Israel on Sunday for talks with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on implementing the U.S. plan to end the Gaza war, a source familiar with the matter said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kushner was expected to meet with Netanyahu on Monday, said the source, speaking on condition of anonymity as the meeting had not been formally announced. The White House and Netanyahu's office did not immediately respond to a Reuters request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Killed on sight': Sudanese fleeing El-Fasher recall ethnic attacks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/killed-sight-sudanese-fleeing-el-fasher-recall-ethnic-attacks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/killed-sight-sudanese-fleeing-el-fasher-recall-ethnic-attacks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As he fled the Sudanese city of El-Fasher in terror, Hassan Osman said he saw ethnic attacks by paramilitary forces, with civilians targeted for their tribe and skin colour. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rapid Support Forces (RSF), which have been at war with the army since April 2023, captured the last military stronghold in western Darfur on October 26. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reports of mass killings, ethnic violence, abductions and sexual assaults have since emerged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AFP spoke to three survivors of the battle for El-Fasher, who are now seeking shelter in the nearby town of Tawila. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 17:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel confirms remains returned are officer Goldin killed in 2014 Gaza war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-confirms-remains-returned-are-officer-goldin-killed-2014-gaza-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-confirms-remains-returned-are-officer-goldin-killed-2014-gaza-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel said the remains it received on Sunday from Hamas were those of Lieutenant Hadar Goldin, an Israeli officer killed more than a decade ago in the 2014 Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Goldin was the 24th deceased hostage whose remains have been returned by Hamas since the start of the ceasefire on October 10 that has halted the latest war in Gaza, which broke out in October 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said forensic experts had confirmed the remains were of Goldin.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 15:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel receives remains of deceased hostage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-receives-remains-deceased-hostage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-receives-remains-deceased-hostage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO (Reuters) -Israel on Sunday received the remains of a deceased hostage held in Gaza that Palestinian militant group Hamas said were of an Israeli soldier killed in the territory more than a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said in a statement the remains were handed over to Israeli forces in the Palestinian territory by the Red Cross.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has not yet been formal identification.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hamas' armed wing had said it would hand over the body of Hadar Goldin, a military officer killed in an ambush in Gaza during the 2014 Israel-Hamas war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 14:01:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mamdani’s New York victory exposes fault lines in Jewish Democratic politics</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/mamdanis-new-york-victory-exposes-fault-lines-jewish-democratic-politics</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/mamdanis-new-york-victory-exposes-fault-lines-jewish-democratic-politics</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Helen Coster and James Oliphant&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NEW YORK (Reuters) -Zohran Mamdani’s election as New York’s next mayor exposed a deepening rift between traditional Democratic Jewish voters and younger progressives — one that could reshape politics for years in the metropolitan area with the world’s largest Jewish population outside Israel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mamdani, a 34-year-old democratic socialist, handily defeated Andrew Cuomo, the Democratic former governor of New York who ran as an independent, while beating back accusations of antisemitism over his support of Palestinians in the conflict in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 11:36:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkish delegation to meet in Pakistan aiming to seal peace deal with Afghanistan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-delegation-meet-pakistan-aiming-seal-peace-deal-afghanistan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkish-delegation-meet-pakistan-aiming-seal-peace-deal-afghanistan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -Turkey's foreign and defence ministers and intelligence chief plan to travel to Pakistan this week to discuss its stop-start talks with Afghanistan over a ceasefire in place in South Asia, President Tayyip Erdogan said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to an official readout on Sunday of his comments on a return flight from Baku, where he met Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif, Erdogan said the tripartite visit aim to seal a permanent ceasefire and peace between the nations as soon as possible. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 09:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>