<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>China opposes recognition of Somaliland, affirms support for Somalia</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/china-opposes-recognition-somaliland-affirms-support-somalia</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/china-opposes-recognition-somaliland-affirms-support-somalia</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIJING, Dec 29 (Reuters) - China opposes any attempt to split territories in Somalia, the foreign ministry said on Monday, affirming Chinese support for the sovereignty, unity and territorial integrity of the East African country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"No country should encourage or support other countries' internal separatist forces for its own selfish interests," ministry spokesperson Lin Jian told reporters at a regular press conference, urging authorities in Somaliland to stop "separatist activities and collusion with external forces".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 08:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria secures Assad-era mass grave revealed by Reuters and opens criminal investigation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-secures-assad-era-mass-grave-revealed-reuters-and-opens-criminal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syria-secures-assad-era-mass-grave-revealed-reuters-and-opens-criminal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 29 - Syria’s government has ordered soldiers to guard a mass grave created to conceal atrocities under Bashar al-Assad and has opened a criminal investigation, following a Reuters report that revealed a yearslong conspiracy by the fallen dictatorship to hide thousands of bodies on the remote desert site.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 07:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seven Turkish police wounded in clash with Islamic State militants</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/seven-turkish-police-wounded-clash-islamic-state-militants</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/seven-turkish-police-wounded-clash-islamic-state-militants</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Umit Bektas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;YALOVA, Turkey, Dec 29 (Reuters) - Seven Turkish police officers were wounded in a clash with suspected Islamic State militants in northwest Turkey on Monday and a police operation against them was ongoing, a Reuters witness and state media reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sporadic gunfire could be heard at the scene of the clash in Yalova province, south of Istanbul on the Sea of Marmara coast, where police teams launched an overnight operation at a house believed to contain militants, the witness said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 07:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu to meet Trump in Florida for crucial Gaza talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-meet-trump-florida-crucial-gaza-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-meet-trump-florida-crucial-gaza-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu will meet Donald Trump in Florida on Monday, with the US president pushing to move to the next stage of the fragile Gaza truce plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crucial meeting at Trump's lavish Mar-a-Lago resort comes as some White House officials fear both Israel and Hamas are slow-walking the second phase of their ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump, who said Netanyahu had asked for the talks, is reportedly keen to announce -- as soon as January -- a Palestinian technocratic government for Gaza and the deployment of an international stabilization force.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 06:00:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia says Bondi review to check if terror attack could have been averted</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australia-says-bondi-review-check-if-terror-attack-could-have-been-averted</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australia-says-bondi-review-check-if-terror-attack-could-have-been-averted</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Dec 29 (Reuters) - Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese said on Monday an independent review into law enforcement agencies set up after the Bondi mass shooting will assess whether authorities could have taken additional steps to prevent the terror attack.    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Albanese said the review will examine whether existing laws or information gaps stopped police and security agencies from acting against the alleged attackers, a father and son, who police say were inspired by the militant group Islamic State.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 03:01:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump, Netanyahu to discuss next phase of Gaza plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/trump-netanyahu-discuss-next-phase-gaza-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/trump-netanyahu-discuss-next-phase-gaza-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/PALM BEACH, Florida, Dec 28 - U.S. President Donald Trump is expected to push for progress in the stalled ceasefire in Gaza when he meets with Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu on Monday for talks that will include Israel’s concerns over Hezbollah in Lebanon and Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Netanyahu said this month that Trump had invited him for talks, as Washington pushes to establish transitional governance and an international security force for the Palestinian enclave.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 23:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Somaliland recognition prompts celebrations, condemnation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/somaliland-recognition-prompts-celebrations-condemnation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/somaliland-recognition-prompts-celebrations-condemnation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;People gathered in several towns in the breakaway region of Somaliland on Sunday to celebrate its recognition by Israel -- a decision condemned by the Somali president as a "threat" to stability in the Horn of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel announced on Friday it was officially recognising Somaliland, a first for the self-proclaimed republic that in 1991 declared it had unilaterally separated from Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, the leader of the Houthis warned that any Israeli presence in Somaliland would be considered a "military target". &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 19:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Three dead in Alawite protests on Syrian coast, local officials say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/three-dead-alawite-protests-syrian-coast-local-officials-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/three-dead-alawite-protests-syrian-coast-local-officials-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Karam al-Masri&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LATAKIA, Syria Dec 28 - Three people were killed on Sunday when protests in Syria's Alawite heartland of Latakia spiralledinto gunfire and other violence, according to the province's media office.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Syria has been rocked by several episodes of sectarian bloodshed since longtime leader Bashar al-Assad, who hails from the Muslim Alawite minority, was ousted by a rebel offensive last year and replaced by a Sunni-led government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 15:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Shivering from cold and fear': winter rains batter displaced Gazans</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/shivering-cold-and-fear-winter-rains-batter-displaced-gazans</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/shivering-cold-and-fear-winter-rains-batter-displaced-gazans</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It only took a matter of minutes after the heavy overnight rain first began to fall for Jamil al-Sharafi's tent in southern Gaza to flood, drenching his food and leaving his blankets sopping wet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The winter rains have made an already precarious life worse for people like Sharafi, who is among the hundreds of thousands in the Palestinian territory displaced by the war, many of whom now survive on aid provided by humanitarian organisations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"My children are shivering from cold and fear... The tent was completely flooded within minutes," Sharafi, 47, said on Sunday. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 13:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraqis cover soil with clay to curb sandstorms</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iraqis-cover-soil-clay-curb-sandstorms</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iraqis-cover-soil-clay-curb-sandstorms</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Deep in Iraq's southern desert, bulldozers and earthmovers spread layers of moist clay over sand dunes as part of a broader effort to fight increasingly frequent sandstorms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iraq has long suffered from sand and dust storms, but in recent years they have become more frequent and intense as the country falls prey to the effects of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 04:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italy arrests nine over alleged Hamas funding through charities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/italy-arrests-nine-over-alleged-hamas-funding-through-charities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/italy-arrests-nine-over-alleged-hamas-funding-through-charities</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ROME, Dec 27 (Reuters) - Italian prosecutors said on Saturday they had arrested nine people on suspicion of financing Hamas through charities based in Italy, in an operation coordinated by anti-mafia and anti-terrorism units.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The suspects are accused of "belonging to and having financed" the Palestinian group, which the European Union designates as a terrorist organisation, prosecutors in the northern Italian city of Genoa said in a statement. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 19:36:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu to meet Trump in US on Monday</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-meet-trump-us-monday</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-meet-trump-us-monday</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu is due to meet US President Donald Trump in Florida on Monday, an Israeli official told AFP, in what is seen as a crucial visit for the next steps of the fragile Gaza truce plan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It will be Netanyahu's fifth visit to see key ally Trump in the United States this year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His trip comes as the Trump administration and regional mediators push to proceed to the second stage of the ceasefire between Israel and Hamas in the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 15:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi-led coalition warns of intervention against Yemen separatists</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-led-coalition-warns-intervention-against-yemen-separatists</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/saudi-led-coalition-warns-intervention-against-yemen-separatists</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Saudi-led coalition warned Saturday it would back Yemen's government in any military confrontation with separatist forces, as Riyadh urged them to withdraw "peacefully" from recently-seized provinces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The statements came a day after reported Saudi air strikes on separatist positions in Yemen's Hadramawt province -- and after Washington called for restraint in the rapidly escalating conflict.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Turki al-Malki, the spokesman for the coalition, warned of intervention if efforts to de-escalate the situation failed because of the separatists' actions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 12:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yemen's Saudi-led coalition says it will deal with military moves in Hadramout</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/yemens-saudi-led-coalition-says-it-will-deal-military-moves-hadramout</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/yemens-saudi-led-coalition-says-it-will-deal-military-moves-hadramout</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Dec 27 (Reuters) - Yemen's Saudi-led coalition said any military moves by the main southern separatist group STC in the eastern province of Hadramout contrary to de-escalation efforts will be dealt with to protect civilians, the Saudi state news agency reported on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 06:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Somalia, African nations denounce Israeli recognition of Somaliland</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/somalia-african-nations-denounce-israeli-recognition-somaliland</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/somalia-african-nations-denounce-israeli-recognition-somaliland</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Somalia and the African Union reacted angrily Friday after Israel became the first country to formally recognise the northern region of Somaliland as an independent state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somaliland declared independence from Somalia in 1991 and has pushed for international recognition for decades, with president Abdirahman Mohamed Abdullahi making it a top priority since taking office last year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 21:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egyptian-British activist Alaa Abd el-Fattah arrives in UK after release from Egyptian prison</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/egyptian-british-activist-alaa-abd-el-fattah-arrives-uk-after-release-egyptian</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/egyptian-british-activist-alaa-abd-el-fattah-arrives-uk-after-release-egyptian</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Dec 26 (Reuters) - High-profile activist Alaa Abd el-Fattah, who was released from prison after an Egyptian presidential pardon in September, has arrived in Britain, the Egyptian-British campaigner's family and British Prime Minister Keir Starmer said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abd el-Fattah, 44, has become Egypt's most prominent political prisoner after spending much of his adult life in and out of detention due to his activism, and a rare symbol of opposition to a far-reaching crackdown under President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 19:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explosion at Alawite mosque in Syria's Homs kills eight</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/explosion-alawite-mosque-syrias-homs-kills-eight</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/explosion-alawite-mosque-syrias-homs-kills-eight</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAMASCUS, Dec 26 (Reuters) - Eight people were killed in an explosion at a mosque of the Alawite minority sect in the Syrian city of Homs on Friday, Syrian state news agency SANA said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An ultra-conservative Sunni Muslim Syrian group known as Saraya Ansar al-Sunnah said on its Telegram channels that it carried out the attack. The group previously claimed responsibility for a suicide bombing at a Damascus church in June that killed 20 people.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 18:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Deadly blast hits mosque in Alawite area of Syria's Homs</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/deadly-blast-hits-mosque-alawite-area-syrias-homs</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/deadly-blast-hits-mosque-alawite-area-syrias-homs</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;An explosion killed at least eight worshippers at a mosque in a predominantly Alawite area of Syria's Homs on Friday, state media said, with an Islamist militant group claiming responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The attack during Friday prayers is the latest on the Alawite community, and the second blast in a place of worship since Islamist authorities took power a year ago, after a suicide bombing in a Damascus church killed 25 people in June.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 16:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel becomes first country to recognize Somaliland in slight to Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-becomes-first-country-recognize-somaliland-slight-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-becomes-first-country-recognize-somaliland-slight-turkey</guid><description>As Somaliland wins diplomatic recognition from Israel, the move could upset Turkey’s interests in Somalia and the Horn of Africa.</description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 16:12:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel becomes first country to recognize Somaliland in slight to Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-becomes-first-country-recognize-somaliland-slight-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-becomes-first-country-recognize-somaliland-slight-turkey</guid><description>As Somaliland wins diplomatic recognition from Israel, the move could upset Turkey’s interests in Somalia and the Horn of Africa.</description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 16:12:26 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>