<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Iranian mourning ceremonies prompt new crackdowns in echo of 1979 revolution</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-mourning-ceremonies-prompt-new-crackdowns-echo-1979-revolution</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-mourning-ceremonies-prompt-new-crackdowns-echo-1979-revolution</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 18 (Reuters) - Iranians have returned to the streets this week to mourn those killed by security forces during last month's anti-government demonstrations, sparking some new crackdowns in an echo of the 1979 Islamic Revolution that brought down the U.S.-backed Shah.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The anti-Shah revolutionaries turned Shi'ite Muslim memorial processions 40 days after each death into new protests, which prompted renewed violence from the authorities and fresh "martyrs" for the cause.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 15:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE president met US senator Graham in Abu Dhabi</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-president-met-us-senator-graham-abu-dhabi</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-president-met-us-senator-graham-abu-dhabi</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 18 (Reuters) - United Arab Emirates President Sheikh Mohammed bin Zayed Al Nahyan met U.S. Senator Lindsey Graham on Wednesday in Abu Dhabi, the senator said in a post on X, where he also criticised what he called “false narratives” circulating about the UAE and its leader.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week, social media speculation about Sheikh Mohammed’s health had surged after Turkey’s President Tayyip Erdogan postponed a planned visit to Abu Dhabi and his office posted — then deleted — a post on X saying the Emirati leader had a “health problem”.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan heads to US as Turkey eyes Gaza troop role: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</guid><description>Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar is also expected to attend the Board of Peace meeting, raising the prospect of the first face-to-face talks between top Turkish and Israeli diplomats since the war amid high-running tensions.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:12:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan heads to US as Turkey eyes Gaza troop role: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</guid><description>Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar is also expected to attend the Board of Peace meeting, raising the prospect of the first face-to-face talks between top Turkish and Israeli diplomats since the war amid high-running tensions.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:12:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan heads to US as Turkey eyes Gaza troop role: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</guid><description>Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar is also expected to attend the Board of Peace meeting, raising the prospect of the first face-to-face talks between top Turkish and Israeli diplomats since the war amid high-running tensions.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:12:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fidan heads to US as Turkey eyes Gaza troop role: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fidan-heads-us-turkey-eyes-gaza-troop-role-what-know</guid><description>Israeli Foreign Minister Gideon Saar is also expected to attend the Board of Peace meeting, raising the prospect of the first face-to-face talks between top Turkish and Israeli diplomats since the war amid high-running tensions.</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:12:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ramadan begins in Gaza amid ruins of shattered mosques</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ramadan-begins-gaza-amid-ruins-shattered-mosques</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ramadan-begins-gaza-amid-ruins-shattered-mosques</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mahmoud Issa&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GAZA, Feb 18 (Reuters) - As the Muslim fasting month of Ramadan began in Gaza on Wednesday, Palestinians headed to the shattered ruins of mosques or to makeshift prayer spaces made of tarpaulins and wood, mourning their dead and their lost places of worship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Gaza City, the dome of the now destroyed Al Hassaina mosque rests on top of a pile of rubble. Its former courtyard, where worshippers once gathered and today families sleep and cook among the ruins, is criss-crossed with washing lines. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 13:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan PM Sharif to seek clarity on troops for Gaza in US visit, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pakistan-pm-sharif-seek-clarity-troops-gaza-us-visit-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pakistan-pm-sharif-seek-clarity-troops-gaza-us-visit-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Asif Shahzad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD, Feb 18 (Reuters) - Before Pakistan commits to sending troops to Gaza as part of the International Stabilization Force it wants assurances from the United States that it will be a peacekeeping mission rather than tasked with disarming Hamas, three sources told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pakistan's Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif is set to attend the first formal meeting of President Donald Trump's Board of Peace in Washington on Thursday, alongside delegations from at least 20 countries. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 13:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite images show Iran repairing and fortifying sites amid US tensions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/satellite-images-show-iran-repairing-and-fortifying-sites-amid-us-tensions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/satellite-images-show-iran-repairing-and-fortifying-sites-amid-us-tensions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Marine Delrue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feb 18 (Reuters) - Satellite images show that Iran has recently built a concrete shield over a new facility at a sensitive military site and covered it in soil, experts say, advancing work at a location reportedly bombed by Israel in 2024 amid tensions with the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Images also show that Iran has buried tunnel entrances at a nuclear site bombed by the U.S. during Israel's 12-day war with Iran last year, fortified tunnel entrances near another, and has repaired missile bases struck in the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 13:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey MPs back moves to 'reintegrate' former Kurdish fighters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-mps-back-moves-reintegrate-former-kurdish-fighters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-mps-back-moves-reintegrate-former-kurdish-fighters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Kurdish fighters who have laid down their arms should be reintegrated into society, Turkish lawmakers urged in a key report released Wednesday, while ruling out an "amnesty". &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recommendations of the cross-party parliamentary commission are meant to prepare the legal groundwork for peace moves between Turkey and the outlawed Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year the PKK formally renounced its armed struggle against Turkey after four decades of violence that claimed some 50,000 lives on both sides.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 13:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>First Ramadan after truce brings flicker of joy in devastated Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/first-ramadan-after-truce-brings-flicker-joy-devastated-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/first-ramadan-after-truce-brings-flicker-joy-devastated-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Little Ramadan lanterns and string lights appeared on streets lined with collapsed buildings and piles of rubble in Gaza City, bringing joy and respite as Islam's holiest month began -- the first since October's ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Omari mosque, dozens of worshippers performed the first Ramadan morning prayer, fajr, bare feet on the carpet but donning heavy jackets to stave off the winter cold.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 11:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey MPs back moves to 'reintegrate' former PKK fighters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-mps-back-moves-reintegrate-former-pkk-fighters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-mps-back-moves-reintegrate-former-pkk-fighters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Kurdish fighters who have laid down their arms should be reintegrated into society, Turkish lawmakers urged in a key report released Wednesday, while avoiding any reference to an "amnesty". &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recommendations of the cross-party parliamentary commission are meant to prepare the legal groundwork for peace moves between Turkey and the outlawed Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK). &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year the PKK formally renounced its armed struggle against Turkey after four decades of violence that claimed some 50,000 lives on both sides. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 11:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey pleased with alignment steps by Syria and Kurdish forces, Erdogan says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-pleased-alignment-steps-syria-and-kurdish-forces-erdogan-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-pleased-alignment-steps-syria-and-kurdish-forces-erdogan-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Feb 18 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan said he is pleased to see steps taken in neighbouring Syria to integrate the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF) into state structures, after a U.S.-backed ceasefire deal late last month between the sides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a readout on Wednesday of his comments to reporters on a return flight from Ethiopia, Erdogan was cited as saying Ankara is closely monitoring the Syrian integration steps and providing guidance on implementing the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Tuvan Gumrukcu; Editing by Jonathan Spicer)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey foreign minister to attend Trump's Board of Peace meeting in Washington</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-foreign-minister-attend-trumps-board-peace-meeting-washington</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-foreign-minister-attend-trumps-board-peace-meeting-washington</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Feb 18 (Reuters) - Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan will travel to Washington in lieu of President Tayyip Erdogan for the inaugural meeting of U.S. President Donald Trump's "Board of Peace" on Thursday, the foreign ministry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Turkish diplomatic source told Reuters that Fidan, during the talks, would call for determined steps to resolve the Palestinian issue and emphasizethat Israel must end actions to hinder the flow of aid into Gaza and stop its ceasefire violations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkish lawmakers to vote on report advancing PKK peace process</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkish-lawmakers-vote-report-advancing-pkk-peace-process</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkish-lawmakers-vote-report-advancing-pkk-peace-process</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ece Toksabay&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Feb 18 (Reuters) - A Turkish parliamentary commission was set to vote on Wednesday on adopting a draft report to facilitate the disarmament of the outlawed Kurdistan Workers Party (PKK), which would advance a peace process meant to end a more than 40-year conflict.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The roughly 60-page report, shared with reporters ahead of the vote in Ankara, proposes making legal reforms in parallel with the PKK laying down arms, urging the judiciary to review legislation and comply with European Court of Human Rights and Constitutional Court rulings.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 09:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Epstein tried to build web of powerful ties across Middle East, documents show</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/epstein-tried-build-web-powerful-ties-across-middle-east-documents-show</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/epstein-tried-build-web-powerful-ties-across-middle-east-documents-show</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jana Choukeir, Andrew Mills and Maha El Dahan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 18 (Reuters) - The departure of the chief executive of Dubai port giant DP World is the biggest fallout in the Middle East from U.S. Department of Justice documents whichshowthat disgraced financier Jeffrey Epstein tried to build a powerful network of political figures and business leaders across the region.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 08:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Starmer, Trump discussed Russia-Ukraine, Iran after Geneva talks, Downing Street says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/starmer-trump-discussed-russia-ukraine-iran-after-geneva-talks-downing-street</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/starmer-trump-discussed-russia-ukraine-iran-after-geneva-talks-downing-street</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 18 (Reuters) - British Prime Minister Keir Starmer spoke to U.S. President Donald Trump on Tuesday night about U.S.-mediated Russia-Ukraine peace talks in Geneva, as well as talks between the U.S. and Iran on their nuclear dispute, a Downing Street spokesperson said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Starmer also discussed Gaza with Trump and stressed on the importance of securing further access for humanitarian aid, the spokesperson said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 07:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Vatican says it will not participate in Trump's 'Board of Peace'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/vatican-says-it-will-not-participate-trumps-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/vatican-says-it-will-not-participate-trumps-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 17 (Reuters) - The Vatican will not participate in U.S. President Donald Trump's so-called "Board of Peace" initiative, Cardinal Pietro Parolin, the Vatican's top diplomatic official, said on Tuesday while adding that efforts to handle crisis situations should be managed by the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo, the first U.S. pope and a critic of some of Trump's policies, was invited to join the board in January.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 05:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Pay or he dies', families told as more Egyptians risk Mediterranean crossing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pay-or-he-dies-families-told-more-egyptians-risk-mediterranean-crossing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pay-or-he-dies-families-told-more-egyptians-risk-mediterranean-crossing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Weeks after Hamdy Ibrahim left his village in Egypt's Nile Delta hoping to reach Europe, his brother's phone rang with a chilling message from Libya: pay now or the boy would die.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A smuggler was on the line, demanding 190,000 pounds ($4,000) to secure the 18-year-old's place on a boat, part of a rising exodus that last year made Egyptians the top African and second-largest global group of irregular migrants to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I told him we couldn't afford it," his brother Youssef told AFP from Kafr Abdallah Aziza in Sharqiya, an hour's drive from Cairo.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 03:30:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Over 80 Berlin Film Festival alumni sign open letter urging organisers to take stance on Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/over-80-berlin-film-festival-alumni-sign-open-letter-urging-organisers-take</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/over-80-berlin-film-festival-alumni-sign-open-letter-urging-organisers-take</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Feb 17 (Reuters) - More than 80 actors, directors and other artists who have taken part in the Berlin Film Festival, including Tilda Swinton and Javier Bardem, signed an open letter to the organisers published on Tuesday calling for them to take a clear stance on Israel's war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We call on the Berlinale to fulfil its moral duty and clearly state its opposition to Israel's genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes against Palestinians," said the open letter, which was published in full in entertainment industry magazine Variety.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 22:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>