<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Crowds in Beirut suburbs mourn Hezbollah commander slain by Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/crowds-beirut-suburbs-mourn-hezbollah-commander-slain-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/crowds-beirut-suburbs-mourn-hezbollah-commander-slain-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT (Reuters) -Hundreds gathered in Beirut's southern suburbs on Monday to mourn Hezbollah's top military commander Haytham Ali Tabtabai and four other fighters from the Lebanese group killed in an Israeli strike on the city's outskirts the previous day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The targeted assassination by Israel - a type of operation that had become rarer since a ceasefire was agreed last year - came a day after Lebanon marked its Independence Day and deepened fears of a renewed Israeli escalation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 15:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's foreign minister to hold talks in Paris on Nov. 26 - French foreign ministry</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/irans-foreign-minister-hold-talks-paris-nov-26-french-foreign-ministry</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/irans-foreign-minister-hold-talks-paris-nov-26-french-foreign-ministry</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS (Reuters) -France's Foreign Minister Jean-Noel Barrot will hold talks with his Iranian counterpart in Paris on November 26 to discuss bilateral and regional issues as well as Iran's contested nuclear programme, France's foreign ministry said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"This will be an opportunity for us to call on Iran to comply with its obligations towards the IAEA and for a swift resumption of cooperation with the agency," the foreign ministry said ahead of Abbas Araqchi's trip to France. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 14:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian far-right senator wears burqa to parliament, sparking outrage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australian-far-right-senator-wears-burqa-parliament-sparking-outrage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australian-far-right-senator-wears-burqa-parliament-sparking-outrage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt; (Corrects to change typographical error in word "risk" in paragraph 13)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY (Reuters) -Australian far-right Senator Pauline Hanson wore a burqa to Parliament on Monday as a political prop in her push to ban the Muslim garment in public, sparking accusations of racism from Muslim senators over the stunt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanson wore the burqa shortly after she was denied permission to introduce a bill that would outlaw burqas and other full-face coverings in public places in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza truce progress slow as Israeli-Hamas violence persists</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-truce-progress-slow-israeli-hamas-violence-persists</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-truce-progress-slow-israeli-hamas-violence-persists</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/JERUSALEM (Reuters) -Israeli forces killed three Palestinians in Gaza near the line demarcating areas of Israeli control on Monday, underlining the struggle to broaden a fragile ceasefire deal approved over six weeks ago to global acclaim. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Palestinian medics said Monday's incidents involved an Israeli drone firing a missile at a group of people east of Khan Younis, killing two and wounding another, and a tank shell killing a person on the eastern side of Gaza City. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah mourns top commander killed in Israeli strike</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-mourns-top-commander-killed-israeli-strike</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-mourns-top-commander-killed-israeli-strike</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hezbollah held the funeral Monday for its top military chief and other members of the militant group a day after Israel killed them in a strike on Beirut's southern suburbs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Haytham Ali Tabatabai is the most senior Hezbollah commander to be killed by Israel since a November 2024 ceasefire sought to end more than a year of hostilities between the two sides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His assassination comes as Israel has escalated its attacks on Lebanon, with the United States increasing pressure on the Beirut government to disarm the Iran-backed Hezbollah.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 11:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope heads to Turkey, Lebanon in first overseas trip</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-heads-turkey-lebanon-first-overseas-trip</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-heads-turkey-lebanon-first-overseas-trip</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo XIV embarks on his debut overseas trip Thursday, travelling to Turkey and Lebanon to promote Christian unity and urge peace efforts amid heightened tensions in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The six-day trip is the first major international test for the US pope, who was elected head of the Catholic Church in May and whose understated style contrasts with that of his charismatic and impulsive predecessor, Francis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Turkey, Leo will celebrate the 1,700th anniversary of the Council of Nicaea, where the Creed -- a foundational declaration of the Christian faith -- was written.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 06:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli army chief fires, reprimands commanders for failures in October 7 attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-army-chief-fires-reprimands-commanders-failures-october-7-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-army-chief-fires-reprimands-commanders-failures-october-7-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt; (Corrects sourcing in paragraph 2 to Israeli military)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -Israel's military chief on Sunday dismissed several senior military personnel and reprimanded others over their roles in the failures on October 7, 2023 when Hamas launched a surprise attack on southern Israel from Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A number of officers were told they would be released from reserve duty and would no longer serve in the military, the military said in a statement. Others were issued formal reprimands while one was informed that their service would be ended. Another tendered his resignation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 04:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gunmen attack Pakistan paramilitary force headquarters, police say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gunmen-attack-pakistan-paramilitary-force-headquarters-police-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gunmen-attack-pakistan-paramilitary-force-headquarters-police-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PESHAWAR, Pakistan (Reuters) -Gunmen attacked a paramilitary force headquarters in Pakistan's  northwestern city of Peshawar on Monday, police said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complex, the headquarters of the frontier constabulary paramilitary force, was also hit by two suicide bombers, sources told Reuters, adding that three people had been killed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The first suicide bomber first carried out an attack on the main entrance of the constabulary and the other one entered the compound," a senior official told Reuters on condition of anonymity.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 04:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Tabtabai, Hezbollah's military leader killed by Israel?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/who-was-tabtabai-hezbollahs-military-leader-killed-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/who-was-tabtabai-hezbollahs-military-leader-killed-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT (Reuters) -The Israeli military on Sunday killed Hezbollah's top military official, Haytham Ali Tabtabai, in a strike on the outskirts of the Lebanese capital that came despite a year-long ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His killing was announced by Israel's military. Hezbollah has not commented on his fate, although Lebanese security sources confirmed he was the target of Israel's strike. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel had already eliminated most of Iran-backed Hezbollah's leadership during a war that raged between October 2023 and November 2024, when a U.S.-brokered truce was agreed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 18:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah chief of staff killed in Israeli strike on Beirut, Israeli media says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-chief-staff-killed-israeli-strike-beirut-israeli-media-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hezbollah-chief-staff-killed-israeli-strike-beirut-israeli-media-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Hezbollah's chief of staff Ali Tabtabai was killed in an Israeli strike on a southern suburb of Beirut on Sunday, multiple Israeli media outlets reported, citing Israeli sources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Muhammad Al Gebaly and Hatem Maher, Editing by Alexandra Hudson)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 17:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says killed Hezbollah chief of staff in Beirut strike</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-says-killed-hezbollah-chief-staff-beirut-strike</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israel-says-killed-hezbollah-chief-staff-beirut-strike</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel killed Hezbollah's military chief in a strike on Beirut on Sunday, the Israeli military and the militant group said, hitting an apartment building and killing five people according to Lebanese authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Haytham Ali Tabatabai is the most senior Hezbollah commander to be killed by Israel since the start of a ceasefire in November 2024 that sought to end more than a year of hostilities between the two.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 16:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli military says it struck Hezbollah militant in Beirut's southern suburbs</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-military-says-it-struck-hezbollah-militant-beiruts-southern-suburbs</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/israeli-military-says-it-struck-hezbollah-militant-beiruts-southern-suburbs</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT (Reuters) -The Israeli military said on Sunday that it struck a militant from the Lebanese Iran-aligned Hezbollah group in the capital Beirut's southern suburbs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strike hit a main road in Beirut’s southern suburbs, where residents told Reuters they heard the roar of warplanes before the blast. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People rushed out of their apartment buildings out of fear there would be further strikes, a Reuters reporter in the area said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At least two dozen were wounded and have been taken to hospitals in the area, medical sources said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 14:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu, Smotrich to meet on Israeli 2026 budget that faces battle for approval</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-smotrich-meet-israeli-2026-budget-faces-battle-approval</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-smotrich-meet-israeli-2026-budget-faces-battle-approval</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM (Reuters) -Israeli Finance Minister Bezalel Smotrich and senior ministry officials will present Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu later on Sunday with the state budget and planned structural reforms for 2026, Smotrich's office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The Finance Minister will present to the Prime Minister the necessary measures to ensure continued economic growth and to combat the high cost of living," it said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It added that cabinet ministers would vote on the budget on Dec. 4 but it is unlikely the budget would be approved by year end.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 13:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan says he will speak to Russia's Putin on Monday</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-erdogan-says-he-will-speak-russias-putin-monday</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-erdogan-says-he-will-speak-russias-putin-monday</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan said he would have a phone call with his Russian counterpart Vladimir Putin on Monday to discuss peace efforts in Ukraine, adding that he would also ask him to restart a deal for the safe passage of grains via the Black Sea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NATO member Turkey has maintained cordial ties with both  Kyiv and Moscow during the war, providing military help to Ukraine but refusing to join Western sanctions on Moscow. It has hosted three rounds of peace talks between the warring parties in Istanbul and offered to host a leaders' meeting.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 13:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas delegation in Cairo to discuss Gaza ceasefire, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-delegation-cairo-discuss-gaza-ceasefire-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/hamas-delegation-cairo-discuss-gaza-ceasefire-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/JERUSALEM (Reuters) -A Hamas delegation was in Cairo on Sunday to meet with Gaza war mediators, an Egyptian security source and a Hamas source said, as both Israel and the Palestinian militant group continue to trade accusations of ceasefire violations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Hamas official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the delegation would be discussing Israel's "continued violation of the ceasefire agreement". &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Egypt, Qatar and the U.S. have been mediating between Hamas and Israel, securing the ceasefire that came into effect last month.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 11:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan praises 'meaningful' deal with Australia on hosting COP31 summit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-erdogan-praises-meaningful-deal-australia-hosting-cop31-summit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/turkeys-erdogan-praises-meaningful-deal-australia-hosting-cop31-summit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA (Reuters) -Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan praised a deal reached with Australia on Saturday to host next year's U.N. climate summit, calling the compromise a meaningful achievement for multilateralism.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Resolving a lengthy standoff, the two countries agreed that Turkey will host the COP31 summit in 2026 while Australia leads the negotiation process. Ankara and Canberra both bid in 2022 to host the conference and had since refused to stand down.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 07:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada PM and German Chancellor Merz discuss Ukraine, Gaza on G20 sidelines</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/canada-pm-and-german-chancellor-merz-discuss-ukraine-gaza-g20-sidelines</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/canada-pm-and-german-chancellor-merz-discuss-ukraine-gaza-g20-sidelines</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(Reuters) -Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney and German Chancellor Friedrich Merz discussed the war in Ukraine and situation in Gaza on the sidelines of the G20 summit in South Africa, the two countries said in a joint statement on Sunday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two leaders reaffirmed support for Ukraine and emphasized that any agreement must involve Kyiv directly, protect its fundamental interests and include concrete security assurances. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 06:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Tejas crash dampens export hopes for Indian fighter jet</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-tejas-crash-dampens-export-hopes-indian-fighter-jet</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/analysis-tejas-crash-dampens-export-hopes-indian-fighter-jet</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Shivam Patel and Tim Hepher&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NEW DELHI/DUBAI (Reuters) -The crash of India's Tejas fighter in front of global arms buyers at the Dubai Airshow is the latest blow to a key national trophy, leaving the jet reliant on Indian military orders to sustain its role as a showcase of home-built defence technology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cause of Friday's crash was not immediately known but it capped a week of jockeying for influence at the event, attended by India's arch-rival Pakistan six months after the neighbouring foes faced off in the world's largest air battle in decades.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 06:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisians escalate protests against Saied, demanding return of democracy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tunisians-escalate-protests-against-saied-demanding-return-democracy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tunisians-escalate-protests-against-saied-demanding-return-democracy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS (Reuters) -Thousands of Tunisians marched in the capital on Saturday in a protest against “injustice and repression”, accusing President Kais Saied of cementing one-man rule by using the judiciary and police.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protest was the latest in a wave that has swept Tunisia involving journalists, doctors, banks and public transport systems. Thousands have also demanded the closure of a chemical plant on environmental grounds.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 02:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia PM says formal deal reached for Turkey to host COP31 climate summit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-pm-says-formal-deal-reached-turkey-host-cop31-climate-summit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/australia-pm-says-formal-deal-reached-turkey-host-cop31-climate-summit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY (Reuters) -Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese said on Sunday a formal agreement had been reached for Turkey to host the COP31 climate summit in 2026, confirming a document released at the COP30 summit in Brazil. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A statement issued by Germany this week at the COP30 summit, after a meeting of the Western European and Others Group tasked with selecting the 2026 host, said Turkey would take the role with Australia leading the negotiation process. It followed an earlier announcement that a compromise arrangement was expected.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 23:36:33 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>