<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Arab states criticise Israel as it expands powers in occupied West Bank</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arab-states-criticise-israel-it-expands-powers-occupied-west-bank</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arab-states-criticise-israel-it-expands-powers-occupied-west-bank</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ali Sawafta and Emily Rose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;RAMALLAH/JERUSALEM, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates led regional states on Monday in condemning Israel's move to ease settlement expansion and widen its powers in the West Bank, a step critics said went in the direction of annexing occupied land.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunday's decisions by Israel's security cabinet will make it easier for Jewish settlers to buy land in the West Bank and give Israeli authorities more power to act in areas supposedly under full Palestinian control, two senior Israeli ministers said. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-What is the two-state solution to the Israel-Palestinian conflict?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/explainer-what-two-state-solution-israel-palestinian-conflict</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/explainer-what-two-state-solution-israel-palestinian-conflict</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 9, (Reuters) - Israel has taken steps to help settlers acquire land in the occupied West Bank and widen its powers in parts of the territory where Palestinians have some self-rule - measures they said aimed to undermine the two-state solution.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It marks the latest blow to the idea of establishing a Palestinian state co-existing peacefully alongside Israel in territory Israel captured in the 1967 Middle East war. Long backed by world powers, this vision formed the bedrock of the U.S.-backed peace process ushered in by the 1993 Oslo Accords. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arms production to air defense: Inside $350M Egypt-Turkey military pact</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arms-production-air-defense-inside-350m-egypt-turkey-military-pact</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/arms-production-air-defense-inside-350m-egypt-turkey-military-pact</guid><description>Ankara and Cairo's military framework agreement goes beyond arms sales, reflecting a gradual strategic convergence that includes intelligence sharing in third countries.</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:18:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudanese nomads trapped as war fuels banditry and ethnic splits</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-nomads-trapped-war-fuels-banditry-and-ethnic-splits</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-nomads-trapped-war-fuels-banditry-and-ethnic-splits</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Eltayeb Siddig&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NEAR AL-OBEID, Sudan, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Gubara al-Basheer and his family used to traverse Sudan's desert with their camels and livestock, moving freely between markets, water sources, and green pastures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But since war erupted in 2023, he and other Arab nomads have been stuck in the desert outside the central Sudanese city of al-Obeid, threatened by marauding bandits and ethnic tensions.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 13:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prince William to begin Saudi Arabia visit overshadowed by Epstein scandal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/prince-william-begin-saudi-arabia-visit-overshadowed-epstein-scandal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/prince-william-begin-saudi-arabia-visit-overshadowed-epstein-scandal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Britain's Prince William will begin Monday his first official visit to Saudi Arabia, aimed at deepening economic cooperation but already overshadowed by his disgraced uncle Andrew's links to Jeffrey Epstein.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of his arrival in Riyadh, Kensington Palace broke years of silence over Andrew's links to the late American convicted sex offender by saying William and his wife Catherine were "deeply concerned by the continuing revelations".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says killed four militants exiting Gaza tunnel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-says-killed-four-militants-exiting-gaza-tunnel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-says-killed-four-militants-exiting-gaza-tunnel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's military said Monday it had killed four armed militants who attacked its troops as they emerged from a tunnel in southern Gaza, accusing the suspects of a "blatant violation" of the ceasefire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a US-brokered truce entering its second phase last month, violence has continued in the Palestinian territory, with Israel and Hamas trading accusations of ceasefire violations. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK's Prince William and Kate 'deeply concerned' about Epstein revelations</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uks-prince-william-and-kate-deeply-concerned-about-epstein-revelations</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uks-prince-william-and-kate-deeply-concerned-about-epstein-revelations</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Britain's Prince William and his wife Kate said on Monday they were deeply concerned by the revelations in the Jeffrey Epstein files amid further damning disclosures about the heir-to-the-throne's uncle Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mountbatten-Windsor, the younger brother of King Charles who had already been cast out of the royal inner circle over his close relationship with Epstein, has faced fresh scrutiny since the recent publication of millions of new documents relating to the late convicted U.S. sex offender.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:01:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US Vice President Vance heads to Armenia, Azerbaijan to push peace, trade</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-vice-president-vance-heads-armenia-azerbaijan-push-peace-trade</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-vice-president-vance-heads-armenia-azerbaijan-push-peace-trade</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Lucy Papachristou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TBILISI, Feb 9 (Reuters) - U.S. Vice President JD Vance will visit Armenia and Azerbaijan this week to push a Washington-brokered peace agreement that could transform energy and trade routes in the strategic South Caucasus region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His two-day trip to Armenia, which begins later on Monday, comes just six months after the Armenian and Azerbaijani leaders signed an agreement at the White House seen as the first step towards peace after nearly 40 years of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Adviser to Iran's Supreme Leader to visit Oman on Tuesday after US-Iranian talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/adviser-irans-supreme-leader-visit-oman-tuesday-after-us-iranian-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/adviser-irans-supreme-leader-visit-oman-tuesday-after-us-iranian-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Ali Larijani, an adviser to Iran's Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei and secretary of its national security council, will visit Oman on Tuesday following indirect U.S.-Iranian talks there, the semi-official Tasnim news agency reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. and Iranian diplomats engaged through Omani mediation in the Gulf Arab state last week in an effort to revive diplomacy amid a U.S. naval buildup near Iran and Tehran's vows of a harsh response if attacked.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain's Prince William to meet Saudi crown prince on official visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/britains-prince-william-meet-saudi-crown-prince-official-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/britains-prince-william-meet-saudi-crown-prince-official-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Britain's Prince William will meet Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman during a three-day visit to Saudi Arabia starting on Monday, an official trip on behalf of the government to deepen ties with the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The royal's visit follows a 2025 trip to Saudi by Britain's finance minister, which London said had unlocked trade and investment agreements worth 6.4 billion pounds ($8.71 billion). &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sydney police pepper spray protesters during rallies against Israeli president's visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sydney-police-pepper-spray-protesters-during-rallies-against-israeli-presidents</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sydney-police-pepper-spray-protesters-during-rallies-against-israeli-presidents</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sydney police used pepper spray on protesters on Monday as a rally against a visit to Australia by Israel's President Isaac Herzog turned violent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The head of state's tightly secured, four-day visit was aimed at consoling Australia's Jewish community in the wake of the December shooting at Sydney's Bondi Beach that killed 15 people at a Hanukkah festival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But he was met with protests in Australia's two largest cities on Monday evening, with a Sydney rally turning violent as police hit protesters and members of the media, including AFP, with pepper spray.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Building collapse in Lebanon's Tripoli kills 13, search for missing continues</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/building-collapse-lebanons-tripoli-kills-13-search-missing-continues</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/building-collapse-lebanons-tripoli-kills-13-search-missing-continues</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 9 (Reuters) - The death toll from the collapse of a residential building in the Lebanese city of Tripoli rose to 13, as rescue teams continued to search for missing people beneath the rubble, Lebanon's National News Agency reported on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rescue workers in the northern city's Bab al-Tabbaneh neighbourhood have also assisted nine survivors, while the search continued for others still believed to be trapped under the debris, NNA said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Officials said on Sunday that two adjoining buildings had collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pro-Palestine protest planned in Sydney against Israeli President Herzog's visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pro-palestine-protest-planned-sydney-against-israeli-president-herzogs-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pro-palestine-protest-planned-sydney-against-israeli-president-herzogs-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Renju Jose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Feb 9 (Reuters) - Pro-Palestine demonstrators plan to rally in Sydney on Monday to protest the visit by Israeli President Isaac Herzog, as authorities declared his visit a major event and deployed thousands of police to manage the crowds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Police have urged the protesters to gather at a central Sydney park for public safety reasons, but protest organisers said they plan to rally at the city's historic Town Hall instead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 23:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon building collapse toll rises to 9: civil defence</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanon-building-collapse-toll-rises-9-civil-defence</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/lebanon-building-collapse-toll-rises-9-civil-defence</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The death toll in a building collapse in the northern Lebanese city of Tripoli on Sunday climbed to nine, a civil defence official said -- the second such incident in weeks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The state-run National News Agency (NNA) reported "the collapse of an old building" in Tripoli's Bab al-Tabbaneh neighbourhood, the poorest in the impoverished city. Rescuers were still searching for survivors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Security personnel evacuated adjacent buildings fearing further collapses, it added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 23:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran Nobel winner given new prison sentence, ends hunger strike: supporters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-nobel-winner-given-new-prison-sentence-ends-hunger-strike-supporters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-nobel-winner-given-new-prison-sentence-ends-hunger-strike-supporters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian Nobel Peace Prize winner Narges Mohammadi is in "deteriorating health" after ending a nearly week-long hunger strike, her supporters said Sunday, as authorities handed the campaigner a fresh prison sentence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mohammadi, who won the peace prize in 2023, has spent the last two months in prison after speaking out against the government at a funeral ceremony in December.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 20:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Norwegian diplomat steps down over Epstein ties, in widening scandal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norwegian-diplomat-steps-down-over-epstein-ties-widening-scandal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norwegian-diplomat-steps-down-over-epstein-ties-widening-scandal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nora Buli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OSLO, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Norway's foreign ministry on Sunday said a prominent ambassador, Mona Juul, would step down due to a "serious failure of judgement" over ties to late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, part of a growing scandal in the Nordic country and across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministry earlier this week suspended Juul from her position as ambassador to Jordan and Iraq pending an internal inquiry of links to Epstein found in a massive set of files released by the United States government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 19:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli president to honour Bondi Beach attack victims on Australia visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-president-honour-bondi-beach-attack-victims-australia-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-president-honour-bondi-beach-attack-victims-australia-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's President Isaac Herzog starts a tightly secured visit to Australia on Monday to honour the victims of an antisemitic gun attack on Sydney's Bondi Beach that killed 15 people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the head of state seeks to console the Jewish Australian community, his four-day trip has also sparked calls for pro-Palestinian protests in Sydney's streets, where the authorities promised a large police presence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 19:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's Nobel winner Narges Mohammadi faces a new prison term of more than seven years</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-nobel-winner-narges-mohammadi-faces-new-prison-term-more-seven-years</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-nobel-winner-narges-mohammadi-faces-new-prison-term-more-seven-years</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Iranian activist and Nobel Peace Prize winner Narges Mohammadi, who has been imprisoned repeatedly in her three-decade campaign for women's rights, was sentenced to a new prison term of 7-1/2 years, a group supporting her said on Sunday.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mohammadi, 53, was on a week-long hunger strike that ended on Sunday, the Narges Foundation said in a statement. It said Mohammadi told her lawyer, Mostafa Nili, in a phone call on Sunday from prison that she had received her sentence on Saturday. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 18:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel to take more West Bank powers and relax settler land buys, media say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-take-more-west-bank-powers-and-relax-settler-land-buys-media-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israel-take-more-west-bank-powers-and-relax-settler-land-buys-media-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Israel's security cabinet approved a series of steps on Sunday that would make it easier for settlers in the occupied West Bank to buy land while granting Israeli authorities more enforcement powers over Palestinians, Israeli media reported.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The West Bank is among the territories that the Palestinians seek for a future independent state. Much of it is under Israeli military control, with limited Palestinian self-rule in some areas run by the Western-backed Palestinian Authority (PA).  &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 16:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia orders 20 high-speed trains from Spain's Talgo</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/saudi-arabia-orders-20-high-speed-trains-spains-talgo</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/saudi-arabia-orders-20-high-speed-trains-spains-talgo</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MADRID, Feb 8 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia has ordered 20 new high-speed trains from Spain's Talgo SA, the company and Spain's transport minister said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Talgo said the deal adds 1.33 billion euros ($1.57 billion) to its order backlog, bringing it to a total of nearly 6 billion euros, a record. The contract also covers maintenance for the trains.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 15:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>