<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Trump says he is considering limited military strike on Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-he-considering-limited-military-strike-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-he-considering-limited-military-strike-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 20 (Reuters) - WU.S. President Donald Trump said on Friday he was considering a limited military strike on Iran but gave no other details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Asked if he was considering a limited strike to pressure  Iran into a deal on its nuclear program, he told reporters at the White House, “I guess I can say I am considering" it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Steve Holland, Bo Erickson and Katharine Jackson; writing by Susan Heavey; Editing by Doina Chiacu)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 15:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I never thought it would be hit, says 'Scream' creator 30 years later</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/i-never-thought-it-would-be-hit-says-scream-creator-30-years-later</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/i-never-thought-it-would-be-hit-says-scream-creator-30-years-later</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When he sat down to write the first "Scream" film which appeared in cinemas exactly 30 years ago, horror movies were out of fashion and aspiring Hollywood creative Kevin Williamson had low expectations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I never thought it would be a hit actually. I was just trying to get a job. I was just trying to write a script to get noticed by Hollywood so that I get hired to write another movie," he told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"And I just wrote what I love: I love horror films," he added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 14:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's FM says US didn’t demand zero enrichment in nuclear talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-fm-says-us-didnt-demand-zero-enrichment-nuclear-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/irans-fm-says-us-didnt-demand-zero-enrichment-nuclear-talks</guid><description>The top Iranian diplomat said the two sides have instead discussed “confidence-building measures" related to its nuclear program.</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 14:02:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US not seeking zero enrichment in talks, Iran's foreign minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-not-seeking-zero-enrichment-talks-irans-foreign-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-not-seeking-zero-enrichment-talks-irans-foreign-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 20 (Reuters) - The United States did not seek zero uranium enrichment during nuclear talks in Geneva this week while Iran did not offer to suspend uranium enrichment, Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have not offered any suspension and the U.S. side has not asked for zero enrichment," he said in an interview on MS NOW.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"What we are now talking about is how to make sure that Iran's nuclear program, including enrichment, is peaceful and would remain peaceful forever," he said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 14:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey jails journalist with Germany's DW for 'insulting president'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-jails-journalist-germanys-dw-insulting-president</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-jails-journalist-germanys-dw-insulting-president</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Turkish journalist with German public broadcaster Deutsche Welle (DW) was jailed by an Istanbul court Friday on charges of "insulting the president", an NGO said a day after his arrest by 30 police officers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alican Uludag was arrested in Ankara on Thursday evening following a warrant issued by the Istanbul public prosecutor's office, which said it had opened an investigation into him for "insulting" President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and "disseminating false news" in connection with "certain posts" on X.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 13:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey, Saudi sign major solar power deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-saudi-sign-major-solar-power-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-saudi-sign-major-solar-power-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia will help Turkey build solar plants capable of powering more than two million homes, under a deal the two countries signed Friday that aims to deepen energy cooperation between the key regional players.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The signing ceremony at an Ottoman-era palace by the waters of the Bosphorus Strait in Istanbul followed a $2-billion inter-governmental energy agreement between the two countries during a landmark visit by Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan to Riyadh on February 3.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 12:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK foreign minister to meet Rubio amid tensions over joint air base</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uk-foreign-minister-meet-rubio-amid-tensions-over-joint-air-base</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uk-foreign-minister-meet-rubio-amid-tensions-over-joint-air-base</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 20 (Reuters) - Britain's foreign minister Yvette Cooper will meet with U.S. Secretary of State Marco Rubio on Friday, after President Donald Trump renewed his criticism of London for ceding sovereignty of the Chagos Islands, which is home to a U.S.-UK air base.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year British Prime Minister Keir Starmer agreed a deal to transfer sovereignty of the Indian Ocean islands to Mauritius, while keeping control of one - Diego Garcia - through a 99-year lease that preserved U.S. operations at the base.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 12:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Norway moves some of its 60 soldiers in Middle East due to security situation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-moves-some-its-60-soldiers-middle-east-due-security-situation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/norway-moves-some-its-60-soldiers-middle-east-due-security-situation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;COPENHAGEN, Feb 20 (Reuters) - Norway is relocating some of the around 60 soldiers it has in the Middle East to Norway as well as to other countries in the region on security grounds, a spokesperson for the Norwegian armed forces said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump warned Iran on Thursday it must make a deal over its nuclear program or "really bad things" will happen, setting a deadline of 10 to 15 days, drawing a threat from Tehran to retaliate against U.S. bases in the region if attacked.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 11:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Despite warnings from Israel's defense elite, Netanyahu pushes for Iran strike</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/despite-warnings-israels-defense-elite-netanyahu-pushes-iran-strike</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/despite-warnings-israels-defense-elite-netanyahu-pushes-iran-strike</guid><description>Although Israeli advisers warn against appearing to drag the US into war, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has not hidden his desire to help topple the Islamic Republic.</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 10:08:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Soccer-FIFA and Board of Peace to support Gaza reconstruction through football</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/soccer-fifa-and-board-peace-support-gaza-reconstruction-through-football</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/soccer-fifa-and-board-peace-support-gaza-reconstruction-through-football</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 20 (Reuters) - FIFA and the Board of Peace signed a partnership agreement on Thursday to attract investment from global leaders and institutions for sustainable development in conflict-affected regions through football.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace, established under the U.S. President Donald Trump, held its first meeting focused on Gaza's reconstruction fund, aimed at rebuilding the territory once Hamas disarms.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 09:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Somaliland, where Muslims love Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/somaliland-where-muslims-love-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/somaliland-where-muslims-love-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;"I love Israel!" Three little words rarely heard together in the Muslim world, and yet have become a common phrase in Somaliland, the breakaway region of Somalia. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Israel became the only country in the world to recognise Somaliland's independence in December -- something the territory has been seeking since declaring its autonomy from Somalia in 1991. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Ramadan started this week in the deeply Muslim territory, almost all its citizens -- young and old, men and women -- were happy to sing Israel's praises. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 09:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Journalist with Germany's Deutsche Welle detained in Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/journalist-germanys-deutsche-welle-detained-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/journalist-germanys-deutsche-welle-detained-turkey</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;FRANKFURT, Feb 20 (Reuters) - Turkish authorities have detained a veteran correspondent of German state-backed international broadcaster Deutsche Welle in Ankara, accusing him of "disseminating misleading information" and "insulting the president".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Istanbul Chief Public Prosecutor's Office said in a statement late on Thursday it detained Alican Uludag and launched a criminal investigation based on some of his social media posts. He will be brought before prosecutors on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 07:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Ukraine's 2026 defence exports could hit 'several billion dollars', official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-ukraines-2026-defence-exports-could-hit-several-billion-dollars</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-ukraines-2026-defence-exports-could-hit-several-billion-dollars</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Feb 20 (Reuters) - Ukraine could export several billion dollars of military goods and services this year after authorising its first wartime foreign sales and is considering introducing a tax on those exports, a senior Ukrainian defence official said. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, the state commission handling related licences in wartime approved the majority of 40 applications from defence sector producers for exports of materiel and services, Davyd Aloian, deputy secretary of Kyiv's National Security and Defence Council, told Reuters in an interview. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 06:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli Druze leader says Syrian community 'besieged' months after clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-druze-leader-says-syrian-community-besieged-months-after-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-druze-leader-says-syrian-community-besieged-months-after-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Seven months after deadly clashes between Syria's Druze minority and government‑backed forces, the spiritual leader of Druze in neighbouring Israel said members of the community across the border remained in peril.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"They're still besieged -- completely encircled. They aren't allowed to bring in any humanitarian aid, including the aid we're trying to deliver," Sheikh Mowafaq Tarif told AFP in an interview this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 03:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Syria's Kurds, dream of autonomy fades under Damascus deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrias-kurds-dream-autonomy-fades-under-damascus-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrias-kurds-dream-autonomy-fades-under-damascus-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At a military base in northeast Syria, Roksan Mohammed recalled joining the battle against Islamic State group jihadists. Now her all-woman fighting unit is at risk after a deal with Damascus ended the Kurds' de facto autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We made many sacrifices," said Mohammed, spokesperson for the Women's Protection Units (YPJ), who stood with a gun slung over her shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Thousands of martyrs shed their blood, including many of my close comrades," the 37-year-old added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:30:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump mixes diplomacy and flattery at peace board meeting</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-mixes-diplomacy-and-flattery-peace-board-meeting</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-mixes-diplomacy-and-flattery-peace-board-meeting</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Bo Erickson, Trevor Hunnicutt and Gram Slattery&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - World leaders who accepted the invitation of President Donald Trump to join his new peace board were greeted in Washington on Thursday with a mix of fanfare and personal flattery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the U.S. president has been chummy with world leaders in the past, he has typically leaned in to a good-cop-bad-cop routine, alternating between praise and threats as his interests dictate. On Thursday, those in attendance saw Trump at his most convivial.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US removing guardrails from proposed Saudi nuclear deal, document says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-removing-guardrails-proposed-saudi-nuclear-deal-document-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-removing-guardrails-proposed-saudi-nuclear-deal-document-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Timothy Gardner and Jonathan Landay&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump has told Congress he is pursuing a civil nuclear pact with Saudi Arabia that does not include non-proliferation safeguards the U.S. has long said would ensure the kingdom does not develop nuclear weapons, according to a copy of the document sent to Congress and reviewed by Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump, a Republican, and former President Joe Biden, a Democrat, have worked with Saudi Arabia on paths to building the first civil nuclear power plants for the kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza deaths in war's first 15 months higher than reported, study says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-deaths-wars-first-15-months-higher-reported-study-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/gaza-deaths-wars-first-15-months-higher-reported-study-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Rami Ayyub&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 19 (Reuters) - More than 75,000 Palestinians were killed in the first 15 months of Israel's military assault in Gaza, a figure far higher than the 49,000 deaths local health officials announced at the time, says a new study by The Lancet Global Health medical journal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The peer-reviewed study, published on Wednesday, found that women, children and the elderly comprised some 56.2% of violent deaths in Gaza during that period, a composition that it said roughly aligned with reporting by Gaza's health ministry.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran tells UN chief it will respond 'decisively' if subjected to military aggression</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-tells-un-chief-it-will-respond-decisively-if-subjected-military-aggression</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-tells-un-chief-it-will-respond-decisively-if-subjected-military-aggression</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Iran told U.N. Secretary-General Antonio Guterres on Thursday that Tehran will consider bases, facilities and assets of the "hostile force" in the region as legitimate targets if it faces military aggression.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump's rhetoric towards Iran "signals a real risk of military aggression," Iran's permanent mission to the United Nations said in the letter, adding Iran did not want a war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran will respond "decisively" if subjected to military aggression, the letter said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FIFA to lead $75m Palestinian soccer rebuilding fund</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fifa-lead-75m-palestinian-soccer-rebuilding-fund</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fifa-lead-75m-palestinian-soccer-rebuilding-fund</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;FIFA will spearhead a $75 million fund to rebuild soccer facilities in Gaza that were destroyed by the war between Israel and Hamas, President Donald Trump and the sport's governing body said Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump made the announcement in Washington at the first meeting of his "Board of Peace," an amorphous institution that features two dozen of the US president's close allies and is initially focused on rebuilding the Gaza strip.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I'm also pleased to announce that FIFA will be helping to raise a total of $75 million for projects in Gaza," said Trump.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>