<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Netanyahu coalition pushes contentious Oct. 7 attack probe, families call for justice</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-coalition-pushes-contentious-oct-7-attack-probe-families-call-justice</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/netanyahu-coalition-pushes-contentious-oct-7-attack-probe-families-call-justice</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 24 (Reuters) - Israel's parliament gave the initial go-ahead on Wednesday for a government-empowered inquiry into the surprise October 7, 2023 attack by Hamas on southern Israel rather than the expected independent investigation demanded by families of the victims.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has resisted calls to establish a state commission to investigate Israel's failures in the run-up to its deadliest day and has taken no responsibility for the attack that sparked the two-year Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 16:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel accuses Hamas of violating Gaza truce, says it will respond</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-accuses-hamas-violating-gaza-truce-says-it-will-respond</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-accuses-hamas-violating-gaza-truce-says-it-will-respond</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 24 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu accused Hamas on Wednesday of violating the Gaza ceasefire agreement after a military officer was wounded by an explosive device in Rafah and Israel vowed retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His office said in a statement that Hamas must fully uphold the October agreement, noting that it envisaged the militant group being removed from power in Gaza as well as demilitarisation and deradicalisation of the territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Israel will respond accordingly," the statement added.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 14:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bethlehem celebrates first festive Christmas since Gaza war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/bethlehem-celebrates-first-festive-christmas-gaza-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/bethlehem-celebrates-first-festive-christmas-gaza-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Scouts marched under a clear blue sky in Bethlehem on Wednesday, as the Palestinian city emerged from the shadow of the war in Gaza to celebrate its first festive Christmas in more than two years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout the Gaza war that began with Hamas's attack on Israel in October 2023, a sombre tone marked Chistmases in Bethlehem, the biblical birthplace of Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But on Wednesday, celebrations were in full swing again in the occupied West Bank city, as a fragile truce held in the Gaza Strip where hundreds of thousands of people face the winter living in makeshift tents.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 13:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey, Hamas discuss Gaza ceasefire deal's second phase, Turkish source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-hamas-discuss-gaza-ceasefire-deals-second-phase-turkish-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-hamas-discuss-gaza-ceasefire-deals-second-phase-turkish-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Dec 24 (Reuters) - Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan on Wednesday met with Hamas political bureau officials in Ankara to discuss the ceasefire in Gaza and advancing the agreement to its second phase, a Turkish Foreign Ministry source said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The source said the Hamas officials told Fidan that they had fulfilled their requirements as part of the ceasefire deal, but that Israel's continued targeting of Gaza aimed to prevent the agreement from moving to the next phase.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 11:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Black box recovered from Libyan general's crashed plane</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/black-box-recovered-libyan-generals-crashed-plane</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/black-box-recovered-libyan-generals-crashed-plane</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turkish authorities on Wednesday found the cockpit voice recorder and black box from a private jet that crashed killing the head of Libya's armed forces and his four aides.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Falcon 50 aircraft requested an emergency landing because of electrical failure minutes after it took off from the Turkish capital Ankara on Tuesday, but contact was lost, Turkish officials said. The plane was returning to Tripoli. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wreckage was located by Turkish security personnel in the Haymana district near Ankara. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 10:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Israel's hilltop settlers coordinate attacks to expel Palestinians</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/how-israels-hilltop-settlers-coordinate-attacks-expel-palestinians</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/how-israels-hilltop-settlers-coordinate-attacks-expel-palestinians</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Pesha Magid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DEIR DIBWAN, WEST BANK, Dec 24 (Reuters) - The Jewish settler outpost of Or Meir is small. A handful of prefabricated white shelters, it sits at the end of a short dirt track on a hill leading up from Road 60, a major route that dissects the Israeli-occupied West Bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, similar modest dwellings have turned into sprawling Israeli housing developments, part of a plan that members of Israel's cabinet acknowledge they have implemented to prevent the birth of a Palestinian state.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 09:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Festive lights, security tight for Christmas in Damascus</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/festive-lights-security-tight-christmas-damascus</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/festive-lights-security-tight-christmas-damascus</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Christmas lights illuminate Damascus's Old City while government forces patrol its shadows as security fears haunt Syria's Christian community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They recall the shooting and suicide attack in June at the Saint Elias church in the Syrian capital that killed 25 people and wounded dozens more.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"People are going home early, and are afraid," said Tala Shamoun, 26, a university student who was visiting a Christmas market with family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 09:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says electrical failure reported before Libyan military jet crash</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-says-electrical-failure-reported-libyan-military-jet-crash</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-says-electrical-failure-reported-libyan-military-jet-crash</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Dec 24 (Reuters) - A private jet carrying the chief of staff of Libya’s army reported an electrical failure and requested an emergency landing shortly before crashing near Ankara, Turkey’s head of communications said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Dassault Falcon 50 jet took off from Ankara’s Esenboga Airport at 1717 GMT on Tuesday en route to Tripoli and at 1733 GMT it informed air traffic control of an emergency caused by an electrical malfunction, Burhanettin Duran said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 06:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian state passes tougher gun, anti-terror laws after Bondi Beach shooting</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australian-state-passes-tougher-gun-anti-terror-laws-after-bondi-beach-shooting</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/australian-state-passes-tougher-gun-anti-terror-laws-after-bondi-beach-shooting</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Renju Jose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SYDNEY, Dec 24 (Reuters) - Australia's most populous state on Wednesday passed sweeping new gun and anti-terror laws following the recent mass shooting on Bondi Beach, tightening firearm ownership, banning public display of terrorist symbols and strengthening police power to curb protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The New South Wales state parliament passed the terrorism and other legislation amendment bill early morning after the upper house approved the bill by 18 votes to eight.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 23:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Libya's top military chief killed in plane crash in Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libyas-top-military-chief-killed-plane-crash-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libyas-top-military-chief-killed-plane-crash-turkey</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The head of Libya's armed forces and four other high ranking military officials died late Tuesday when their business jet crashed shortly after taking off from Ankara, officials in Turkey's capital and Tripoli said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wreckage of their Falcon 50 aircraft was located by Turkish security personnel in the Haymana district near Ankara, Turkish Interior Minister Ali Yerlikaya said. Three crew members were also killed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 21:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Libya says its army chief dies in plane crash in Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libya-says-its-army-chief-dies-plane-crash-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/libya-says-its-army-chief-dies-plane-crash-turkey</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Dec 23 (Reuters) - The Libyan army's chief of staff, Mohammed Ali Ahmed Al-Haddad, died in a plane crash on Tuesday after leaving Turkey's capital Ankara, the prime minister of Libya's internationally recognised government said, adding that four others were on the jet as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"This followed a tragic and painful incident while they were returning from an official trip from the Turkish city of Ankara. This grave loss is a great loss for the nation, for the military institution, and for all the people," Libyan Prime Minister Abdulhamid Dbeibah said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 21:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US, Iran spar over nuclear talks at UN</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-iran-spar-over-nuclear-talks-un</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/us-iran-spar-over-nuclear-talks-un</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 23 (Reuters) - The United States and Iran traded barbs at the United Nations Security Council on Tuesday over conditions for reviving nuclear talks, with the U.S. saying it remains ready for direct negotiations and Iran rejecting Washington's terms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two countries held five rounds of nuclear talks prior to a 12-day war between Iran and Israel in June, which Washington joined by striking Iranian nuclear sites.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 19:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jet carrying Libyan army chief crashes after departing Ankara</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/jet-carrying-libyan-army-chief-crashes-after-departing-ankara</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/jet-carrying-libyan-army-chief-crashes-after-departing-ankara</guid><description>The jet lost contact after departing Ankara, with Turkish authorities launching search and rescue efforts.</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 19:21:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria's Shibani talks defense, economic ties with Russia's Putin during Moscow visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syrias-shibani-talks-defense-economic-ties-russias-putin-during-moscow-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/syrias-shibani-talks-defense-economic-ties-russias-putin-during-moscow-visit</guid><description>The visit is the second to Russia for Syrian Foreign Minister Asaad al-Shibani and Defense Minister Maj. Gen. Murhaf Abu Qasra, and follows other signs of rapprochement.</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 18:27:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency plunges to historic low amid factional blame game</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</guid><description>As Iran's judiciary publicly rebukes the central bank over the rial's collapse, the currency crisis is no longer economic and is fast becoming a test of political accountability and regime stability.</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 17:52:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency plunges to historic low amid factional blame game</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</guid><description>As Iran's judiciary publicly rebukes the central bank over the rial's collapse, the currency crisis is no longer economic and is fast becoming a test of political accountability and regime stability.</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 17:52:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency plunges to historic low amid factional blame game</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</guid><description>As Iran's judiciary publicly rebukes the central bank over the rial's collapse, the currency crisis is no longer economic and is fast becoming a test of political accountability and regime stability.</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 17:52:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran currency plunges to historic low amid factional blame game</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-currency-plunges-historic-low-amid-factional-blame-game</guid><description>As Iran's judiciary publicly rebukes the central bank over the rial's collapse, the currency crisis is no longer economic and is fast becoming a test of political accountability and regime stability.</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 17:52:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Citing better cooperation, Montenegro lifts visas for Turkish citizens</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/citing-better-cooperation-montenegro-lifts-visas-turkish-citizens</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/citing-better-cooperation-montenegro-lifts-visas-turkish-citizens</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BELGRADE, Dec 23 (Reuters) - Montenegro on Tuesday revoked its decision to insist on visas for Turkish citizens and reintroduced a visa-free regime but for a shortened duration, citing improved cooperation with Turkish authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following violence triggered by the stabbing of a Montenegrin man in the capital Podgorica by a group of Turks, Montenegro in October suspended a regime that had allowed visa-free stays of up to 90 days for Turkish nationals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 16:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greta Thunberg arrested at pro-Palestinian protest in London</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/greta-thunberg-arrested-pro-palestinian-protest-london</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/greta-thunberg-arrested-pro-palestinian-protest-london</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;London police on Tuesday arrested Swedish activist Greta Thunberg at a demonstration in support of pro-Palestinian hunger strikers, Palestinian campaign groups said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thunberg's arrest makes her the highest profile person to be detained by police since the government banned the Palestine Action group under anti-terror laws.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prisoners for Palestine, which organised the protest, said in a statement that Thunberg was arrested under the UK Terrorism Act. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thunberg, 22, was holding a sign reading: "I support the Palestine Action prisoners. I oppose genocide."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 16:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>