<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israel cabinet set to approve 2026 budget but faces battle for final approval</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-cabinet-set-approve-2026-budget-faces-battle-final-approval</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-cabinet-set-approve-2026-budget-faces-battle-final-approval</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Israel's cabinet began debate on the 2026 state budget plan that is likely to face an uphill battle and lead to new elections if not approved by March.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ministers began what is usually a marathon session on Thursday ahead of a vote that could come early on Friday. If it passes, it heads to parliament for its initial vote.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 15:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey summons Ukrainian, Russian envoys over Black Sea attacks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-summons-ukrainian-russian-envoys-over-black-sea-attacks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-summons-ukrainian-russian-envoys-over-black-sea-attacks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Turkey summoned Ukraine's ambassador and Russia's acting charges d'affaires to the foreign ministry to convey its concerns over a series of attacks on Russia-linked vessels inside its exclusive economic zone in the Black Sea, Deputy Foreign Minister Berris Ekinci said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are witnessing a very serious escalation in recent weeks in the Russia-Ukraine war with reciprocal attacks. And lastly, there were certain attacks in the Black Sea within our exclusive economic zone as well," Ekinci told parliament's foreign affairs commission.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 15:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Security Council says ready to support Syria on first-ever visit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-security-council-says-ready-support-syria-first-ever-visit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/un-security-council-says-ready-support-syria-first-ever-visit</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A United Nations Security Council delegation made its first-ever visit to Syria on Thursday, pledging the international community's support for the country days before the anniversary of Bashar al-Assad's ousting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We reiterated our clear support for sovereignty, unity, independence and territorial integrity of Syria," Slovenian UN ambassador Samuel Zbogar told a press conference in Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 15:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says it strikes two south Lebanon towns</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-says-it-strikes-two-south-lebanon-towns</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-says-it-strikes-two-south-lebanon-towns</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 4 (Reuters) - Israel's military said it struck targets in two southern Lebanese towns on Thursday after ordering the evacuation of two buildings it alleged were being used by Hezbollah militants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;About an hour after the initial warning, the army's Arabic spokesperson issued another notice instructing residents of buildings in two other towns to leave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strikes came a day after Israel and Lebanon sent civilian envoys to a committee overseeing a fragile ceasefire agreed a year ago that both sides have accused the other of breaking.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 15:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>War insurance costs spike for ship owners as Black Sea threats grow, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/war-insurance-costs-spike-ship-owners-black-sea-threats-grow-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/war-insurance-costs-spike-ship-owners-black-sea-threats-grow-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Saul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Dec 4 (Reuters) - War insurance costs for ships sailing to the Black Sea have spiked again, with insurers reviewing policies daily as the conflict in Ukraine spills into sea lanes, five shipping and insurance sources said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Black Sea is crucial for the shipment of grain, oil and oil products. Its waters are shared by Bulgaria, Georgia, Romania and Turkey, as well as Russia and Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 15:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel launches fresh strikes on south Lebanon after warnings</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-launches-fresh-strikes-south-lebanon-after-warnings</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-launches-fresh-strikes-south-lebanon-after-warnings</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli raids hit south Lebanon on Thursday as Israel's military said it was striking Hezbollah targets, a day after Lebanese and Israeli civilian representatives held their first direct talks in decades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a November 2024 ceasefire that was supposed to end more than a year of hostilities between Israel and the Iran-backed militant group, Israel has kept up strikes on Lebanon and has also maintained troops in five south Lebanon areas it deems strategic.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 15:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Eurovision members debate call to boycott Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-members-debate-call-boycott-israel-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-members-debate-call-boycott-israel-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Organisers of the Eurovision Song Contest -- the world's largest music event -- on Thursday began two days of debate about Israel's future participation, after mounting calls to exclude it, notably due to the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Members of the European Broadcasting Union (EBU) met behind closed doors and under tight security in Geneva, following threats of mass withdrawals from the annual show if Israel takes part next year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 14:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran invites Lebanon's foreign minister to discuss bilateral ties</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-invites-lebanons-foreign-minister-discuss-bilateral-ties</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iran-invites-lebanons-foreign-minister-discuss-bilateral-ties</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Iran's Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi invited Lebanon's Foreign Minister Youssef Raji to visit Iran in the near future to discuss bilateral ties, Iran's foreign ministry said on Thursday, amid a U.S.-backed roadmap in Lebanon to disarm the Iran-aligned Hezbollah group. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 13:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Microsoft faces complaint in EU over Israeli surveillance data</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/microsoft-faces-complaint-eu-over-israeli-surveillance-data</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/microsoft-faces-complaint-eu-over-israeli-surveillance-data</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Microsoft is facing a complaint in the European Union filed by a non-profit organisation alleging it illegally stored data on Palestinians used for Israeli military surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Irish Data Protection Commission (DPC) confirmed Thursday it had received the complaint against the US tech giant, saying it was "currently under assessment".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since Microsoft's European headquarters are located in Ireland, the DPC is the EU's lead data regulator for the company.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 13:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leader of Lithuanian government party found guilty of hatred against Jews</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/leader-lithuanian-government-party-found-guilty-hatred-against-jews</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/leader-lithuanian-government-party-found-guilty-hatred-against-jews</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Andrius Sytas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;VILNIUS, Dec 4 (Reuters) - A Lithuanian court found the leader of a junior party in the ruling coalition government on Thursday guilty of incitement to hatred against Jews and belittling the Holocaust in social media posts in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remigijus Zemaitaitis, founder of the populist Nemunas Dawn, was fined 5,000 euros ($5,835) for falsely accusing the Jewish people, as a group, of historical crimes, encouraging hostility and strengthening negative stereotypes, the court said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 13:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisian police arrest top opposition figure Nejib Chebbi to enforce 12-year jail term, his family says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/tunisian-police-arrest-top-opposition-figure-nejib-chebbi-enforce-12-year-jail</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/tunisian-police-arrest-top-opposition-figure-nejib-chebbi-enforce-12-year-jail</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TUNIS, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Tunisian police arrested on Thursday top opposition figure Nejib Chebbi, one of President Kais Saied’s fiercest opponents, to enforce a 12-year jail term on a conviction for conspiracy against state security, his family said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An appeals court last week handed jail terms of up to 45 years to dozens of opposition leaders including Chebbi, business figures and lawyers on charges of conspiracy to overthrow President Kais Saied, in what critics said was a sign of his increasingly authoritarian rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Eurovision bosses to consider if Israel should take part amid boycott threats</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-bosses-consider-if-israel-should-take-part-amid-boycott-threats</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-bosses-consider-if-israel-should-take-part-amid-boycott-threats</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Dec 4 (Reuters) - National broadcasters behind the Eurovision Song Contest meet on Thursday to discuss whether Israel should be barred from participating next year, amid threats by some to pull out over the Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting in Geneva marks a watershed moment for the competition which draws millions of viewers worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Spanish and others national broadcasters have threatened to boycott the event if Israel is included, citing the death count in Gaza, and accused it of not following rules meant to guard the contest's neutrality.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italy says Germany and other countries may be interested in GCAP jet programme</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/italy-says-germany-and-other-countries-may-be-interested-gcap-jet-programme</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/italy-says-germany-and-other-countries-may-be-interested-gcap-jet-programme</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ROME, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Italy's defence minister on Thursday said other countries, including Germany and Australia, may be interested in entering the GCAP fighter jet programme in the future, with requests also coming from Saudi Arabia and Canada.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The GCAP, which currently involves Italy, Britain and Japan, is an effort to build a next-generation fighter by 2035 and is being led by Mitsubishi Heavy Industries in Japan, BAE Systems in Britain and Leonardo in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 10:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq freezes funds of Hezbollah and Houthis, official gazette says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iraq-freezes-funds-hezbollah-and-houthis-official-gazette-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/iraq-freezes-funds-hezbollah-and-houthis-official-gazette-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Iraq will freeze the money of Iran-backed armed groups, including Lebanon's Hezbollah and Yemen's Houthis, the official gazette said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The move will likely be welcomed by Washington, which has long sought to reduce Iran's influence in Iraq and other countries in the Middle East where Tehran has allies. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 09:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel awaits return of last hostage remains from Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-awaits-return-last-hostage-remains-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-awaits-return-last-hostage-remains-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel awaited the return of the last hostage remains held by Palestinian militants in Gaza, as the military said on Thursday that those of a Thai national had been identified after they were handed over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the first phase of the US-brokered ceasefire between Israel and Hamas in Gaza, militants were due to return all 48 hostages they held captive, 20 of whom were still alive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All but the remains of Israeli Ran Gvili have since been handed over, though Israel has accused the Palestinian militants of dragging their feet on returning bodies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 09:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Eurovision members debate call to boycott Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-members-debate-call-boycott-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/eurovision-members-debate-call-boycott-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's participation in the Eurovision Song Contest will be debated at a two-day meeting of member broadcasters in Geneva starting Thursday, following calls to exclude the country over its Gaza war tactics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Countries including Iceland, Ireland, Spain and the Netherlands, have threatened in recent months to pull out of the 2026 contest if Israel takes part.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Others, including Belgium, Finland and Sweden, have also indicated they were considering a boycott over the situation in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 07:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>China to provide $100 million humanitarian aid for Gaza, Xi says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/china-provide-100-million-humanitarian-aid-gaza-xi-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/china-provide-100-million-humanitarian-aid-gaza-xi-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BEIJING, Dec 4 (Reuters) - China will provide $100 million in aid to the Palestinians to help alleviate the humanitarian crisis in Gaza and support reconstruction efforts, President Xi Jinping said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Xi was speaking at a joint press conference with French President Emmanuel Macron after their meeting in Beijing.     &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Ethan Wang and Joe Cash; Editing by Himani Sarkar)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 06:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey told Russia, Ukraine to keep energy infrastructure out of war, minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-told-russia-ukraine-keep-energy-infrastructure-out-war-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/turkey-told-russia-ukraine-keep-energy-infrastructure-out-war-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Can Sezer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Turkey is telling Russia, Ukraine, and all other parties to keep energy infrastructure out of their conflict and wants energy flows to continue uninterrupted, Energy Minister Alparslan Bayraktar said after a series of attacks off Turkey's Black Sea coast. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 06:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How an oil pipeline battle shows the US gaining sway in Iraq</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/how-oil-pipeline-battle-shows-us-gaining-sway-iraq</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/how-oil-pipeline-battle-shows-us-gaining-sway-iraq</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ahmed Rasheed, Maha El Dahan, Humeyra Pamuk and Anna Hirtenstein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD/WASHINGTON, Dec 4 (Reuters) - Iranian drones swept through the mountain air of northern Iraq's Kurdistan region in mid-July, homing in on their targets: oilfields run by Americans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fired by an Iranian-backed militia group within Iraq, likely in retaliation for U.S. strikes on Iran's nuclear sites weeks earlier, one struck the Sarsang field operated by HKN Energy, a company owned by the son of Texas billionaire Ross Perot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another hit a nearby field run by Dallas-based Hunt Oil.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 05:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel identifies body of returned hostage, remains of Israeli officer still in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-identifies-body-returned-hostage-remains-israeli-officer-still-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/12/israel-identifies-body-returned-hostage-remains-israeli-officer-still-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Dec 4 (Reuters) - Israel has identified the remains of the hostage it received from Hamas on Wednesday as Thai agricultural worker Sudthisak Rinthalak, the prime minister's office said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The body of Israeli police officer Ran Gvili, the last of the living and deceased hostages to be returned, is still in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The handover of the last hostages' bodies in Gaza would complete a key condition of the initial part of U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end the two-year Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 05:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>