<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Greece warns shipping fleet of risks after Black Sea drone attacks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-warns-shipping-fleet-risks-after-black-sea-drone-attacks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-warns-shipping-fleet-risks-after-black-sea-drone-attacks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Greece has warned its shipping fleet to review their security measures when sailing to Russian Black Sea ports after drone attacks on two Greek-operated tankers this week, according to shipping ministry advisories.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drones struck two oil tankers on Tuesday, including one chartered by U.S. oil major Chevron, as they sailed toward a Black Sea terminal on Russia's Black Sea coast.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 14:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians flee Kurdish-controlled area near Aleppo</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-flee-kurdish-controlled-area-near-aleppo</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-flee-kurdish-controlled-area-near-aleppo</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syrians began fleeing an area east of Aleppo city on Thursday after the army gave civilians a deadline to leave amid fears of an escalation in clashes with Kurdish forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is seeking to extend its authority across the country following the ouster of longtime leader Bashar al-Assad a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, government troops took full control of Aleppo city over the weekend after capturing two Kurdish-majority neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says it opposes military intervention in Iran, priority is avoiding destabilisation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-says-it-opposes-military-intervention-iran-priority-avoiding</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-says-it-opposes-military-intervention-iran-priority-avoiding</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Spicer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Turkey is opposed to any military intervention in Iran and its priority is to avoid destabilisation there, Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan said on Thursday, as Tehran continues its crackdown on protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Iran's leadership trying to quell the worst domestic unrest the Islamic Republic has ever faced, and with U.S. President Donald Trump's repeated threats to intervene on behalf of the protesters, Tehran has warned its neighbours including Turkey that it would hit American bases if Washington were to strike.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>European airlines continue to avoid Iran and Iraq despite airspace reopening</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/european-airlines-continue-avoid-iran-and-iraq-despite-airspace-reopening</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/european-airlines-continue-avoid-iran-and-iraq-despite-airspace-reopening</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joanna Plucinska&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 15 (Reuters) - European airlines like Wizz Air, Lufthansa and British Airways dodged Iraqi and Iranian airspace on Thursday, according to flight tracking websites, opting instead for routes over Afghanistan and central Asia in an effort to mitigate risks associated with the ongoing geopolitical turmoil in Iran and the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria's use of force against Kurdish-led SDF seems an option, Turkey says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-use-force-against-kurdish-led-sdf-seems-option-turkey-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-use-force-against-kurdish-led-sdf-seems-option-turkey-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Spicer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Turkey's foreign minister said on Thursday he hopes problems in neighbouring Syria can be resolved peacefully but the use of force by the government in Damascus could be an option after recent clashes with Kurdish fighters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Five days of fighting in the northern Syrian city of Aleppo last week killed at least 23 people, according to Syria's health ministry, while more than 150,000 fledthe two Kurdish-run pockets of the city.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran protests show bitter schism among exiled opposition factions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protests-show-bitter-schism-among-exiled-opposition-factions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protests-show-bitter-schism-among-exiled-opposition-factions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By John Irish&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Huge protests in Iran have galvanised exiled foes of the authorities but despite their hatred of the ruling clerics, a bitter schism dating to before the 1979 Islamic Revolution still afflicts the leading opposition factions. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That split, between monarchists supporting Reza Pahlavi, son of the ousted shah, and a more organised leftist group, the Mujahedin-e Khalq, has played out online and even in angry arguments in street protests in Europe and North America. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia pledges $500 million Yemen development after UAE withdrawal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabia-pledges-500-million-yemen-development-after-uae-withdrawal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabia-pledges-500-million-yemen-development-after-uae-withdrawal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;RIYADH, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia has announced a slew of development projects across southern Yemen worth about $500 million, many in areas long-held by the United Arab Emirates and allied separatistswho were routed in a Saudi-backed offensive this month.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey to deploy jets to Estonia, Romania under NATO air policing missions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-deploy-jets-estonia-romania-under-nato-air-policing-missions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-deploy-jets-estonia-romania-under-nato-air-policing-missions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Turkey plans to deploy fighter jets to Estonia and Romania as part of NATO's enhanced air policing missions, the defence ministry said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey plans to conduct a four-month deployment in Estonia between August and November 2026, followed by another rotation in Romania from December 2026 to March 2027, the ministry said in its weekly press briefing. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey has contributed significantly to NATO’s air policing operations aimed at protecting allied airspace during peacetime, the ministry added. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran vows to defend itself as Trump says will 'watch it and see'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-vows-defend-itself-trump-says-will-watch-it-and-see</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-vows-defend-itself-trump-says-will-watch-it-and-see</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran vowed on Thursday to defend itself against any foreign threat, after US President Donald Trump said he would "watch it and see" about military action over the crackdown on protesters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran's judiciary said a protester who the United States and rights groups feared faced imminent execution would not be sentenced to death, after Trump had warned of strikes should people arrested for demonstrating be killed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump sees Iranian crackdown easing, Tehran denies man to be executed</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-sees-iranian-crackdown-easing-tehran-denies-man-be-executed</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-sees-iranian-crackdown-easing-tehran-denies-man-be-executed</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/DUBAI, Jan 15 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said he had been told that killings in Iran’s crackdown on protests were easing and that he believed there was no current plan for large-scale executions, adopting a wait‑and‑see posture after earlier threatening intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian state media on Thursday reported that a 26-year-old man arrested during the protests in the city of Karaj would not be given the death sentence, after a rights group reported earlier this week that he was due to be executed on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Macron convenes emergency meeting to discuss Greenland, Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/macron-convenes-emergency-meeting-discuss-greenland-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/macron-convenes-emergency-meeting-discuss-greenland-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Jan 15 (Reuters) - President Emmanuel Macron convened an emergency defence cabinet in Paris on Thursday to discuss U.S. President Donald's Trump's stated intent to acquire Greenland and the forceful crackdown on nationwide protests in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an overnight message on X, Macron said a first group of French military personnel were already headed to Greenland to participate in an exercise organised by Denmark and Greenland, an overseas Danish territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crisis meeting, confirmed by a French official, was scheduled to begin at 0700 GMT. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan, Philippines sign new security pacts as regional tensions rise</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/japan-philippines-sign-new-security-pacts-regional-tensions-rise</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/japan-philippines-sign-new-security-pacts-regional-tensions-rise</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mikhail Flores&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MANILA, Jan 15 (Reuters) - The Philippines and Japan signed two defence pacts on Thursday, including a deal allowing their forces to exchange supplies and services, with both countries seeking to strengthen security cooperation in response to rising regional tensions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Acquisition and Cross-Servicing Agreement, designed to enable the swift provision of supplies and services between their militaries, comes months after a landmark Reciprocal Access Agreement between two of Washington's closest Asian allies took effect.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 05:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI-created Iran protest videos gain traction&lt;br /&gt;</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ai-created-iran-protest-videos-gain-traction</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ai-created-iran-protest-videos-gain-traction</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;AI-generated videos purportedly depicting protests in Iran have flooded the web, researchers said Wednesday, as social media users push hyper-realistic deepfakes to fill an information void amid the country's internet restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US disinformation watchdog NewsGuard said it identified seven AI-generated videos depicting the Iranian protests -- created by both pro- and anti-government actors -- that have collectively amassed some 3.5 million views across online platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 03:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Trump questions Reza Pahlavi's ability to garner support in Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-trump-questions-reza-pahlavis-ability-garner-support-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-trump-questions-reza-pahlavis-ability-garner-support-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steve Holland&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 14 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said on Wednesday that Iranian opposition figure Reza Pahlavi "seems very nice" but expressed uncertainty over whether Pahlavi would be able to muster support within Iran to eventually take over.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 01:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran minister says 'there is no plan for hanging' when asked about protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-minister-says-there-no-plan-hanging-when-asked-about-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-minister-says-there-no-plan-hanging-when-asked-about-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi said on Wednesday "there is no plan" by Iran to hang people, when asked about the anti-government protests in the Middle Eastern nation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"There is no plan for hanging," the foreign minister told Fox News in an interview on the "Special Report with Bret Baier" show. "Hanging is out of the question," he said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Norway-based Iran Human Rights Society, hangings are common in Iranian prisons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Kanishka Singh in Washington; Editing by Chris Reese)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 23:36:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says he has been told killings in Iran are stopping</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-has-been-told-killings-iran-are-stopping</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-has-been-told-killings-iran-are-stopping</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nandita Bose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 14 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump said on Wednesday he has been told that killings in Iran's crackdown on nationwide protests were subsiding and that he believes there is currently no plan for large-scale executions, even as tensions between Tehran and Washington remain high.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Asked who told him that the killings stopped, Trump described them as "very important sources on the other side."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 21:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US says Gaza truce plan entering phase two as governance body formed</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-says-gaza-truce-plan-entering-phase-two-governance-body-formed</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-says-gaza-truce-plan-entering-phase-two-governance-body-formed</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A US-backed plan to end the war in Gaza was moving into its second phase, Washington's top negotiator said Wednesday, as Palestinian factions agreed on the make-up of a post-war governing committee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump's envoy Steve Witkoff wrote on X that phase two of the US leader's 20-point plan would shift the Palestinian territory "from ceasefire to demilitarization, technocratic governance and reconstruction".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Phase one, launched in October, involved a ceasefire, a hostage-prisoner exchange, partial Israeli withdrawal and a surge of humanitarian aid.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 21:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italy urges its citizens to leave Iran because of security concerns</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/italy-urges-its-citizens-leave-iran-because-security-concerns</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/italy-urges-its-citizens-leave-iran-because-security-concerns</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ROME, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Italy has strongly renewed an appeal to its citizens to leave Iran because of the security situation in the country, the foreign ministry said in a statement on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are around 600 Italians in Iran, most of them in the Tehran area, it added.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Iran's leadership trying to quell the worst domestic unrest the Islamic Republic has ever faced, Tehran is seeking to deter U.S. President Donald Trump's repeated threats to intervene on behalf of anti-government protesters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 20:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israelis rally in support of Iranian protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israelis-rally-support-iranian-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israelis-rally-support-iranian-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Around 100 people rallied in a central Israeli city on Wednesday in support of Iranian protesters, as the Islamic republic is shaken by more than two weeks of anti-government demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demonstrators in Holon, a city near Tel Aviv home to a large Persian Jewish community, waved Israeli flags next to Iranian flags from before the Islamic revolution in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Be the voice of the Iranian people," a sign read in Hebrew and Persian.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 20:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ugandans, Iranians turn to Dorsey's messaging app Bitchat in web crackdowns</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ugandans-iranians-turn-dorseys-messaging-app-bitchat-web-crackdowns</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/ugandans-iranians-turn-dorseys-messaging-app-bitchat-web-crackdowns</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Harshita Mary Varghese, Jaspreet Singh and Aditya Soni&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 14 (Reuters) - A little-known offline messaging app launched by Twitter co-founder Jack Dorsey has emerged as a key lifeline for Ugandans cut off from the internet ahead of a contentious election that could extend President Yoweri Museveni's four-decade rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bitchat has surged to the top of Apple and Google app stores in the African country after clocking more than 28,000 downloads this year, according to research firm Apptopia. That marks a nearly fourfold increase over the previous two months combined.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 20:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>