<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Syrian security deploy in key Kurdish city under US-backed deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrian-security-deploy-key-kurdish-city-under-us-backed-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syrian-security-deploy-key-kurdish-city-under-us-backed-deal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Orhan Qereman, Khalil Ashawi and Feras Maqdisi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QAMISHLI, Syria, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Syrian government security forces entered the Kurdish-controlled northeastern city of Qamishli on Tuesday, security sources and witnesses said, implementing a U.S.-backed deal to bring Kurdish-run regions back under central government control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The accord, declared on Friday, staved off the risk of more conflict between Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa's government and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, which lost swathes of eastern and northern Syria to government troops in January.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US-Iran talks 'still scheduled' after drone shot down: White House</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-iran-talks-still-scheduled-after-drone-shot-down-white-house</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-iran-talks-still-scheduled-after-drone-shot-down-white-house</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The United States is still planning talks with Iranian officials this week, the White House said Tuesday, even after a US warplane shot down an Iranian drone that approached an American aircraft carrier in the Arabian Sea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I just spoke with special envoy (Steve) Witkoff, and these talks as of right now are still scheduled," Press Secretary Karoline Leavitt told reporters, adding that they were due to happen "later this week."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"President Trump is always wanting to pursue diplomacy first, but obviously it takes two to tango," Leavitt said outside the West Wing.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran demands changes in venue and scope of talks with US, source says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-demands-changes-venue-and-scope-talks-us-source-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-demands-changes-venue-and-scope-talks-us-source-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi, Humeyra Pamuk and Idrees Ali&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI/WASHINGTON, Feb 3 - Iran is demanding that talks with the U.S. this week be held in Oman not Turkey, and that the scope be narrowed to two-way talks on nuclear issues only, a regional source said on Tuesday, casting doubt on whether the meeting will go ahead as planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran's effort to change the venue and agenda for the talks, currently scheduled for Friday in Istanbul, came amid heightened tensions as the U.S. builds up forces in the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UAE pledges $500 million for Sudan aid as Washington gathers donors</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-pledges-500-million-sudan-aid-washington-gathers-donors</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uae-pledges-500-million-sudan-aid-washington-gathers-donors</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Simon Lewis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 3 - The United Arab Emirates on Tuesday pledged to donate $500 million to a U.N. fund for humanitarian aid for Sudan, amid a U.S. push to renew efforts towards a truce in the conflict that has devastated the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sudan has accused the UAE of arming the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) which have been fighting the Sudanese army in thecivil war that broke out in April 2023- a charge the UAE denies butU.N. expertsandU.S. lawmakershave found credible.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran seeks nuclear-only US talks, to drop Turkey as host: Source</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-seeks-nuclear-only-us-talks-drop-turkey-host-source</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iran-seeks-nuclear-only-us-talks-drop-turkey-host-source</guid><description>Iran’s push for a bilateral, nuclear-only format and a possible shift to Oman has frustrated mediators.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:46:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian boats approach US-flagged tanker in Strait of Hormuz, maritime sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-boats-approach-us-flagged-tanker-strait-hormuz-maritime-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-boats-approach-us-flagged-tanker-strait-hormuz-maritime-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 3 (Reuters) - A group of Iranian gunboats approached a U.S.-flagged tanker in the Strait of Hormuz north of Oman, maritime sources and a security consultancy said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Iranian boats ordered the tanker, the Stena Imperative, to stop its engine and prepare to be boarded before it could speed up and continue its voyage, maritime risk management group Vanguard said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vessel did not enter Iranian internal territorial waters and was escorted by a U.S. warship, the maritime risk management group said. An American official confirmed it was U.S. flagged. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey determined to take relations with Saudi Arabia to higher level, Erdogan tells crown prince</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-determined-take-relations-saudi-arabia-higher-level-erdogan-tells-crown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/turkey-determined-take-relations-saudi-arabia-higher-level-erdogan-tells-crown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Turkey's President Tayyip Erdogan met Saudi Arabia's Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman in Riyadh on Tuesday and told him Turkey was determined to take relations to a higher level in areas including renewable energy and defence industry, Erdogan's office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Erdogan also told the Saudi crown prince that Turkey's support for stability in Syria would continue, and Turkey would work in cooperation with Saudi Arabia to rebuild Syria, the Turkish presidency said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Huseyin HayatseverEditing by Peter Graff)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq's Maliki says he would welcome decision to replace him as PM candidate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iraqs-maliki-says-he-would-welcome-decision-replace-him-pm-candidate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iraqs-maliki-says-he-would-welcome-decision-replace-him-pm-candidate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 3 (Reuters) - Iraq's former Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki, nominated by a powerful alliance of Shi'ite political parties to return to the premiership, said on Tuesday that he would welcome a decision to replace his candidacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On January 27, U.S. President Donald Trump said that if Maliki, who served as prime minister for most of the U.S.-led war in Iraq, were chosen to return to the post, Washington would no longer help Iraq, a major oil producer and close U.S. ally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Menna Alaa El-Din and Ahmed RasheedEditing by Peter Graff)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:01:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-US shoots down Iranian drone approaching aircraft carrier, official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-us-shoots-down-iranian-drone-approaching-aircraft-carrier-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/exclusive-us-shoots-down-iranian-drone-approaching-aircraft-carrier-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 3 (Reuters)  - The U.S. military shot down on Tuesday an Iranian drone that approached the Abraham Lincoln aircraft carrier in the Arabian Sea, a U.S. official told Reuters on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Iranian Shahed-139 drone was flying towards the carrier and was shot down by a F-35 U.S. fighter jet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Idrees Ali and Phil Stewart; Editing by Chizu Nomiyama )&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian women describe 'journey of horror’ crossing back into Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-women-describe-journey-horror-crossing-back-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/palestinian-women-describe-journey-horror-crossing-back-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Mahmoud Issa&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/GAZA, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Palestinian women among the few people let back into Gaza after Israel's delayed reopening of the Rafah crossing under last year's ceasefire have described being blindfolded, handcuffed and interrogated by Israeli forces as they tried to get home. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their journey from Egypt on Monday through the frontier post and across the "yellow line" zone controlled by Israel and an allied Palestinian militia group, involved lengthy delays and the confiscation of gifts including toys, one of the women said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US F-35 downs Iran drone as IRGC boats target tanker near Hormuz</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-f-35-downs-iran-drone-irgc-boats-target-tanker-near-hormuz</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-f-35-downs-iran-drone-irgc-boats-target-tanker-near-hormuz</guid><description>The US military accused Iran of "unnecessary aggression" after shooting down an Iranian drone near the USS Abraham Lincoln in the Arabian Sea and IRGC vessels approached a US-flagged oil tanker in the Strait of Hormuz in run-ins ahead of US-Iran talks later this week.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:11:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria govt forces enter Qamishli under agreement with Kurds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-govt-forces-enter-qamishli-under-agreement-kurds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/syria-govt-forces-enter-qamishli-under-agreement-kurds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syrian government forces entered the Kurdish-majority city of Qamishli on Tuesday as part of a deal agreed last week to gradually integrate the Kurds' forces and institutions into the state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their arrival in the stronghold of the Kurds' de facto autonomous administration came after government security personnel entered the mixed Kurdish-Arab city of Hasakeh and the countryside around the Kurdish town of Kobane the day before.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Putin and Saudi crown prince discuss work of OPEC+, Kremlin says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-putin-and-saudi-crown-prince-discuss-work-opec-kremlin-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russias-putin-and-saudi-crown-prince-discuss-work-opec-kremlin-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Russian President Vladimir Putin held a phone call with Saudi Arabia's Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman, the Kremlin said on Tuesday, saying they had agreed to deepen cooperation in the political, economic, trade and humanitarian spheres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Kremlin statement, the two leaders also discussed the progress of their joint work within the OPEC+ format and efforts to maintain stability on global energy markets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saudi state news agency SPA said the prince and Putin discussed bilateral relations and regional and international developments.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudanese army says it has broken siege of famine-stricken Kadugli</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-army-says-it-has-broken-siege-famine-stricken-kadugli</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/sudanese-army-says-it-has-broken-siege-famine-stricken-kadugli</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nafisa Eltahir and Khalid Abdelaziz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feb 3 - The Sudanese army said it broke a years-long siege on the city of Kadugli on Tuesday, potentially providing tens of thousands of people a reprieve from famine and signaling a shift in the war's momentum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conflict between the Sudanese army and the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) has displaced millions, drawn in regional powers and caused a vast humanitarian crisis since it broke out in April 2023.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff meets Netanyahu as Israel warns against potential Iran deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</guid><description>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and Israel’s security chiefs briefed US envoy Steve Witkoff on the country’s concerns ahead of Friday’s US-Iran talks.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:18:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff meets Netanyahu as Israel warns against potential Iran deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</guid><description>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and Israel’s security chiefs briefed US envoy Steve Witkoff on the country’s concerns ahead of Friday’s US-Iran talks.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:18:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff meets Netanyahu as Israel warns against potential Iran deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</guid><description>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and Israel’s security chiefs briefed US envoy Steve Witkoff on the country’s concerns ahead of Friday’s US-Iran talks.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:18:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff meets Netanyahu as Israel warns against potential Iran deal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/witkoff-meets-netanyahu-israel-warns-against-potential-iran-deal</guid><description>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and Israel’s security chiefs briefed US envoy Steve Witkoff on the country’s concerns ahead of Friday’s US-Iran talks.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:18:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel's Netanyahu to meet US envoy Witkoff amid revived Iran nuclear talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-meet-us-envoy-witkoff-amid-revived-iran-nuclear-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israels-netanyahu-meet-us-envoy-witkoff-amid-revived-iran-nuclear-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emily Rose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Feb 3 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu was scheduled to meet U.S. Special Envoy Steve Witkoff on Tuesday amid efforts to revive diplomacy over a long-running dispute about Iran's nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting was scheduled for 1430 GMT and would include the director of Israel's Mossad spy agency David Barnea, Israeli Defense Minister Israel Katz, and Israeli Military Chief of Staff Eyal Zamir, two Israeli officials told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's drone deployment to border raises stakes in Sudan's civil war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/egypts-drone-deployment-border-raises-stakes-sudans-civil-war-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/egypts-drone-deployment-border-raises-stakes-sudans-civil-war-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt; (Refiles to correct spelling of Janes in 22nd paragraph)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Dziadosz, Marine Delrue  and Maria Paula Laguna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Feb 2 (Reuters) - The deployment of a powerful model of Turkish combat drone to a remote airstrip on Egypt’s southwestern border signals a sharp escalation in Sudan’s civil war, suggesting one of its largest neighbours is being drawn deeper into the fray, more than a dozen officials and regional experts say.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>