<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>UN says Houthi seizure of telecom gear threatens Yemen aid</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-says-houthi-seizure-telecom-gear-threatens-yemen-aid</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-says-houthi-seizure-telecom-gear-threatens-yemen-aid</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 30 (Reuters) - Yemen's Iran‑aligned Houthi paramilitary has removed critical telecommunications equipment belonging to the U.N., the global body said on Friday, warning that further restrictions on its work would fuel a worsening humanitarian crisis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Houthis, who control areas in north Yemen, entered at least six unstaffed U.N. offices in the capital Sanaa and took telecommunications equipment and several vehicles to an unknown location, the U.N.'s Resident and Humanitarian Coordinator for Yemen Julien Harneis said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 15:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US issues fresh Iran-related sanctions, Treasury Dept website says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-issues-fresh-iran-related-sanctions-treasury-dept-website-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-issues-fresh-iran-related-sanctions-treasury-dept-website-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 30 (Reuters) - The United States on Friday issued fresh Iran and counter terrorism-related sanctions, targeting seven Iranian nationals and at least one entity, according to the U.S. Treasury Department's website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Katharine Jackson and Daphne Psaledakis)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 15:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisia's famed blue-and-white village threatened after record rains</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/tunisias-famed-blue-and-white-village-threatened-after-record-rains</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/tunisias-famed-blue-and-white-village-threatened-after-record-rains</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Perched on a hill overlooking Carthage, Tunisia's famed blue-and-white village of Sidi Bou Said now faces the threat of landslides, after record rainfall tore through parts of its slopes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, Tunisia saw its heaviest downpour in more than 70 years. The storm killed at least five people, with others still missing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Narrow streets of this village north of Tunis -- famed for its pink bougainvillea and studded wooden doors -- were cut off by fallen trees, rocks and thick clay. Even more worryingly for residents, parts of the hillside have broken loose.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 15:30:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'He probably would've survived': Iran targeting hospitals in crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/he-probably-wouldve-survived-iran-targeting-hospitals-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/he-probably-wouldve-survived-iran-targeting-hospitals-crackdown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hospitals are no longer places of safety as Iran's crackdown on anti-government protests impacts all aspects of life, rights groups say, with authorities arresting wounded protesters and even the medics who treat them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Activists accuse security forces of killing thousands of people and wounding more by directly firing on protests, often with birdshot that can leave metal pellets lodged in the body until hygienically extracted by a professional.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 15:30:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MSF says it will not share staff details demanded by Israel to access Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/msf-says-it-will-not-share-staff-details-demanded-israel-access-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/msf-says-it-will-not-share-staff-details-demanded-israel-access-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 30 (Reuters) - Medical charity Medecins Sans Frontieres said on Friday it will not submit lists of staff demanded by Israel to maintain access to Gaza and the West Bank, saying it had not been able to obtain assurances over the safety of its teams. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MSF, which supports and helps staff hospitals in Gaza, is one of 37 international organisations that Israel ordered this month to stop work in the Palestinian territories unless they meet new rules including providing employee details.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 14:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran prepared for 'fair' talks with US but not on defence capabilities, Araqchi says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-prepared-fair-talks-us-not-defence-capabilities-araqchi-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-prepared-fair-talks-us-not-defence-capabilities-araqchi-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Jan 30 (Reuters) - Iran is prepared for the resumption of talks with the United States, but they should be fair and not include Iran's defence capabilities, Iran's chief diplomat said on Friday, as regional powers work to prevent military conflict between the two foes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump said on Thursday he planned to speak with Iran, even as the U.S. sent another warship to the Middle East and the Pentagon chief said the military would be ready to carry out whatever the president decided.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 13:01:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia halts strikes on Kyiv until Sunday at Trump's request, Zelenskiy to reciprocate</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-halts-strikes-kyiv-until-sunday-trumps-request-zelenskiy-reciprocate</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-halts-strikes-kyiv-until-sunday-trumps-request-zelenskiy-reciprocate</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olena Harmash&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KYIV, Jan 30 (Reuters) - Russia has agreed to a request from U.S. President Donald Trump to halt airstrikes on Kyiv until February 1 amid harsh winter temperatures, and Ukraine said it was ready to reciprocate as Washington pushes for a diplomatic solution to end the war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 13:01:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians decry soaring electricity prices</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-decry-soaring-electricity-prices</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-decry-soaring-electricity-prices</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When Hani Massalkhi went to pay his electricity bill in Damascus this week, he discovered that, under the new tariffs, the amount due was higher than his monthly income.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Massalkhi, a retired agricultural engineer who lives on a $70-a-month pension, left without paying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"My bill used to vary between 15,000 and 20,000 pounds (less than $2). Now, it has surpassed 800,000 pounds", or $72, he told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In October, Syria's energy ministry hiked prices by up to 6,000 percent, sending shockwaves through a population already reeling from more than 13 years of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 13:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurds, Damascus step back from brink as SDF signs fresh deal with Syrian government</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurds-damascus-step-back-brink-sdf-signs-fresh-deal-syrian-government</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurds-damascus-step-back-brink-sdf-signs-fresh-deal-syrian-government</guid><description>After intense US-led diplomacy, Syria’s interim government and the Kurdish-led SDF agreed to a ceasefire and phased integration, averting all-out conflict.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 12:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran to label EU armed forces as 'terrorists' over Guards blacklist</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-label-eu-armed-forces-terrorists-over-guards-blacklist</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-label-eu-armed-forces-terrorists-over-guards-blacklist</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 30 (Reuters) - Iran plans to designate the armed forces of European Union countries that have blacklisted the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps as "terrorists", according to a post by top Iranian security official Ali Larijani on X. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Therefore, the consequences will fall on the European countries that undertook such an action," Larijani said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai Newsroom;Editing by Alison Williams)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 12:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Explainer-How does Iran's system of power work?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-how-does-irans-system-power-work</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/explainer-how-does-irans-system-power-work</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 30 (Reuters) - The United States is considering new military strikes against  the Islamic Republic of Iran over its deadly suppression of protests this month.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complexities of Iran's ruling system, the ideological nature of its support base, and the power of its Revolutionary Guards make it hard to predict its resilience or vulnerability in the face of external attack, or what might come next.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following explains how the system operates and who the main figures are in today's Iran:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WHY DOES IRAN HAVE A 'SUPREME LEADER'?&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 12:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza’s Rafah crossing with Egypt to reopen on Sunday, Israel says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/gazas-rafah-crossing-egypt-reopen-sunday-israel-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/gazas-rafah-crossing-egypt-reopen-sunday-israel-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 30 (Reuters) - Israel will reopen the Rafah border crossing on Sunday for people to travel between Gaza and Egypt, the Israeli government agency that coordinates civilian policy in Gaza, COGAT, said on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The return of residents from Egypt to the Gaza Strip will be permitted, in coordination with Egypt, for residents who left Gaza during the course of the war only, and only after prior security clearance by Israel," COGAT said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 12:01:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel military reported to accept death toll of around 70,000 in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-military-reported-accept-death-toll-around-70000-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-military-reported-accept-death-toll-around-70000-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 30 (Reuters) - Israel's military has accepted that around 70,000 Palestinians were killed during the war in Gaza, after having earlier cast doubt on death tolls reported by the enclave's health officials, Israeli media reported on Friday citing senior military officials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has long accepted death tolls recorded by health authorities in Gaza as accurate. Israel has cast doubt on the figures, arguing that the health ministry in the enclave was run by Hamas and could not be trusted.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel ups Iran intel sharing with US, expects Trump to strike within 'weeks'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</guid><description>Israel is making vast amounts of intelligence available to the United States in preparation for a potential attack on Iran.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel ups Iran intel sharing with US, expects Trump to strike within 'weeks'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</guid><description>Israel is making vast amounts of intelligence available to the United States in preparation for a potential attack on Iran.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel ups Iran intel sharing with US, expects Trump to strike within 'weeks'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</guid><description>Israel is making vast amounts of intelligence available to the United States in preparation for a potential attack on Iran.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel ups Iran intel sharing with US, expects Trump to strike within 'weeks'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-ups-iran-intel-sharing-us-expects-trump-strike-within-weeks</guid><description>Israel is making vast amounts of intelligence available to the United States in preparation for a potential attack on Iran.</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran says defence capabilities 'never' up for negotiation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-defence-capabilities-never-negotiation</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-says-defence-capabilities-never-negotiation</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's top diplomat said Friday that his country's missile and defence capabilities would "never" be on the negotiating table, as US President Donald Trump appeared to cool on threats of a strike after a military build-up in the region. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tehran and Washington have been trading warnings since Trump first threatened to intervene over a deadly crackdown on recent protests and sent a naval fleet to the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kremlin says Trump asked Putin to halt strikes on Kyiv until February 1</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kremlin-says-trump-asked-putin-halt-strikes-kyiv-until-february-1</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kremlin-says-trump-asked-putin-halt-strikes-kyiv-until-february-1</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 30 (Reuters) - The Kremlin said on Friday that Russian President Vladimir Putin had received a personal request from his U.S. counterpart, Donald Trump to halt strikes on Kyiv until February 1 in order to create a favourable environment for peace negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Asked about the request and Russia's response, Kremlin spokesman Dmitry Peskov declined further comment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ukraine has said it will reciprocate if Russia forgoes strikes on the country's energy infrastructure amid a period of bitterly cold weather.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 10:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudanese paramilitary force abducting children in Darfur, witnesses say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudanese-paramilitary-force-abducting-children-darfur-witnesses-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudanese-paramilitary-force-abducting-children-darfur-witnesses-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Reade Levinson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 30 (Reuters) - Paramilitary fighters kidnapped children during their takeover of the Sudanese city of al-Fashir in October and in other attacks in the Darfur region over the course of Sudan's civil war, in some cases killing their parents first, witnesses say.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The descriptions, based on Reuters interviews with more than two dozen witnesses, included four accounts of fighters from the paramilitary Rapid Support Forces (RSF) telling families the children would be used as slaves, to herd animals.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 10:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>