<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Netanyahu submits pardon request in Israel corruption cases</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-submits-pardon-request-israel-corruption-cases</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-submits-pardon-request-israel-corruption-cases</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, on trial facing corruption charges, announced Sunday he had submitted a pardon request, saying the long-running cases were tearing the country apart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump wrote to Israeli President Isaac Herzog earlier this month, asking him to pardon Netanyahu, who has repeatedly denied wrongdoing in the ongoing court cases.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The trial in my case has been ongoing for nearly six years, and is expected to continue for many more years," Netanyahu said in a video statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 12:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netanyahu officially asks Israeli president for pardon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-officially-asks-israeli-president-pardon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/netanyahu-officially-asks-israeli-president-pardon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nov 30 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu has submitted an official request for his pardon to Israeli President Isaac Herzog, the Israeli president's office said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The Office of the President is aware that this is an extraordinary request which carries with it significant implications. After receiving all of the relevant opinions, the President will responsibly and sincerely consider the request," Herzog's office said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was no immediate comment from the prime minister's office.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After call for Christian unity, pope leaves Turkey for Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-call-christian-unity-pope-leaves-turkey-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/after-call-christian-unity-pope-leaves-turkey-lebanon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo XIV headed to Lebanon on Sunday with a message of peace for the crisis-hit nation after wrapping up a four-day trip to Turkey's tiny Christian community that focused on unity within the Church. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ending the first part of his maiden overseas tour since being elected leader of the world's 1.4 billion Catholics, Leo boarded the papal plane which left Istanbul for Beirut, where he was expected to arrive around 3:45 pm (1345 GMT). &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 10:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Operations restart at Iraq's Khor Mor field, transporting gas to power stations, ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/operations-restart-iraqs-khor-mor-field-transporting-gas-power-stations-ministry</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/operations-restart-iraqs-khor-mor-field-transporting-gas-power-stations-ministry</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD, Nov 30 (Reuters) - Operations restarted at Iraq's Khor Mor gas field, with the transmission of gas to power stations starting at 2:00 a.m. Sunday (2300 GMT Saturday), the Kurdish regional government's electricity ministry announced, days after a drone attack halted production and led to extensive power cuts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Khor Mor gas field, one of the largest in the Kurdistan region, provides supplies for regional power generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 07:01:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope Leo taking peace message to Lebanon, target of Israeli strikes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-taking-peace-message-lebanon-target-israeli-strikes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-leo-taking-peace-message-lebanon-target-israeli-strikes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Nov 30 (Reuters) - Pope Leo travels to Lebanon on Sunday, where he is expected to appeal for peace in a country that is a continued target of Israeli air strikes, on the second and final leg of his first overseas trip as leader of the Catholic Church.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first U.S. pope will arrive from Turkey, where he has been visiting for four days and warned that humanity's future was at risk because of the world's unusual number of bloody conflicts and condemned violence in the name of religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:36:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Dinosaur tartare' and holograms: Dubai AI chef sparks awe and ire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dinosaur-tartare-and-holograms-dubai-ai-chef-sparks-awe-and-ire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/dinosaur-tartare-and-holograms-dubai-ai-chef-sparks-awe-and-ire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Dubai restaurant has opened that prides itself on having the world's "first AI chef", the latest ostentatious dive into new technology in a city obsessed with being on the cutting edge of the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Emirati city has become increasingly known for its growing culinary scene, with thousands of restaurants on offer from luxurious Michelin-starred eateries to greasy spoons serving up bona fide street food from across the Middle East and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 03:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OPEC+ likely to maintain current output levels</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/opec-likely-maintain-current-output-levels</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/opec-likely-maintain-current-output-levels</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ministers of the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries and allied nations (OPEC+) are expected to keep current output levels unchanged when they meet for online meetings on Sunday, analysts told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biannual ministerial meeting comes as uncertainty remains over how oil prices will develop in the near future, with traders looking for signs that indicate progress in ongoing negotiations on resolving the conflict in Ukraine, which could lead to the return of Russian crude to markets.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 02:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope to wrap up Turkey trip before heading to Lebanon</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-wrap-turkey-trip-heading-lebanon</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-wrap-turkey-trip-heading-lebanon</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pope Leo XIV wraps up a four-day trip to Turkey Sunday after a warm welcome by its tiny Christian community, before heading to Lebanon with a message of peace for the crisis-mired nation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On his first overseas trip since being elected leader of the world's 1.4 billion Catholics, Leo met President Recep Tayyip Erdogan before travelling to Iznik for a celebration marking 1,700 years since the First Council of Nicaea, one of the early Church's most important gatherings. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 02:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US State Department stops processing visas for Afghan allies</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-state-department-stops-processing-visas-afghan-allies</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/us-state-department-stops-processing-visas-afghan-allies</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Humeyra Pamuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Nov 29 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump’s administration has ordered its diplomats worldwide to stop processing visas for Afghan nationals, according to a State Department cable seen by Reuters, effectively suspending the special immigration program for Afghans who helped the United States during its 20-year-long occupation of their home country.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 20:36:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza death toll tops 70,000, health ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-death-toll-tops-70000-health-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/gaza-death-toll-tops-70000-health-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Nov 29 (Reuters) - The number of people confirmed killed in Israel's offensive in  the Gaza Strip has passed the 70,000 mark, the enclave's health ministry said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A total of 301 people have been added to the toll since Thursday, taking it to 70,100, the ministry added. Two died in recent Israeli strikes, the rest were identified from remains buried for some time in the rubble, according to the statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 17:36:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prominent activist arrested as hundreds protest in Tunisia</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/prominent-activist-arrested-hundreds-protest-tunisia</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/prominent-activist-arrested-hundreds-protest-tunisia</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A prominent Tunisian activist was arrested on Saturday as hundreds protested in the capital against the curtailing of freedoms, an AFP journalist and lawyers said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protest in Tunis came a day after a mass appeal trial saw some 40 public figures, mainly critics of President Kais Saied, handed hefty sentences over plotting against the state.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Poet and political figure Chaima Issa, who was handed a 20-year sentence during the trial on Friday, was arrested during the rally, lawyers and witnesses said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 17:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tunisian police arrest opposition figure Chaima Issa to enforce 20-year jail term</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tunisian-police-arrest-opposition-figure-chaima-issa-enforce-20-year-jail-term</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tunisian-police-arrest-opposition-figure-chaima-issa-enforce-20-year-jail-term</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Tarek Amara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TUNIS, Nov 29 (Reuters) - Tunisian police arrested prominent opposition figure Chaima Issa at a protest in the capital Tunis on Saturday to enforce a 20-year prison sentence, her lawyers said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An appeals court handed jail terms of up to 45 years to opposition leaders, business leaders and lawyers on Friday on charges of conspiracy to overthrow President Kais Saied, in what critics said was a sign of increasingly authoritarian rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 17:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria's Sharaa in Aleppo a year after fall of second city</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrias-sharaa-aleppo-year-after-fall-second-city</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/syrias-sharaa-aleppo-year-after-fall-second-city</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed al-Sharaa visited Syria's northern city of Aleppo Saturday as the country marks a year since a lightning Islamist-led offensive that eventually toppled longtime ruler Bashar al-Assad last December.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Islamist alliance, led by Sharaa, entered Aleppo on November 29 last year and swiftly took control of Syria's second city.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 16:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Piastri wins Qatar F1 sprint, title favourite Norris third</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/piastri-wins-qatar-f1-sprint-title-favourite-norris-third</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/piastri-wins-qatar-f1-sprint-title-favourite-norris-third</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Pole-sitter Oscar Piastri won Saturday's sprint race at the Qatar Grand Prix with his McLaren teammate and title favourite Lando Norris third.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norris now leads Piastri by 22 points and the Briton can claim his maiden Formula One crown if results go his way in Sunday's penultimate grand prix.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other title contender Max Verstappen finished fourth for Red Bull to drop 25 points behind Norris with a maximum 50 points remaining from Sunday's race and the season-closer in Abu Dhabi next weekend.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 15:30:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Death toll from Gaza war surpasses 70,000: health ministry</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/death-toll-gaza-war-surpasses-70000-health-ministry</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/death-toll-gaza-war-surpasses-70000-health-ministry</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The health ministry in Hamas-run Gaza on Saturday said more than 70,000 people have been killed since the war between Israel and Hamas erupted more than two years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The milestone comes as a fragile US-brokered ceasefire largely holds, but with both sides accusing the other of violating the terms of the deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Gaza's health ministry said the death toll from the war had risen to 70,100.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministry said that since the ceasefire came into effect on October 10, 354 Palestinians had been killed by Israeli fire.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 15:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ultra-Orthodox military conscription row reignites in Israel</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ultra-orthodox-military-conscription-row-reignites-israel</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/ultra-orthodox-military-conscription-row-reignites-israel</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A new draft law on conscripting ultra-Orthodox Jews, whose support is crucial for Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's government, has sparked uproar in Israel, with the opposition denouncing it as a special privilege for "draft-dodgers".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under a ruling established at the time of Israel's creation in 1948, men who devote themselves full-time to studying sacred Jewish texts are given a de facto pass from mandatory military service.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 09:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pope removes shoes but doesn't pray on visit to Istanbul's Blue Mosque</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-removes-shoes-doesnt-pray-visit-istanbuls-blue-mosque</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/pope-removes-shoes-doesnt-pray-visit-istanbuls-blue-mosque</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joshua McElwee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Nov 29 (Reuters) - Pope Leo visited Istanbul's famed Blue Mosque on Saturday, removing his shoes in a sign of respect but not appearing to pray in his first visit as leader of the Catholic Church to a Muslim place of worship during his four-day visit to Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first U.S. pope bowed slightly before entering the mosque and was led on a tour of the expansive complex, able to hold 10,000 worshippers, by its imam and the mufti of Istanbul.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 08:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The tiring task of repairing Gaza's tattered banknotes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tiring-task-repairing-gazas-tattered-banknotes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/tiring-task-repairing-gazas-tattered-banknotes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;With a pot of glue, a blade and a keen eye, Manal al-Saadani repairs tattered banknotes -- a necessity in the Gaza Strip, where the cash in circulation is wearing out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For every revived note she gives back to a customer, they give her a few coins in return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Gaza remained blockaded for much of the Israel-Hamas war since October 2023, basic supplies were depleted, including banknotes, with no new ones supplied to its banks.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 03:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Blasts hit sanctioned tankers off Turkey's coast, rescues underway</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/blasts-hit-sanctioned-tankers-turkeys-coast-rescues-underway</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/blasts-hit-sanctioned-tankers-turkeys-coast-rescues-underway</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Can Sezer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL (Reuters) -Blasts rocked two tankers from Russia's shadow fleet in the Black Sea near Turkey's Bosphorus strait on Friday, causing fires on the vessels, and rescue operations were launched for those on board, Turkish authorities and sources said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 274-meter-long tanker Kairos suffered an explosion and caught fire in the Black Sea while en route from Egypt to Russia, Turkey's Transport Ministry said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 21:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Advantage Ogier as Evans' title hopes punctured at Rally Saudi Arabia</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/advantage-ogier-evans-title-hopes-punctured-rally-saudi-arabia</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2025/11/advantage-ogier-evans-title-hopes-punctured-rally-saudi-arabia</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Elfyn Evans' hopes of claiming his first World Rally Championship title suffered a major blow on Friday when the Welshman lost valuable time with a puncture in Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He had to change a rear-left tyre which cost him around two minutes, giving the title advantage to his Toyota teammate Sebastien Ogier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We had a puncture alarm right at the beginning," said Evans.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It was going down quite slow but it was so far to go that we had to make a decision to change it where we could. Not ideal."&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 18:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>