<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Iranian parliament warns of jihad if Supreme Leader is attacked, ISNA</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-parliament-warns-jihad-if-supreme-leader-attacked-isna</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-parliament-warns-jihad-if-supreme-leader-attacked-isna</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Any attack on Iranian Supreme Leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei would trigger a declaration of jihad, or holy war, the Iranian Students News Agency quoted Iran's national security parliamentary commission as saying on Tuesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tensions between Iran and the United States have grown following a severe crackdown of protests across Iran, which U.S. President Donald trump warned could lead to a response from Washington. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Macron tells Davos of a 'shift towards a world without rules'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/macron-tells-davos-shift-towards-world-without-rules</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/macron-tells-davos-shift-towards-world-without-rules</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DAVOS, Switzerland, Jan 20 (Reuters) - The world is experiencing a shift away from rules and international law, French President Emmanuel Macron told the World Economic Forum in Davos on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It's ... a shift towards a world without rules, where international law is trampled underfoot and where the only law that seems to matter is that of the strongest," Macron said, adding that what he called "imperial ambitions" were resurfacing..&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Michel Rose and Alessandro Parodi, editing by Richard Lough)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi state TV says King Salman chairs cabinet days after leaving hospital</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-state-tv-says-king-salman-chairs-cabinet-days-after-leaving-hospital</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-state-tv-says-king-salman-chairs-cabinet-days-after-leaving-hospital</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia's 90-year-old King Salman chaired in person a cabinet meeting on Tuesday, Saudi state TV reported, days after he left hospital where he was undergoing medical tests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;King Salman, whose country is the world's largest oil exporter and a major U.S. ally in the Middle East, went to a hospital in Riyadh on Friday for medical tests and left on the same day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saudi TV published a video dated January 20, showing the king chairing the cabinet and reading files with his ministers. Reuters could not independently verify the video.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Blast kills seven at Chinese-run restaurant in Afghan capital</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/blast-kills-seven-chinese-run-restaurant-afghan-capital</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/blast-kills-seven-chinese-run-restaurant-afghan-capital</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mohammad Yunus Yawar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KABUL, Jan 19 (Reuters) - Militant group Islamic State claimed an explosion that officials said killed a Chinese national and six Afghans, while injuring several more as it tore through a Chinese-run restaurant in a heavily guarded part of Afghanistan's capital.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Monday's blast took place in the commercial Shahr-e-Naw area that is home to offices, shopping complexes and embassies, police spokesperson Khalid Zadran said. It is considered one of the safest neighbourhoods in the city.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exclusive-Some European states rethink presence at US-backed Gaza base, diplomats say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-some-european-states-rethink-presence-us-backed-gaza-base-diplomats-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/exclusive-some-european-states-rethink-presence-us-backed-gaza-base-diplomats-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Cornwell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Several European countries are considering whether to stop sending personnel to a U.S. military-led coordination centre for Gaza, saying it has failed to increase aid flows to the war-shattered enclave or achieve political change, diplomats said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Trump's 'Board of Peace'?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/what-trumps-board-peace-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/what-trumps-board-peace-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump's government has asked countries to pay $1 billion for a permanent spot on his "Board of Peace" aimed at resolving conflicts, according to its charter seen by AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The board was originally conceived to oversee the rebuilding of Gaza, but the charter does not appear to limit its role to the occupied Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;- What will it do? -&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace will be chaired by Trump, according to its founding charter.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey's Erdogan will soon decide whether to join Trump's Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-will-soon-decide-whether-join-trumps-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkeys-erdogan-will-soon-decide-whether-join-trumps-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Turkish President Tayyip Erdogan will soon decide whether to join U.S. President Donald Trump's Board of Peace initiative after having received an invitation, Turkey's foreign minister said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We have received an invitation. Our President is being invited as a founding member, on behalf of Turkey (and) will likely make his decision on this matter very soon," Hakan Fidan said in a televised interview with state media.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Reporting by Tuvan Gumrukcu; Editing by Jonathan Spicer)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US-led coalition negotiating Al-Hol camp handover, Syrian sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-led-coalition-negotiating-al-hol-camp-handover-syrian-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-led-coalition-negotiating-al-hol-camp-handover-syrian-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 20 (Reuters) - The U.S.-led coalition against the Islamic State was negotiating a handover of the Al-Hol camp, which houses IS-linked civilians, to Syrian authorities, three Syrian sources familiar with the matter said on Tuesday. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the sources, a Syrian official, said the talks were focused on a smooth transition of control from Kurdish security forces who had been holding the camp, to avoid any security risks or detainees fleeing. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Suleiman Al-Khalidi, Mahmoud Hasano and Khalil Ashawi; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US invited Israel to join board of peace, Israeli minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-invited-israel-join-board-peace-israeli-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-invited-israel-join-board-peace-israeli-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 20 (Reuters) - Israel foreign minister Gideon Saar said on Tuesday that Israel was invited by the United States to join the board of peace initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Omri Taasan; Editing by Andrew Heavens)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greece will cooperate with Israel on anti-drone systems, cybersecurity, Greek minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-will-cooperate-israel-anti-drone-systems-cybersecurity-greek-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-will-cooperate-israel-anti-drone-systems-cybersecurity-greek-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Greece will cooperate with Israel on anti-drone systems and cybersecurity, Greek Defence Minister Nikos Dendias said on Tuesday after meeting his Israeli counterpart in Athens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With strong economic and diplomatic ties, Greece and Israel operate an air training center on Greek territory and have held joint military drills in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Elefterios Papadimas; Writing by Angeliki Koutantou; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel orders Gaza families to move in first forced evacuation since ceasefire</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-orders-gaza-families-move-first-forced-evacuation-ceasefire</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-orders-gaza-families-move-first-forced-evacuation-ceasefire</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Israeli forces have ordered dozens of Palestinian families in the southern Gaza Strip to leave their homes in the first forced evacuation since October's ceasefire, as residents and Hamas said on Tuesday the military was expanding the area under its control.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Residents of Bani Suhaila, east of Khan Younis, said the leaflets were dropped on Monday on families living in tent encampments in the Al-Reqeb neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Talks between Damascus, Kurdish-led forces 'collapse': Kurdish official to AFP</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/talks-between-damascus-kurdish-led-forces-collapse-kurdish-official-afp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/talks-between-damascus-kurdish-led-forces-collapse-kurdish-official-afp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Negotiations have collapsed between the Syrian president and the chief of the country's Kurdish-led forces, a Kurdish official told AFP, as the army deployed reinforcements to flashpoint areas in the north.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed al-Sharaa and Mazloum Abdi, who heads the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces (SDF), were meeting to discuss a ceasefire agreement that included integrating the Kurds' administration into the state.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN rights council to hold emergency session on Iran, document shows</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-council-hold-emergency-session-iran-document-shows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/un-rights-council-hold-emergency-session-iran-document-shows</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin and Emma Farge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Jan 20 (Reuters) - The U.N. Human Rights Council will hold an emergency session on Iran in the coming days, with proponents aiming to discuss "alarming violence" used against protesters, a document showed on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An Iranian official said authorities have verified at least 5,000 deaths in the protests which are the biggest demonstrations since 2022, prompting U.N. rights chief Volker Turk to condemn the violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:01:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel begins demolitions at UNRWA headquarters in east Jerusalem</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-begins-demolitions-unrwa-headquarters-east-jerusalem</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-begins-demolitions-unrwa-headquarters-east-jerusalem</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israeli bulldozers began demolitions at the headquarters of the UN agency for Palestinian refugees in east Jerusalem on Tuesday, in what the organisation called an "unprecedented attack".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNRWA spokesman Jonathan Fowler said in a statement to AFP that Israeli forces "stormed into" the compound shortly after 7 am (0500 GMT) and ejected security guards from the site, before bulldozers entered and began demolishing buildings.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's Sisi to meet Trump on the sidelines of Davos, presidency says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-sisi-meet-trump-sidelines-davos-presidency-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-sisi-meet-trump-sidelines-davos-presidency-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Egypt's President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi will meet U.S President Donald Trump on the sidelines of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Egypt's presidency said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will be the first meeting between the two leaders since the U.S announced it was launching the second phase of its plan to end the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sisi and Trump met in the Red Sea resort of Sharm el-Sheikh in October during a summit convened by Egypt to sign a ceasefire deal aimed at ending the war.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel demolishes buildings in UN Palestinian agency's East Jerusalem compound</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-demolishes-buildings-un-palestinian-agencys-east-jerusalem-compound</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-demolishes-buildings-un-palestinian-agencys-east-jerusalem-compound</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Pesha Magid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Israel demolished structures inside the U.N. Palestinian refugee agency's East Jerusalem compound on Tuesday after seizing the site last year, in an act condemned by the agency as a violation of international law. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Surrounded by Israeli forces, bulldozers razed several large buildings and other smaller structures inside the United Nations Relief and Works Agency's compound, where dozens of agency staff once worked. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump threatens 200% tariffs on French wines to get Macron on Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-threatens-200-tariffs-french-wines-get-macron-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-threatens-200-tariffs-french-wines-get-macron-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nandita Bose and Bo Erickson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/PARIS, Jan 20 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump threatened to hit French wines and champagnes with 200% tariffs in an apparent effort to cajole French President Emmanuel Macron into joining his Board of Peace initiative aimed at resolving global conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump's initiative, which would start by addressing Gaza and then expand to deal with other conflicts, raises questions about the role of the United Nations and a source close to Macron said the French president intended to decline the invitation to join.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Police, pro-Kurd protesters clash at Turkey border with Syria</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/police-pro-kurd-protesters-clash-turkey-border-syria</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/police-pro-kurd-protesters-clash-turkey-border-syria</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Clashes erupted on Turkey's border with Syria Tuesday between police and pro-Kurdish protesters angered by a Syrian military offensive targeting Kurds, an AFP correspondent said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The violence broke out in the border town of Nusaybin, just across from the northern Syrian town of Qamishli, at a protest called by the pro-Kurdish DEM, Turkey's third-largest party.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 1,000 demonstrators marched through the town towards the border, ending in a confrontation with police, who fired tear gas and used water cannon to disperse them.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Pakistan's 'combat tested' jets boost weapons sales</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-pakistans-combat-tested-jets-boost-weapons-sales</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-pakistans-combat-tested-jets-boost-weapons-sales</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saad Sayeed and Ariba Shahid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Pakistan's defence manufacturing industry is running red hot since its jets, drones and missiles earned the coveted 'combat tested' tag in a conflict with India last year, attracting a slew of interested buyers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Islamabad has held talks with 13 countries, six to eight of which are in an advanced stage, for deals involving JF-17 jets made jointly with China as well as training aircraft, drones, and weapons systems, said three Pakistani sources who have knowledge of defence sales.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Canada's Carney aims to lead new global trading order less reliant on US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-canadas-carney-aims-lead-new-global-trading-order-less-reliant-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-canadas-carney-aims-lead-new-global-trading-order-less-reliant-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Promit Mukherjee, Andrew Mills and Federico Maccioni&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;OTTAWA/DOHA/DUBAI, Jan 20 (Reuters) - Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney is trying to foster a new global trading order by working more closely with China and inking smaller trade deals, but faces constraints from Canada's still overwhelming economic dependency on the United States.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>