<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Russia slams US strike threats, warns against interference in Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-slams-us-strike-threats-warns-against-interference-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-slams-us-strike-threats-warns-against-interference-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Russia on Tuesday condemned what it described as "subversive external interference" in Iran's internal politics and said  U.S. threats of new military strikes against the country were "categorically unacceptable."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Those who plan to use externally inspired unrest as a pretext for repeating the aggression against Iran committed in June 2025 must be aware of the disastrous consequences of such actions for the situation in the Middle East and global international security," the Russian Foreign Ministry said in a statement.      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 15:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK condemns Iran leadership for 'brutal killing' of protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uk-condemns-iran-leadership-brutal-killing-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uk-condemns-iran-leadership-brutal-killing-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 13 (Reuters) - British foreign minister Yvette Cooper on Tuesday condemned the Iranian leadership for what she described as the "horrendous and brutal killing" of protesters, saying Britain had summoned the Iranian ambassador to underline the gravity of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The United Kingdom condemns in the strongest of terms the horrendous and brutal killing of Iranian protesters, and we demand that the Iranian authorities respect the fundamental rights and freedoms of their citizens," Cooper told parliament.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 15:01:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Aide to Cypriot president quits after uproar over online video</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/aide-cypriot-president-quits-after-uproar-over-online-video</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/aide-cypriot-president-quits-after-uproar-over-online-video</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;NICOSIA, Jan 13 (Reuters) - A senior aide to the Cypriot president has quit over a video that opposition politicians allege shows high-level corruption on the east Mediterranean island but which the authorities dismiss as an attempt to discredit the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charalambos Charalambous, who ran President Nikos Christodoulides' private office and was one of two people at the presidency overseeing a fast-track process for investments in Cyprus, denied wrongdoing but resigned on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 15:01:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump tells Iranians to keep protesting, says 'help is on its way'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-tells-iranians-keep-protesting-says-help-its-way</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-tells-iranians-keep-protesting-says-help-its-way</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 13 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump on Tuesday told Iranians to keep protesting and said help was on the way, but did not give details.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Iranian Patriots, KEEP PROTESTING - TAKE OVER YOUR INSTITUTIONS!!!... HELP IS ON ITS WAY," Trump said in a post on Truth Social, adding he had canceled all meetings with Iranian Officials until the "senseless killing" of protesters stopped.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Susan Heavey, Bhargav Acharya and Doina Chiacu;)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 15:01:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lebanon charges ex-central bank governor Salameh over alleged $44.8 million embezzlement</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/lebanon-charges-ex-central-bank-governor-salameh-over-alleged-448-million</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/lebanon-charges-ex-central-bank-governor-salameh-over-alleged-448-million</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Laila Bassam&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BEIRUT, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Lebanese prosecutors have indicted former central bank governor Riad Salameh and two lawyers on charges including embezzlement of public funds, forgery and illicit enrichment, judicial authorities said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salameh, who headed the Lebanese Central Bank for three decades, was detained for about 13 months over alleged financial crimes committed during his tenure and was released in September after paying record bail of more than $14 million. He remains in Lebanon and is subject to a travel ban.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria's Kurds protest Aleppo violence as fears of wider conflict grow</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-kurds-protest-aleppo-violence-fears-wider-conflict-grow</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-kurds-protest-aleppo-violence-fears-wider-conflict-grow</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;QAMISHLI, Syria, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Several thousand people marched under the rain in northeast Syria on Tuesday to protest the expulsion of Kurdish fighters from the city of Aleppo the previous week after days of deadly clashes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The violence in Aleppo has deepened one of the main faultlines in Syria, where President Ahmed al-Sharaa's promise to unify the country under one leadership after 14 years of war has faced resistance from Kurdish forces wary of his Islamist-led government.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:36:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian goes on trial in France ahead of possible prisoner swap</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-goes-trial-france-ahead-possible-prisoner-swap</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-goes-trial-france-ahead-possible-prisoner-swap</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;An Iranian went on trial in France Tuesday accused of promoting "terrorism" on social media in a case linked to a possible prisoner swap with two French citizens held by the Islamic republic for over three-and-a-half years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mahdieh Esfandiari, a 39-year-old Iranian, was arrested in France in February on charges of promoting and inciting "terrorism" on social media over comments she is said to have made, including on Palestinian militant group Hamas attacking Israel on October 7, 2023, according to French authorities. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran to press capital crime charges for 'rioters': prosecutors</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-press-capital-crime-charges-rioters-prosecutors</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-press-capital-crime-charges-rioters-prosecutors</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian authorities will press capital crime charges against some suspects arrested over recent demonstrations, prosecutors said Tuesday, as alarm grows that the Islamic republic could extensively use the death penalty to crack down on the protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The office of the Tehran prosecutor said in a statement quoted by state television that an unspecified number would be charged with "moharebeh", or "waging war against God", a sharia law term which is a capital crime in Iran and used widely in the past in death penalty cases.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria Druze leader Hijri calls for independent entity, says country ‘heading towards partition’</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</guid><description>Controversial Druze spiritual leader Hikmat al-Hijri, in Syria’s southern province of Suwayda, praised Israel as the only party he said intervened to stop the killing of Druze during a wave of unrest last summer.</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:11:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria Druze leader Hijri calls for independent entity, says country ‘heading towards partition’</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</guid><description>Controversial Druze spiritual leader Hikmat al-Hijri, in Syria’s southern province of Suwayda, praised Israel as the only party he said intervened to stop the killing of Druze during a wave of unrest last summer.</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:11:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria Druze leader Hijri calls for independent entity, says country ‘heading towards partition’</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</guid><description>Controversial Druze spiritual leader Hikmat al-Hijri, in Syria’s southern province of Suwayda, praised Israel as the only party he said intervened to stop the killing of Druze during a wave of unrest last summer.</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:11:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria Druze leader Hijri calls for independent entity, says country ‘heading towards partition’</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syria-druze-leader-hijri-calls-independent-entity-says-country-heading-towards</guid><description>Controversial Druze spiritual leader Hikmat al-Hijri, in Syria’s southern province of Suwayda, praised Israel as the only party he said intervened to stop the killing of Druze during a wave of unrest last summer.</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:11:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Somali regions reject Mogadishu's move to cut ties with UAE</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/somali-regions-reject-mogadishus-move-cut-ties-uae</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/somali-regions-reject-mogadishus-move-cut-ties-uae</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Giulia Paravicini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NAIROBI, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Three self-governing regions in Somalia that have close relations with the United Arab Emirates have dismissed a decision this week by the central government to sever ties with the UAE, a longterm sponsor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Monday Somalia annulled all agreements with the UAE, including in the field of security, accusing the Gulf country, which has trained and funded Somalia's army and invested in its ports, of undermining Somalia's national sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas to elect first leader since Sinwar killed by Israel, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/hamas-elect-first-leader-sinwar-killed-israel-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/hamas-elect-first-leader-sinwar-killed-israel-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Hamas is expected to elect a new leader this month, two sources in the group told Reuters, filling the role left vacant since Israel killed Yahya Sinwar in 2024 despite concerns that a successor could suffer the same fate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khalil Al-Hayya and Khaled Meshaal are seen as frontrunners for the helm at a vital moment for the militant Islamist group, battered by two years of war ignited by its October 7, 2023 attack on Israel and facing international demands to disarm.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran ex-empress urges security forces to join protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-ex-empress-urges-security-forces-join-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-ex-empress-urges-security-forces-join-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The former empress of Iran, widow of the shah deposed by the Islamic revolution, on Tuesday urged the Iranian security forces to support protests shaking the clerical leadership that ousted her husband.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Farah Pahlavi, 87, echoing calls made by her son the former crown prince Reza Pahlavi, said she believed "light will triumph over darkness" despite a crackdown by authorities that activists fear has left hundreds dead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 13:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU to 'swiftly' propose further sanctions on Iran, von der Leyen says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-swiftly-propose-further-sanctions-iran-von-der-leyen-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-swiftly-propose-further-sanctions-iran-von-der-leyen-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Jan 13 (Reuters) - The EU will "swiftly" propose further sanctions on those responsible for the repression of demonstrations in Iran, European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The rising number of casualties in Iran is horrifying. I unequivocally condemn the excessive use of force and continued restriction of freedom, " von der Leyen said on social media platform X.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Further sanctions on those responsible for the repression will be swiftly proposed."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Six dead as Gaza’s displaced struggle to hold ground in torrential rain</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/six-dead-gazas-displaced-struggle-hold-ground-torrential-rain</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/six-dead-gazas-displaced-struggle-hold-ground-torrential-rain</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Dawoud Abu Elkas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/GAZA, Jan 13 (Reuters) - A rainstorm swept across the Gaza Strip on Tuesday, flooding hundreds of tents, collapsing homes sheltering families displaced by two years of war and killing at least six people, local health officials said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medics said five people, including two women and a girl, died when homes collapsed near Gaza City’s beach, while a one-year-old boy died of extreme cold in a tent in Deir Al-Balah in central Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:36:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sudan 'lost all sources of revenue' in the war: finance minister to AFP</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudan-lost-all-sources-revenue-war-finance-minister-afp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/sudan-lost-all-sources-revenue-war-finance-minister-afp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Widespread destruction, massive military spending and plummeting oil and gold revenues have left Sudan's economy in "very difficult times", army-aligned finance minister Gibril Ibrahim said, nearly three years into the army's war with rival paramilitary forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with AFP from his office in Port Sudan, Ibrahim said the government is eyeing deals for Red Sea ports and private investment to help rebuild infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Why Iran’s clerical regime still holds as protests rage</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-why-irans-clerical-regime-still-holds-protests-rage</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/analysis-why-irans-clerical-regime-still-holds-protests-rage</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 13 (Reuters) - Despite Iran's nationwide protests and years of external pressure, there are as yet no signs of fracture in the Islamic Republic's security elite that could bring an end to one of the world's most resilient regimes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adding to the stress on Iran's clerical rulers, U.S. President Donald Trump has repeatedly threatened military action over Tehran's severe crackdown on the protests, which follow an Israeli and U.S. bombing campaign last year against Iran's nuclear program and key officials.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel assesses Trump may opt for Iran strike despite protest crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-assesses-trump-may-opt-iran-strike-despite-protest-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-assesses-trump-may-opt-iran-strike-despite-protest-crackdown</guid><description>The prevailing assessment in Israel is that US President Trump will opt to strike the Tehran government in order to show the protesters that the United States has not abandoned them.</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:06:16 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>