<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Trump says US will give UN money to make it stronger, more viable</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-us-will-give-un-money-make-it-stronger-more-viable</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-us-will-give-un-money-make-it-stronger-more-viable</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - The United States will give the United Nations money to strengthen it and help make it viable, President Donald Trump told the opening meeting of his Board of Peace on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. is the biggest contributor to the U.N. budget, but under the Trump administration it has refused to make mandatory payments to regular and peacekeeping budgets, and slashed voluntary funding to U.N. agencies with their own budgets.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 16:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says US needs to make meaningful deal with Iran, cites good talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-us-needs-make-meaningful-deal-iran-cites-good-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-us-needs-make-meaningful-deal-iran-cites-good-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump said on Thursday that the United States had to make a meaningful deal with Iran, citing good talks with the Middle Eastern country. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Good talks are being had. It's proven to be, over the years, not easy to make a meaningful deal with Iran. We have to make a meaningful deal, otherwise bad things happen," Trump told the first meeting of his Board of Peace in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says allies have contributed over $7 billion to Gaza relief</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-allies-have-contributed-over-7-billion-gaza-relief</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-says-allies-have-contributed-over-7-billion-gaza-relief</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said on Thursday that various U.S. allies have contributed over $7 billion to relief efforts in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to the initial meeting of the Board of Peace, which Trump created, the U.S. president said that it looks like Palestinian militant group Hamas will disarm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Trevor Hunnicutt and Gram Slattery; Editing by Lisa Shumaker)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France says surprised by European Commission presence at Board of Peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-says-surprised-european-commission-presence-board-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/france-says-surprised-european-commission-presence-board-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Feb 19 (Reuters) - France said on Thursday it was surprised that the European Commission had sent a commissioner to the Board of Peace in Washington saying it did not have the mandate to represent member states, its foreign ministry spokesperson said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pascal Confavreux said as far as Paris was concerned, the Board of Peace needed to recentre to focus on Gaza in line with a United Nations Security Council resolution and that until that ambiguity was lifted, France would not take part.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:36:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump touts pledges of troops, billions for Gaza at Board of Peace summit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</guid><description>As the board meets for the first time, questions hang over Gaza’s ceasefire, which calls for the&amp;nbsp;disarmament of Hamas and the withdrawal of Israeli troops.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:33:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump touts pledges of troops, billions for Gaza at Board of Peace summit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</guid><description>As the board meets for the first time, questions hang over Gaza’s ceasefire, which calls for the&amp;nbsp;disarmament of Hamas and the withdrawal of Israeli troops.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:33:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump touts pledges of troops, billions for Gaza at Board of Peace summit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</guid><description>As the board meets for the first time, questions hang over Gaza’s ceasefire, which calls for the&amp;nbsp;disarmament of Hamas and the withdrawal of Israeli troops.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:33:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump touts pledges of troops, billions for Gaza at Board of Peace summit</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-touts-pledges-troops-billions-gaza-board-peace-summit</guid><description>As the board meets for the first time, questions hang over Gaza’s ceasefire, which calls for the&amp;nbsp;disarmament of Hamas and the withdrawal of Israeli troops.</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:33:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New Gaza administration committee starts police recruitment drive</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-gaza-administration-committee-starts-police-recruitment-drive</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/new-gaza-administration-committee-starts-police-recruitment-drive</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Pesha Magid and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/CAIRO, Feb 19 (Reuters) - A U.S.-backed Palestinian committee established to take over the civil administration of Gaza opened applications for a police force for the strip on Thursday, ahead of the inaugural meeting of President Donald Trump's Board of Peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump is expected to announce a multi-billion-dollar reconstruction plan for Gaza and detail plans for a U.N.-authorized stabilization force for the Palestinian enclave at the meeting in Washington. Establishing security in Gaza is one of many formidable hurdles.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US and Israel issue dire warnings to Iran alongside US military buildup</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-and-israel-issue-dire-warnings-iran-alongside-us-military-buildup</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-and-israel-issue-dire-warnings-iran-alongside-us-military-buildup</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump said on Thursday Iran must make a "meaningful deal" in its negotiations with Washington in the next 10 days or else "bad things happen", as he deployed warships, fighter jets and other military hardware in the region.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It's proven to be over the years not easy to make a meaningful deal with Iran. We have to make a meaningful deal otherwise bad things happen," Trump told the inaugural meeting of the "Board of Peace", his initiative to secure stability in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>MSF will keep operating in Gaza 'as long as we can': mission head</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/msf-will-keep-operating-gaza-long-we-can-mission-head</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/msf-will-keep-operating-gaza-long-we-can-mission-head</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The head of Doctors Without Borders in the Palestinian territories told AFP the charity would continue working in Gaza for as long as possible, following an Israeli decision to end its activities there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In early February, Israel announced it was terminating all the activities in Gaza by the medical charity, known by its French acronym MSF, after it failed to provide a list of its Palestinian staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MSF has slammed the move, which takes effect on March 1, as a "pretext" to obstruct aid.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia warns of escalating Iran tensions amid U.S. military build up</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-warns-escalating-iran-tensions-amid-us-military-build</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-warns-escalating-iran-tensions-amid-us-military-build</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Russia warned against an "unprecedented escalation of tension" around Iran on Thursday and urged restraint amid a U.S. military build-up in the region that a senior American official said should be complete by mid-March. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. threats to bomb Iran, with the two sides far apart in talks on Tehran's nuclear programme, have pushed up oil prices and a Russian corvette on Thursday joined planned Iranian naval drills in the Gulf of Oman, a vital sea route for global energy. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN says Israeli actions raise 'ethnic cleansing' fears in West Bank, Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-says-israeli-actions-raise-ethnic-cleansing-fears-west-bank-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/un-says-israeli-actions-raise-ethnic-cleansing-fears-west-bank-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's increased attacks and forcible transfers of Palestinians "raise concerns over ethnic cleansing" in the Gaza Strip and West Bank, the United Nations said Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cumulative impact of Israel's military conduct during the war in Gaza and blockade of the territory, has inflicted living conditions "increasingly incompatible with Palestinians' continued existence as a group in Gaza", said the UN human rights office.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia urges restraint as US builds up military assets near Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-urges-restraint-us-builds-military-assets-near-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/russia-urges-restraint-us-builds-military-assets-near-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Russia said on Thursday that it was seeing an unprecedented escalation of tension around Iran as the United States moved military assets into the Middle East, and the Kremlin urged both Tehran and "other parties" to exercise prudence and restraint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. has deployed warships near Iran, while also holding talks with Tehran on limiting its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli forces and Hamas committed atrocity crimes in Gaza, UN report says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-forces-and-hamas-committed-atrocity-crimes-gaza-un-report-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-forces-and-hamas-committed-atrocity-crimes-gaza-un-report-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Olivia Le Poidevin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GENEVA, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Israeli forces, Hamas and other Palestinian armed groups have both committed serious violations of international humanitarian law in Gaza and carried out atrocity crimes, a U.N. report published on Thursday said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intensified Israeli attacks and the forcible transfer of Palestinians appeared aimed at a permanent demographic shift in Gaza "raising concerns over ethnic cleansing," the report by the U.N. human rights office said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PKK militant group source says Turkish approval of peace roadmap is important step</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pkk-militant-group-source-says-turkish-approval-peace-roadmap-important-step</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pkk-militant-group-source-says-turkish-approval-peace-roadmap-important-step</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD, Feb 19 (Reuters) - A Turkish parliamentary commission's approval of a report setting out a roadmap for legal reforms alongside the disbandment of the Kurdistan Workers Party (PKK) militant group is an important step and the beginning of a fundamental change in Turkish policy, a PKK source told Reuters on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The commission voted overwhelmingly on Wednesday to approve the report, advancing a peace process designed to end decades of conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Facing US warnings, Iran defends right to nuclear enrichment</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/facing-us-warnings-iran-defends-right-nuclear-enrichment</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/facing-us-warnings-iran-defends-right-nuclear-enrichment</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's atomic energy chief on Thursday said "no country can deprive Iran of the right" to nuclear enrichment, following fresh US warning that there were "many reasons" to strike the Islamic republic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two foes recently resumed indirect talks, after US President Donald Trump repeatedly threatened military action against Iran, at first over a deadly crackdown on protesters last month then more recently over its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>British couple held in Iran sentenced to 10 years</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/british-couple-held-iran-sentenced-10-years</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/british-couple-held-iran-sentenced-10-years</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A British couple detained in Iran since January 2025 have been sentenced to 10 years in jail for espionage, their family announced on Thursday, triggering condemnation from the UK government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lindsay and Craig Foreman, both in their 50s, were arrested while travelling through the country on an around-the-world motorcycle journey, according to relatives, and have consistently denied Tehran's spying claims.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 09:30:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK condemns 10-year sentence for British couple in Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uk-condemns-10-year-sentence-british-couple-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/uk-condemns-10-year-sentence-british-couple-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Feb 19 (Reuters) - British foreign minister Yvette Cooper on Thursday condemned as "totally unjustifiable" the 10-year sentence given to a British couple in Iran for spying, saying the government would continue to press for their release.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Craig and Lindsay Foreman had been charged with espionage after Iran accused them of gathering information in several parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We will pursue this case relentlessly with the Iranian government until we see Craig and Lindsay Foreman safely returned to the UK and reunited with their family," Cooper said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 08:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hamas tightens grip in Gaza as Trump pushes peace plan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hamas-tightens-grip-gaza-trump-pushes-peace-plan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hamas-tightens-grip-gaza-trump-pushes-peace-plan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nidal al-Mughrabi and Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAIRO/JERUSALEM, Feb 19 (Reuters) - Hamas is cementing its hold over Gaza by placing loyalists in key government roles, collecting taxes and paying salaries, according to an Israeli military assessment seen by Reuters and sources in the Palestinian enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hamas’ continuing influence over key Gaza power structures has fuelled widespread scepticism about the prospects of U.S. President Donald Trump’s peace plan, which requires the militant group to give up its weapons in exchange for an Israeli military withdrawal from the territory.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 06:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>