<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Iran rounds up thousands in mass arrest campaign after crushing unrest, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-rounds-thousands-mass-arrest-campaign-after-crushing-unrest-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-rounds-thousands-mass-arrest-campaign-after-crushing-unrest-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Plainclothes Iranian security forces have rounded up thousands of people in a campaign of mass arrests and intimidation to deter further protests after crushing the bloodiest unrest since the 1979 Islamic Revolution, sources told Reuters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 15:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Afghanistan launches $100 million food security programme as crisis deepens</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/afghanistan-launches-100-million-food-security-programme-crisis-deepens</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/afghanistan-launches-100-million-food-security-programme-crisis-deepens</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Mohammad Yunus Yawar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KABUL, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Afghanistan will roll out a $100 million food security project, the United Nations said on Thursday, as it contends with a worsening hunger crisis driven by mass deportations of Afghans from neighbouring states, foreign aid cuts and economic crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan's humanitarian situation is deteriorating sharply, with millions pushed into hunger by the loss of remittances, limited job opportunities and a sharp reduction in international assistance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 14:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia is ready to evacuate its staff from Iran's Bushehr nuclear plant if necessary, TASS reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-ready-evacuate-its-staff-irans-bushehr-nuclear-plant-if-necessary-tass</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-ready-evacuate-its-staff-irans-bushehr-nuclear-plant-if-necessary-tass</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Russia is ready to evacuate its staff from Iran's Bushehr nuclear power plant if necessary, Alexei Likhachev, the head of Russia's state nuclear corporation, was cited as saying on Thursday by the state news agency TASS.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Vladimir Putin said last year that hundreds of Russians were working at the facility, Iran's only operating nuclear power plant, which Moscow built for Iran. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More nuclear facilities are currently being built at the Bushehr site by Russia. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 13:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's IRGC: the feared 'Pasdaran' set for EU terror listing</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-irgc-feared-pasdaran-set-eu-terror-listing</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-irgc-feared-pasdaran-set-eu-terror-listing</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps is the ideological army of the Islamic republic tasked with protecting the revolution from external and domestic threats but is accused by the West of militant activity abroad and serial rights violations at home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The EU is expected on Thursday to agree to list the IRGC as a terrorist organisation, which would match similar classification enacted by the United States, Canada and Australia&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 12:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran vows 'crushing response', EU targets Revolutionary Guards</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-vows-crushing-response-eu-targets-revolutionary-guards</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-vows-crushing-response-eu-targets-revolutionary-guards</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran on Thursday vowed a "crushing response" to any attack after US President Donald Trump warned time was running out for a nuclear deal, and as the European Union looked to declare the Revolutionary Guards a terrorist organisation. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foes Washington and Tehran have exchanged sharp warnings since a protest wave in Iran led Trump to threaten military action over a violent crackdown, while the Islamic republic blamed the United States for fuelling what it deemed "riots".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 12:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Putin tells UAE leader he wants to discuss Iran tensions with him</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russias-putin-tells-uae-leader-he-wants-discuss-iran-tensions-him</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russias-putin-tells-uae-leader-he-wants-discuss-iran-tensions-him</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Russian President Vladimir Putin on Thursday told his UAE counterpart Mohammed bin Zayed Al Nahyan that Russia was closely monitoring the situation in Iran and wanted to discuss it with him in Kremlin talks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Putin made the comment at the start of talks with the UAE president whose country has recently hosted peace talks between Russia and Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 12:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli fire kills two in Gaza, as truce deal moves to next phase</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-two-gaza-truce-deal-moves-next-phase</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-fire-kills-two-gaza-truce-deal-moves-next-phase</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Israeli fire killed at least two Palestinians in the Gaza Strip, health officials said, in the latest incident of violence, as Hamas and Israel braced to implement the second phase of the U.S.-brokered Gaza ceasefire deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medics said two men were killed by Israeli forces in eastern Khan Younis, in an area adjacent to where the army operates. The Israeli military didn't make an immediate comment. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gaza health ministry said Israeli fire has killed at least 490 people since the truce began in October in the war-shattered enclave.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 12:01:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU ministers approve new Iran sanctions in response to crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-ministers-approve-new-iran-sanctions-response-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-ministers-approve-new-iran-sanctions-response-crackdown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Jan 29 (Reuters) - European Union foreign ministers adopted new Iran sanctions on Thursday targeting individuals and entities involved in a violent crackdown on protesters and the country's support to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministers are also expected to reach a political agreement to include Iran's Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps (IRGC) on the bloc's list of terrorist organisations, putting the group in a category similar to the Islamic State andal Qaeda and marking a symbolic shift in Europe's approach to Iran's leadership. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 11:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia urges US-Iran talks, warns against use of force</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-urges-us-iran-talks-warns-against-use-force</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-urges-us-iran-talks-warns-against-use-force</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Russia said on Thursday that there was still room for negotiation between Iran and the United States and warned that any use of force against Tehran would have dangerous consequences and cause chaos throughout the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kremlin spokesman Dmitry Peskov was commenting a day after U.S. President Donald Trump urged Iran to come to the table and make a deal on nuclear weapons or face a possible U.S. attack. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 11:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey to offer mediation on US-Iran tensions, weighs border measures</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-offer-mediation-us-iran-tensions-weighs-border-measures</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-offer-mediation-us-iran-tensions-weighs-border-measures</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Turkey will offer to mediate between Washington and Tehran during a visit by Iran's foreign minister on Friday, officials said, as Ankara considers reinforcing security along its border should the dispute escalate. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Friday's visit by Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araghchi comes after US President Donald Trump threatened a military strike on Iran over its deadly protest crackdown earlier this month. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A US naval strike group arrived in Middle East waters on Monday with Trump warning it was "ready, willing and able" to hit Iran "if necessary". &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 11:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran's foreign minister to visit Turkey for talks on tensions with US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-foreign-minister-visit-turkey-talks-tensions-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/irans-foreign-minister-visit-turkey-talks-tensions-us</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi will visit Turkey on Friday for talks with his counterpart Hakan Fidan on the recent developments in Iran and tensions with the United States, a Turkish Foreign Ministry source said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump urged Iran on Wednesday to come to the table and make a deal on nuclear weapons or the next U.S. attack would be far worse. Trump has sent an "armada" to the Middle East and warned Tehran against killing anti-government protesters or restarting its nuclear programme.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany's Merz calls for stronger NATO within Europe, but wants to maintain US ties</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germanys-merz-calls-stronger-nato-within-europe-wants-maintain-us-ties</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germanys-merz-calls-stronger-nato-within-europe-wants-maintain-us-ties</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Germany's Chancellor Friedrich Merz on Thursday called for a stronger NATO within Europe but said that it should also always extend the hand of cooperation to the United States. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaking to the German parliament, Merz also said that Europe will not be cowed by tariff threats any longer. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Sarah Marsh and Matthias Williams, Editing by Friederike Heine)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 09:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel parliament gives initial approval for 2026 budget, averting snap election for now</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-parliament-gives-initial-approval-2026-budget-averting-snap-election-now</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-parliament-gives-initial-approval-2026-budget-averting-snap-election-now</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Steven Scheer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 29 (Reuters) - Israel's parliament gave initial approval to the 2026 state budget draft on Thursday, handing Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu a temporary political reprieve by averting the immediate prospect of an early election.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers voted 62-55 in favor of the spending plan, which totals 662 billion shekels ($214.43 billion), excluding debt servicing, and sets a budget deficit ceiling of 3.9% of gross domestic product this year.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 08:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU expected to put Iran Guards on 'terrorist list'</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-expected-put-iran-guards-terrorist-list</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eu-expected-put-iran-guards-terrorist-list</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;EU foreign ministers are expected to agree Thursday to put Iran's Revolutionary Guards on the bloc's "terrorist list" after a deadly crackdown on mass protests, the EU's foreign policy chief said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"If you act as a terrorist, you should also be treated as terrorists," top diplomat Kaja Kallas told journalists ahead of the ministers' meeting in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She said the step puts the Revolutionary Guards on the same level as jihadist groups such as Al-Qaeda and the Islamic State group.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 08:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU's Kallas: We expect to list Iran's revolutionary guards as a terrorist organization</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eus-kallas-we-expect-list-irans-revolutionary-guards-terrorist-organization</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/eus-kallas-we-expect-list-irans-revolutionary-guards-terrorist-organization</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BRUSSELS, Jan 29 (Reuters) - The European Union will most likely include Iran's Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps on its list of terrorist organisations, the bloc's foreign policy chief Kaja Kallas said on Friday ahead of a foreign affairs ministers council.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are putting new sanctions on Iran and I also expect we will list the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps as a terrorist list," she said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Lili Bayer and Benoit Van Overstraeten; Editing by Inti Landauro)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 07:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump weighs Iran strikes to inspire renewed protests, sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-weighs-iran-strikes-inspire-renewed-protests-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-weighs-iran-strikes-inspire-renewed-protests-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul, Humeyra Pamuk, Rami Ayyub and Parisa Hafezi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 29 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump is weighing options against Iran that include targeted strikes on security forces and leaders to inspire protesters, multiple sources said, even as Israeli and Arab officials said air power alone would not topple the clerical rulers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two U.S. sources familiar with the discussions said Trump wanted to create conditions for "regime change" after a crackdown crushed a nationwide protest movement earlier this month, killing thousands of people.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 01:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US jails man over plot to kill Iranian-American journalist</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-jails-man-over-plot-kill-iranian-american-journalist</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-jails-man-over-plot-kill-iranian-american-journalist</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A man was sentenced Wednesday to 15 years in prison at a US court for his involvement in a plot to assassinate Masih Alinejad, an Iranian-American journalist highly critical of Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlisle Rivera, 50, was arrested in November 2024 before carrying out the plan that the US Justice Department said was directed by the government of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alinejad is one of the most prominent dissident campaigners against Iranian authorities and for years has pushed for the abolition of the obligatory headscarf in Iran under the banner of "MyStealthyFreedom."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She left Iran in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US says Brooklyn man sentenced to 15 years in Iran-backed plot to kill dissident</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-says-brooklyn-man-sentenced-15-years-iran-backed-plot-kill-dissident</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-says-brooklyn-man-sentenced-15-years-iran-backed-plot-kill-dissident</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 28 (Reuters) - A Brooklyn man was sentenced to 15 years in prison on Wednesday for taking part in what prosecutors called a failed Iran-backed murder-for-hire plot against Masih Alinejad, a prominent Iranian dissident living in the U.S., the Justice Department said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 23:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian officials vow 'harsh' response as Trump threatens action: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-officials-vow-harsh-response-trump-threatens-action-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-officials-vow-harsh-response-trump-threatens-action-what-know</guid><description>Iranian officials signaled openness to a nuclear deal but warned they would retaliate against any US military strike.</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:38:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian officials vow 'harsh' response as Trump threatens action: What to know</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-officials-vow-harsh-response-trump-threatens-action-what-know</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-officials-vow-harsh-response-trump-threatens-action-what-know</guid><description>Iranian officials signaled openness to a nuclear deal but warned they would retaliate against any US military strike.</description><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:38:42 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>