<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Russia taunts US: UN should monitor ship attacks in Caribbean, not Red Sea</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-taunts-us-un-should-monitor-ship-attacks-caribbean-not-red-sea</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-taunts-us-un-should-monitor-ship-attacks-caribbean-not-red-sea</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS, Jan 14 (Reuters) - The U.N. Security Council on Wednesday asked U.N. Secretary-General Antonio Guterres to continue providing monthly reports on any further attacks on vessels in the Red Sea by Yemen's Houthis, spurring Russia to taunt the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We believe that amid present-day realities, the Security Council would be well advised to monitor attacks on commercial transport in the Caribbean, not the Red Sea," Russia's Deputy U.N. Ambassador Anna Evstigneeva told the 15-member body.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:36:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US pulls some personnel from Qatar as Iran warns of response to attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-pulls-some-personnel-qatar-iran-warns-response-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-pulls-some-personnel-qatar-iran-warns-response-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran warned the United States on Wednesday that it was capable of responding to any attack, as Washington appeared to be pulling personnel out of a base that Iran targeted in a strike last year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tensions between the two foes, who have had no diplomatic relations since the Islamic revolution of 1979, come after President Donald Trump warned Tehran it could face action over a crackdown on protests that a rights group said had left at least 3,428 people dead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:31:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French publisher withdraws school books over 'Jewish settler' reference</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-publisher-withdraws-school-books-over-jewish-settler-reference</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-publisher-withdraws-school-books-over-jewish-settler-reference</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;French publisher Hachette said Wednesday it was recalling three textbooks for high-school children which refer to the Israeli victims of the October 7, 2023 attacks on the country as "Jewish settlers".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The worst attack in Israeli history saw militants from the Palestinian armed group Hamas kill around 1,200 people in settlements close to the Gaza Strip and at a music festival.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revision manuals for final-year students refer to all the victims as "Jewish settlers" -- a term usually used to describe Israelis living on illegally occupied Palestinian land.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:31:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US announces launch of phase two of Gaza plan, says Witkoff</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-announces-launch-phase-two-gaza-plan-says-witkoff</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-announces-launch-phase-two-gaza-plan-says-witkoff</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 14 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump's special envoy Steve Witkoff announced on Wednesday the launch of phase two of the plan to end the conflict in Gaza with the establishment of a technocratic Palestinian administration in the enclave.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The US expects Hamas to comply fully with its obligations, including the immediate return of the final deceased hostage. Failure to do so will bring serious consequences," Witkoff wrote in a post on X. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Costas Pitas, Editing by Bhargav Acharya)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:02:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian army tells civilians to stay away from Kurdish positions east of Aleppo</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-tells-civilians-stay-away-kurdish-positions-east-aleppo</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-tells-civilians-stay-away-kurdish-positions-east-aleppo</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria's army told civilians to stay away from Kurdish military positions east of second city Aleppo on Wednesday, after it moved reinforcements to the area following deadly clashes last week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deployment comes as Syria's Islamist-led government seeks to extend its authority across the country, but progress has stalled on integrating the Kurds' de facto autonomous administration and forces into the central government under a deal reached in March.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:00:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Azerbaijan releases four Armenian prisoners in sign of deepening peace</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/azerbaijan-releases-four-armenian-prisoners-sign-deepening-peace</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/azerbaijan-releases-four-armenian-prisoners-sign-deepening-peace</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TBILISI/BAKU, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Azerbaijan has released four Armenian prisoners arrested during wars between the two countries in 2020 and 2023, Armenia said on Wednesday, in a further sign of normalising ties between the long-standing foes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Armenian Prime Minister Nikol Pashinyan wrote on the Telegram messaging app that all four men were in satisfactory health and were headed for the capital Yerevan after being released by Azerbaijani authorities at the Khakari Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 16:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US to suspend visa processing for 75 nations next week, Fox News reports</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-suspend-visa-processing-75-nations-next-week-fox-news-reports</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-suspend-visa-processing-75-nations-next-week-fox-news-reports</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 14 (Reuters) - The Trump administration is suspending all visa processing for visitors from 75 countries starting January 21, Fox News reported on Wednesday, citing a memo from the U.S. State Department.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somalia, Russia, Iran, Afghanistan, Brazil, Nigeria, Thailand are among the affected countries, according to the report. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 15:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran tops Netanyahu's many challenges as Israeli elections loom</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-tops-netanyahus-many-challenges-israeli-elections-loom</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-tops-netanyahus-many-challenges-israeli-elections-loom</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maayan Lubell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu will face voters this year for the first time since the 2023 Hamas attack shook his security credentials, with the outcome of the latest crisis in Iran likely to be key to salvaging his legacy, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Successive polls since late 2023, including all those by the three main news channels in Israel over the past month, have shown Netanyahu losing the election, due in October.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 15:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In call with Araghchi, Turkey's Fidan urges Iran to negotiate with US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</guid><description>The top Turkish diplomat held back-to-back calls with Iranian and US officials as Ankara watches developments in Iran with mounting concern.</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 15:29:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In call with Araghchi, Turkey's Fidan urges Iran to negotiate with US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</guid><description>The top Turkish diplomat held back-to-back calls with Iranian and US officials as Ankara watches developments in Iran with mounting concern.</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 15:29:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In call with Araghchi, Turkey's Fidan urges Iran to negotiate with US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</guid><description>The top Turkish diplomat held back-to-back calls with Iranian and US officials as Ankara watches developments in Iran with mounting concern.</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 15:29:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In call with Araghchi, Turkey's Fidan urges Iran to negotiate with US</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/call-araghchi-turkeys-fidan-urges-iran-negotiate-us</guid><description>The top Turkish diplomat held back-to-back calls with Iranian and US officials as Ankara watches developments in Iran with mounting concern.</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 15:29:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK interior minister has no confidence in police chief after Israeli soccer fan ban</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uk-interior-minister-has-no-confidence-police-chief-after-israeli-soccer-fan-ban</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/uk-interior-minister-has-no-confidence-police-chief-after-israeli-soccer-fan-ban</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 14 (Reuters) - British interior minister Shabana Mahmood said on Wednesday she no longer had confidence in one of Britain's top police officers after his force recommended Israeli fans be barred from attending an Aston Villa soccer game last year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ban, imposed on security grounds, was condemned by both the British and Israeli governments, while Jewish community leaders accused the force of misrepresenting intelligence and undermining public confidence.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 14:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US evacuates some personnel from Qatar air base amid Trump threat to strike Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-evacuates-some-personnel-qatar-air-base-amid-trump-threat-strike-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-evacuates-some-personnel-qatar-air-base-amid-trump-threat-strike-iran</guid><description>Iran's Defense Minister Aziz Nasirzadeh warned Tuesday that Tehran will retaliate for any attacks on the country.</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 14:05:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranians arrive in Turkey through border gate as crackdown persists</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranians-arrive-turkey-through-border-gate-crackdown-persists</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranians-arrive-turkey-through-border-gate-crackdown-persists</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Ismet Mikailogullari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KAPIKOY, Turkey, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Dozens of Iranians crossed the border into Turkey on Wednesday, as authorities in Iran crack down on one of the biggest ever waves of protest against the Islamic Republic's clerical rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump urged Iranians on Tuesday to keep protesting, saying help is on the way. A rights group said 2,600 people have been killed in Iran as the clerical rulers try to quash the major wave of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>France studying possible transfer of Eutelsat terminals to Iran, foreign minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/france-studying-possible-transfer-eutelsat-terminals-iran-foreign-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/france-studying-possible-transfer-eutelsat-terminals-iran-foreign-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Jan 14 (Reuters) - France's foreign minister said on Wednesday that Paris was looking at the possibility of sending Eutelsat satellite terminals to Iran to help provide internet services after the recent communications blackout imposed by the Iranian authorities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are exploring all options, and the one you have mentioned is among them," Jean-Noel Barrot told lawmakers in parliament responding to a question about sending Eutelsat terminals to Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by John Irish; Editing by Hugh Lawson)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 13:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany open to deepening ties with Syrian government, says Berlin</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germany-open-deepening-ties-syrian-government-says-berlin</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/germany-open-deepening-ties-syrian-government-says-berlin</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BERLIN, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Germany is open to deepening relations with the new Syrian government, a German government spokesperson said, adding that Berlin is closely monitoring the situation in the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The German government is, of course, open to deepening relations and a fresh start with the new Syrian government," said the spokesperson at regular government press conference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spokesperson added that Berlin is closely monitoring the situation in the Syrian city of Aleppo, where deadly clashes broke out recently, also in close consultation with Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 13:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia's Lavrov says the U.S. is smashing the world around with its raid on Venezuela and threats to Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russias-lavrov-says-us-smashing-world-around-its-raid-venezuela-and-threats-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russias-lavrov-says-us-smashing-world-around-its-raid-venezuela-and-threats-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov said on Wednesday that the United States was fragmenting the very international system which Washington helped to create by undertaking what he said was an illegal operation to topple Venezuelan leader Nicolas Maduro and by threatening Iran with attack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We are talking about a gross violation of international law," Lavrov said of the U.S. operation to capture Maduro. He added that Russia remained committed to its agreements with Venezuela, a Russian ally.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Where are the main US military bases in the Middle East?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/where-are-main-us-military-bases-middle-east</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/where-are-main-us-military-bases-middle-east</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 14 (Reuters) - Following are the significant military bases in the Middle East. Iran has threatened to strike U.S. bases in the region if attacked by Washington, after U.S. President Donald Trump told Iranians to keep protesting and declared "help is on the way".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAHRAIN:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Home to the headquarters of the U.S. Navy's Fifth Fleet, whose area of responsibility includes the Gulf, Red Sea, Arabian Sea and parts of the Indian Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;QATAR:&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kazakhstan urges Europe and US to help secure oil transport after CPC attack</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kazakhstan-urges-europe-and-us-help-secure-oil-transport-after-cpc-attack</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kazakhstan-urges-europe-and-us-help-secure-oil-transport-after-cpc-attack</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 14 (Reuters) - Kazakhstan has urged Europe and the U.S. to help secure the transport of oil following drone attacks on tankers heading to a Black Sea terminal, the Central Asian country's foreign ministry said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministry said in a statement that it made the request during meetings with ambassadors from several European countries, as well as U.S. representatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>