<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Syrian forces seize major oil, gas fields in eastern Syria, security sources say</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-seize-major-oil-gas-fields-eastern-syria-security-sources-say</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-forces-seize-major-oil-gas-fields-eastern-syria-security-sources-say</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 18 (Reuters) - Syrian troops fighting U.S.-backed Kurdish-led forces seized the Omar oil field, the country’s largest, and the Conoco gas field in the eastern Deir Zor province as allied Arab tribal forces advanced in the oil-rich area along the border with Iraq, officials and security sources said on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The takeover of the oil fields that lie east of the Euphrates River — a main source of revenue for the Kurdish-led forces — was a major blow to the group, which officials said had deprived the state of resources used by the militia.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 10:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurdish-led forces withdraw from Syria's largest oil field: monitor</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-led-forces-withdraw-syrias-largest-oil-field-monitor</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/kurdish-led-forces-withdraw-syrias-largest-oil-field-monitor</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Kurdish-led forces withdrew on Sunday from Syria's largest oil field, a conflict monitor said, as government troops extended their grip over swathes of territory in the country's north and east.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The push came after President Ahmed al-Sharaa issued a decree granting the Kurds official recognition in an apparent goodwill gesture, even as his Islamist government seeks to assert its authority over all of Syria after the ousting of longtime ruler Bashar al-Assad in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian official says verified deaths in Iran protests reaches at least 5,000</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-official-says-verified-deaths-iran-protests-reaches-least-5000</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iranian-official-says-verified-deaths-iran-protests-reaches-least-5000</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 18 (Reuters) - An Iranian official in the region said on Sunday the authorities had verified at least 5,000 people had been killed in protests in Iran, including about 500 security personnel, blaming "terrorists and armed rioters" for killing "innocent Iranians".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jordan says King Abdullah received invitation to join Gaza peace board</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/jordan-says-king-abdullah-received-invitation-join-gaza-peace-board</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/jordan-says-king-abdullah-received-invitation-join-gaza-peace-board</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 18 (Reuters) - Jordan's foreign ministry said on Sunday that King Abdullah received an invitation from U.S. President Donald Trump to join the so-called "Board of Peace" for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The foreign ministry said it was currently reviewing related documents within the country's internal legal procedures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The board is set to supervise the temporary governance of Gaza, which has been under a shaky ceasefire since October.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Menna Alaa El-Din and Muhammad Al Gebaly;Editing by Elaine Hardcastle)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 08:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump wants nations to pay $1 billion to stay on his peace board, report says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-wants-nations-pay-1-billion-stay-his-peace-board-report-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-wants-nations-pay-1-billion-stay-his-peace-board-report-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 17 (Reuters) - The Trump administration wants nations to pay $1 billion to stay on his peace board, Bloomberg News reported on Saturday, citing a draft charter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;United States President Donald Trump would serve as its inaugural chairman and each member state shall serve a term of no more than three years from this charter's entry into force, subject to renewal by the chairman, the report said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reuters could not immediately verify the report.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:01:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands march in France to back Iranian protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-march-france-back-iranian-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/thousands-march-france-back-iranian-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of people rallied in France on Saturday in a show of support for demonstrators in Iran risking their lives to demand an end to theocratic rule.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests in Iran over past weeks are the largest since the "Woman, Life, Freedom" street movement in 2022-2023, sparked by the death in custody of an Iranian Kurdish woman arrested for allegedly not following a required dress code. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Woman, Life, Freedom," chanted marchers in the French capital, some holding portraits of deceased Iranian protesters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 19:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq takes full control of air base after US withdrawal, defence ministry says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraq-takes-full-control-air-base-after-us-withdrawal-defence-ministry-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iraq-takes-full-control-air-base-after-us-withdrawal-defence-ministry-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;BAGHDAD, Jan 17 (Reuters) - U.S. forces have withdrawn from Iraq's Ain al-Asad Airbase, which housed U.S.-led forces in Western Iraq, and the Iraqi army has assumed full control, the Iraqi defence ministry said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2024, Washington and Baghdad reached an understanding on plans for the withdrawal of U.S.-led coalition forces from Iraq and a move towards a bilateral security relationship.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian army extends hold over north Syria, Kurds report clashes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-extends-hold-over-north-syria-kurds-report-clashes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-army-extends-hold-over-north-syria-kurds-report-clashes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syria's army has seized swathes of the country's north, dislodging Kurdish forces from territory over which they held effective autonomy for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government appeared to be extending its grip on Kurdish-run areas after President Ahmed al-Sharaa issued a decree declaring Kurdish a "national language" and granting the minority group official recognition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Kurds have said Friday's announcement fell short of their aspirations, while the implementation of a March deal -- intended to see Kurdish forces integrated into the state -- has stalled.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel says US Gaza executive board composition against its policy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-says-us-gaza-executive-board-composition-against-its-policy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-says-us-gaza-executive-board-composition-against-its-policy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;TEL AVIV, Jan 17 (Reuters) - Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu's office said on Saturday that this week's Trump administration announcement on the composition of a Gaza executive board was not coordinated with Israel and ran counter to government policy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It said Foreign Minister Gideon Saar would raise the issue with U.S. Secretary of State Marco Rubio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The statement did not specify what part of the board's composition contradicted Israeli policy. An Israeli government spokesperson declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel objects to line-up of Trump panel for post-war Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-objects-line-trump-panel-post-war-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-objects-line-trump-panel-post-war-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel said on Saturday it objected to the line-up of a Gaza panel that will operate under US President Donald Trump's Board of Peace, which oversees post-war governance in the Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The panel, known as the Gaza executive board, notably includes Turkish Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan and a Qatari official and was announced by the White House on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace began to take shape on Saturday as the leaders of Egypt, Turkey, Argentina and Canada were asked to join. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 15:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran leader demands crackdown on 'seditionists' after protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-leader-demands-crackdown-seditionists-after-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-leader-demands-crackdown-seditionists-after-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's supreme leader said Saturday that authorities "must break the back of the seditionists", whom he accused of killing thousands during the wave of protests that were brutally repressed in the country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The demonstrations were sparked by anger over economic hardship that exploded into the biggest protests against the Islamic republic in more than three years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But demonstrations have subsided after the crackdown that rights groups say left thousands of people dead under an internet blackout that has lasted more than a week.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 13:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian troops sweep northern towns as Kurdish fighters withdraw</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-troops-sweep-northern-towns-kurdish-fighters-withdraw</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-troops-sweep-northern-towns-kurdish-fighters-withdraw</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DEIR HAFER, Jan 17 (Reuters) - Syrian troops swept through dozens of towns and villages in the country's north on Saturday after Kurdish fighters withdrew under an agreement that aimed to avoid a bloody showdown between the rival forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For days, Syrian troops had amassed around a cluster of villages that lie just west of the winding Euphrates River and had called on the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces stationed there to redeploy their forces on the opposite bank of the river.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 11:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'My nightmare': Iranians recount crackdown under internet blackout</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/my-nightmare-iranians-recount-crackdown-under-internet-blackout</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/my-nightmare-iranians-recount-crackdown-under-internet-blackout</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One move in the wrong direction and Kiarash would have been dead, he said, as a shooter opened fire on him and other protesters in the Iranian capital during a wave of demonstrations met by a deadly crackdown. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Blood stained the street after a person dressed in a full chador covering shot at a large crowd that had gathered in the north of Tehran on January 10, during anti-government protests sparked by economic strain that exploded in size and intensity on January 8. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 10:30:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt's Sisi says he values offer by Trump to mediate Egypt-Ethiopia dispute on Nile River waters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-sisi-says-he-values-offer-trump-mediate-egypt-ethiopia-dispute-nile-river</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypts-sisi-says-he-values-offer-trump-mediate-egypt-ethiopia-dispute-nile-river</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 17 (Reuters) - Egypt's President Abdel Fattah al-Sisi said he valued an offer by U.S. President Donald Trump to mediate a dispute over Nile River waters between Egypt and Ethiopia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a post on X, Sisi said on Saturday that he addressed Trump's letter by affirming Egypt's position and concerns about the country's water security in regards to Ethiopia's Grand Ethiopian Renaissance Dam.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Menna Alaa El-Din and Muhammad Al Gebaly; Editing by Toby Chopra)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Luciano Benavides wins Dakar bike title by two seconds</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/luciano-benavides-wins-dakar-bike-title-two-seconds</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/luciano-benavides-wins-dakar-bike-title-two-seconds</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Argentina's Luciano Benavides won the Dakar Rally bike title by a mere two seconds in Saudi Arabia on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second in the 13th and closing stage was enough for the 30-year-old KTM rider to deny Honda's American two-time champion Ricky Brabec and secure his debut Dakar crown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I've dreamed of this moment my whole life," said the winner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brabec, winner in 2020 and 2024, was on target for a third title but lost time when going the wrong way close to the finish of the 105km ride around Yanbu.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 10:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Nothing's changed' in Gaza as US peace deal enters second phase</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/nothings-changed-gaza-us-peace-deal-enters-second-phase</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/nothings-changed-gaza-us-peace-deal-enters-second-phase</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;From his tent in Gaza City, Mahmoud Abdel Aal said residents were frustrated and worried because nothing had changed in the Palestinian territory since the start of the US-brokered ceasefire's second phase.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a post-apocalyptic landscape of bombed-out buildings and makeshift camps devastated by recent winter rains, Palestinians who spoke to AFP mostly expressed bitterness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Though Israeli strikes have been less intense since the ceasefire between Hamas and Israel began in October 2025, bombs still fall every day.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:30:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French publisher recalls dictionary over 'Jewish settler' reference</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-publisher-recalls-dictionary-over-jewish-settler-reference</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/french-publisher-recalls-dictionary-over-jewish-settler-reference</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;French publisher Hachette on Friday said it had recalled a dictionary that described the Israeli victims of the October 7, 2023 attacks as "Jewish settlers" and promised to review all its textbooks and educational materials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Larousse dictionary for 11- to 15-year-old students contained the same phrase as that discovered by an anti-racism body in three revision books, the company told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:30:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian president declares Kurdish a national language</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-president-declares-kurdish-national-language</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-president-declares-kurdish-national-language</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syrian President Ahmed al-Sharaa issued a decree on Friday declaring Kurdish a "national language", in an apparent gesture of good will towards the minority following clashes in recent days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The decree is the first formal recognition of Kurdish national rights since Syria's independence in 1946.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It stated Kurds were "an essential and integral part" of Syria, where they have suffered decades of marginalisation and oppression under former rulers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:30:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump taps Tony Blair, US military head for Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-taps-tony-blair-us-military-head-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-taps-tony-blair-us-military-head-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump on Friday gave a key role in post-war Gaza to former British prime minister Tony Blair and appointed a US officer to lead a nascent security force.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump named members of a board to help supervise Gaza that was dominated by Americans, as he promotes a controversial vision of economic development in a territory that lies in rubble after two-plus years of relentless Israeli bombardment.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:30:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Death toll in Iran protests over 3,000, rights group says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/death-toll-iran-protests-over-3000-rights-group-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/death-toll-iran-protests-over-3000-rights-group-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 17 (Reuters) - More than 3,000 people have died in Iran's nationwide protests, rights activists said on Saturday, while a "very slight rise" in internet activity was reported in the country after an eight-day blackout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S.-based HRANA group said it had verified 3,090 deaths, including 2,885 protesters, after residents said the crackdown appeared to have broadly quelled protests for now and state media reported more arrests.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 05:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>