<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Dark times under Syria's Assad hit Arab screens for Ramadan</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/dark-times-under-syrias-assad-hit-arab-screens-ramadan</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/dark-times-under-syrias-assad-hit-arab-screens-ramadan</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Syrian prison warden screams at a group of chained, crouching inmates in a harrowing scene from one of several Ramadan television series this year that tackle the era of former ruler Bashar al-Assad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Talking about Syria's prisons and the torture, enforced disappearances and executions that took place there was taboo during half a century of the Assad family's iron-fisted rule, but the topics are now fertile ground for creative productions, though not without controversy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 02:00:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia rejects report it is repatriating families of IS militants from Syrian camp</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australia-rejects-report-it-repatriating-families-militants-syrian-camp</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/australia-rejects-report-it-repatriating-families-militants-syrian-camp</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 22 (Reuters) - Australia's centre-left government on Sunday rejected a local media report that said it was working to repatriate Australians in a Syrian camp holding families of suspected Islamic State militants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 34 women and children were released on Monday from the camp in northern Syria, but returned to the detention centre due to technical reasons. The group is expected to travel to Damascus before eventually returning to Australia, despite objections from ruling and opposition lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 00:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Islamic State claims two attacks on Syrian army, announces ‘new phase’ of operations</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/islamic-state-claims-two-attacks-syrian-army-announces-new-phase-operations</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/islamic-state-claims-two-attacks-syrian-army-announces-new-phase-operations</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Feras Dalatey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feb 22 - Islamic State claimed responsibility on Saturday for two attacks targeting Syrian army personnel in northern and eastern Syria, as the militant group signaled what it described as a new phase of operations against the country’s leadership.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The militant group said on its Dabiq news agency that it had targeted “an individual of the apostate Syrian regime” in the city of Mayadin in Deir al-Zor province using a pistol, and attacked two other personnel with machine guns in the northern city of Raqqa.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 22:36:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FIFA's Gaza support 'in keeping' with international federation - IOC</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fifas-gaza-support-keeping-international-federation-ioc</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fifas-gaza-support-keeping-international-federation-ioc</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The International Olympic Committee (IOC) said Saturday that FIFA's support of an investment programme in Gaza was "in keeping with the role" of an international federation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;IOC president Kirsty Coventry said on Friday she was unaware that FIFA president Gianni Infantino had attended the first meeting of the Board of Peace alongside US President Donald Trump in Washington on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 19:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italy's RAI apologises after latest gaffe targets Israeli bobsleigh team</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/italys-rai-apologises-after-latest-gaffe-targets-israeli-bobsleigh-team</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/italys-rai-apologises-after-latest-gaffe-targets-israeli-bobsleigh-team</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Andrea Mandala&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MILAN, Feb 21 (Reuters) - Italy's state broadcaster RAI was forced to apologise to the Jewish community on Saturday after an off‑air remark advising its producers to "avoid" the Israeli crew was broadcast before coverage of the Four-Man bobsleigh event at the Winter Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The head of RAI's sports division had already resigned earlier in the week after his error-ridden commentary at the Milano Cortina 2026 opening ceremony two weeks ago triggered a revolt among its journalists.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 18:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian students begin new university term with protests</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-students-begin-new-university-term-protests</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-students-begin-new-university-term-protests</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 21 (Reuters) - Students held protests at several Iranian universities at the start of a new semester on Saturday, some clashing with pro-government groups, according to local news agencies and posts on social media.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protests coincided with ceremonies traditionally held after 40 days to mourn those killed by security forces during last month's anti-government demonstrations, which saw thousands lose their lives in the worst domestic unrest since Iran's 1979 Islamic Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 17:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fears of renewed conflict haunt Tehran as US issues threats</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fears-renewed-conflict-haunt-tehran-us-issues-threats</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/fears-renewed-conflict-haunt-tehran-us-issues-threats</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Tehran resident Hamid struggles to sleep as fears of renewed conflict haunt the Iranian capital after last year's 12-day war with Israel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I don't sleep well at night even while taking pills," Hamid told AFP, as he expressed concern for his "family's health... my kids and grandchildren".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The city woke up to blasts overnight from June 12 to 13 last year as Iran's arch-enemy Israel launched an unprecedented military campaign.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 17:30:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iranian students chant anti-government slogans, as US threats loom</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-students-chant-anti-government-slogans-us-threats-loom</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/iranian-students-chant-anti-government-slogans-us-threats-loom</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iranian students chanted anti-government slogans and scuffled with counter-protesters on Saturday in the latest display of anger at the country's clerical leaders, who also face a US military build-up aimed at pressuring them into a nuclear deal.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The gatherings at universities, which were reported by both local and diaspora media outlets, followed a mass protest movement that was met with a government crackdown last month that left thousands dead.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 16:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Libya's Ramadan celebrations tempered by economic woes</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/libyas-ramadan-celebrations-tempered-economic-woes</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/libyas-ramadan-celebrations-tempered-economic-woes</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Libyans have been enjoying Ramadan with feasts and fireworks -- but soaring prices, a devalued currency and political divisions have left many with little to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fifteen years on from the fall of longtime leader Muammar Gaddafi, the country remains split between east and west, while shortages of goods, including fuel, disrupt daily life, despite Libya sitting atop vast oil and gas reserves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the Muslim holy month of Ramadan, shoppers stock up on treats, as families gather for lavish meals before and after the daytime fast that stretches from sunrise to sunset.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 16:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hezbollah vows resistance after deadly Israeli strike</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hezbollah-vows-resistance-after-deadly-israeli-strike</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/hezbollah-vows-resistance-after-deadly-israeli-strike</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hezbollah warned Saturday that it would have no choice but to fight on after an Israeli strike on targets in Lebanon killed eight of its operatives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lebanon's government has vowed to disarm Hezbollah, but Israel insists it retains the right to defend itself by striking the Iran-backed militant group.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the Israeli military said it had hit Hezbollah command centres in eastern Lebanon and targets linked to the Palestinian group Hamas in the south.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 15:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Political drama 'Yellow Letters' wins Berlin's Golden Bear</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/political-drama-yellow-letters-wins-berlins-golden-bear</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/political-drama-yellow-letters-wins-berlins-golden-bear</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;"Yellow Letters", directed by German filmmaker Ilker Catak, won the Berlin Film Festival's Golden Bear for best film Saturday, at a ceremony reflecting the controversy over Gaza that has dogged this year's edition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some award winners spoke out in favour of the Palestinian cause, pushing back after jury president Wim Wenders had sparked outrage earlier by trying to steer the festival away from the issue.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 15:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pezeshkian says Iran will not bow to pressure amid US nuclear talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pezeshkian-says-iran-will-not-bow-pressure-amid-us-nuclear-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/pezeshkian-says-iran-will-not-bow-pressure-amid-us-nuclear-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 21 (Reuters) - Iranian President Masoud Pezeshkian said on Saturday that his country would not bow its head to pressure from world powers amid nuclear talks with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"World powers are lining up to force us to bow our heads... but we will not bow our heads despite all the problems that they are creating for us," Pezeshkian said in a speech carried live by state TV.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Dubai newsroom; Editing by Sharon Singleton)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 14:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli strikes in Lebanon kill at least 10, including senior Hezbollah official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-strikes-lebanon-kill-least-10-including-senior-hezbollah-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/israeli-strikes-lebanon-kill-least-10-including-senior-hezbollah-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Feb 20 (Reuters) - At least 10 people were killed and 50 wounded in Israeli strikes in Lebanon's Bekaa Valley on Friday, two security sources told Reuters, after the Israeli military said it had targeted Hezbollah sites in the Baalbek area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strikes are among the deadliest reported in eastern Lebanon in recent weeks and risk testing a fragile U.S.-brokered ceasefire between Israel and Shi'ite Islamist group Hezbollah, which has been strained by recurring accusations of violations.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 12:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukrainians, scattered across Europe, trapped in limbo by war</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukrainians-scattered-across-europe-trapped-limbo-war</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/ukrainians-scattered-across-europe-trapped-limbo-war</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kuba Stezycki and Ali Kucukgocmen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WARSAW/ISTANBUL, Feb 21 (Reuters) - Maryna Bondarenko says she has three suitcases packed in her apartment in Poland, waiting for the day when peace returns to Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 51-year-old journalist fled Kyiv with her son and mother after Russia launched its invasion on February 24, 2022. She thought they would be abroad for a month or two until the war ended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four years later, she is still there, working in a Ukrainian‑language newsroom that caters to a community of more than 1.5 million Ukrainians living in Poland.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 10:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-Trump pushes US toward war with Iran as advisers urge focus on economy</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/analysis-trump-pushes-us-toward-war-iran-advisers-urge-focus-economy</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/analysis-trump-pushes-us-toward-war-iran-advisers-urge-focus-economy</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Matt Spetalnick, Bo Erickson, Nandita Bose and Tim Reid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Feb 21 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump has pushed the United States to the brink of war with Iran even as aides urge him to focus more on voters' economic worries, highlighting the political risks of military escalation ahead of this year's midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 06:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump meets Vietnam leader, vows to remove Hanoi from restricted lists</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-meets-vietnam-leader-vows-remove-hanoi-restricted-lists</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/trump-meets-vietnam-leader-vows-remove-hanoi-restricted-lists</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/HANOI, Feb 20 (Reuters) - President Donald Trump met Vietnamese leader To Lam on Friday and said he would work to remove Hanoi from lists of countries restricted in accessing U.S. advanced technology, according to a summary of the talks posted on the news website of the Vietnamese government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first formal in-person meeting between the two took place at the White House after the head of Vietnam's ruling Communist Party attended the inaugural meeting of the Board of Peace in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 02:01:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Battered by Gaza war, Israel's tech sector in recovery mode</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/battered-gaza-war-israels-tech-sector-recovery-mode</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/battered-gaza-war-israels-tech-sector-recovery-mode</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Israel's vital tech sector, dragged down by the war in Gaza, is showing early signs of recovery, buoyed by a surge in defence innovation and fresh investment momentum.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cutting-edge technologies represent 17 percent of the country's GDP, 11.5 percent of jobs and 57 percent of exports, according to the latest available data from the Israel Innovation Authority (IIA), published in September 2025.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Sat, 21 Feb 2026 01:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysis-US and Iran slide towards conflict as military buildup eclipses talks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/analysis-us-and-iran-slide-towards-conflict-military-buildup-eclipses-talks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/analysis-us-and-iran-slide-towards-conflict-military-buildup-eclipses-talks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Samia Nakhoul, Parisa Hafezi and John Irish&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Feb 20 (Reuters) - Iran and the United States are sliding rapidly towards military conflict as hopes fade for a diplomatic solution to their standoff over Tehran’s nuclear programme, officials on both sides and diplomats across the Gulf and Europe say.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran’s Gulf neighbours and its enemy Israel now consider a conflict to be more likely than a settlement, these sources  say, with Washington building up one of its biggest military deployments in the region since the invasion of Iraq in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 22:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US partners shy away as Pentagon readies for potential strikes against Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-partners-shy-away-pentagon-readies-potential-strikes-against-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-partners-shy-away-pentagon-readies-potential-strikes-against-iran</guid><description>Turkey and the United Kingdom are the latest among Washington’s military partners seeking to distance themselves from being tied to any planned strikes against Iran.</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 21:22:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US partners shy away as Pentagon readies for potential strikes against Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-partners-shy-away-pentagon-readies-potential-strikes-against-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/02/us-partners-shy-away-pentagon-readies-potential-strikes-against-iran</guid><description>Turkey and the United Kingdom are the latest among Washington’s military partners seeking to distance themselves from being tied to any planned strikes against Iran.</description><pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 21:22:33 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>