<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>The Trump-backed Palestinian who wants to push Gaza's rubble into the sea</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-backed-palestinian-who-wants-push-gazas-rubble-sea</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-backed-palestinian-who-wants-push-gazas-rubble-sea</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Rami Ayyub and Nidal al-Mughrabi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM/CAIRO, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Ali Shaath, the Palestinian former government official chosen to administer Gaza under a U.S.-backed deal, has an ambitious plan that includes pushing war debris into the Mediterranean Sea and rebuilding destroyed infrastructure within three years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The appointment of the civil engineer and former deputy planning minister on Thursday marked the start of the next phase of U.S. President Donald Trump's plan to end Israel's war in Gaza. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia says the West should stop claiming Moscow wants to occupy Greenland</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-says-west-should-stop-claiming-moscow-wants-occupy-greenland</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-says-west-should-stop-claiming-moscow-wants-occupy-greenland</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Dmitry Antonov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Russia said on Thursday that its was unacceptable for the West to keep claiming that Russia and China threatened Greenland, and said the crisis over the territory showed the double-standards of Western powers which claimed moral superiority.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. President Donald Trump has repeatedly said that the United States will take Greenland because unless it does so then Russia and China will - and that the United States does not want them as neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump administration wins appeal of ruling releasing pro-Palestinian activist Khalil</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-administration-wins-appeal-ruling-releasing-pro-palestinian-activist-khalil</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-administration-wins-appeal-ruling-releasing-pro-palestinian-activist-khalil</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Nate Raymond&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jan 15 (Reuters) - A federal appeals court ruled on Thursday that a judge had no jurisdiction to order the release of Columbia University graduate Mahmoud Khalil from immigration detention, delivering President Donald Trump's administration a victory in its efforts to deport the pro-Palestinian activist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2-1 ruling by a panel of the Philadelphia-based 3rd U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals opened the door to Khalil being re-arrested after it ordered the dismissal of a lawsuit he filed challenging his initial detention.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US issues new Iran-related sanctions, US Treasury website shows</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-issues-new-iran-related-sanctions-us-treasury-website-shows</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-issues-new-iran-related-sanctions-us-treasury-website-shows</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 15 (Reuters) - The Trump administration on Thursday issued new Iran-related sanctions that target what appeared to be shipping, trading and energy companies, according to a post on the U.S. Treasury Department website on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new sanctions come amid Iran's crackdown on protests in Iran, where the clerical establishment has cracked down hard on nationwide unrest since December 28. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sanctions also target 11 individuals and Fardis Prison, according to the website. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US imposes sanctions on Iran over crackdown on protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-imposes-sanctions-iran-over-crackdown-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-imposes-sanctions-iran-over-crackdown-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Daphne Psaledakis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 15 (Reuters) - The United States on Thursday imposed sanctions on five Iranian officials it accused of being behind the crackdown on protests and warned it was tracking Iranian leaders' funds being wired to banks around the world, as U.S. President Donald Trump's administration increases pressure on Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Putin says the world is getting more dangerous but is silent on Maduro and Iran</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/putin-says-world-getting-more-dangerous-silent-maduro-and-iran</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/putin-says-world-getting-more-dangerous-silent-maduro-and-iran</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MOSCOW, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Russian President Vladimir said on Thursday that the international situation had deteriorated and that the world was getting more dangerous but he was silent on the situation in Venezuela and Iran.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Putin has yet to comment in public on the toppling of Venezuela's Nicolas Maduro by the United States, the protests in Iran or U.S. President Donald Trump's threats against Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Forced confession fears as Iran chief justice interrogates protesters</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/forced-confession-fears-iran-chief-justice-interrogates-protesters</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/forced-confession-fears-iran-chief-justice-interrogates-protesters</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Iran's hardline judiciary chief has personally interrogated protesters arrested in a crackdown that has sparked an international outcry, amplifying fears among rights groups about the use of "forced confessions" to instil fear in society.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, state television showed Gholamhossein Mohseni Ejei, who has spent his career at the heart of the Islamic republic's legal apparatus and has been sanctioned by both the European Union and United States, quizzing several people the authorities accuse of being "rioters".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia, China unlikely to back Iran against US military threats</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-china-unlikely-back-iran-against-us-military-threats</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/russia-china-unlikely-back-iran-against-us-military-threats</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;While Russia and China are ready to back protest-rocked Iran under threat by US President Donald Trump, that support would diminish in the face of US military action, experts told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran is a significant ally to the two nuclear powers, providing drones to Russia and oil to China. But analysts told AFP the two superpowers would only offer diplomatic and economic aid to Tehran, to avoid a showdown with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Back from Iran, Pakistani students say they heard gunshots while confined to campus</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/back-iran-pakistani-students-say-they-heard-gunshots-while-confined-campus</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/back-iran-pakistani-students-say-they-heard-gunshots-while-confined-campus</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Asif Shahzad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Pakistani students returning from Iran on Thursday said they heard gunshots and stories of rioting and violence while being confined to campus and not allowed out of their dormitories in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran's leadership is trying to quell the worst domestic unrest since its 1979 revolution, with a rights group putting the death toll over 2,600. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the protests swell, Tehran is seeking to deter U.S. President Donald Trump's repeated threats to intervene on behalf of anti-government protesters.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-What are shipping companies' plans for return to Suez Canal?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-what-are-shipping-companies-plans-return-suez-canal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-what-are-shipping-companies-plans-return-suez-canal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 15 (Reuters) - Major shipping companies are devising strategies for a return to the Suez Canal after more than two years of disruptions due to security risks in the Red Sea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They have been rerouting vessels via longer, costlier routes around Africa since November 2023, following attacks on commercial ships by Yemen's Houthi forces, reportedly in solidarity with Palestinians during warfare in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ceasefire agreement reached in October 2025 has led some companies to explore resumption plans, although security remains a key concern. Below are the latest updates:&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:01:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greece warns shipping fleet of risks after Black Sea drone attacks</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-warns-shipping-fleet-risks-after-black-sea-drone-attacks</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/greece-warns-shipping-fleet-risks-after-black-sea-drone-attacks</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ATHENS, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Greece has warned its shipping fleet to review their security measures when sailing to Russian Black Sea ports after drone attacks on two Greek-operated tankers this week, according to shipping ministry advisories.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drones struck two oil tankers on Tuesday, including one chartered by U.S. oil major Chevron, as they sailed toward a Black Sea terminal on Russia's Black Sea coast.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 14:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrians flee Kurdish-controlled area near Aleppo</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-flee-kurdish-controlled-area-near-aleppo</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrians-flee-kurdish-controlled-area-near-aleppo</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Syrians began fleeing an area east of Aleppo city on Thursday after the army gave civilians a deadline to leave amid fears of an escalation in clashes with Kurdish forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is seeking to extend its authority across the country following the ouster of longtime leader Bashar al-Assad a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, government troops took full control of Aleppo city over the weekend after capturing two Kurdish-majority neighbourhoods.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:30:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey says it opposes military intervention in Iran, priority is avoiding destabilisation</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-says-it-opposes-military-intervention-iran-priority-avoiding</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-says-it-opposes-military-intervention-iran-priority-avoiding</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Spicer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Turkey is opposed to any military intervention in Iran and its priority is to avoid destabilisation there, Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan said on Thursday, as Tehran continues its crackdown on protests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Iran's leadership trying to quell the worst domestic unrest the Islamic Republic has ever faced, and with U.S. President Donald Trump's repeated threats to intervene on behalf of the protesters, Tehran has warned its neighbours including Turkey that it would hit American bases if Washington were to strike.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>European airlines continue to avoid Iran and Iraq despite airspace reopening</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/european-airlines-continue-avoid-iran-and-iraq-despite-airspace-reopening</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/european-airlines-continue-avoid-iran-and-iraq-despite-airspace-reopening</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Joanna Plucinska&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LONDON, Jan 15 (Reuters) - European airlines like Wizz Air, Lufthansa and British Airways dodged Iraqi and Iranian airspace on Thursday, according to flight tracking websites, opting instead for routes over Afghanistan and central Asia in an effort to mitigate risks associated with the ongoing geopolitical turmoil in Iran and the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria's use of force against Kurdish-led SDF seems an option, Turkey says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-use-force-against-kurdish-led-sdf-seems-option-turkey-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrias-use-force-against-kurdish-led-sdf-seems-option-turkey-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Jonathan Spicer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISTANBUL, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Turkey's foreign minister said on Thursday he hopes problems in neighbouring Syria can be resolved peacefully but the use of force by the government in Damascus could be an option after recent clashes with Kurdish fighters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Five days of fighting in the northern Syrian city of Aleppo last week killed at least 23 people, according to Syria's health ministry, while more than 150,000 fledthe two Kurdish-run pockets of the city.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran protests show bitter schism among exiled opposition factions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protests-show-bitter-schism-among-exiled-opposition-factions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/iran-protests-show-bitter-schism-among-exiled-opposition-factions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By John Irish&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PARIS, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Huge protests in Iran have galvanised exiled foes of the authorities but despite their hatred of the ruling clerics, a bitter schism dating to before the 1979 Islamic Revolution still afflicts the leading opposition factions. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That split, between monarchists supporting Reza Pahlavi, son of the ousted shah, and a more organised leftist group, the Mujahedin-e Khalq, has played out online and even in angry arguments in street protests in Europe and North America. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 10:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Saudi Arabia pledges $500 million Yemen development after UAE withdrawal</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabia-pledges-500-million-yemen-development-after-uae-withdrawal</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/saudi-arabia-pledges-500-million-yemen-development-after-uae-withdrawal</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;RIYADH, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Saudi Arabia has announced a slew of development projects across southern Yemen worth about $500 million, many in areas long-held by the United Arab Emirates and allied separatistswho were routed in a Saudi-backed offensive this month.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Turkey to deploy jets to Estonia, Romania under NATO air policing missions</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-deploy-jets-estonia-romania-under-nato-air-policing-missions</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/turkey-deploy-jets-estonia-romania-under-nato-air-policing-missions</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ANKARA, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Turkey plans to deploy fighter jets to Estonia and Romania as part of NATO's enhanced air policing missions, the defence ministry said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey plans to conduct a four-month deployment in Estonia between August and November 2026, followed by another rotation in Romania from December 2026 to March 2027, the ministry said in its weekly press briefing. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Turkey has contributed significantly to NATO’s air policing operations aimed at protecting allied airspace during peacetime, the ministry added. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:36:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump convinced 'to give Iran a chance' after threats over protest crackdown</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-convinced-give-iran-chance-after-threats-over-protest-crackdown</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-convinced-give-iran-chance-after-threats-over-protest-crackdown</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Gulf allies have convinced Donald Trump to "give Iran a chance", a Saudi official said on Thursday, after the US leader repeatedly threatened strikes on the Islamic republic over a crackdown on protests that activists say has left thousands dead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran was shaken over the last week by some of the biggest anti-government protests in the history of the Islamic republic, although the demonstrations appear to have diminished over the last few days in the face of repression and an almost week-long internet blackout.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:30:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump sees Iranian crackdown easing, Tehran denies man to be executed</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-sees-iranian-crackdown-easing-tehran-denies-man-be-executed</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-sees-iranian-crackdown-easing-tehran-denies-man-be-executed</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON/DUBAI, Jan 15 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump said he had been told that killings in Iran’s crackdown on protests were easing and that he believed there was no current plan for large-scale executions, adopting a wait‑and‑see posture after earlier threatening intervention.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iranian state media on Thursday reported that a 26-year-old man arrested during the protests in the city of Karaj would not be given the death sentence, after a rights group reported earlier this week that he was due to be executed on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>