<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Project Syndicate Archive Feed</title><link>https://www.project-syndicate.org/</link><description>Combined feed with archive links</description><item><title>Israel sees spike in PTSD and suicide among troops as war persists</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-sees-spike-ptsd-and-suicide-among-troops-war-persists</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israel-sees-spike-ptsd-and-suicide-among-troops-war-persists</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Emily Rose&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JERUSALEM, Jan 16 (Reuters) - Israel is grappling with a dramatic increase in post-traumatic stress disorder and suicide among its troops after its two-year assault on Gaza, precipitated by the October 7, 2023, Hamas attack on southern Israel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent reports by the Defence Ministry and by health providers have detailed the military's mental health crisis, which comes as fighting persists in Gaza and Lebanon and as tensions flare with Iran.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 07:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US approves possible sale of equipment, services to shift Peruvian naval base</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-approves-possible-sale-equipment-services-shift-peruvian-naval-base</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-approves-possible-sale-equipment-services-shift-peruvian-naval-base</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 15 (Reuters) - The U.S. State Department has approved the potential sale to Peru of $1.5 billion in equipment and services to support the country's efforts to shift its main naval base in the city of Callao, the Pentagon said in a statement on Thursday, so it can expand a neighboring seaport.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Peruvian government plans to relocate its naval base at Callao, on the coast just west of the capital Lima, a few kilometers away.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 03:36:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Libyan filmmaker fights for cinema revival</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/libyan-filmmaker-fights-cinema-revival</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/libyan-filmmaker-fights-cinema-revival</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Mouayed Zabtia shoots most scenes for his latest movie in a studio he built at his Tripoli home. For the filmmaker, it is one way to overcome the obstacles he faces in a country where cinema once nearly vanished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before a 1969 coup that brought Moamer Kadhafi to power, Libya's capital Tripoli was home to more than 20 movie theatres.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Today we have none," Zabtia told AFP.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kadhafi was overthrown and killed in 2011, and though the censorship of his era has declined, its effects are still deeply felt through underinvestment and public disinterest.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 03:30:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump announces 'board of peace' formed for Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-announces-board-peace-formed-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-announces-board-peace-formed-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;US President Donald Trump on Thursday announced the formation of a Gaza "board of peace," a key phase two element of a US-backed plan to end the war in the Palestinian territory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It is my Great Honor to announce that THE BOARD OF PEACE has been formed," Trump posted on his Truth Social platform, adding that the members of the body will be announced "shortly."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I can say with certainty that it is the Greatest and Most Prestigious Board ever assembled at any time, any place," Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 02:00:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says he is backing 'newly appointed Palestinian Technocratic Government' in Gaza</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-backing-newly-appointed-palestinian-technocratic-government-gaza</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/trump-says-he-backing-newly-appointed-palestinian-technocratic-government-gaza</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Jan 15 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump on Thursday said he is backing "a newly appointed Palestinian Technocratic Government" in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"As Chairman of the Board of Peace, I am backing a newly appointed Palestinian Technocratic Government, the National Committee for the Administration of Gaza, supported by the Board's High Representative, to govern Gaza during its transition," Trump said in a post on Truth Social. "These Palestinian leaders are unwaveringly committed to a PEACEFUL future!"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; (Reporting by Christian Martinez; Editing by Himani Sarkar)&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:36:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Factbox-Trump's foreign policy called imperialist by experts</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-trumps-foreign-policy-called-imperialist-experts</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/factbox-trumps-foreign-policy-called-imperialist-experts</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Kanishka Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;WASHINGTON, Jan 15 (Reuters) - U.S. President Donald Trump has made a series of controversial moves that have shaken up the world order, including a military raid that toppled Venezuela's leader and renewed threats to annex Greenland. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump, who campaigned on what was seen as an isolationist "America First" platform, defends his policies as advancing U.S. economic and security interests. But to many experts, his moves echo the actions of 19th-century colonial powers. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:01:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Threats to Iran spike 'volatility': UN official</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/threats-iran-spike-volatility-un-official</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/threats-iran-spike-volatility-un-official</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A senior UN official warned on Thursday that threats of military action against Iran, like those made by US President Donald Trump, increased "volatility" in the protest-torn country.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Iran was shaken over the last week by some of the biggest anti-government protests in the history of the Islamic republic, although the demonstrations appear to have diminished in the face of repression and a week-long internet blackout. &lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US envoy to UN: US stands by Iranian people, all options on table</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-envoy-un-us-stands-iranian-people-all-options-table</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-envoy-un-us-stands-iranian-people-all-options-table</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Michelle Nichols&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNITED NATIONS, Jan 15 (Reuters) - The United States stands by the “brave people of Iran,” and President Donald Trump "has made it clear all options are on the table to stop the slaughter," U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations Mike Waltz told the U.N. Security Council on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump has repeatedly threatened to intervene in support of protesters in Iran, where thousands of people have been reported killed in a crackdown on the unrest against clerical rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 21:36:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian activist Sarah Mardini acquitted of migrant trafficking in Greece</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-activist-sarah-mardini-acquitted-migrant-trafficking-greece-0</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-activist-sarah-mardini-acquitted-migrant-trafficking-greece-0</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Greek court on Thursday acquitted Syrian competitive swimmer and activist Sarah Mardini, whose rescue of her sister inspired a hit Netflix film, and 23 others of migrant trafficking in a decision applauded by top rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The verdict came almost a month after the start of their trial at a court on Lesbos, ending a legal ordeal for the activists since 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They had been charged in the Greek island with "forming a criminal organisation" and "illegally facilitating the entry of third-country nationals into Greece".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan-Saudi-Turkey defence deal in pipeline, Pakistani minister says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-saudi-turkey-defence-deal-pipeline-pakistani-minister-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/pakistan-saudi-turkey-defence-deal-pipeline-pakistani-minister-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Saad Sayeed, Asif Shahzad and Jonathan Spicer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ISLAMABAD/ISTANBUL, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Pakistan, Saudi Arabia and Turkey have prepared a draft defence agreement after nearly a year of talks, Pakistan's Minister for Defence Production said, a signal they could be seeking a bulwark against a flare-up of regional violence in the last two years.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 19:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian activist Sarah Mardini acquitted of migrant trafficking in Greece</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-activist-sarah-mardini-acquitted-migrant-trafficking-greece</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/syrian-activist-sarah-mardini-acquitted-migrant-trafficking-greece</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Greek court Thursday acquitted Syrian competitive swimmer and activist Sarah Mardini, whose rescue of her sister inspired a hit Netflix film, and 23 others of migrant trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The verdict came almost a month after the start of their trial at a court on Lesbos, ending a legal ordeal for the activists since 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They had been charged in the Greek island with "forming a criminal organisation" and "illegally facilitating the entry of third-country nationals into Greece".&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 19:30:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>From Egypt to Lebanon: What’s at stake for regional states on Trump’s visa ban list?</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypt-lebanon-whats-stake-regional-states-trumps-visa-ban-list</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/egypt-lebanon-whats-stake-regional-states-trumps-visa-ban-list</guid><description>The State Department claimed that citizens from the affected countries are more likely to use social welfare services at a high rate.</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:15:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US court overturns order releasing pro-Palestinian activist</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-court-overturns-order-releasing-pro-palestinian-activist</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/us-court-overturns-order-releasing-pro-palestinian-activist</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A US appeals court overturned a ruling that led to the release of prominent pro-Palestinian protest leader Mahmoud Khalil, according to court documents filed Thursday, raising the prospect of his re-arrest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Khalil, a legal permanent resident in the United States who is married to a US citizen and has a US-born son, was detained by immigration authorities for three months beginning in March. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He faced potential deportation for allegedly posing a threat to US foreign policy interests.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Four Arab states urged against US-Iran escalation, official says</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/four-arab-states-urged-against-us-iran-escalation-official-says</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/four-arab-states-urged-against-us-iran-escalation-official-says</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;By Maha El Dahan and Andrew Mills&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DUBAI, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Four Arab states conducted intense diplomacy with the United States and Iran this week to prevent a threatened U.S. attack on Iran over Tehran's use of force against protesters that they feared would have impacts across the region, a Gulf official said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Oman and Egypt were involved in the diplomacy over 48 hours before U.S. President Donald Trump signalled on Thursday that he had ultimately decided against an attack for now, saying the killings in Iran were easing.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli strikes kill five in Gaza, say local health authorities</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-strikes-kill-five-gaza-say-local-health-authorities</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/israeli-strikes-kill-five-gaza-say-local-health-authorities</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;CAIRO, Jan 15 (Reuters) - Two Israeli airstrikes killed five people, including a 16-year-old, in Deir al-Balah on Thursday, said local health authorities. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military did not immediately respond to a Reuters request for comment on the incident. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was not immediately clear what triggered the attacks, which were in areas outside the control of Israeli forces in the strip. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More than 400 Palestinians and three Israeli soldiers have been reported killed since a fragile ceasefire took effect in October.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:01:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Iran regime’s potential collapse spells more risk than benefit for Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</guid><description>Iran’s leadership faces its most serious unrest in years, and rising Kurdish mobilization makes the prospect of regime collapse particularly risky for Turkey.</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:00:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Iran regime’s potential collapse spells more risk than benefit for Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</guid><description>Iran’s leadership faces its most serious unrest in years, and rising Kurdish mobilization makes the prospect of regime collapse particularly risky for Turkey.</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:00:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Iran regime’s potential collapse spells more risk than benefit for Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</guid><description>Iran’s leadership faces its most serious unrest in years, and rising Kurdish mobilization makes the prospect of regime collapse particularly risky for Turkey.</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:00:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Iran regime’s potential collapse spells more risk than benefit for Turkey</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/why-iran-regimes-potential-collapse-spells-more-risk-benefit-turkey</guid><description>Iran’s leadership faces its most serious unrest in years, and rising Kurdish mobilization makes the prospect of regime collapse particularly risky for Turkey.</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:00:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bomb hoax forces Turkish Airlines to make emergency landing in Barcelona</title><link>https://archive.is/o/11Q8k/https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bomb-hoax-forces-turkish-airlines-make-emergency-landing-barcelona</link><guid>https://www.al-monitor.com/originals/2026/01/bomb-hoax-forces-turkish-airlines-make-emergency-landing-barcelona</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;MADRID, Jan 15 (Reuters) - A false bomb threat delivered via an onboard mobile connection  caused a Turkish Airlines flight from Istanbul to make an emergency landing at Barcelona's El Prat Airport on Thursday, Spanish police and the airline said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Turkish Airlines spokesperson said earlier that the plane had landed after crew detected that a passenger had created an in-flight internet hotspot which was named to include a bomb threat as the aircraft approached Barcelona.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:36:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>